<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-29T09:40:05Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Cartel Land</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/29/cartel-land.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CartelLand" />
    <published>2016-01-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/29/cartel-land</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re one crazy sonofabitch, aren’t you? Embedding yourself with gun-toting mercenaries, meth cooks, and cartel members is not exactly a sane way to make a paycheque. The fact that director/producer/cinematographer/editor Matthew Heineman seems willing to put his life on the line is one thing – he gets all the final glory if things go right. But you’re just a hired gun (sorry, bad metaphor). I don’t exactly know which scenes you filmed, but whether it was State-side with armed minute-men hunting drug traffickers, or following a mini-revolution within Mexico, the chance of you getting shot before getting the shot you wanted seemed stupidly high. </p>

<p>But damn. What a hell of film.</p>

<p>There’s no shortage of movies about the U.S. government’s bloody war on drugs.  <em>Cartel Land,</em> however, ups the ante by actually going into the trenches with the foot soldiers who are either profiting from the chaos, or simply trying to protect their home. </p>

<p>The film starts off with a deceptively slow-pace, with drug producers being interviewed in an undisclosed desert location at night. The masked interviewee is calm, thoughtful and personable. He’s fully aware that the drugs they’re making in Mexico are ruining people’s lives, but he’s also fairly unapologetic about his participation. After all, he’s out of options. This humanizing introduction is an important touch that I thought back on a lot over the course of the film, especially when horror stories are relayed about how the cartels take over small towns. One woman in particular goes into gory detail about the ways the cartel assert their control over the population by brutally murdering not only men and women, but infants and children. Thank God you didn’t capture any of that.</p>

<p>But you do come pretty close, especially during a climactic raid by the Autodefensas – a paramilitary group trying to reclaim one cartel-run Mexican town at a time. The shoot-out is so intense that I had to remind myself this was a documentary. People’s lives are at risk – including yours – during the sequence of events. It was the most breathtaking scene I’ve watched all year. </p>

<p>The visuals throughout the film are powerful, with beautiful compositions not only during the less intense transitional moments, but also when you’re under fire. How you guys managed to keep your trigger fingers operating a zoom lens while bullets are whizzing by, or while people are being interrogated at gun point, is a truly compelling feat of cinematography.   </p>

<p>Heinman’s approach totally immerses the audience in the chaos. There are no voiceovers to tie together the different stories we’re following, and no convenient confrontation linking the subjects together. They are just two sides of the same coin, making up the complicated cross-border battlefront of the drug war that most of us are blessedly removed from. You helped bring it into our lives in a very real way.</p>

<p>Stay safe, man.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tangerine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/26/tangerine.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Tangerine" />
    <published>2016-01-26T17:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-26T17:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/26/tangerine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iSePbQVR284">interview</a> for the 1991 documentary <em>Hearts of Darkness</em> (which I can’t recommend enough) Francis Ford Coppola describes the future of film making in this short sentence: </p>

<p>“<em>One day, some little fat girl in Ohio is going to be the new Mozart and make a beautiful film.</em>”</p>

<p><em>Tangerine</em> is that film. Which means, I guess, you’re the chubby new Mozart from Ohio.*  </p>

<p>Shot guerilla style on modified iPhone 5’s, <em>Tangerine</em> is a ludicrously exciting film, and a perfect example of how you can do something really interesting if you know how to compose a frame and tell a story. That the performances are uneven, or that the production values are utterly low rent, doesn’t detract from what is, in its finished state, a remarkable movie. Those things that might seem to be shortcomings in larger budget films actually help to create, in a film like <em>Tangerine,</em> a world that is both neo-realist and still somehow dreamlike. </p>

<p>The story is simple. It follows one person (a weirdly engaging and still amateurish performance from the oh-so-aptly named Kitana Kiki Rodriguez) in her search for a wayward boyfriend. Along the way a whole collection of outré characters pop in and out of frame, but it’s how the story is told—a great soundtrack, imaginative and constantly invigorating camerawork, and a verite that comes from something so intimate and small scale—that makes it special.</p>

<p>Coppola, in the same 35-second segment, also talks about how this new kind of filmmaker will liberate the art form from the artificial constraints of what he brackets as “professionalism”.</p>

<p>I think what he means is fairly simple: once filmmaking becomes a process that only requires a few willing participants, a couple of iPhones, a good computer, and some innate talent, then the artform is taken out of the hands of people who are only concerned with the economics of the film business. It changes the balance of power, which means that executive producers and distributors, financiers and beancounters move to their proper place in the hierarchy. Because, while these people are clearly an important part of the process, they are important only <em>after</em> the fact.</p>

<p>Too often—at least up till now—the only time an artist has had the wherewithal to make the work they really want to make is after they have emptied whatever pool of real talent they possess. People like Christopher Nolan and Tarantino only achieved that kind of autonomy after years of negotiating the studio system which seems (to me) to have sucked them dry of what made films like <em>Reservoir Dogs</em> or <em>The Following</em> so vital and alive (although apparently that has not happened to George Miller—so maybe proximity to Hollywood is also part of the equation). All these revered auteurs seem capable of creating now are these bloated, over-wrought <em>productions</em>, that are long on surface concerns like the Imax sequences in <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em> or Tarantino’s 70mm roadshow for <em>The Hateful Eight</em> and short on what was so promising in their early works: a real engagement with storytelling and character.</p>

<p>The whole film industry seems on the edge of catastrophic changes and <em>Tangerine</em> is one of the harbingers of that welcome disaster. It’s an example—for anyone with the foresight to see—of what it’s possible to do with nothing more than a couple of jacked up iPhones and a good idea. </p>

<p>And, of course, prodigious talent as well.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The 5th Wave</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/26/the-5th-wave.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=The5thWave" />
    <published>2016-01-26T04:01:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-26T04:01:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/26/the-5th-wave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Supporting roles are an interesting barometer—they can tell you a lot about the film as whole. If they are well rounded, interesting and memorable often times the rest of the movie follows suit. If they are forgettable, paper thin, and flaccid, chances are it will be difficult to avoid an inadvertent nap.</p>

<p>Suffice it to say, Ron, I left the <em>The 5th Wave</em> feeling unexpectedly well rested. </p>

<p>I have a real soft spot for you as an actor. Your folksy portrayal as “Nix” (often tinged with a hint of a pretty dark interior life) in <em>Band Of Brothers</em> really engaged me. Even a film as throwaway as <em>Office Space</em> was elevated by your quiet—and sort of weird—reverse charisma. It is as if the less you speak the more interesting you become. </p>

<p>Going into the screening of <em>The 5th Wave</em>—which according to the trailer I saw, looked like the best I could hope for was a cookie cutter dystopian narrative made with a kind of minimal competence (see: <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/9/22/maze-runner-the-scorch-trials.html"><em>Maze Runner: Scorch Trials</em></a> et al)—I was at least hoping I could lean on your performance as a something to keep me engaged.</p>

<p>Instead you got was about seven minutes of utterly forgettable screen time, and while you were building your second pool with the paycheck this film afforded you, I was left floundering with a film that was passionless, disinterested in its own premises, and often horribly miscast. How otherwise to explain another fine supporting actor like Liev Schreiber coming off even more rail thin and hollow than your portrayal as “The Dad” of Chloe Moretz’s turn at the Chosen One motif. </p>

<p>Sometimes films that generally aren’t that great have something that helps them rise above their own limitations. Last year’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/8/27/the-end-of-the-tour.html"><em>The End of The Tour</em> </a>(in which you also had a small part) was made greater than the sum of its parts partially on the strength of a supporting cast that included you, Joan Cusak, and Becky Anne Baker. But for that to happen, there has to be far more commitment and interest in the material than I got from anyone attached to this film—other than Moretz, who labored, unsuccessfully, to invest her character with something emotionally meaningful. </p>

<p>That <em>The 5th Wave</em> is largely a waste of its 38 million dollar budget obviously isn’t on your shoulders. The direction is workmanlike at best, the genre tropes are so tired that they may as well have just been written out on title cards—<em>obligatory montage where various plagues and disasters reduce the population to numbers our budget and capabilities can manage</em>. Even the visuals feel like mid-level FX network series quality.</p>

<p>But I suppose what I had hoped for was that your attachment to <em>The 5th Wave</em> meant perhaps the script, or even the performances, would somehow rise above the limitations of listless direction or poorly conceived genre tropes. Unfortunately, that was not the case.</p>

<p>I hope you at least enjoy the pool, Ron.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Svengali</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/22/svengali.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Svengali" />
    <published>2016-01-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/22/svengali</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There are three things the British do better than anyone else; comedy, satire, and junk food. John Hardwick’s <em>Svengali</em> attempts to cover the first two. The dangerous amount of Walkers cheese &amp; onion crisps and Rowntree’s Fruit Gums consumed while watching it (inadvisable, but <em>highly</em> recommended) speaks to my fondness for the third. </p>

<p>Adorable and amiable Welshman, Dixie, dreams of being a music manager, a ‘Svengali’ in the vein of Alan McGee and Tony Wilson. He moves to London with his unfailingly supportive girlfriend to manage a band he discovered on YouTube. Hardwick attempts to braid together three main narrative threads: a satire of the music business, a love story, and a small-town-boy-in-the-big-city tale, complete with the requisite archetypes including Mean, High-strung Boss and Asshole Foreign Landlady. It’s hard for me to say bad things about the film, but I also wish I had more emphatically <em>good</em> things to say about it. </p>

<p>Full disclosure: I am not cool when it comes to music. I don’t know bands, and have no idea what the kids are into these days. There are apparently quite a few clever cameos in the film, like some person from something called ‘The Libertines’, but it all went right over my head. You know how I mentioned ‘Svengalis in the vein of Alan McGee and Tony Wilson’ in the paragraph above? I had to google them for that sentence to make any sense. But even if you’re clueless and un-hip like me, you get that this is supposed to be a send-up of an industry filled with assholes. Except it isn’t – not entirely. For every asshole Dixie encounters, there is at least one very nice person who readily helps him out, or gives him a bit of encouragement. Things actually go so well for Dixie - from getting the band to make him their manager, to bringing attention to them as the next big thing - that the obstacles thrown into his path seem forced. Regardless, obstacles abound, but they end up throwing the narrative out of whack, and it becomes difficult to know where to pay attention. </p>

<p>At the beginning, the three narrative threads take turns pulling in and out of focus, each of them compelling and entertaining on their own, and as part of the whole. But as things start to go sideways for Dixie, both business-wise and romantically, I was unsure which loss I was supposed to dread more, mostly because Dixie seems unsure which of the two he is more upset about. Eventually, the music business thread loses steam entirely, and our focus shifts clumsily to the romantic plotline. The focus on satire is lost entirely, if it was ever meant to be satirical in the first place. There are a few odd, overplayed characters, such as Dixie’s boss, and the owners of two rival record companies, but there is no irony in the film’s portrayal of the music business. To me, it just didn’t go very far beyond saying “Here are a bunch of generally ordinary people trying to make it in an industry run by assholes.” </p>

<p>There needs to be irony if there is to be satire, and this film is just too earnest for that. There could have been irony in the way the music business changes Dixie – but it doesn’t change him. He never stops being his sweet, guileless self. Perhaps the film’s irony lies, then, in its title. Dixie claims to want to be a ‘Svengali’, but he is, in fact, the anti-Svengali. There is no dubious intent on his part, no manipulation of the band or anyone else around him. He is surrounded by quite a few bastard Svengali types, but he never goes over to the dark side himself. </p>

<p>In the same way you would pull visual focus to the most interesting element in a shot or scene, pulling the narrative focus to a more interesting internal metamorphosis on Dixie’s part would have been a lot more engaging. As I said before, it’s hard to say anything truly bad about the film, but it just doesn’t maintain its own focus well enough for me to call it a really good film. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Iñárritu Or (The Expected Defect Of Film Twitter)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/21/inarritu-or-the-unexpected-defect-of-film-twitter.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=IñárrituOr(TheExpectedDefectOfFilmTwitter)" />
    <published>2016-01-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/21/inarritu-or-the-unexpected-defect-of-film-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>First off, it would be disingenuous to call myself a ‘film critic’ because I don’t have any formal film education, or any real interest in pursuing that particular calling. I suppose the best description of my relationship to criticism is one that suits anyone with a more than passing interest in films and filmmaking—“Film enthusiast” perhaps. All of this is to say that I make no claim to any kind of expertise, apart from whatever aesthetic sense I may have developed over fifty-odd years of watching movies with the same kind of rapt attention other people pay to their favorite pornography.</p>

<p>That said, I have a bone to pick with a couple of the self-appointed literati of online criticism—Scott Tobias, formerly of the defunct <strong>Dissolve</strong> and <a href="http://birthmoviesdeath.com/2015/12/28/i-dont-care-how-hard-it-was-to-make-the-revenant">Devin Faraci</a> of <strong>Birth. Movies. Death.</strong> You two are broadly representative of a prevalent critical bent these days—especially online and <em>especially</em> on twitter. Essentially you are starting to sound like the sort of people who stand backstage mocking the prima ballerina because her ankles are a centimeter too thick, while barely being able to take a breath because of your own morbid obesity. </p>

<p>There are times where your critical engagement seems almost entirely concerned with your perception of the foibles and shortcomings of a particular filmmaker and virtually nothing to do with the film itself. </p>

<p>I am talking specifically, in this case, about Alejandro González Iñárritu.</p>

<p>Aside from the fact that the twitterverse’s opinions of Iñárritu as a human being are about as consequential, or interesting, as watching paint flake, that this kind of psychological conjecture is coming from people with degrees in film studies smacks of the worst kind of unselfconscious irony. </p>

<p>Of course, someone can be an atrocious human being and a perfectly fine film critic (or director for that matter). Each of you clearly seems to understand film and filmmaking, and you often express that understanding in interesting, and often astute, ways. What you do seem <em>particularly</em> unqualified to do is make any kind of assessment about the nature and value of a specific director’s character, or how that might reflect upon his or her work. Unless you know where specific corpses are buried, or whom exactly Iñárritu has chained to a radiator, your speculations about his <a href="https://thedissolve.com/reviews/1152-birdman/">integrity</a>, which seem mostly based on press releases and your own thinly veiled projections of self-loathing, aren’t even minimally pertinent.</p>

<p>Not incidentally, this preoccupation with reading the tea leaves of a creator’s psyche by parsing his press releases within an inch of their life also seems to have very little to do with what is useful in film criticism as a whole. </p>

<p>It was informative to watch the collective knife sharpening that went on within certain critical circles when <em>The Revenant</em> was first announced. The pre-emptive sniggering was deafening. One particularly vituperative Twitterette wondered aloud, oh so cuttingly, “<em>Why would I watch two hours of dudes shitting in the woods</em>?” </p>

<p>Why indeed. So much better to watch someone trying to be clever by reducing literally thousands of hours spent by people of enormous commitment, talent—and in Emmanuel Lubezki’s case—genius, into a caustic tweet. </p>

<p>Now that’s entertainment.</p>

<p>Rebecca Solnit recently wrote a <a href="http://lithub.com/men-explain-lolita-to-me/">couple of interesting pieces</a> about the inherent stupidity of  “must read” lists—specifically about lists of books that are, ostensibly, for men only. One of the more astute observations she made about <em>Lolita</em> was that for some subset of the potential audience it would be almost impossible for them to distance themselves enough to really engage with the novel’s larger themes—that their personal experiences made it too fraught for them to even try. This is almost painfully obvious as a truth. But what it also implies is that any interaction with a cultural artifact—whether book or movie, theatre or music—is inherently constrained as much by the person engaging with it as it is by the original text.</p>

<p>The point here is that maybe Iñárritu isn’t for you. So how about—to save us all from the obvious pain and suffering his work causes you—you and your cadre are hereby released from ever having to engage with Iñárritu and his films again. Then you can avoid the obvious moral and spiritual damage it does to your soul(s) and leave it to the rest of us philistines to struggle with his work: some bad, some good, some, yes, even <em>great</em>. Just like most other artists worth paying attention to.</p>

<p>I certainly understand that no one is holding a gun to my head as far as engaging with <em>your</em> work, but what I’m actually hoping for is that you give your heads a bit of a shake. Because while we have more than enough twitter wags making their reputations for their scathing 140 character bon mots, we don’t have nearly enough interesting and incisive film criticism—something you are both exceptionally good at.</p>

<p>Finally, here is something that Iñárritu had to say about the protagonist of his 2014 film <em>Birdman</em> (for which he <em>somehow</em> won the rare trifecta of Best Picture, Best Director and Best Original Screenplay). </p>

<p>“<em>If you stretch tragedy, it will always become comedy. That&#39;s the comedy that I like. And I always thought about Riggan Thomson as a Don Quixote of La Mancha, where humor comes from the disparity between his solemn, furious attempts and ambitions to become a serious artist and the ungovernable reality that is contrary to his wishes. That&#39;s basically the story of every human being, including me. It&#39;s hard to deal with our mediocrity, I think.</em>”</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>13 Hours: The Secret Soldiers of Benghazi</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/19/13-hours-the-secret-soldiers-of-benghazi.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=13Hours:TheSecretSoldiersofBenghazi" />
    <published>2016-01-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/19/13-hours-the-secret-soldiers-of-benghazi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Your job on set is to capture hi-res images during filming to be used in promotional materials. For <em>13 Hours: The Secret Soldiers of Benghazi</em>, it seems like every piece of promo circulating is a tribute to John Krasinski’s transformation from mischievous <em>Office</em> heart-throb into a rugged, muscular army man.</p>

<p>I can tell you’re a passionate photographer who provides a solid selection of images for any film or TV show you’re a part_ <a href="http://christianblack.com/">of</a>. Unfortunately for you, most of your images were presumably scrapped in favor of highlighting Krasinski’s new-found identity as a tough-as-nails leading man. Which is a shame, because I’m sure_ _you busted your ass while braving the Libyan heat to capture striking images that would represent the realities of warfare in a city on the brink of revolution.</p>

<p>I waited for the screening of 13 Hours to begin, alongside old, bearded men and college bros — who I suppose are the expected crowd at a Michael Bay biopic about six military operatives fighting off hordes of guerrilla fighters in war-torn Benghazi, Libya. I wondered what the film would do for John Krasinski’s career. Would it do what <em>Taken</em> did for Liam Neeson? Or what <em>John Wick</em> did for Keanu Reeves? The answer is neither. Once the rat-a-tat finally begins, one thing is evident, or not evident as the case may be—John Krasinski is nowhere to be found. </p>

<p>As our brave operatives mow down baddies from their rooftop advantage, I couldn’t help but notice Krasinski’s absence. It is only after the final bullet shell clinks against the concrete, and the smoke clears that he pops his face back into focus, covered in sweat as if he did something. This was a recurring theme throughout the film; any time the heat gets turned up, our hero is invisible. At most, the only time you see Krasinski jump into the fray is when he runs into a burning consulate to try and rescue the U.S. Ambassador.</p>

<p>Was all the media focus on Krasinski purposeful? Only you and the rest of the cast and crew can vouch for that. All I know is I took offence at this misrepresentation, because after viewing <em>13 Hours</em>, Krasinski couldn’t have been more useless.</p>

<p>The spotlight should have been on the true main characters; Rone and Tonto, who carried the film during its most pivotal parts. The exhaustion on their faces was believable—and warranted. 13 Hours isn’t comprised of A-list actors, so any one of the other five men featured could have been the focal point and I wouldn’t have cared. It was the promotional positioning of 13 Hours as the “John Krasinski Show”—and how that was completely untrue—that tarnished the experience for me.</p>

<p>To make matters worse, <em>13 Hours</em> is two hours of military glorification and rampant patriotism. The type of fodder that would be played at a GOP rally. I couldn’t help but think of the infamous scene in Inglorious Basterds where Adolf Hitler and his Nazi sympathizers howl and applaud at the movie screen as Fredrick Zoller levels a wave of Allied troops from his clocktower. It is this brainwashed sense of heroism featured in 13 Hours that make Benghazi seem like a Call of Duty victory, rather than the actual events in which the U.S. government treated these brave men as expendable resources.</p>

<p>I’m not surprised that Michael Bay chose to focus on the ground combat at Benghazi rather than on boardroom politics. It’s his bread and butter. But I was surprised about how the only time we really see Krasinski provide anything of value_ _is in one of your photos.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>45 Years is Unconditionally the Best Film of 2015</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/15/45-years-is-ununconditionally-the-best-film-of-2015.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=45YearsisUnconditionallytheBestFilmof2015" />
    <published>2016-01-15T12:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-15T12:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/15/45-years-is-ununconditionally-the-best-film-of-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>2015 offered up some pretty high-octane cinema - a man on Mars, a Max gone mad, and galaxies far, far away. But none of these <em>magna opera</em> hold a candle to the quiet, unadorned, explosion-free drama that is my absolute favourite film of 2015. Andrew Haigh’s <em>45 Years</em> commanded all of my attention and emotion, broke my heart, and haunts me months after seeing it. </p>

<p>A week shy of his 45th wedding anniversary, Geoff learns that the remains of his former lover, Katya, have been found, 50 years after she fell to her death during a Swiss hiking holiday. He drifts away to where his wife, Kate, can’t seem to reach him. And with that slight tug, a lifetime of contentment and comfort begins to unravel, exposing the fragile center that arguably lies at the heart of all human bonds, even those we think unbreakable. Especially those. </p>

<p>A huge part of why I love <em>45 Years</em> so much is that it reminds me of Daphne du Maurier’s <em>Rebecca</em>, which is only the most awesome and flawless novel ever written. In it, the memory of the deceased first love poisons the mind of the new wife with questions and doubts. In <em>45 Years</em>, Katya, perfectly preserved in a glacier, frozen in time and in Geoff’s old photographs hidden in the attic, comes to haunt Kate, no longer the new wife, but aged and weathered compared to the ghost of the woman whose place she took. But while Rebecca in du Maurier’s novel is a sinister, overwhelming presence that almost commands more of our attention as the live characters, Katya never really becomes important to the audience. It is Kate to whom our hearts go out, as Geoff withdraws into his memories and residual grief, leaving her to her sadness, jealousy, and disillusionment. As Kate and Geoff, Charlotte Rampling and Tom Courtenay are amazing together, breathtakingly intimate one instant, and suddenly, jarringly, alien to each other the next. The undoing of their relationship is so tough to watch because, at the beginning, they do such a brilliant job of drawing you into their cozy, content little world. </p>

<p>The film has an elegant ‘bare bones’ feel to it, from its simple yet masterful cinematography to the absence of a musical score. Yet, it never feels empty or lacking. Each scene is suffused with an intimacy and energy that belie its slow pace. The neat, static framing of each shot allows the characters to draw together and apart as they struggle to grasp at what was once solid between them and is now startlingly fragile. The lighting plays between obscuration and illumination, the week-long, foggy, greyness giving way to warmth and brightness only towards the end (with no small amount of irony), at Geoff and Kate’s anniversary party, the happy ending that should be but is not to be. </p>

<p><em>45 Years</em> is getting some well-deserved love at the top of awards season, most notably for Charlotte Rampling’s portrayal of Kate. The camera often remains on her face for long stretches, and it’s like she packs three pages of dialogue into the wordless droop of her eyes and the subtle turn at corners of her mouth. Rampling is never less than utterly brilliant, so it almost feels redundant to go on about what a great job she does, but I will say that the real marvel of her performance is that it owns the narrative but also grants you room to move with her and feel as she feels, and you can’t help but wonder, “What would I do if…?” or “How would I feel if…?” Going into the Oscar race for Best Actress, there is only one shot that really needs to be submitted for consideration – the very last one; Kate’s face in close up, placid on the surface, struggling to contain the turmoil just beneath. It is a devastating image, and I was a mess as the credits rolled.  </p>

<p>As much as I love to be entertained and dazzled, I can’t resist the small, out-of-nowhere films that swipe my legs out from under me. While <em>45 Years</em> is a pretty film, and at first seems like a gentle film, it is by no means an easy film. I enjoyed the big blockbusters on most ‘Best of 2015’ lists, but this one broke me in a way none of the post-apocalyptic, outer-space, teeth-rattling fare even came close.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mad Max: Fury Road is Obviously the Best Film of 2015</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/15/mad-max-fury-road-is-obvioulsy-the-best-film-of-2015.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MadMax:FuryRoadisObviouslytheBestFilmof2015" />
    <published>2016-01-15T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-15T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/15/mad-max-fury-road-is-obvioulsy-the-best-film-of-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>These year-end assignments present a bit of a conundrum for me. I have this set of critical ideals in which I try to judge each film I see on its own merits (or lack thereof), and those alone. It’s a bit of a fool’s errand, since I can’t wipe the slate completely clean every time I walk into the theatre. Hell, it sometimes even causes crises of conscience. But when I can lock out all the external noise, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/7/wolf-of-wall-street.html">the work speaks for itself</a>. Of course, that’s also how I can end up <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/26/pain-gain.html">kind of liking a Michael Bay film</a>. It’s a system with some distressing outcomes.</p>

<p>Yet, here I am, doing that one thing I try to avoid: judging each film not on its own merit, but on how out holds up against others for the sole reason they were released in the same calendar year. But we humans do like order, and if a particular 12-month span affords us that, we’ll take it. There’s comfort to be found in a world that makes sense.</p>

<p>Which may be the very reason I found <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> so thrilling. It’s a movie that feels like it’s about to come off the rails at any moment. The world George Miller throws us into is bananas. It’s a film that <em>feels</em> out of control. Instead, it’s one of the best examples of filmmaking precision I’ve seen in years.</p>

<p>Unlike <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/9/sorry-the-lego-movie-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html">my choice last year</a>, this one’s not based on a personal, emotional reaction, but a purely visceral one. And honestly, it’s refreshing to respond to a film on that pure gut level – to be reminded that the craft of cinema itself, when executed on a master level, is enough in and of itself to excite. </p>

<p>That’s not to say that I find <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> lacking in any other departments. What I thought of it in terms of character, story, and acting, is covered <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/20/mad-max-fury-road.html">in my review</a>. This essay is simply about falling in love with cinema again. Lately, my relationship with film has felt more like a marriage that&#39;s gone a bit stale: I love it dearly, but I hadn&#39;t felt that all-consuming infatuation that drew me to it in the first place; the kind that had me returning to the same films over and over, desperate for the heady rush that comes from pure passion.</p>

<p>It’s fortuitous that I saw <em>Hitchcock/Truffaut</em> before writing this. Though that film didn&#39;t fully work for me, what I did love was watching filmmakers lose themselves in discussing Hitchcock&#39;s total mastery of cinema: his cutting, camera placement, use of actors. It&#39;s that same rapture that keeps bringing me back to <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em>. Miller is so confident in every insane idea, that he overrode the built-in skepticism that has been a key instrument in my film-watching toolkit for years. Actually, it didn&#39;t just override it, it blew it right up. I came out of <em>Mad</em> <em>Max: Fury Road</em> with the fervour of a born-again zealot. I wanted to preach the Gospel of Miller, whether or not anyone wanted to hear it.</p>

<p>Despite my earlier protestations, one of the things I like to do at the end of any year is to try and figure out what has changed for me as a moviegoer. Often that fans into the ever-growing chasm of technological progress: the reemergence of 3D as gimmick, the transition from film to digital projection. 2015, however, was about teaching me that maybe I don’t have to fret so much about consciously placing every movie into its own hermetically-sealed chamber. A great film will do that all on its own, and I won’t even realize it. The irony is that it took a movie possibly surpassed only by <em>Star Wars: The Force Awakens</em> preconceived expectations to do that. <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> not only introduces a new actor in its iconic lead role, but it also bares the weight of 30 years of anticipation. And it leaves those expectations in the figurative and literal dust as it races forward, daring us all to keep up. </p>

<p>Or maybe it’s not ironic at all. Maybe it’s perfectly fitting. Miller took my own preconceived ideas—about the <em>Mad Max</em> series and about cinema itself—and turned them on their head, showing me something I didn’t even know I wanted.</p>

<p>And because of that, <em>Mad Max:Fury Road</em> is the best film of 2015.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Creed is Surprisingly the Best Film of 2015</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/14/creed-is-surprisingly-the-best-film-of-2015.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CreedisSurprisinglytheBestFilmof2015" />
    <published>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/14/creed-is-surprisingly-the-best-film-of-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Sports films resonate because, by and large, they’re comfortably predictable. They appeal to our basest human needs – to persevere, to win, to feel the thrill of victory and the agony of defeat, as the saying goes. Many of us adults will never experience the life-altering rush of an athletic triumph, but we all face obstacles in our lives that we must find the strength to overcome.</p>

<p>Boxing movies specifically cater to this instinct because they are quite literally about fighting. And though the good ones are about much more than that, at their very essence, boxing movies lay out a blueprint for success: set your goal, test your physical and mental capacities, find something inside of yourself that you didn’t know existed, and push yourself to the limits. Watching that cinematic journey and savouring vicarious victory is one of life’s small pleasures. Call it sophomoric, call it cliché, but you know what? A lot of the time life <em>is</em> fucking cliché. And <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/27/creed.html"><em>Creed</em></a> director Ryan Coogler knows that. He embraces these clichés and still manages to exceed expectations. He made the <em>Rocky</em> film a fan would have made. Because he <em>is</em> a fan. </p>

<p>When you’re six or seven you’re not necessarily able to articulate why certain things appeal to you more than others, you simply love the things that you love. Most kids in the late 70s/early 80s were obsessed with the original <em>Star Wars</em> trilogy. I was obsessed with the <em>Rocky</em> movies. An unknown, past-his prime, palooka from Philly defying all odds to go up against Apollo Creed, the heavyweight boxing champion of the world? Those other kids could keep their light sabres and their dark sides, my heart belonged to the Italian Stallion, king of the underdogs</p>

<p>As much as I enjoy a rollicking sci-fi or fantasy flick, even as a kid, I always felt more connected to quiet, character-based movies rooted in reality. And when elements of the <em>Rocky</em> films became formulaic and cheesy, I always found something – a song, a character, a memorable line of dialogue – that kept me hanging on. Being able to look past certain idiosyncrasies, missteps, and outright disaster (<em>Rocky</em> goddamned <em>V</em>), and not walk away is the basis of unconditional love. It’s also the classic definition of an unhealthy, co-dependent relationship. </p>

<p><em>Creed</em> was the chance to make things right again - and not just with me and other die-hard fans who would have been content to let things end with 2006’s better than expected <em>Rocky Balboa</em>. It was an opportunity to reintroduce a set of characters and circumstances for a whole new generation to fall in love with. Even with the winning combo of director Ryan Coogler and actor Michael B. Jordan (lauded for delivering 2013’s critical darling <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/8/6/fruitvale-station.html"><em>Fruitvale Station</em></a>), I honestly didn’t know if <em>Creed</em> could do it. I walked into the theatre with lowered expectations. I walked out a born-again believer. </p>

<p>There was one specific moment when <em>Creed</em> won back my affections. Adonis, Apollo Creed’s illegitimate son, has just moved into Rocky’s house to train with him full time. On a shelf, Adonis sees a picture of Rocky and his son, Robert, taken when Rocky was in his prime, and Robert was a child. Rocky mentions that Robert moved away, that it was difficult for him living in Philly being Rocky’s kid, and that they have a good relationship though they don’t see each other often. </p>

<p>This scene is played matter-of-factly. Coogler doesn’t force Sylvester Stallone or Jordan to mine the emotional depths of the father/son dynamic in a film that is so plainly about the father/son dynamic. But those of us with an encyclopedic knowledge of the <em>Rocky</em> franchise recognized that the picture is of Stallone and his real-life son, Sage, who died in 2012. This scene could have been maudlin, or tacky, or gross, but instead it was something every <em>Rocky</em> film since the first one hasn’t been: powerfully understated. </p>

<p>There’s a truth in <em>Creed</em> that I just wasn’t expecting, and when it showed up in this, and every other scene, I realized how much it had been missing from the other films. After the unlikely runaway success of the first <em>Rocky</em> film in 1976, each subsequent sequel became more interested in putting butts in seats, than in reaching any kind of emotional honesty. Sure, there were scenes that moved me –  Rocky’s monologue when Adrian is in a coma (<em>Rocky II</em>) , Mickey’s death (<em>Rocky III</em>), Rocky’s speech in front of the Politburo (<em>Rocky IV</em>)– but I was always aware that I was being manipulated, either through sweeping soundtrack strings, painfully sentimental dialogue, or yet another training montage. I felt <em>something</em>, but they were cheap jabs, never gut punches.</p>

<p><em>Creed</em> hit me. Hard.</p>

<p>I expected that <em>Creed</em> would focus on family bonds. The title is kind of a giveaway. I knew Adonis’ internal fight would be to accept his father’s legacy. But I wasn’t prepared for Rocky’s fight for his life, and the larger theme of mortality. And I certainly wasn’t prepared to see Stallone deliver the performance of his career. Perhaps because for once, he hadn’t written Rocky’s dialogue, or because this is the first movie in which Rocky doesn’t box, or maybe because his primary job on <em>Creed</em> was as an actor, but it really freed him to explore the character of Rocky as a mere mortal, and not as a legend. When he delivers the line, “Time takes us all down in the end. It’s undefeated,” it’s not done for effect. It’s just the truth. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html">If <em>Rocky IV</em> was the movie I didn’t know I needed after my dad died in 1985</a>, then <em>Creed</em> is the movie I didn’t know I needed in 2015, when I became the primary caregiver to my mother who is battling Stage IV metastatic melanoma. Which we found out about on February 11th, 30 years to the day after my dad’s death because yes, life is a fucking cliché, and we all have to fight whether we want to or not. The alternative isn’t an option. </p>

<p>“One step at a time. One punch at a time. One round at a time.” It’s a mantra from <em>Creed</em>, and it may be simplistic and banal, but it reminds me that there’s just as much triumph to be had from helping my mother get up my four porch steps without both of us collapsing from exhaustion, as there is in running up the famous steps of the Philadelphia Museum of Art. And it’s enough to just enjoy an unexpectedly solid film that lets me savour a predictable victory. In life, it’s a gift we’re rarely given. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mad Max: Fury Road is Unapologetically the Best Film of 2015</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/13/mad-max-fury-road-is-unapologetically-the-best-film-of-2015.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MadMax:FuryRoadisUnapologeticallytheBestFilmof2015" />
    <published>2016-01-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/13/mad-max-fury-road-is-unapologetically-the-best-film-of-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Someone once recently called me that most derogatory of critical terms—fan boy—because I wrote that I‘d seen <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> <strong>ten</strong> (10) times in the theatre. That’s like accusing someone of being a snob because they go to the Louvre every week. There is just a fundamental misapprehension of the impulse at work.</p>

<p>A fan boy is driven by slavish, unthinking devotion to a piece of culture he sees, sadly, as somehow self-actualizing. Experiencing a flat out piece of art like <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> multiple times is simply a question of good taste being rewarded with each interaction. </p>

<p>George Miller’s ridiculous film is so outside the realm of what’s probable that it smacks of a kind of magic. There really aren’t that many experimental art films that have a price tag of 150 million dollars and feature two pre-eminent actors like Charlize Theron and Tom Hardy. More importantly, there aren’t that many experimental art films that are so fucking entertaining. When I say entertaining, I mean there is a sequence early on that utterly enraptured every audience I experienced the film with. And each time the ten-minute-or-so-sequence ended, <em>each time,</em> there was a collective silence for three beats followed by a slow exhalation—then usually a smattering of things like “Christ almighty” or something similar.</p>

<p>I don’t really care much who wins Oscar, to be honest. The actual value of it seems disproportionate, but I do think that some of the conversations surrounding the ceremony make it completely worthwhile as an exercise. <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> is especially worthy of being a part of that conversation for a lot of reasons, but here is the one I think is most significant. It is completely true to itself as a piece of art. It never contradicts its own logic, never sacrifices story and its narrative integrity, and always treats it characters as three-dimensional—no matter how heightened and outlandish they seem externally. This is a world George Miller <em>believes</em> in and he is possessed of the craft and the talent to bring the audience fully into that world with him. </p>

<p>So much about what’s good art versus what is not, once you get past a kind of qualitative baseline (some things are just so poorly conceived and executed they never pass the starting gate) is about each persons’ willingness to engage with the work on its own terms. That doesn’t mean disengaging with your critical faculties or empty-headed consumption, it just means that whatever your initial preconceptions, you allow the film to confound them—if it can. The real genius of <em>Fury Road</em> is that it takes those preconceptions and burns them with fire from the end a guitar.</p>

<p>So far I’m one for one with my Dear Cast and Crew <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/8/seriously-birdman-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html">Best Picture Oscar Predictions™</a>. <em>Birdman</em>—last year’s winner—and <em>Fury Road</em> definitely share some DNA. They are both products of minds possessed of original, daring, boisterous and Loki-like levels of mischief. Each of these films is predicated on a big fuck you to the industry that helped spawn them. In <em>Birdman</em> it is textual and overt (Iñárritu is like that) but <em>Fury Road</em> is a middle finger to convention simply by existing. There is no way to exaggerate how hopeful <em>Fury Road</em> makes me about what is possible when there is a perfect convergence of creator, circumstance, concept and just plain dumb luck.</p>

<p>And if there is anything the Academy falls all over itself to reward, it is a film that holds everything they value in utter contempt. So it is just possible I could go two for two.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>