<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-17T23:02:39Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>10 Cloverfield Lane</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/17/10-cloverfield-lane.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=10CloverfieldLane" />
    <published>2016-03-17T10:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-17T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/17/10-cloverfield-lane</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You seem to have found your niche in this business. But it’s not (surprisingly) as a director. Rather, you’re someone who seems to excel at matching talent with content and shepherding the whole herd of cats to a (mostly) satisfying conclusion. </p>

<p>Made for a budget of 5 million, <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> is an unique amalgam of low budget indie and slick studio product. It is helmed by first time director Dan Trachtenberg, yet looks and feels nothing like a first effort. With technical and creative support from you and your production studio, Bad Robot, <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> never suffers from the kind of ragged edges low budget films often display. It is well shot, crisply edited, and boasts three strong performances. </p>

<p><em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> spends most its time in an underground survival shelter built and occupied by a twitchy former satellite engineer Howard (John Goodman). The shelter has two other occupants Michelle (Mary Elizabeth Winstead) and Emmett (John Gallagher Jr.). Emmett fought his way in while Michelle woke after a car crash to find herself shackled to a water pipe. The rest of the film takes it time exploring exactly what lead to these peculiar circumstances—and how each of the three copes with what they discover about one another, and the truth of their predicament.</p>

<p>This film is one example of how to marry the resources of a studio to a low-budget script, and, in so doing, how to create a workaround for the roadblocks that these kind of films often have to negotiate. It has become a truism that it’s impossibly difficult for original content to find a home anywhere in the studio system, so unless a property has some kind of name recognition it’s unlikely to get green lit. What you managed to do with <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> was produce an original script by marrying the content to an already existing property—in this case the 2008 film, <em>Cloverfield</em>. I have my reservations about this particular model—specifically how much you have to compromise the initial vision in order to include the franchise elements—but it’s certainly a path that seems viable.  </p>

<p>There are a few visible seams between what is a self-contained three hander about the particular kind of crazy that leads someone to construct an elaborate bomb shelter—which is then melded with a very different kind of story involving much more expansive themes. The odd mix of humor, tension, and creeping dread is consistently effective. There comes a point in the film where it is not clear at all whether Michelle, Emmitt and Howard are safer inside the shelter, or facing the very real, but not entirely distinct, danger that lurks just outside the door.</p>

<p>There is one caveat, at least for me, in all of this: this film occasionally resembles fusion cuisine that is less than the sum of its parts. Neither beast nor fowl, it has a few moments that feel heavy-handed—especially a kind of overt Chekov’s gun reveal early in the first act. This is how you tried to foreshadow a big turn, but it felt awkward and interrupted the otherwise clockwork rhythm of the film, making the <em>Cloverfield</em> connection sometimes feel like it was grafted onto an original script with more low-key ambitions.</p>

<p>I like Kraft Dinner. And I like Salmon. I’m just not sure I love them mashed together. And while <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> was well crafted throughout, I could never quite shake the feeling that it was as much marketing experiment as clever genre exercise. </p>

<p>It was, all in all, a pretty enjoyable thriller though. And a lot of that success comes from you being smart enough to know exactly where your strengths lie. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kilo Two Bravo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/11/kilo-two-bravo.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=KiloTwoBravo" />
    <published>2016-03-11T09:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-11T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/11/kilo-two-bravo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Legacy minefields. Now there’s some Newspeak for you. </p>

<p>This is the term used to describe the millions of unexploded mines that litter the landscape of Afghanistan—most of which are left over from the Soviet incursion in the eighties. </p>

<p>It was your job to faithfully reproduce the injuries that these anti-personnel mines inflict. And you were uncomfortably successful. Perhaps the most important fact about these mines is that they are designed to maim, rather than to kill, in order to drain resources away from engagement with the central conflict. But with the advances in battlefield medicine, unprecedented numbers of soldiers are surviving the kind of injuries that just a few decades ago would have almost certainly killed them. This is both a blessing and sometimes a curse.</p>

<p><em>Kilo Two Bravo</em> is the story of 3 Para, a small company of British soldiers tasked with overseeing a desolate piece of the Afghani landscape in 2006. A three-member patrol is moving through a dry riverbed—or wadi—when one of them steps on one of the aforementioned legacy mines. The rest of the story becomes an almost unbearably tense clusterfuck of failed rescue attempts, which make up the most uncomfortable two hours of film I have ever experienced. Once the first mine explodes (and there had been a number of foreshadowing events, including a camp dog missing a back leg) every footfall and stray rock is potentially fatal—or at least disabling.</p>

<p>Interestingly, for a war film, there is nary a shot fired in anger. In fact, the only close contact the company has with indigenous Afghanis comes very early in the film—in a moment that is almost absurdly benign. This is a film about the kind of damage that war does to the human body and it is relentless in that depiction. The work you did in mimicking the debilitating injuries these mines inflict was on constant display—and was made all the more effective by the level of authenticity the whole production exhibited. I have personally spent some time in and around the military and these were exactly the sort of conversations and personalities I’ve experienced—especially around the lower ranks. Right down to the slightly melodramatic tattoos and hyper-masculine displays. </p>

<p>Time and energy is spent fleshing out these real-life characters—the film meticulously reenacts an actual incident—and the film possesses an understated naturalism that made the whole experience impossible to distance oneself from. There is no engagement with larger geopolitical issues, nor does it feel like there is a particular agenda at work, other than to document, as lucidly as possible, a very specific set of horrifying circumstances.</p>

<p>But that doesn’t mean <em>Kilo Two Bravo</em> doesn’t raise the spectre of just how appalling these legacy minefields are. These men, as badly as they are injured, have a vast infrastructure to support them, however imperfect those institutions may be. From the medical treatment they receive onsite to the hospital and rehabilitation facilities they have access to when they return home (one of the soldiers, after losing a leg, returns to active duty with a sophisticated prosthetic) there is, at least, some hope to live close to a normal life.</p>

<p>Unfortunately mines don’t discriminate between an Afghan child and a combatant. Which couldn’t help but raise the question of how often this occurs when the people subjected to this kind of violent trauma don’t have access to modern military field medicine, or helicopter evac, or physical therapy, or advanced prosthetics. What kind of physical and emotional damage that will that inflict over the course of generations, and how can that do anything other than foster hostility and distrust?</p>

<p>So while I certainly respected the horror that these men endured and the heroism they displayed, I was left with a nagging question at the end of this film. What does it really mean when we use the term “legacy” minefield? </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Expectations vs. Revelation:  Deadpool vs. The Witch</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/9/expectations-vs-revelation-deadpool-vs-the-witch.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Expectationsvs.Revelation: Deadpoolvs.TheWitch" />
    <published>2016-03-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/9/expectations-vs-revelation-deadpool-vs-the-witch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>One of the more interesting bits of culture clash going on these days is the contrast between fan centric entertainments like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/12/deadpool.html"><em>Deadpool</em></a>, and films like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/the-witch.html"><em>The Witch</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/5/crimson-peak.html"><em>Crimson Peak</em></a>, or even last years’ <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html"><em>Under the Skin</em></a>—films that spring, unasked for, from a singular vision.</p>

<p>It is true that very few people were clamoring for a film like <em>The Witch</em>: a historical psychodrama involving puritans, witches and the most talented goat ever to grace the screen. Conversely <em>Deadpool</em> only became more than Ryan Reynolds’ wet dream because its creators were able to convince their studio that a significant audience for their product already existed.</p>

<p>I’m not sure there is a better way to describe the difference between a work of art and a competent piece of entertainment. One is something you weren’t even aware you needed, while the other’s success is often dependant on being exactly what you expected.</p>

<p>This difference is also why after-movie polling (things like Cinemascore and its ilk) are only useful in the case of films where the audience is sure of what it is they’re getting themselves into. <em>The Witch</em>, <em>Crimson Peak</em> and <em>Under The Skin</em>, critical darlings all, drew poor Cinemascore ratings at least partly because they confounded and subverted the expectations of a large segment of their audience. <em>Deadpool</em>, on the other hand, seems to have been what people wanted when they walked into the theatre.</p>

<p>One of the downfalls of tools like Cinemascore and even Rotten Tomatoes is they aren’t much use once you step outside a very narrow band of genre entertainments. In fact they’re usually misleading, because what they measure has far more to do with expectations than quality. A lot of the negative backlash directed towards <em>The Witch</em>, in particular, seems to come from people who were expecting a genre exercise like <em>Insidious</em>, and instead were faced with something far more complex and subtle.</p>

<p>Part of this negative response is born out of how pre-eminent trailers have become as a way to sell your film. While <em>Deadpool</em> was laser sharp in selling itself as a seditious and bold piece of R-rated insouciance, the film was actually designed specifically to fulfill audience expectations. There was nothing at all surprising about it—every bit of marketing was aimed at reassuring a potential ticket buyer that this is <em>your Deadpool</em>. And the degree to which that campaign was successful was measured in how much the promise of the trailers manifested in the finished product. But there is no way to encapsulate <em>The Witch</em> in a couple of minutes because most of what makes the film compelling is irreducible.  There is no elevator pitch that can really do it justice.</p>

<p>However, more and more it seems like some significant percentage of the audience are basing their enjoyment of a film on whether or not it fits a certain predetermined criteria. Part of this is because we have become used to consuming entertainment in a way that doesn’t necessarily require our full attention. So many people multi-task their entertainment time, scrolling through Twitter or Instagram while half-watching something, that it is perhaps too much to ask for some to engage with a film that doesn’t simply check some boxes. </p>

<p>This isn’t new. There has always been a push and pull between movies, books and music that comfort and reassure us with their familiarity and works that unsettle and upset, leaving us with far more questions than answers. And in some real ways the avenues open to individuals to create that second variety of art are easier to negotiate now than ever before. But that kind of work will also rarely pass a particular commercial threshold, because it requires more from audiences than most people are interested in investing. </p>

<p>So it isn’t necessarily a zero sum circumstance—<em>The Witch</em> and <em>Deadpool</em> both have their place. The squawking between tribes that seems to fuel much of social media is perhaps more sound than fury. But there is a disquieting narrowing that seems to be happening, at least in the conversation surrounding the two different modes. In the same way that political differences seem to have become more acute—at least partly abetted by the kind of insulating bubbles that social media seems to encourage, or at least facilitate—there seems to be the cultural equivalent lurking in the darker recesses of twitter, tumblr and all the other various forms of social media. And sadly, because most of this discourse seems like the ill-informed ranting of small children, I think a lot of people dismiss its power.</p>

<p>Cumulatively the group-think that often surrounds these kinds of social media conversations—so much of what is deemed “good” is the result of a kind of bullying sophistry rather than actual persuasion or even revelation—is becoming more and more influential. And it sometimes feels like the creative process is being steered by a committee of millions.</p>

<p>The critic and the audience are fundamentally important but their influence should be at a remove from the actual creative process, otherwise the whole procedure is circumscribed by exactly the sort of people who really shouldn’t have that kind of influence. How interesting can any kind of creative output be if it is nothing more than transcribing someone else’s idea—to the letter, if they had their way.</p>

<p>I tend to think that my responsibility as an audience member is more about broadening and simultaneously refining my own aesthetics. Improving my capacity to recognize something that has some value, after the fact, is far more useful than trying to directly influence the process as it occurs. </p>

<p>There is no way to game the system so that you will be guaranteed what you’re spending your hard earned money on is going to be what you expected, at least without seriously diminishing one of the things that makes any kind of art valuable—its capacity to surprise. So while I’m happy that <em>Deadpool</em>, and cultural products like it, are part of the landscape, I sure hope that particular species of entertainment doesn’t become so ubiquitous that it blots out everything else. Because, for me at least, if it ever does become that zero sum, I would rather a world filled with <em>The Witch</em> than its smart-assed, low stakes alternative.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>London Has Fallen</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/8/london-has-fallen.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LondonHasFallen" />
    <published>2016-03-08T09:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-08T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/8/london-has-fallen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Hey, Trevor. Me again. I know my <a href="https://www.google.ca/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=0ahUKEwikgv3i5LHLAhVhsYMKHXN6D5AQFggcMAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.dearcastandcrew.com%2Fcontent%2F2013%2F3%2F22%2Folympus-has-fallen.html&amp;usg=AFQjCNHRDgK8DaAME33G2YHXQyvdloGfkw&amp;sig2=sE2s24i6W-uuLYeGfbjDUg">overly enthusiastic response to <em>Olympus Has Fallen</em></a> might have come across a bit sarcastic, but it was nonetheless rooted in something very real: that film’s pedagogic adherence to action movie tropes. I gave you and the other filmmakers the benefit of the doubt, that it was big and silly and self-serious <em>on purpose</em>. And what I said about your score was absolutely true: if that film had been released two decades earlier, I would have worn out the soundtrack in my portable Discman.  </p>

<p>So how do I judge the quality of <em>London Has Fallen</em>, the much-anticipated (sic) follow-up? It is, objectively, by virtually any critical standard, a pretty terrible movie. But it’s objectively terrible in a different way than <em>Olympus</em>.</p>

<p>The actors, I think, would agree with me. Their performances suggest that they know they’re in a terrible movie. Morgan Freeman floats ethereally through the frame like an Andy Serkis motion-capture performance of Morgan Freeman. Even his voice seems devoid of its usual God-like gravitas; he has given more affecting performances in credit card commercials. Aaron Eckhardt’s earnestness is hard to watch, and poor Melissa Leo has approximately one word of dialogue, which is spoken overtop someone else’s line of dialogue, and contributes approximately nothing to the plot, her character, or even the general ambience of the scene that she’s half-acting in.</p>

<p>(But there’s something about Gerard Butler, isn’t there? That kind of steady, monotone, autistic machismo—it’s the sort of thing that can work perfectly as a stabilizing force at the center of movies like this. He’s certainly the most invested performer—it’s a shame his investment pays such small dividends.) </p>

<p>The scale of the film is hard to pin down, too. It thinks it’s an epic. The entire city of London is blown to pieces; historic landmark after historic landmark is consumed by dust and flame. But the CGI in those sequences is really rough, barely at par with what we regularly see in late night parodies of such sequences. In an era when relatively small films like <em>Ex Machina</em> are winning visual effects Oscars, it feels strange, in a wide-release film like <em>London</em> <em>Has Fallen</em>, to see the seams so clearly.</p>

<p>And the first half of this movie is <em>all</em> seams. It looks God-awful. Not just the effects, either. The cinematography, too, belies visual flair and narrative cohesion for cramming as much as possible into each frame. Director Babak Najafi’s aesthetic seems to be quantity over quality, but he’s never able to make sense of the chaos the way good action directors can.</p>

<p>It’s a shame that things begin so poorly, because later in the film there are a few rather neat sequences, one of which is a sort of poor man’s Emmanuel Lubiezki long-take as Butler leads a British special forces team down a barricaded back alley guarded by innumerable international mercenaries (the film is very careful to point out that, though the mastermind behind this plot is a vengeful brown person from somewhere in the Middle-East, the army he has recruited, which Butler gleefully and gruesomely dispatches, is culturally diverse). Sure, the whole scene is basically a story mission from Call of Duty, and the whip-pans and foreground pass-bys that stitch the takes together are pretty obvious—but, still, points for ambition. </p>

<p>Sadly, it’s the only place ambition is evident. Maybe that’s the biggest bummer about this movie. Even if the original movie was, as I feared, “a misanthropic wannabe-blockbuster drowning in its own manufactured gravitas,” at least it wanted to <em>be</em> something. <em>London Has Fallen</em> aspires to nothing more than simply existing. </p>

<p>But how does your score compliment this mess? By being a bit of a mess itself. I get the impression that you, like the cast, like writers Creighton Rothenberger and Katrin Benedikt, returned to the franchise because it was easy, not because you had anything new to say. But I can’t blame you for phoning it in. How do you bring rhythm and coherence to a movie that’s as arrhythmic and incoherent as this? Just like you can see the seams in the special effects, you can hear the seams in the score: those triumphant, patriotic horns; those ominous strings; that thrumming beat—it’s all cut-and-pasted, a bad mix-tape recorded off the radio. </p>

<p>Sometimes the generic can be satisfying. Store brand pasta sauce, a white T-shirt, adult contemporary pop music—we value these things for their lack of complexity. They address a simple desire, and they address it directly. <em>Olympus Has Fallen</em> might have been such a pleasure. I had hoped (perhaps foolishly) that it was one. <em>London Has Fallen</em>, on the other hand, proves that sometimes the simplest objectives are the easiest to screw up.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Zootopia</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/7/zootopia.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Zootopia" />
    <published>2016-03-07T11:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-07T11:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/7/zootopia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Yours is a fairly modern occupation, and one essential to good business-to-business relationships. Especially, say, if you’re partnered with Pixar, Lucasfilm, Marvel, ABC Television Studios, Walt Disney Parks and Resorts, and a slew of merchandising subsidiaries. However, the characters from The Magical World of Disney™ have almost always been removed from this reality. They normally exist in a pre-industrial age, free of commercial bombardment and even 20th century detached irony. That’s all changed with <em>Zootopia</em>.</p>

<p>Or has it? </p>

<p>It’s true that the most iconic films from Walt Disney Animation Studios, up to and including the smash-hit <em>Frozen</em>, were based on fairy tales and legends. Failing that, talking animals have usually filled the void to deliver that signature Disney <em>je ne sais quoi</em>. But in the past few years, stories have shifted into the contemporary world (<em>Wreck It Ralph</em>, <em>Meet the Robinsons</em>) or future-fantasy (<em>Treasure Planet</em>, <em>Big Hero 6</em>). And when that happens, audiences usually smile and shrug, willing to enjoy the film as an independent entity, while quietly re-assuring ourselves that these aren’t the “real” Disney films. This is not something a person like you would ever admit to clients. You would try to spin them from seeing what everyone already knows is true. Because before the public ever buys in, your marketing partners have to. </p>

<p>So I’m curious – how did you <em>really</em> sell <em>Zootopia</em>? The first point you would no doubt lean on, is the talking animals. That’s the entire conceit behind the film – it exists in a world where mammals have evolved into bipedal bureaucrats and blue collar workers. This world-building is almost effortlessly introduced with a clever mix of humour, character development, and foreshadowing. Hops, a young bunny, is putting on a school play, explaining how the world used to be divided between predators and prey. The savage nature of this ancient history is played for laughs as the small-town residents recoil at the gory details of the natural world. Fast-forward a few years when Hops decides to pursue her dreams and become the first rabbit on the ZPD police force, and the film quickly shifts into a typical underdog (underbunny?) story. </p>

<p>What happens next is much less in line with prince and princesses saving their people, and more of a typical buddy-cop movie with a crime procedural plot. Or, again, is it? Paired with a sarcastic and sly fox, voiced (of course) by Jason Bateman, the two follow clues to uncover a web of corruption in the city. It’s a much more <em>noir</em> story than something normally associated with the Disney brand, but yet it still adheres to the same principles of chosen soldiers protecting the kingdom. There are also plenty of smart re-assurances throughout that this story has a solid moral compass, even if the late reveal of a femme fatale does threaten to turn an entire generation against a cuddly species.  </p>

<p>A little more disconcerting is the integration of branded contemporary technology. While the product placement never felt entirely offensive, it did rub me the wrong way that an entire new society could be built, but the principle design of the iPhone would remain intact. That felt less about about making the audience feel at ease in <em>Zootopia</em> than it did your clients. </p>

<p>Most surprising of all, however, is the film’s barely hidden themes about racism and prejudice. While I’m sure you didn’t shy away from explaining these deeper levels of meanings to clients, where a “10% minority” is seen as being less evolved and more dangerous to the population, I can all but guarantee you assured them no actual ethnic stereotypes (such as, say, African animals and accents) would be employed to drive the metaphor home. And the film is richer as a result. </p>

<p>Ultimaely, the film made me laugh several times and moved me when it was supposed to. I felt a great sense of wonder when first being introduced to Zootopia, the city, even if the film never truly explored the world to its full potential. But that’s okay, this wasn’t <em>really</em> a Disney film, right? </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Triple 9</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/2/triple-9.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Triple9" />
    <published>2016-03-02T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-02T09:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/2/triple-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The first time I ever wondered <em>how the fuck did they do that without someone dying</em> was while watching <em>The French Connection</em>—William Friedkin’s gritty thriller about 70’s New York cops and their intersection with the heroin trade. The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2TVyJ-51jzc">scene in question</a> involves Popeye Doyle (played pitch perfectly by Gene Hackman) careening down Stilwell Avenue in Brooklyn, chasing a hijacked L train, while driving (insanely fast) in a commandeered Pontiac. It is, arguably, the most intense scene of its kind ever filmed.</p>

<p><em>Triple 9</em> had more than a few of those kinds of moments. There were two extended car scenes that were phenomenally well crafted, and the rest of the film incorporated the kind of practical effects that make this kind of crime thriller grounded and pleasingly retro. <em>Triple 9</em> begins with a tautly choreographed heist that culminates in an insane chase onto a crowded Atlanta overpass. And your work shone through. In the same way that the above mentioned scene in <em>The French Connection</em> completely immerses the audience in the moment—through sharp edits, great camerawork and most importantly, skilful and often dangerous stunt work—so too does <em>Triple 9</em>.</p>

<p>The rest of the film, specifically the parts where people speak, is more uneven. Director John Hillcoat has made a couple of great films—<em>The Road</em> and <em>The Proposition</em>—and a near miss, <em>Lawless</em>. <em>Triple 9</em> is more the latter than the former but it also suffers from a genre fatigue that particularly afflicts crime thrillers. Films like <em>Triple 9</em> are (fairly or not) often held up in comparison to <em>The French Connection</em> or Michael Mann’s <em>Heat</em> or even something like <em>Live and Die in LA</em>—another Friedkin film and the one <em>Triple 9</em> most closely resembles.</p>

<p>Part of the reason for this kind of close reading vs. what came earlier is that films like <em>Triple 9</em> have a very specific pedigree: urban, often morally ambiguous, and deeply connected with whatever city it’s located in (this time a very well articulated Atlanta cityscape). <em>Triple 9</em> is also filled with a kind of retrograde masculinity that is both compelling and weirdly out of time. This feels like a film that easily could have been made in the early seventies—which raises the bar substantially. Sometimes <em>Triple 9</em> meets that gold standard, and sometimes it doesn’t.</p>

<p>This version of Atlanta is a seedy place, populated by authority figures that are only differentiated from the criminals by their institutional veneer. That moral greyness is multiplied by a whole slew of shifting loyalties that, unfortunately, also slow the film down. Still, <em>Triple 9</em> has some great performances (Chiwetel Ejiofor, Luis Da Silva and Kate Winslet in particular), remarkable atmosphere, and a few tension filled set pieces. It just never really coheres as a narrative; there are just too many plot threads, especially for a genre that thrives best when it is laser sharp in its focus. </p>

<p><em>Triple 9</em> does have more than a few memorable scenes though, even if all of them are kinetic and mostly dialogue free—including Casey Affleck leading a SWAT team in a breach. There is a <em>Silence of The Lambs</em> night-vision-in-the-basement-tension to it that is completely effective. And it is in these moments that the film works best.</p>

<p>You certainly helped make those parts of the film thrum with a real threat and menace, Mickey, and because of that <em>Triple 9</em> rises above the crowd. But just barely.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Black Mark of the 2016 Oscars</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/2/the-black-mark-of-the-2016-oscars.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheBlackMarkofthe2016Oscars" />
    <published>2016-03-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/2/the-black-mark-of-the-2016-oscars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I feel for you. I really do. Not because you may or may not have been overlooked by the Academy Awards in the past, but because of how intensely you’ll be scrutinized and second-guessed by the public in the future.  No matter how worthy your performance, you will be accused of simply benefitting from affirmative action. </p>

<p>Your place in history will be tainted by the context of the 2016 ceremony.</p>

<p>Before the show even began, the 88th Annual Academy Awards were hijacked by a single issue: the lack of black nominees, particularly in the acting categories. As host, Chris Rock didn&#39;t just address the elephant in the room, he beat it into submission. He was so relentless that I&#39;m worried his approach will prove detrimental to the real goal. </p>

<p>Was he funny? Absolutely. Rock had plenty of well-crafted jokes about race and a signature pleasantly-angry delivery that was pretty much the ideal vehicle for the message. But every chance he had to advance the conversation was a detour right back on the same subject. For three and a half hours. At one point he almost managed to diverge from his manifesto – pointing out the progress and luxury of black people even caring about Academy Award nominations. But even that elegant point wasn&#39;t enough for him to pivot into new territory. Instead, every punchline, save maybe one about a lime green suit, was racialized. Even the Girl Guides gag was built on the back of white guilt. Focusing so exclusively on race may have been the easy – and even necessary – target, but I can&#39;t help but think there will be unintended consequences. </p>

<p>In the last decade or so, it seemed that a point had been reached where black actors who won or were nominated had earned it (at least the same way everyone else does—with expensive studio marketing campaigns). The world was swept away by Lupita N&#39;yongo. Barkhad Abdi stole the show with his rags-to-(temporary)-riches story. Everyone knows Chiwetel Ejiofor is going to be a star (and are relieved at how surprisingly easy his name is to pronounce). We were all charmed by 8-year-old Quvenzhané Wallis. Gabourey Sidibe was a breath of fresh air. I&#39;m not digging into ancient history here – these are just a few of the standouts from the past five years. </p>

<p>I fear that after the #OscarsSoWhite campaign, and after the way this year’s ceremony unfolded, the protests have taken progress a step backwards. Look at some of the most famous Oscar wins for black actors: Cuba Gooding Jr., Halle Berry, Jamie Foxx, Forrest Whitaker, Jennifer Hudson. They weren&#39;t the biggest stars at the time, but they still managed to be front-runner winners based on some semblance of consensus merit. It will be years before another black actor has that same luxury.</p>

<p>The conversation came from a good place. The Academy Awards are a high profile event, and are (among other things) an opportunity to reward excellence and bring light to lesser-seen films and performances. But by the time Cheryl Boone Isaacs, the President of the Academy was pleading for members to vote differently, personal aesthetic taste had been officially usurped by an instruction to enact social change. But is the Oscars the right place to do that? Doesn’t the real problem lie much earlier in the filmmaking process, as Wesley Morris <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/24/movies/oscars-so-white-or-oscars-so-dumb-discuss.html?_r=0">pointed out earlier this year in the New York Times</a>. </p>

<p>The worst part is, it will happen again. There will be another year with no black nominees. Statistically, it&#39;s almost unavoidable. What happens then? </p>

<p>Where can the protest honestly go from here? It&#39;s horribly unpopular to point out that black actors have been statistically over-represented in acting category wins since 2000 - even after the back-to-back years of no nominees - but <a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/prospero/2016/01/film-and-race">it&#39;s also true</a>. No one can expect a permanent seat for nominations - this isn&#39;t the UN Security Council. Unless of course, Chris Rock was somehow serious when he said the Academy just needed a black category. Otherwise, how on earth can you guarantee “diversity”? Actually, the term diverse is too broad. The hashtag might have been about whiteness, but therein lies another part of the problem. </p>

<p>Overshadowed in all the controversy are the unprecedented achievements of Latino Americans in the past several years. Alphonso Cuarón winning Best Director, back-to-back directing wins by Alejandro G. Iñárritu, three wins in a row by Emmanuel Lubezki for Best Cinematographer – three!! – which just happen to come after Chilean cinematographer Claudia Miranda’s win for <em>Life of Pi</em>. Even Lupita N’yongo is Mexican-born. Yes, black actors matter, but it’s a shame the media isn&#39;t paying equal attention to this Latin wave. </p>

<p>It&#39;s also worth saying that there were no egregious “black” snubs this year, though as mentioned, that is obviously part of the problem. <em>Creed</em> and <em>Straight Outta Compton</em> were better than expected, not exceptional. Feel free to <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/24/straight-outta-comptopn.html">agree</a> or <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/1/14/creed-is-surprisingly-the-best-film-of-2015.html">disagree</a> on that. But Sylvester Stallone didn&#39;t really deserve a nomination for his performance, either. It was quite obviously an accumulation of respect and acknowledgement for a character that has had an enormous effect on American pop culture over 40 years. To compare apples-to-apples, Nick Nolte was far more deserving of his supporting performance in <em>Warrior</em> a few years ago, but that film (which is just as good as <em>Creed</em>), was quietly left relegated to its “better than expected” status. Snubbed? Hardly. At least <em>Selma</em> felt like a contender, but even that film’s non-nominations felt more like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/26/is-it-oscarssowhite-or-just-oscarssowrong.html">missed opportunities</a>, which can be counted by the dozen across the board each year. </p>

<p>It might not feel like progress to have no black nominees, but is it perhaps an inevitable part of the process? </p>

<p>Let’s take a quick look into the future. You can be sure that Academy members are already penciling in <em>The Birth of a Nation</em> on their ballot. After premiering at Sundance last month, Nate Parker’s film about the Nat Taylor slave rebellion (which he both directs and stars in) already carries the weight of being the Great Black Oscar Hope. Months before seeing the film, every Oscar voter has implicitly been challenged by the president of their academy to vote for – or, by default, <em>against</em> – that film. </p>

<p>And they probably will give it some love. Because living through another three-and-a-half hour televised lecture is not high on anyone’s to-do list. The question is, will the film be deserving? Or will it be just good enough to meet requirements? Unfortunately for Nate Parker and you, other black actors and filmmakers destined to be nominees, we may never really know.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Shaun the Sheep Movie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/1/shaun-the-sheep-movie.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ShauntheSheepMovie" />
    <published>2016-03-01T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-01T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/1/shaun-the-sheep-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Trying to create unique character designs for stop motion animals has got to be a major challenge, especially when the titular lead in your movie is a sheep. If there is a species known for individuals that are indistinguishable from one another, it has got to be <em>Ovis aries.</em> They even wear the same goddamn sweater, every last one of them.</p>

<p>Yet you somehow managed to not only create memorable and engaging characters, but you also did so without relying on iconic voice actors. Instead, <em>Shaun The Sheep Movie</em> distinguishes one character from the next through sharp visual storytelling, a deft understanding of why silent films can still work, and your inspired design work. </p>

<p>When the sheep find themselves bored and slightly depressed by the endless monotony of farm life, they decide to take a day off. They incapacitate The Farmer and manage to neutralize Bitzer the dog (whose IQ is north of The Farmers) and settle in for a day of crap TV and smoothies. Surprise, surprise it all goes south and The Farmer ends up an amnesiac in the big city and—through a series of incidents that only make sense in this world—semi-famous in a career he had no idea he had been in training for his entire adult life. The rest of the film revolves around the sheep (often in people’s clothing) trying to restore balance to their universe.</p>

<p>There is a broadness to this film, a kind of Benny Hill energy, that isn’t for everyone. <em>Shaun The Sheep Movie</em> is certainly a film aimed at a particular demographic, and while well executed it is not more than the sum of its parts. Clever and relatively low stakes, without ever taking itself too seriously, it is just fine as an entertainment. There are even the occasional references to noir-ish films, like <em>Cape Fear</em> or (of course) <em>Silence of the Lambs</em>, which dot the stop motion landscape. There are also moments of real emotion, especially a subplot involving stray animals prepping for visiting day in the animal shelter, but everything is in a minor key. And rightly so, given the intended audience.</p>

<p>But the real charm of the film is almost entirely visual: the inventive slapstick, how each character is invested with its own distinct personality (there is stray dog that is the epitome of cute/ugly) and how the world is filled with small details, like Banksy-ish graffiti, is what makes <em>Shaun the Sheep Movie</em> memorable. </p>

<p>That it allows for anyone to enjoy it, whatever their age or native language, is both the strength of <em>Shaun The Sheep Movie</em>, and the thing that means it will never engage in the kind of complex narrative that something like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/26/the-boxtrolls.html"><em>The Boxtrolls</em> </a>features so prominently. As a film its ambitions are simply to entertain and amuse, and in that it is entirely successful.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/22/inside-out.html"><em>Inside Out</em></a> may have the Oscar, but that loss has nothing to do with you, Kate. Your work was subtle but memorable and was a major strength of this quiet, gentle film.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Gods of Egypt</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/29/gods%20of%20egypt.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=GodsofEgypt" />
    <published>2016-02-29T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-29T08:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/29/gods of egypt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As <em>Gods of Egypt</em> gets torn by critics of all kinds, I hope you’re sitting in a room, preferably a dark room with a glass of scotch and lit cigarette resting next to you. And in this room, I hope you’re contemplating the events in your life that brought you to pitch, fund, cast, and direct what I can only describe as the worst movie of 2016. The fact it’s only February, be damned.</p>

<p>Where shall I begin? </p>

<p>How about the obvious? 95% of your cast is Caucasian in a film based off Egyptian mythology. I know you’re fed up of hearing this and you’ve already<a href="http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/envelope/cotown/la-et-mn-gods-of-egypt-racial-miscasting-20151128-story.html"> apologized</a> for the oblivious casting decisions, but you need to hear it again. Your movie starts off with Bek, played by Brenton Thwaites, who has the acting ability of a stale piece of cheese. The moment he opens his mouth; you can’t help but notice a distinct British (even though he’s Australian) accent. This is followed by Dutch actor, Nikolaj Coster-Waldau having disagreements with Scottish actor, Gerard Butler. You went around the world to cast these men except the only place that actually mattered: Africa. The casting is not just misguided, it’s part of a proven recipe of failure. </p>

<p><em>Exodus: Gods and Kings</em>, another Egyptian epic plagued by white actors was a box-office bomb. No one for one second believed that Christian Bale was Moses, the Hebrew prophet. Just like they didn’t believe Emma Stone was Asian-American in <em>Aloha</em> and Rooney Mara was Native-American in <em>Pan</em>. Racial miscasts aren’t just insulting to deserving actors who are right for the role, they’re prime examples of why many high budget and high profile movies flat-out fail at the box office. </p>

<p>Racial blunders aside, <em>Gods of Egypt</em> is a plot-hole ridden nightmare. I couldn’t count how many times I leaned over to my girlfriend with a confused look on my face. There are so many egregious attempts at mysticism, I couldn’t tell up from down. The only way I could make sense of anything featured in <em>Gods of Egypt</em> was to start laughing and convince myself that I’m watching a comedy. I was very tempted to walk out but my occupation as a critic sometimes means I have to witness shit. So I stuck through it. </p>

<p>I witnessed you turn a mythical adventure about gods into a space odyssey, complete with flying robots, space vessels and strange, extra-terrestrial beasts—at which point I threw up my hands and said ‘fuck it’. </p>

<p>How could you let this happen? What compelled you to believe this was a good idea? Were you driven by creativity? Did you want to create something that turned the ‘sword and sandal’ saga on its head? Well, if that was your attempt, you failed. You ended up creating a film infested with banality. I sound surprised, but I shouldn’t be. You only hired Matt Sazama and Burk Sharpless, two of the three writers behind<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/3/the-last-witch-hunter.html"> <em>The Last Witch</em> <em>Hunter</em></a><em>—</em>a gothic cliché of epic proportions. </p>

<p>At least I feel like I’m a part of cinematic history. I got to see a movie that is the embodiment of everything that is wrong in Hollywood today: greed, intense CGI, nonsensical plot lines, cringe-worthy dialogue, and whitewashing. It’s a testament to how studio execs will turn a blind-eye to almost anything just so they can rake in money – which, by the way, won’t be much based on its opening weekend. </p>

<p>It’s safe to say I didn’t enjoy <em>Gods of Egypt</em>. I think it’s also safe to say you didn’t enjoy it. How could you? Any straight-minded director knows that <em>Gods of Egypt</em> is destined to fail. The script itself should have screamed failure. <em>Gods of Egypt</em> is a cash grab and nothing else; there is no substance, no enjoyment, and no excuses. You have created  a failure of biblical proportions. </p>

<p>2016 has been a year of firsts for me. I gave out my first<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/17/racing-extinction.html"> 5-star</a> review, and today, I give my first zero stars.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Risen</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/27/risen.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Risen" />
    <published>2016-02-27T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-27T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/27/risen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You are, bluntly put, a tool of Satan. Or the production arm of Sony studios dedicated to producing Christian evangelical films like <em>Faith Like Potatoes</em>, <em>Heaven is Real</em>, Kirk Cameron’s magnum opus <em>Fireproof</em>—and now the Kevin Reynold’s helmed <em>Risen</em>.</p>

<p>So, a tool of Satan. And Sony. But let’s face it, these days they are pretty much indistinguishable.</p>

<p>The problem with these films is not that they are Christian themed, it is that they are terrible. And they are terrible for a fundamental (heh) reason. It is almost impossible to square the circle of revealed truth and interesting filmmaking. You have to be remarkably adept as a filmmaker to produce a film whose ending everyone already knows (see: <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html"><em>Spotlight</em></a>). And Kevin Reynolds—he of <em>Waterworld</em> and <em>Robin Hood: Prince of Thieves</em>—is not that adept.</p>

<p>That this particular film echoes the ersatz biblical epic at the centre of the Coens’ latest <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar.html"><em>Hail Caesar!</em> </a>(there is almost a shot for shot sequence involving the first reveal of Christ as something more than a simple carpenter) doesn’t help either. The real problem is that the film is—from the very first frame—inexorably pointed in one direction. And the only way to make that uni-directional narrative structure engaging for an audience is to create some tension around the why of it. <em>Why</em> is this inevitable, <em>why</em> can this be no other way? And that can’t happen, since to answer that question requires the filmmakers to literally know the mind of God. </p>

<p>Which, you have to admit, is a pretty big ask of any piece of art. </p>

<p>What <em>Risen</em> does instead—rather than trying to come to grips with these big questions—is to introduce Joseph Fiennes as the Roman Centurion Clavius. A simple soldier charged with keeping order in Jerusalem in and around the year 33AD, Clavius returns from a hard day fighting the Peoples’ Front of Judea (or was it The Judean’s Peoples Front? I can never get those straight) to find Peter Firth’s Pontius Pilate all atwitter because he had to crucify some pesky messiah. This leads to a watered down CSI-like plot contrivance where Clavius tries to make sure that this Christ fellow isn’t more trouble dead than alive.</p>

<p>But, too late, he realizes that he is dealing with forces beyond his control—in this case the creator of the entirety of space-time. So the film pivots and becomes a journey to spiritual awakening for this bereft Centurion as he follows Jesus and his disciples to Galilee—with the fishing, and the ascension and whatnot.</p>

<p>Look, Affirm Films (even that title is vaguely cloying in its ostensible cleverness) I don’t give  a rat’s ass what you think is commercially viable or even what drives you to produce films in the first place. As an atheist I have very little interest in your particular worldview. But if you give me a movie that actually tries to come to grips with the animating reasons for faith, or how, in the face of all the evidence to the contrary, smart people still find a way to believe in the ineffable, I will watch the shit out of that. But no one is interested in your just-so stories that reveal nothing but the tautological nature of your specific beliefs, other than adherents of your particular interpretation of the Godhead.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>