<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-03T19:18:31Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Victor Frankenstein</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/3/victor-frankenstein.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=VictorFrankenstein" />
    <published>2015-12-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/3/victor-frankenstein</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Victor Frankenstein</em> is a film of such obvious conceits that you can almost hear the elevator pitch. “So… imagine Guy Ritchie directing a gothic romance/monster movie with homoerotic overtones.”</p>

<p>“Magic!”</p>

<p>The film is a tired and largely unimaginative retelling of Mary Shelly’s <strong>Frankenstein.</strong> The only potentially interesting change is that it is told largely from the POV of Igor—played gamely by Daniel Radcliffe. Even that conceit falls prey to your tendency to see every narrative as a way to stitch together various genre tropes in what you consider new and interesting ways.  </p>

<p>Max, you are the epitome of self-circumscription (pun intended). Your definition of screenwriting, as it currently exists on your IMDB page, all but guarantees what you write will always end up as creatively vacuous as <em>Victor Frankenstein,</em> or this year’s underwhelming <em>American Ultra.</em> You might want to consider that the emptiness of your work has more to do with your writing than it has to do with the environment you lament. </p>

<p>It is not the visual excess, or the overt genre busting, or the playful edges that exist in the protagonist’s relationship that drag this film into the swampland of mediocrity—the same mire that the aforementioned Ritchie’s <em>Sherlock Holmes</em> or even the <em>Underworld</em> series swim in. No Max, it is the relentless lack of any kind of real character that wrecks this film utterly. There is not one genuine human voice anywhere in this work.</p>

<p>James McAvoy, as the titular Victor, chews every single ounce of the set he can sink his teeth into in a failed effort to inject some heart into what is essentially a filmmaking exercise rather than an actual movie. That McAvoy fails miserably is not for lack of effort, but simply there is nothing here for him to grab hold of. The story is literally a series of obvious signposts that see it lurch forward with no more intention or purpose than if a drunk followed a single high-banked road. It is as if you think it is possible to just skip the basics of plot and character by using visual and literary tropes to stand in for these essential elements.</p>

<p>Every scene is played as a nod and a wink at what came before (if I see one more iteration of the “it’s alive!” moment I will remove my own eyes with an ice cream scoop). As a consequence, the film rests on the idea that its weight comes from what <em>Victor Frankenstein</em> references rather than creating it’s own center of gravity. There is no skeleton here to hang the meat of the monster on—so the whole thing falls to pieces.</p>

<p>For a film that works hard to incorporate every Frankenstein moment <em>ever</em>—from the Hammer films to a half-clever nod to Mel Brooks <em>Young Frankenstein—</em>there is an undercurrent of dismissal that permeates <em>Victor Frankenstein.</em> If you don’t understand or respect the underlying strength of the source material, then why bother Max?</p>

<p>In fact, if there is one question I would really be curious to ask you Max, it is this: why should any of us bother when you clearly do not?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Trumbo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/1/trumbo.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Trumbo" />
    <published>2015-12-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/1/trumbo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Combing through a script to verify historically accuracy, pointing out legal conflicts and continuity errors, making suggestions for alternatives—you don’t have an easy job, Malcolm. Even under the simplest of circumstances. And with <em>Trumbo</em>, you were given a script about one of the darkest moments in Hollywood’s history: the jailing and blacklisting of screenwriters accused of Communism in post-WWII America. </p>

<p>So, you know—no pressure. </p>

<p>I can imagine your conundrum. You have a real-life story that takes place during a time of great cultural and political change, colourful characters and toothsome subject matter, but the script itself is jokey, plodding, and decidedly small-screen in its scope. Do you speak up? Or do you just keep mum to stay employed? 
The real crime here is that 
this period of history – so bleakly fascinating, and featuring the most famous of all blacklisted writers -  is given such humdrum treatment.  </p>

<p>Dalton Trumbo was already living comfortably as one of the most famous scribes in Hollywood when his support of striking film workers singled him out as an agitator. With the threat of the Red Menace reaching panic levels, U.S. Congress called a hearing to determine which writers in Hollywood were Communists. Trumbo and nine others, dubbed the Hollywood 10, were held in contempt and jailed for their political beliefs. Once released, Trumbo continued writing under pseudonyms, employing his family as a scriptwriting sweat-shop to get his work out. When word leaked that Trumbo had, by proxy, written Oscar-winners <em>Roman Holiday</em> and <em>The Brave One</em>, it became difficult to keep Hollywood heavyweights like Kirk Douglas (<em>Spartacus</em>) and Otto Preminger (<em>Exodus</em>) away. Trumbo was determined to get his name back on the credits and off of the blacklist. </p>

<p>But the film <em>Trumbo</em> is nothing more than proof that we have reached “peak biopic”. It’s full of big name actors – Bryan Cranston as Trumbo, Helen Mirren as gossip-columnist Hedda Hopper, Diane Lane as Cleo Trumbo – all playing one-dimensional characters who meander through a by-the-numbers story intent on showing audiences <em>just how far we’ve come</em>. In your research you must have found so many interesting sub-plots and lesser-known players that could have given this film a little more depth. Instead, it strives so much to be an <em>Important _Film</em> that, much like the House Un-American Activities Committee, it becomes a victim of its own hubris.</p>

<p>The stuff the script gets right, like Trumbo’s huge personality and self-righteousness, are well-served by an actor like Bryan Cranston. It’s clear that his mugging on <em>Malcolm in the Middle</em> prepared him to chew some period-appropriate scenery. Director Jay Roach, better known for helming <em>Austin Powers</em> and <em>Meet the Parents</em>, doesn’t seem to know whether he’s making a comedy or a drama, and both elements suffer. His mis-casting of Louis CK as a doomed member of the Hollywood 10 proves this point. It seems like CK was given free rein to re-write his own dialogue. I feel for you, Malcolm; keeping up with his anachronisms must have given you writer’s cramp.</p>

<p>CK’s character is a composite, which in itself must have been a head-scratcher for you, considering the wealth of fascinating real-life writers screenwriter John McNamara could have brought to life (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0488057/?ref_=fn_al_nm_1">Ring Lardner Jr.</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0778789/?ref_=fn_al_nm_1">Adrian Scott</a>, to name just two). Or maybe you tried and failed to get clearance from the families who wanted nothing to do with this trifle.</p>

<p>The real heart of the story is supposed to be Trumbo’s difficult relationship with his family, who must suffer his verbal abuse while he writes in the tub, high on Bennies. But the more interesting relationship is the one he has with actor Edward G. Robinson, who sold out others to save his career. Michael Stuhlbarg looks nothing like Robinson, but he and Cranston generate the film’s most honest moments. One is a man who refuses to give up his ideals, the other is a man torn between doing what’s right and doing what’s best for him, and they’re both trying to stay alive in the cutthroat world of the Hollywood film industry. </p>

<p>It’s a shame that a movie about one of the greatest screenwriters who ever lived is so uninspired. A story like this deserves more gravitas, fewer guffaws. Instead of telling a serious story and injecting it with humour, we got a lot of slap-happy hijinks and over-the top moralizing. I’m not sure who exactly on this film should be held responsible for turning in such a mess, but I don’t expect you to name names. You’ve been through enough.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Good Dinosaur</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/29/the-good-dinosaur.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheGoodDinosaur" />
    <published>2015-11-29T07:00:01Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-29T07:00:01-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/29/the-good-dinosaur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re a staple at Pixar studios. You’ve used your expertise in 3D set modeling to provide Pixar with some of their most visually striking films, such as <em>Wall-E</em>, <em>Brave</em>, and <em>Up</em>. But your work on <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> is a whole new level of magic.</p>

<p>Watching a Pixar film always guarantees two things: a warm feeling in your chest, and tears. Pixar has mastered the art of playing our heartstrings like a fiddle. Try mentioning <em>Up</em> to anyone without being told how much they cried during the opening few minutes. You can’t, it’s impossible. Pixar has become synonymous with raw emotion, which is what makes your set modeling all the more impressive. You steered the conversation away from heart strings to eyeballs. </p>

<p>Inspired by the picturesque Jackson, Wyoming, your expert layering and texturing created an atmosphere so lifelike, moviegoers have had trouble distinguishing a computer-generated image from a real fly-over of Snow King Mountain. Your attention to detail and command of Presto, Pixar’s in-house 3D animation software, was paramount when modeling the varying densities in the foliage, the ripples in a calm body of water, and the precision ridges in distant mountains. It was awe-inspiring.</p>

<p><em>The Good Dinosaur</em> is Pixar’s second 2015 release—which is a pretty big deal. Following the monumental firestorm that was <em>Inside Out</em>, <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> takes place in an alternate universe where the asteroid that wiped out the dinosaurs, missed. After losing his father in a severe storm, Arlo, an easily frightened Apatosaurus, must learn to fight his fears and make his mark in a vast and unknown, yet beautiful landscape. </p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, every Pixar film is stunning, but the lumps in people’s throats are always part of the chatter as they leave the theatre—and <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> provides a hefty one. But the pace is a lot slower and a tad darker here than what we’re used to with a _Pixar vehicle. There are recurring themes of death and loneliness that will warrant some consoling for the younger viewers—as was the case for the two small children sitting behind me. Despite that, your environment is the main takeaway for audiences.</p>

<p>Your set design is further enhanced by the recognizable caricature design style of Pixar. The protruding, gangly shape of Arlo complimented your detailed landscape surprisingly well. They both shared the screen without stealing each other’s thunder. Speaking of thunder, I’d classify your set as a character of its own. Although Arlo meets a slew of characters on his journey, it’s his relationship with the force of nature that strikes a chord. Arlo is constantly interacting with nature, whether it’s scaling up a jagged cliff, powering through a strong river current or trembling as a thick storm cloud brews; the set is the ultimate test of dino manhood and your greatest work yet. </p>

<p>I wouldn’t be surprised if <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> has been your most rewarding experience. It was a pleasure to watch, but probably a bitch to create.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Steve Jobs</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/29/steve-jobs.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SteveJobs" />
    <published>2015-11-29T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-29T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/29/steve-jobs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Clearly, you’ve taken a completely different approach than writer Matt Whiteley did with the biopic <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/8/21/jobs.html"><em>Jobs</em></a>  in 2013. You didn’t for a second <em>try</em> to cram Steve Jobs’ entire life into a 122-page script. Rather you constructed your script as the most specific thesis paper imaginable. And though I longed for more flashbacks and chronological context (show –don’t tell, remember!), I have to commend you for succeeding admirably in your intention. Thank you for making an honest film about people, and not simply the glorification of one man. </p>

<p>Your script for <em>Steve Jobs</em> is distinguishably presented in three acts depicting the moments leading up to three separate product launches that define Jobs’ career –the 1984 launch of the Macintosh, the 88’ NeXT computers launch of the Black Cube, and finally the 98’ launch of the iMac (outlined narratively as failure, redemption, and victory). Like Walter Isaacson’s book, of the same name, and upon which the script is based, <em>Steve Jobs</em> is comprised almost entirely of dialogue. The most intimate conversations Jobs shares with those closest to him; his marketing exec. Joanna, his ex-girlfriend Chrisann, his daughter Lisa, the co-founder of Apple, Steve Wozniak, and of course, the only other CEO – John Sculley. </p>

<p>You had each of these characters confront Jobs with a concern or query during the opening launch. The topics of conversation persist throughout all three acts, cross-cutting between past and present and what could have been. It is through the persistence of these secondary characters, and their inability to be silenced that we as spectators come to learn about the other side of Steve Jobs. You subject the viewer to full disclosure – and apart from the occasional check in with Kate Winslet’s Joanna -  we remain present in the room with Jobs. </p>

<p>You captured the culmination of the film in a moment of truth between Jobs and Wozniak, the final sequence that truly defines the film’s purpose – to acknowledge the Apple 2 team. A request that ‘Woz’ makes and Steve refuses. Thankfully, <em>you</em> didn’t. Your secondary characters are stand-ins for what the “Apple 2 team” represents – characters that shed some light on who Jobs really is, 40 minutes before he steps out on stage. You let us stand and bear witness to the truth, before ethics are engulfed by sleek design, net result and thunderous applause. You have designed the operating system of this film as an <em>open</em> system. We’re given a lot to process, but modifications are condoned. So again, thank you Aaron Sorkin, for finally playing the second version of the same song. </p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong></p>

<p>Matt</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Creed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/27/creed.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Creed" />
    <published>2015-11-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/27/creed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The <em>Rocky</em> universe wouldn’t exist if it wasn’t for you. As an angst-ridden, out-of-work actor in 1976, you created the boxer Rocky Balboa as the ultimate underdog. The first movie was a fluke and almost didn’t happen. That it went on to win multiple Oscars Including Best Picture, then spawned a lucrative and beloved franchise is nothing short of miraculous. </p>

<p>I knew before walking into the theatre to see <em>Creed</em> that I would address this letter to you. How could I not? After successfully bookending the series with the surprisingly satisfying - albeit fantastical - <em>Rocky Balboa</em> in 2006, if <em>Creed</em> failed I could hold you to task for letting the franchise down again (ahem, <em>Rocky V</em>). If <em>Creed</em> was good, I could congratulate you for backing the right horse in director Ryan Coogler, and the right jockey in actor Michael B. Jordan. What I didn’t expect was that after seeing you reprise your role as Rocky that I would genuinely want to address this letter to you, the actor.</p>

<p><em>Creed</em> isn’t just the best <em>Rocky</em> film since the first one, it’s the best Rocky <em>you’ve</em> been in decades. </p>

<p>I’ve made no secret of my love for the <em>Rocky</em> franchise <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html">here before</a>, and of my love of boxing movies in general. My first review for DC&amp;C was of your forgettable <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/12/19/grudge-match.html"><em>Grudge Match</em></a>, a film that left such a foul taste in my mouth, it might be part of why your portrayal of an aged Rocky Balboa is such a revelation. But being a fan of the <em>Rocky</em> movies means accepting certain idiosyncrasies - cheesy dialogue, treacly sentimentality, repetitive montages, and a predictable plot – as part of the deal. This is why <em>Rocky Balboa</em> was such a great film to end the series on, as it eschewed many of the more cringe-inducing moments of the previous five films. But it’s also why I was reluctant to see <em>Creed.</em> I was worried that it would either stick too close to the franchise’s winning but tired formula, or go too far in a new direction and alienate the die-hards.</p>

<p><em>Creed</em> stands on its own, and as a lifelong fan, I am happy to stand behind it.  </p>

<p>We meet Adonis “Donnie” Johnson as a kid who has lost his mother and is stuck in juvie, where he is constantly in trouble for fighting. Donnie is taken in by Mary Anne Creed, widow of World Heavyweight Boxing Champion Apollo Creed, who knows he is the product of her husband’s infidelity. Flashing forward to present day, Donnie, though raised in the lap of luxury, gives up his cushy job to pursue his dream of being a boxer. Not finding anyone willing to train him in L.A., Donnie moves to Philadelphia and convinces Rocky to train him. When word of Donnie’s parentage leaks, he is invited to be the longshot on a ticket fighting against the reigning world champion, “Pretty” Ricky Conlon. </p>

<p>The set-up is a tweak on the original <em>Rocky</em> movie, where you were the unknown in a fight against the champ, except Donnie isn’t broke and fighting for a purse. Like Rocky, he’s fighting because it’s all he knows how to do. Of course there’s a love interest, but unlike your Adrien, Bianca is confident, successful, and determined, which makes her Donnie’s equal. She’s more than just a cheerleader, and it’s a welcome change. Obviously Coogler, who co-wrote the script with Aaron Covington, was careful to keep the spirit of the franchise intact, but he also borrows from one of my other favourite boxing films, <em>The Fighter</em>. Coogler makes the streets of South Philly look almost exactly like they did when you first ran through them in ’76, but he filmsthem like David O. Russell filmedLowell, Massachusetts – the camera constantly moving; the cars, storefronts and faces almost pastiche; the pace rapid-fire but steady; the background subliminally reminding Donnie of where he, and you, came from.</p>

<p>For the fight scenes Coogler cribs a page from Scorsese (but not specifically from <em>Raging Bull</em>, the boxing film upon which all others are measured). In one of the standout scenes, he films the match as one continuous take: through the crowd, into the ring with the corner men, and from Donnie’s POV. For the Big Fight Scene, Coogler follows behind you as you walk to the ring beside Donnie, your hand never leaving his shoulder. Because Coogler knows what we all know; boxing movies are really about relationships. They’re about family. We see it when Donnie puts the fight between Rocky and Apollo up on a big screen TV and shadow boxes his dad. And though it wasn’t as saccharine as <em>Rocky</em> fans are used to, we all know what’s coming – by the end, you’ve become the father Donnie never had. I couldn’t have predicted, though, that you would almost steal the whole movie.</p>

<p>Michael B. Jordon is the perfect fit for Creed, and the two of you have natural chemistry, perhaps because he was written to be more humble than his father. But <em>Creed</em> isn’t just about introducing audiences to a new hero, it’s about giving the old one his due. Even though you’ve owned the character of Rocky for close to four decades, and you wear him as comfortably as Rocky wears his trademark porkpie hat, perhaps you had become <em>too</em> close to him. This is the first <em>Rocky</em> film where you haven’t written your own dialogue, and the writers inject some much needed dimension into the character, which you deliver in spades. Rocky has his own fight here and you make it just as compelling as any he’s had in the ring. Donnie may be the muscle in this film, but you are the heart. </p>

<p>I’d like to end with a prediction, which you should take with a huge grain of salt, because I loved this movie so much so that my judgement might be clouded, but here goes: I predict you might just get an Oscar nom for this role. Think about it, the Academy creams over these kinds of stories, and I’m not just talking about the one up on the screen. If you get nominated for Best Supporting Actor, it would be the first time any actor has been nominated for playing the same character twice, years apart. I’m not saying it would be a lock.  <a href="http://www.indiewire.com/article/2016-oscar-predictions-best-supporting-actor-20150525">So far it looks like</a> you’d be up against some heavy hitters. But who doesn’t love a good underdog story?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Secret in Their Eyes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/26/secret-in-their-eyes.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SecretinTheirEyes" />
    <published>2015-11-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/26/secret-in-their-eyes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’ve made up a lot of Hollywood’s most famous faces, so I doubt that you’re ever star-struck. Still, you must get a bit of a thrill being hired to ply your craft on one of the most beautiful women in the world (even if this isn’t the first time). That is, it must have been thrilling until you read the script for <em>The Secret in Their Eyes</em>. Much of the movie has Julia not just glammed-down, but nearly <em>unrecognizable</em>. </p>

<p>This might seem derisive, but it certainly seems like the tired cliché of “pretty star gets drastic make-under in hopes of snagging an Oscar nom” applies here.  </p>

<p>In fact, the whole movie feels like one big “for your consideration” promo reel. </p>

<p>The original 2009 Argentinian film, <em>The Secret in Their</em> <em>Eyes</em>, already won the Academy Award for Best Foreign Film, and deservedly so. It manages a delicate but assured balance between being a taut thriller, unrequited love story, and nuanced character study that haunts you long after the credits have rolled. Americanizing <em>The Secret in Their Eyes</em> is an idea that works better in theory than in practice. Like the folly of trying to apply makeup in a speeding car, all you end up with is a pretty mess. </p>

<p>The foundation is there: it’s 2003, Ray is an FBI agent sent to L.A. to work for the newly formed Department of Homeland Security. His partner is Jess, a sharp investigator and dedicated single mom. When Jess’ daughter Carolyn is discovered murdered beside a mosque the team has been investigating, Ray’s failure to bring the murderer to justice threatens to upend the Department’s operation. Twelve years later, Ray, returns to L.A., convinced he has found Carolyn’s murderer, and enlists the help of Claire, his former co-worker and unrequited love, who is now the District Attorney.</p>

<p>This movie <em>looks</em> good. Too good. The Homeland Security offices are artfully disheveled, the walls covered in boutique hotel paintings, the file boxes stacked just so; it <em>should</em> seem real, yet it all somehow feels as though the art department has spray cans of Hollywood Gloss with which they liberally coat each set. Even the grit feels faux. The leads, Chiwetel Ejiofor as Ray, and Nicole Kidman as Claire, are fantastic actors and even more fantastically good looking, but they share exactly zero chemistry, rendering their will-they-won’t-they subplot as translucent as your finishing powder. </p>

<p>Julia Roberts does stand out here—and I don’t just mean figuratively. When the film flashes back to 2003, we see the Julia Roberts audiences know and love – pretty, perky: America’s Sweetheart. When the film follows her into present day, it’s painful to see the effect the events of the film have had on her. You give her dark circles under her eyes, a sallow complexion and hollow sockets. Jess is a shell of her former self. She is hunched over and walks like a wounded animal. Robert’s performance of a long-grieving mother is heartbreaking, yes, but we’re never able to forget that it’s <em>Julia Roberts</em>. As anyone who rolled their eyes at the no-makeup selfie trend would know, it’s obvious when something is trying too hard to look “real.” </p>

<p>Writer/Director Billy Ray has had success in the past with cerebral adult thrillers, namely his work on <em>Shattered Glass</em>, <em>State of Play</em>, and <em>Captain Phillips</em>, all of which boasted stripped-down veracity and multi-layered characters searching for some intangible truth. None of that honesty is on display here. The dialogue tries alternately to be flip and trenchant, and often fails at both. Danny Moder’s cinematography does it’s best to operate around the bland staging, and if it wasn’t for the top-notch cast – which is rounded out by Alfred Molina, Dean Norris, and Michael Kelly – the whole thing would read as a particularly convoluted, high-pedigree police procedural. </p>

<p>When you were a very little girl did you ever put makeup on yourself? The lipstick ends up clownish, the eye shadow is exaggerated, and the blush is severe. Which isn’t surprising when the elements are applied with such a heavy hand. It seems the same technique was employed here: so much fuss to make something that was already beautiful less remarkable. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Night Before</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/23/the-night-before.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheNightBefore" />
    <published>2015-11-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/23/the-night-before</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>On the night before Christmas</p>

<p>three ride-or-die friends</p>

<p>meet for annual hijinx</p>

<p>they’ve decided to end.</p>

<p>The lawyer, the slacker,<br>
the big football star</p>

<p>have outgrown their mic rocking</p>

<p>at the karaoke bar.</p>

<p>But they have one last night</p>

<p>to raise their beer mugs,</p>

<p>in a Redbull stretch limo</p>

<p>with a box full of drugs.</p>

<p>While some will be cheered </p>

<p>by the usual Yule tropisms, </p>

<p>the film has a weak, </p>

<p>unsteady sinus rhythm.</p>

<p>Celebrity cameos </p>

<p>don’t make it worth the hassle</p>

<p>to find the Nutcracka Ball</p>

<p>(this movie’s Whitecastle).</p>

<p>There is one clear standout,</p>

<p>a hands-down scene stealer,</p>

<p>and that’s Michael Shannon</p>

<p>as a weirdo weed dealer.</p>

<p>I wanted much more </p>

<p>from this fine all-star cast</p>

<p>than half-assed homages</p>

<p>to Christmas flicks past.</p>

<p>There’s a vague doping subplot</p>

<ul>
<li>why is that even there?!</li>
</ul>

<p>It’s random, out of place,</p>

<p>and I just didn’t care.</p>

<p>The good jokes don’t land,</p>

<p>the bad jokes drag on,</p>

<p>and the plot threads go scattering</p>

<p>hither and yon.</p>

<p>This film is a let-down,</p>

<p>I sadly concluded – </p>

<p>like a toy under the tree</p>

<p>with no batteries included.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The 33</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/23/the-33.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=The33" />
    <published>2015-11-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/23/the-33</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I love disaster movies, don’t you? Especially the ones “based on actual events”. I love disasters so much that when I saw <em>Titanic</em> I planned to nap through the first half’s lovey-dovey romantic subplot and told my friend to wake me up for the iceberg. I’m such a fan of the TV show <em>Mayday</em> that I actually have a <em>favourite plane crash</em> (Potomac River, Air Florida, 1982). There’s something about watching a dramatized real-life horrific event that appeals to my love of the underdog. It’s fascinating to watch regular people find the strength to survive. But I have a feeling that you watch these movies with a different perspective.</p>

<p>You’ve worked on other films and television series, but I bet doing health &amp; safety for a film whose entire plot relies on the very lack of workplace health and safety gave you an added sense of purpose. In 2010, 33 Chilean miners were trapped more than a kilometer underground after a series of mine collapses. Miraculously, they survived for more than two months before their heroic rescue. <em>The 33</em> chronicles their story.</p>

<p>You don’t have a job that allows you to blithely gloss over details and say, “meh, good enough”, but it seems the writers of <em>The 33</em> don’t share that sentiment. Ordinarily I have a very difficult time overcoming a conceit which sees a group of Spanish actors, playing Chileans, speaking English with Spanish accents. I cringe when the first few minutes of a film sets up so many clichéd scenarios – the miner two weeks from retirement, the miner considering changing jobs before the birth of his child, the miner who has the day off but volunteers to work anyway – that I half expect a baby-faced soldier to pull out a picture of his “girl back home”. But I forgive these trivialities the same way I forgave white people playing Spanish people in <em>Alive</em> and <em>The Impossible,</em> because, impending disaster!</p>

<p>You are responsible for assessing risks, identifying hazards and recommending safety measures. Your job is the most important on the set, but you still have to answer to the director, and hope that he or she is just as committed to the safety of the cast and crew. In <em>The 33</em>, your job is done by Lou Diamond Phillips, as the safety foreman Don, his complaints to the higher ups about an impending catastrophe have fallen on deaf ears. When the inevitable happens, it is indeed terrifying, but quick. The real drama begins after the miners realize they are trapped with only enough supplies for ten men for three days. </p>

<p>Above ground, the families, led by a defiant Juliette Binoche as Maria, the estranged sister of one of the miners, demand the foot-dragging government spare no expense in attempting to free the miners. But after more than two weeks with no luck, everyone is about to give up hope. Except for “Super” Mario Sepulveda played by Spanish Harrison Ford, Antonio Banderas. As the de facto leader, Mario keeps the men’s spirits up, divvies up their dwindling supplies, and argues with Don over what they should do next. In one of the film’s best scenes, Mario serves up the last of the food and we are treated to a dream sequence involving their wives and girlfriends feeding them their favourite dishes. Normally this kind of chauvinistic scenario would make me cringe, but it was so well imagined and executed that it intensified the impact of the miner’s dire situation, and humanized the otherwise flat characterizations. </p>

<p><em>The 33</em> gets really interesting when the miners are discovered alive. This is when the whole world gets involved. Engineers, oil rig drills, extraction experts and news pundits from around the globe all have suggestions about how to get the men out. I wonder, did you watch the drama as it unfolded in real time and imagine how you might proceed if you were there? The collapse has displaced a rock right beside the miner’s position that is twice the size of the Empire State Building and twice as hard as granite. Even though the miners are able to receive supplies and communicate with their loved ones, it becomes apparent that the risks of attempting a rescue may put the miners in even more danger. </p>

<p>If a “true story” disaster movie is really good –think <em>Touching the Void</em>, or <em>United 93</em> - it doesn’t matter if you know the outcome. Kind of like your job – you know you’ve doing it right when there are no surprises. But keeping up an exciting level of suspense is only half the battle. Perhaps because the story of <em>The 33</em> is still fresh in the public consciousness, or perhaps because it relies more on sentimentality than on veracity, it manages only a pedestrian level of tension. <em>The 33</em> is a predictable film with a lot of heart. Just wish the filmmakers hadn’t played it so safe.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Room</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/23/room.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Room" />
    <published>2015-11-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/23/room</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I should really schedule an appointment to see you, but that might be tough. Between publishing books on complex trauma, holding workshops across North America, and coaching soon-to-be A-list actresses like Brie Larson, you’ve got a full dance card. Still, I need to talk to someone.  <em>Room</em> is a hard film to shake. Which is strange - most of your work is about helping people out of incredibly dark places. But in this case, you did the opposite. You threw us into it.</p>

<p>Thank you.</p>

<p>It’s a testament to director Lenny Abrahamson’s approach that he brought you on set. After his previous film <em>Frank</em>, a lighter look at a self-imposed form of entrapment, Abrahamson obviously wanted to help his team understand what it would truly be like to be locked in a room for seven years. Thankfully, not many people can relate. Having the book’s original author Emma Donoghue adapt her original story into a screenplay was another way to preserve the material’s emotional authenticity. But the success of <em>Room</em> comes down to tone and mood – which, I’m sure you appreciate, can make a world of difference when dealing with difficult subject matter.</p>

<p>I went into <em>Room</em> with some weighty expectations. My populist taste puts a lot of credence in the audience award at the Toronto International Film Festival – not to mention the fact I have a well-documented affinity for Canadian film. So imagine my glee at finally seeing a film that checks both those boxes. Not loving it would have been its own personal trauma – or at least an existential crisis. And while it admittedly took me some time to calm the cheerleading voice in my brain and judge the film on its own merit, I was unquestionably swept up with emotion at the exact moment I was probably supposed to – the truck.  In a scene loaded with re-traumatizing images, but also life affirming hope, it was to my surprise delight, only partway through the journey.</p>

<p>See, in the same way someone in recovery tries to avoid triggering flashbacks, my routine is to literally avert my eyes and cover my ears during previews for films I plan to see. I don’t want to be watching a film with images of the trailer running through my mind, anticipating upcoming plot twists or character developments. Like Larson’s character, I want to create a new reality free of expectations to re-discover child-like wonder. Now that I have a kid getting old enough to watch films, again, like Larson’s character, that’s getting easier. Not that I would bring him to see <em>Room</em> – that will ignite conversations I hope are still years away. But for the adult, parental me, it was certainly more uplifting and entertaining than a stale lecture on the subject of traumatization (no offense). And connecting to this material was much more of a joy than I expected.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/20/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-2.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheHungerGames:Mockingjay-Part2" />
    <published>2015-11-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/20/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You evil, evil bastard. All this bloodshed over the course of four long years has just been a game to you, hasn’t it? Yeah sure, you were just doing your job, using the manipulated spectacle of teenage deaths to pacify the masses, but did you ever stop to think about the consequences of your involvement in the project? No, really. I’m not just comparing you to the evil game makers within the world of <em>The Hunger Games</em> – I’m talking about your real-life job with this franchise. The one where you and your merchandising masters cram in on-screen action that’s more appealing to the consumer video game market. I could feel your sweaty little button pushing fingers everywhere.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, I didn’t need the love triangle storyline between Katniss, Peta and Gale dragged out any more than it has been. I actually looked forward to the much-promised action sequences of storming the Capitol and wreaking retribution against President Snow. The only problem is, there came a point where I could feel the filmmakers hearts weren’t in this story for the thrills. The action was often treated like a necessary evil to appease the demands of big budget studio filmmaking. </p>

<p>Look no further than the film’s reverse action movie structure, which opens small and closes small, only cramming in action to the middle sections to pad the already stretched exposition. In almost every other action series, that formula is reversed. <em>Mission: Impossible</em>, James Bond,<em>Fast &amp; Furious</em> – they all rely on opening with a grand stunt to set the stage for what’s to come. <em>Mockingjay,</em>both parts, actually, go in the opposite direction. Both cold opens linger on the psychological effects that killing and manipulation has had on its characters. It’s actually a refreshing change of pace. But it also is an implicit statement of where the heart of the franchise lies – and it is surely not in escaping mutated monsters that are given absolutely no context within the film. In fact, I have a strong feeling they were cooked up by one of your gaming programmers as an easy-to-kill foe that can be cloned and repeated in whatever video game spin-off this series spits out.</p>

<p>The rest of the action, however, feels much truer to the spirit of the franchise. In theory, <em>Mockingjay Part 2</em> finds a way to shoe-horn in the idea of violence as spectacle with President Snow saying he’ll film the invasion and subsequent quashing of the rebels to help propagandize his cause. So the hidden booby-traps spread around the city are at least motivated by some internal logic, and lead to some exciting and consequential scenes. But action in the<em>The Hunger Games</em> series is only effective as an expression of love, and that gets harder to swallow when Katniss starts engaging in <em>Avengers</em>-level invincibility against the sewer monsters (who, truth to be told, look pretty great).</p>

<p>It’s probably not fair for me to pin all the film’s short comings on an admittedly small section of the film. The series definitely suffered by splitting up these final two films, and expecting a casual audience to have thought of this world at all in between. So by the time I felt caught up with all the personal dynamics, it already felt too late. Too many characters were only given a token amount of screen time, to the point their inclusion felt more like fan-service than smart storytelling. Not to mention the eeriness of seeing a resurrected Philip Seymour Hoffman sleepwalking through a thankless role (with only one situation that felt like a CGI manipulation). </p>

<p>The film was strongest when it rejected the idea of the games altogether. Plotlines about refugees and asylum seekers from the Capitol can’t help but evoke reminders of the people from Syria, and it’s a credit to <em>The Hunger Games</em> that none of these issues are given an easy solution. The rejection of being treated like pawns, even when it’s proven effective, elevates the material beyond what you’d expect to be directed at teenagers. It would have been nice if you and your team had followed suit.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>