<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-12T16:11:36Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Deadpool</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/12/deadpool.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Deadpool" />
    <published>2016-02-12T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-12T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/12/deadpool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My plan was to address this letter to <em>Deadpool’s</em> title sequence designer<em>—</em>after which I would make some clever comments about how, if nothing else, the film had a kind of internal integrity worth recommending. Then I was going to compare <em>Deadpool</em>’s opening credits—which were absolutely true to the tone of the film throughout—to other, more opaque, and nonrepresentational (to the point of distraction) opening sequences, like David Fincher’s <em>Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em>.</p>

<p>All this was going make the larger point that <em>Deadpool</em>, while essentially being the lucid dream of some really clever, but utterly perverse, 13 year old boy’s id, was at least fundamentally honest about its intentions from the start.</p>

<p>Anyway, that whole conceit kind of swallowed its own tail when I found out that you were a first time director who had largely made his bones as the creative force behind Blur Studios—which, among other things, had fashioned the opening titles for David Fincher’s version of <em>Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em>.</p>

<p>So instead of that I will go with plan B—where I point out that along with the writing team from <em>Zombieland</em> (Rhett Reese and Paul Wernick), you have managed to create a film that is flat out fun to watch. The opening titles skewer the film’s own narrative premises (the usual superhero origin story tinged by dark and gritty regret) without actively sneering at the larger framework (superhero movies in general)—and, in doing so, they announce that the movie we are about to see is as happy to laugh at itself as anything else, while still managing to follow a narrative compelling enough to carry us through the various inevitable discursions. </p>

<p>Oddly enough, the structure of this review has ended up mirroring what <em>Deadpool</em> does so well, which is comment upon its own story as it is occurring. This kind of narrative balancing act is really delicate to maintain—and probably only viable when the story is so boilerplate that it requires very little effort to follow. So while <em>Deadpool</em> the movie is a uniformly fun ride, it really doesn’t hold together under scrutiny. The only way to get anything at all out of this film is simply let it wash over you without spending too much time examining all the moving parts.</p>

<p>This is the kind of movie that probably was going to happen sooner or later—a late period superhero film that lives and dies on the expectation that the various tropes being skewered are so thoroughly inculcated that they don’t need much explanation. <em>Deadpool</em> is built upon the probability that the people watching it are at least moderately familiar with what it’s lampooning, so in some significant ways it is kind of a niche market. Like <em>Zombieland</em> before it, <em>Deadpool</em> is a fine confection—like a really good cheesecake. So if you like cheesecake, you’re good. If you think cheesecake is a pointless, empty collection of fat and calories, I wouldn’t bother.</p>

<p><em>Deadpool</em> has very little to add to a larger cultural conversation and even as a story it is pretty small stakes, but, in this case, these are both definitely points in its favor. Because I think you and your team seem to have remembered something a lot of other people have lost track of—comics and the movies they spawn can be fun just for the sake of it. So thanks for a night of just that, Mr. Miller. And I look forward to whatever you next put your hand to.</p>

<p>As long as it isn’t yourself. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Winter On Fire: Ukraine’s Fight for Freedom</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/10/winter-on-fire-ukraines-fight-for-freedom.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=WinterOnFire:Ukraine’sFightforFreedom" />
    <published>2016-02-10T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-10T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/10/winter-on-fire-ukraines-fight-for-freedom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Normally I’m suspicious of large groups of pale young people gathering together to subvert what they see as a repressive regime. Too often—in a North American context at least—such an insurgency is embodied by Oberlin college students boycotting the campus cafeteria, because they believe serving General Tso’s chicken is a type of <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/news/2015/12/oberlin-protest-dining-hall-food">cultural appropriation</a>. </p>

<p>But in your case, there’s no doubting the righteousness of your cause or the courage you have shown in the face of real adversity. As with the recent Arab Spring (so starkly portrayed in the documentary <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/25/the-square.html"><em>The Square</em></a>—a direct antecedent to <em>Winter On Fire</em>) this is the story of a populist uprising, largely propelled by politically engaged university students. Like the Tiananmen Square protests in 1989 or the Paris riots of 1968, these spontaneous, populist revolutions were in response to politically repressive (or otherwise unresponsive) regimes. All of these movements also began as small, student lead protests, but soon engaged a much broader coalition, from former soldiers, to union members and then schoolteachers, clergy and finally, just plain folks.</p>

<p>Both the Arab Spring and the Ukrainian uprising share one significant difference from both Tiananmen and the ’68 riots: they were largely facilitated by social media platforms like facebook and twitter. This made coordination of protests much more efficient as well as allowing for the widespread dissemination of video. This footage, often shot on mobile phones and mini-cams, was effective in demonstrating how disproportionate and brutal the government response was to what were initially peaceful protests, not to mention providing an enormous reservoir of primary material for the filmmakers. </p>

<p>Much of <em>Winter on Fir</em>e revolves around this primary footage, which is interlaced with after the fact interviews with various participants—and these interviews are often shot in the same locations as the events they are describing. As a documentary <em>Winter On Fire</em> also makes clever use of graphics, specifically CGI maps that help paint a remarkably lucid picture of the geography in question. These maps are effective in helping describe what was a fluid set of circumstances—significant events would occur simultaneously, in complicated urban environments, and they are presented here in a way that was remarkably useful in understanding the larger narrative.</p>

<p>This documentary has an obvious bias and if someone is interested in a more complete understanding of the appallingly complicated clusterfuck that is European-Ukrainian-Russian relations, <em>Winter on Fire</em> is probably more useful as supplemental material than as a primary source. Still, most western viewers will likely side with the protesters. There is a rare kind of clarity to the issues in question, and some of the footage is both horrifying and inspiring: unarmed protesters, often carrying makeshift metal shields, being attacked by government snipers—yet still continuing to move forward. Kids of fourteen or fifteen dressed in makeshift armor, cooking pot helmets and sheets of metal used as ersatz bulletproof vests, all looking like they came from an illustrated version of Alice In Wonderland.</p>

<p>The interviews themselves are filled with real characters. There’s a Muslim cleric who looks like an accountant from Des Moines, an Orthodox priest who I’m not sure is old enough to shave, and a crusty, Andy Rooney-looking, left-leaning, Ukrainian academic who accuses the regime of having “unleashed a bacchanalia of dictatorship”. <em>Winter on Fire</em> is, by turns, an oddly giddy and sometimes tragically serious film. But the real centerpiece is you, the university and high school students that started the whole thing. Engaged, committed, well informed, and serious about your (and your children’s) future, you saw the promise of European economic and cultural membership, and chose, at great risk, and often with mortal consequence, to defy the governments attempts to link the Ukraine with Russia.</p>

<p>To see that kind of commitment is a substantial slap in the face to the surface level and self-interested squalling that often passes for political speech in North America. And it’s particularly damning in contrast with the kind of stupidities that seem to occupy a particular white, upper-middle-class segment of our universities. There is a lot to admire in this film, but nothing more so than kids like you who care enough about abstract concepts like democracy and free speech to risk life and limb in support of them.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pride and Prejudice and Zombies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/9/pride-and-prejudice-and-zombies.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=PrideandPrejudiceandZombies" />
    <published>2016-02-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/9/pride-and-prejudice-and-zombies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I extend to you my deepest admiration for your efforts in the motion picture offering <em>Pride and Prejudice and Zombies</em>, and hope this letter finds you in the pink of health. I had feared the film would cause offense and upset to those who think fondly upon that greatest of literary works wrought so cleverly by Miss Jane Austen, but you will be relieved to hear my fellow filmgoers appeared to find it most diverting. </p>

<p>I must admit to having no real fondness for the work of Miss Austen. While her artful turn at social satire cannot be faulted, I have never managed to rally any real interest in tales centered upon the subject of marriage - be they tales of ladies consumed with the desire to marry, or of ladies chafing obstinately at the prospect of it. By peppering the work with an army of the undead, the film lends a certain bite to the trials and tribulations of the five Bennett sisters with their beauty, bearing, and BRRRAAAAAINS (forgive me).</p>

<p>At first blush, it appears that the bones of dear Miss Austen’s novel have been well-preserved, with entire scenes and conversations between characters bearing a familiar ring. Thrusting the characters into battle with zombie hordes is a rather entertaining means of adding flesh to bone, and a refined, if rather plodding tale suddenly bares its teeth. The sight of well-bred young ladies unsheathing daggers from between the soft folds of their pretty gowns appeared to heat the blood of many a gentleman audience member, a hard thing to begrudge the dear fellows, albeit highly improper. </p>

<p>Just as bland cooking is brightened by the adding of spice and seasoning, I have often felt that <em>Pride and Prejudice</em> would benefit greatly from the addition of subversive behaviours to liven up the interactions between its characters - a ribald word, untimely flatulence... <em>anything</em> that would prevent me from dozing off in the middle of all those tediously repressed exchanges. I must, therefore, applaud the use of violence toward this end. Turning Mr. Darcy’s failed proposal of marriage to Miss Bennett into an antique-smashing dust-up between the two infuses the scene with unprecedented passion – bravo indeed. </p>

<p>Alas, whatever bite there may be at the start, the film is rendered toothless by the finish. The incongruous presence of zombie creatures and well-born country girls up to their corsets in gore is an entertaining novelty at first, but becomes repetitive by the halfway point. I fear the boring, marriage-obsessed plot is ultimately not saved even by a whist party that ends in smashed skulls and guests spattered with the viscera of the undead. That being said, I lend my voice in support of introducing zombies to other well-loved period pieces; <em>Northanger Abbey and Zombies</em> would be marvellous. <em>Downton Abbey and Zombies</em> would, in modern parlance, be simply off the hook. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Brooklyn</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/4/brooklyn.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Brooklyn" />
    <published>2016-02-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/4/brooklyn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What I find compelling about the films you’re involved with is their lucid portrayal of a particular species of love. In <em>High Fidelity, About A Boy, Wild,</em> and now <em>Brooklyn,</em> love is depicted as an effort to pay attention, and to understand without judgment. In the worlds you create, love is about seeing the person in front of you, and accepting that they’re probably as flawed a creature as you.  </p>

<p>This is something John Cusak’s Rob Gordon is slow to learn in <em>High Fidelity</em>, and Hugh Grant’s Will Freeman is perhaps even slower to comprehend in <em>About A Boy</em>. It is a truth that evades Reese Witherspoon’s Cheryl—especially when it comes to herself—for almost the entirety of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html"><em>Wild</em></a>. But in <em>Brooklyn,</em> this truth seems to be integral to Saoirse (sounds like inertia) Ronan’s Eilis from birth. Consequently, the film is far more concerned with the impediments that life throws in front of all of us—in our search for love and belonging—than any kind of interior journey.</p>

<p>Set in the early 1950’s, <em>Brooklyn</em> is very much Eilis’s story. We follow her from her native Ireland, where she is completely unfulfilled, to Brooklyn, New York—and what is essentially a halfway house for young, unmarried women. There she is shepherded by an Irish priest—played benevolently by Jim Broadbent in a role he could have sleepwalked through, but didn’t—until she finds employment in a Macy’s-like department store.</p>

<p>The rest of the film concerns itself with Eilis and her new life—the ups and downs, ins and outs of a young women discovering how the world operates. In many ways, this film is boilerplate in its plot construction, but it is never hackneyed. This is due to the restrained tone (there is never a scene that feels heightened or contrived), uniformly strong performances and the superb attention to detail in the costume and set design. However, what really makes <em>Brooklyn</em> special is Ronan and her tremendous presence. She is a remarkable actress and entirely too self possessed for someone so young. So many moments in this film are carried by a simple gesture or a subtle tell in Ronan’s demeanor. Couple this rare ability with her talent for infusing dialogue with a quiet veracity, and Ronan’s performance becomes something special to watch. </p>

<p>While Eilis’s burgeoning love life is what drives the plot, it is the small, idiosyncratic details that you include that help differentiate this film from a thousand others. The most entertaining of which is Mrs. Keogh—the tyrannical matriarch of the boarding house—portrayed in a marvelously cranky turn by Julie Waters. She is a both a <em>character</em> and the same time a fully realized human being— a feat of writing that is vanishingly rare in any medium. As a result of this kind of nuanced work, moments that could have been heavy handed or overt are given a gentle twist that feels authentic and emotionally honest in a way that you don’t often see, especially in major studio releases. Add to that the absolute fidelity of the visuals to a particular time and place—this <em>is</em> Brooklyn in the early fifties—and you have a film that is far more than the sum of its trailers. </p>

<p>Also, the sharp casting choice of her two suitors—Emory Cohen as Tony and Domhnall Gleeson as Jim—is just another feature in a long list that helps elevate <em>Brooklyn</em> far above the <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/27/far-from-the-madding-crowd.html">Madding Crowd</a>. </p>

<p>It is perhaps surprising to some that <em>Brooklyn</em> is nominated for an Oscar in the Best Picture, Best Adapted Screenplay and Best Actress categories. In many ways this is a small, intimate film without much in the way of overt fireworks. But the craft at work, the script you produced, and the memorable character that Ronan creates in Eilis, make this a special film. </p>

<p>All things considered, <em>Brooklyn</em> is eminently worthy of the kind of recognition it is receiving and a fine addition to an already impressive body of work. Good luck on Oscar night, Nick.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Danish Girl</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/3/the-danish-girl.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheDanishGirl" />
    <published>2016-02-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/3/the-danish-girl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It takes a lot of balls to pull off a transgender character. Any asshole can throw on a wig and a dress and go <em>To Wong Fu, Thanks</em> <em>For</em> <em>Everything! Julie</em> <em>Newmar</em>, but rising above the gimmicks of drag takes a much lighter touch. Especially when differentiating between cross-dressers, homosexuals, transsexuals, intersex persons, etc. One wrong step and the critics will have their knives out. That’s the conventional logic, anyway. But as Eddie Redmayne’s tepid and uninspired performance in _The Danish Girl proves, being bland is a far greater cinematic offence than going over the top.</p>

<p><em>The Danish Girl</em> feels like a film from another time. Not because the story is set in the European high-art scene of the 1920s, but because it treats its subject with such naivety and earnestness that the story itself feels secondary to the premise. Following someone who is born as a man and transitions to a woman is simply not enough to hold an audience’s interest. Twenty years ago, making a film about a transgender pioneer would have certainly ruffled more than a few feathers, and sparked conversations and think-pieces merely by existing. But not in 2015. Not months after Bruce Jenner became Caitlyn Jenner, not a couple years after Jared Leto won an Oscar for playing a transgender woman, and not decades after <em>The Rocky Horror Picture Show</em> crossed over into the mainstream. Novelty has given way to nuance. Substance matters, now more than ever. </p>

<p>Which is why the film’s painfully dull execution felt all the more offensive.  Redmayne opting to take most of his physical cues from a shy Japanese school girl, covering his mouth as he giggles, always averting his eyes, is a choice that I can live with. Accuracy and subtlety aren’t nearly as important as conveying an emotional truth. At times, your coaching helps him do this effectively, like when he delicately lays dresses across his chest or slides on high heels for the first time. These moments were well-choreographed to communicate sensuality and excitement. It was after Einar became Lili that the film started to feel tragically uninspired and predictable.</p>

<p>The story veers towards calamity, and we can see it coming, but instead of providing a deeper exploration of personal dynamics or ratcheting up the suspense, the narrative is pinned down under the weight of the inevitable tragedy, which becomes stifling to watch. By the time we reach the conclusion, rather than feeling surprised or inspired, it felt as if the filmmakers were simply trying to craft a graceful exit. </p>

<p>The film’s saving grace is Alicia Vikander, playing the conflicted but understanding wife, and equally talented (more so, perhaps) painter. She gives each of her scenes a much needed energy and purpose, propelling the story forward and poignantly conveying mood with a simple look or playful gesture. It may be the more thankless and less showy of the two roles, but it’s certainly the more substantial. </p>

<p>After all, it doesn’t matter how a character moves as long as they move <em>us</em>. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Finest Hours</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/2/the-finest-hours.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheFinestHours" />
    <published>2016-02-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/2/the-finest-hours</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Set medics are often seen as a precaution. On a good day, you shouldn’t have anything to do. Actors and stunt workers play their scenes and leave unscathed. You pack up your stethoscope and purple latex gloves and walk off into the sunset. But in <em>The Finest Hours</em>, you’re not just a precaution—you’re a necessity.  </p>

<p><em>The Finest Hours</em> is, for the most part, a disaster movie. It’s the true story of the heroic 1952 rescue of 32 seamen aboard the SS Pendleton, which was led by Bernie Webber and his ragtag crew. It was mission that has gone down in U.S. Coast Guard history as the single greatest small boat rescue ever attempted; a severe storm crippled the SS Pendleton, leaving the coast guards no choice but to brave aggressive waves that threatened to tear their 36-foot motorboat into pieces. Their chances of survival were slim to none. </p>

<p>To recreate this harrowing affair, you and the cast of <em>The Finest Hours</em>  endured weeks of filming in what seems to have been a <a href="http://www.king5.com/story/entertainment/television/programs/evening/2016/01/29/who-got-wettest-behind-scenes-finest-hours/79487252/">watery hell</a>. Your days began and ended in a massive 800,000-gallon water tank, and the cast was drenched in ice-cold water while they acted out their scenes; a torrential downpour blasted from a fire-hose. That kind of exposure to cold temperatures can take a toll on the human body, and, as the set medic, it was your job to make sure nobody fell ill during the shoot. You had to be prepared with the proper equipment and ready to jump into action the moment the director yelled cut. If a pivotal performer got injured or fell sick, production would halt. I can imagine it was a very difficult task, especially with such a huge cast, so you could probably relate to the long odds and seemingly insurmountable task that the rescuers in the film faced. </p>

<p>I was impressed how director Craig Gillespie was able to capture the desperate strain on the protagonists’ faces. I certainly didn’t get the sense that the film’s stars, Chris Pine, Casey Affleck, Ben Foster, etc, were sitting back and relaxing while their stunt-doubles accepted all the on-screen punishment. </p>

<p>Not to say the stunt doubles didn’t have their own troubles. To mimic the ragdoll motions of bluejackets being tossed around in an oil tanker, <em>The Finest Hours</em> stunt team look like they were launching themselves against iron walls and metal grates. They weren’t being ravaged by the sea, but instead, the vessel itself. How often did they have to check in to the McPeake clinic over the course of shooting? More than a few times, I’ll bet.</p>

<p>As exhausting as this must have been for you and the rest of the cast and crew, the events depicted in <em>The Finest Hours</em> are riveting. It’s one of Hollywood’s more recent disaster-themed action-adventures that I’ve been able to enjoy. That speaks volumes when you take the large, CGI waves into consideration. Too much CGI has a tendency to strip away any real sense of danger—but not this time. <em>The Finest Hours</em> carefully balances CGI and authenticity to deliver a solid end product. The moment the first crack tears its way through the bow of the SS Pendleton’s reinforced walls, I was hooked. </p>

<p>And a lot of that was thanks to your presence on the set. You were able to create a safe environment in which the performers could push themselves to the limit and bring a striking realism to the screen. And for that, I thank you.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Big Short</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/1/the-big-short.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheBigShort" />
    <published>2016-02-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/1/the-big-short</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Your family name, “Lax”, would be ironic in any profession where attention to detail is essential to the job. In your case, you might over-compensate by vigilantly triple-checking every ledger, just to make sure no one can accuse you of succumbing to your careless moniker. Or you might go the other way, embracing your brand so hard (by becoming, say, a well-known amoral number cruncher), that the combination of title and purpose seems predestined. You know, like discovering that some Wall Street traders bet on the collapse of the entire financial system and made out like bandits.</p>

<p>Herein lies the central narrative for <em>The Big Short</em>. Based on the true events of a handful of outsiders who saw the mortgage housing meltdown coming and banked its collapse, we get an oddball story told with such untethered glee that it’s impossible not to get caught up in the crazy. No small feat considering the unsexy source material. </p>

<p>See, the whole vocabulary of the banking system might be second nature to people like you, but its intellectual anesthesia for the rest of us. So of course we’re happy to play along when Margo Robbie spells something out for us in a bubble bath, or Anthony Bourdain chops up a tasty metaphor. These are the types of flourishes that help elevate <em>The Big Short</em> from just another straight forward drama or low-brow comedy, into a rousing genre-bending piece of entertainment.</p>

<p>The mad man behind the camera, Adam Mackay, directs every scene with the careless confidence of a high-rolling hedge fund manager. He knows he has A-list stars to spare, which allows him to be almost reckless in their treatment. Christian Bale leans hard into his glass eye for maximum eccentricity. Ryan Gosling smooth talks directly into the camera with excessive smarm. Steve Carell seethes in every scene, waiting for any chance to go off. Brad Pitt mumbles life-changing advice from behind his financial- guru beard. Then there’s his visual approach which uses every trick in the book – zooms, flares, flash frames, stock footage, smash cuts, breaking the fourth wall – and you’ve got either the recipe for a filmmaking disaster, or a longshot success. </p>

<p>Well, cha ching.</p>

<p><em>The Big Short</em> believes in its approach and capitalizes on the chances it takes. The subject matter is serviced thoroughly without ever sacrificing a laugh. It’s a rare example of being both creative and responsible to your shareholders – in this case, the audience – who have put their money and confidence in the returns being promised. For once, the laugh isn’t being had at our expense.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Anomalisa</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/29/anomalisa.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Anomalisa" />
    <published>2016-01-29T11:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-29T11:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/29/anomalisa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’m going to guess that you’re sisters, around six and eight. The woman you walked in with was most likely your mother, and the three of you arrived just as the film was about to start. You sat beside a man who was most likely your father. </p>

<p>I’ve seen this kind of thing before at free screenings. A movie with puppets, or teddy bears, or animation seems like a fun mid-week treat. A cheap night out for the family. Until the bear starts smoking weed and swearing, or the puppets start touching each other in their bathing suit areas and the next thing you know, the kids are being dragged out of the theatre, a trail of popcorn behind them.</p>

<p>But you stayed. And saw things and heard things that you likely hadn’t seen or heard before. I know I did. I went in expecting <em>Anomalisa</em>, a stop-motion animated film by Charlie Kaufman, to be dark and bizarre and a little sardonic. I’m not sure what <em>you</em> expected, but by the end of the film you probably had more questions than answers. I spent several hours afterwards trying to dissect what I’d just seen. And I’m a grown-up. </p>

<p>In most kid’s movies, the protagonist is the hero of the story, someone to look up to, someone to root for. Not so here. Michael Stone, the semi-famous customer service guru who has arrived Cincinnati for a seminar, is kind of an asshole (I don’t feel bad swearing in front of you; not after what we’ve been through). The first lines of dialogue in the film use the f-word liberally as Michael reads a letter from a jilted lover. Soon after that, Michael urinates in his hotel bathroom, takes a shower, and visits a sex shop. Probably not the type of stuff you’re used to seeing on <em>Sesame Street</em> or <em>Treehouse</em>. But hey, now you know that the thing you found in Mummy’s bedside table isn’t a flashlight like she told you.</p>

<p>I don’t have kids myself, but I remember being pretty perceptive when I was your age. Did you <em>also</em> notice that Michael constantly misses opportunities to make genuine, human connections with the people around him? Or that everyone he interacts with looks and sounds the same? The figures used in the film have faces that are attached like masks, and with the exception of David Thewlis, who voices Michael, and Jennifer Jason-Leigh, who voices Lisa, the only other actor in the film is Tom Noonan, who voices everyone else. Even you guys probably picked up on the fact that this is meant to reflect Michael’s view of the world as mundane, lacking variety and joy. Everyone around him moves through their lives like mindless automatons. And although he has a wife and son at home, and a successful career, he mopes about like a put-upon, spoiled, petulant child. </p>

<p>When Michael finally cajoles his ex-lover to visit him in the hotel bar, we see just how selfish and narcissistic he is. His attempts to force intimacy result in his eventual meeting with Lisa, who he is attracted to because she doesn’t look or sound like anyone else. She’s an <em>anomaly</em>. Get it? Lisa is sweet, and self-deprecating, and though she is scarred both physically and emotionally, she is real. It’s this realness that mesmerizes Michael. Jennifer Jason Leigh’s portrayal of Lisa is the bright spot in this dull world. She sings Cyndi Lauper, reveals her joys and fears, and allows Lisa some bravery in her vulnerability. </p>

<p>Little girls often make their dolls do inappropriate things. But I’m fairly certain you’ve never done to your dolls what Michael does to Lisa. Instead of playing the sex scenes for laughs like <em>Team America: World Police</em>, Kaufman and co-director Duke Johnson take care to present the (anatomically correct) sex between Michael and Lisa as honestly and lovingly as possible. Just remember kids, oral sex is only for puppets who think they love each other very, very much. But because this is a Kaufman movie, I knew better than to expect a happily ever after ending. Even a child could see that Lisa, in all her Middle-American ordinariness, is too good for Michael.</p>

<p>For all its naturalism and attention to detail, the conceit of 
<em>Anomalisa</em>, though beautifully executed, smacks of gimmickry. In the end, we’re left with a mediocre Charlie Kaufman oddity that feels like more like an extended therapy session than a story. The themes of isolation and mid-life identity crisis are a little on the nose, especially when Michael’s customer service advice (“Look for what is special about each individual, focus on that”) is juxtaposed against his inability to view people as different. See kids? That’s called irony! Then there were some headscratchers like a dream sequence that brought the pace of the story to a dead halt, and the fact that for some reason the film takes place in 2006, perhaps so Michael can go off on a George Bush rant in the middle of his conference speech. Kids, George Bush was the president before Obama, and he…oh, never mind.  </p>

<p>But I must commend you for sticking it out. Many, <em>many</em> adults walked out of the screening—more than I’ve ever seen leave a film before. Maybe they were expecting the strange wit of <em>Being John Malkovich</em>, or the bubble-gum visuals of <em>Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind,</em> or maybe they were expecting <em>Wallace &amp; Gromit</em>. Who knows. I was hoping for Kaufman’s trademark whimsical melancholy, that rare gift that allows him to consistently deliver movies that manage that balance between art and mainstream. <em>Anomalisa</em> almost gets the balance right, but like most kid’s puppet shows, between the kissing scenes and the fighting scenes, the story just isn’t all that interesting.</p>

<p>As I watched you walk down the aisle after the screening, one of you had obviously been crying. The other was staring straight ahead, clutching a box of Poptopia for dear life. I will remember <em>Anomalisa</em> as the only Charlie Kaufman movie that made me check my watch. I’m sure it will be memorable for you too, but for very different reasons. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Cartel Land</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/29/cartel-land.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CartelLand" />
    <published>2016-01-29T04:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-29T04:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/29/cartel-land</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re one crazy sonofabitch, aren’t you? Embedding yourself with gun-toting mercenaries, meth cooks, and cartel members is not exactly a sane way to make a paycheque. The fact that director/producer/cinematographer/editor Matthew Heineman seems willing to put his life on the line is one thing – he gets all the final glory if things go right. But you’re just a hired gun (sorry, bad metaphor). I don’t exactly know which scenes you filmed, but whether it was State-side with armed minute-men hunting drug traffickers, or following a mini-revolution within Mexico, the chance of you getting shot before getting the shot you wanted seemed stupidly high. </p>

<p>But damn. What a hell of film.</p>

<p>There’s no shortage of movies about the U.S. government’s bloody war on drugs.  <em>Cartel Land,</em> however, ups the ante by actually going into the trenches with the foot soldiers who are either profiting from the chaos, or simply trying to protect their home. </p>

<p>The film starts off with a deceptively slow-pace, with drug producers being interviewed in an undisclosed desert location at night. The masked interviewee is calm, thoughtful and personable. He’s fully aware that the drugs they’re making in Mexico are ruining people’s lives, but he’s also fairly unapologetic about his participation. After all, he’s out of options. This humanizing introduction is an important touch that I thought back on a lot over the course of the film, especially when horror stories are relayed about how the cartels take over small towns. One woman in particular goes into gory detail about the ways the cartel assert their control over the population by brutally murdering not only men and women, but infants and children. Thank God you didn’t capture any of that.</p>

<p>But you do come pretty close, especially during a climactic raid by the Autodefensas – a paramilitary group trying to reclaim one cartel-run Mexican town at a time. The shoot-out is so intense that I had to remind myself this was a documentary. People’s lives are at risk – including yours – during the sequence of events. It was the most breathtaking scene I’ve watched all year. </p>

<p>The visuals throughout the film are powerful, with beautiful compositions not only during the less intense transitional moments, but also when you’re under fire. How you guys managed to keep your trigger fingers operating a zoom lens while bullets are whizzing by, or while people are being interrogated at gun point, is a truly compelling feat of cinematography.   </p>

<p>Heinman’s approach totally immerses the audience in the chaos. There are no voiceovers to tie together the different stories we’re following, and no convenient confrontation linking the subjects together. They are just two sides of the same coin, making up the complicated cross-border battlefront of the drug war that most of us are blessedly removed from. You helped bring it into our lives in a very real way.</p>

<p>Stay safe, man.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tangerine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/1/26/tangerine.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Tangerine" />
    <published>2016-01-26T17:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-26T17:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/1/26/tangerine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iSePbQVR284">interview</a> for the 1991 documentary <em>Hearts of Darkness</em> (which I can’t recommend enough) Francis Ford Coppola describes the future of film making in this short sentence: </p>

<p>“<em>One day, some little fat girl in Ohio is going to be the new Mozart and make a beautiful film.</em>”</p>

<p><em>Tangerine</em> is that film. Which means, I guess, you’re the chubby new Mozart from Ohio.*  </p>

<p>Shot guerilla style on modified iPhone 5’s, <em>Tangerine</em> is a ludicrously exciting film, and a perfect example of how you can do something really interesting if you know how to compose a frame and tell a story. That the performances are uneven, or that the production values are utterly low rent, doesn’t detract from what is, in its finished state, a remarkable movie. Those things that might seem to be shortcomings in larger budget films actually help to create, in a film like <em>Tangerine,</em> a world that is both neo-realist and still somehow dreamlike. </p>

<p>The story is simple. It follows one person (a weirdly engaging and still amateurish performance from the oh-so-aptly named Kitana Kiki Rodriguez) in her search for a wayward boyfriend. Along the way a whole collection of outré characters pop in and out of frame, but it’s how the story is told—a great soundtrack, imaginative and constantly invigorating camerawork, and a verite that comes from something so intimate and small scale—that makes it special.</p>

<p>Coppola, in the same 35-second segment, also talks about how this new kind of filmmaker will liberate the art form from the artificial constraints of what he brackets as “professionalism”.</p>

<p>I think what he means is fairly simple: once filmmaking becomes a process that only requires a few willing participants, a couple of iPhones, a good computer, and some innate talent, then the artform is taken out of the hands of people who are only concerned with the economics of the film business. It changes the balance of power, which means that executive producers and distributors, financiers and beancounters move to their proper place in the hierarchy. Because, while these people are clearly an important part of the process, they are important only <em>after</em> the fact.</p>

<p>Too often—at least up till now—the only time an artist has had the wherewithal to make the work they really want to make is after they have emptied whatever pool of real talent they possess. People like Christopher Nolan and Tarantino only achieved that kind of autonomy after years of negotiating the studio system which seems (to me) to have sucked them dry of what made films like <em>Reservoir Dogs</em> or <em>The Following</em> so vital and alive (although apparently that has not happened to George Miller—so maybe proximity to Hollywood is also part of the equation). All these revered auteurs seem capable of creating now are these bloated, over-wrought <em>productions</em>, that are long on surface concerns like the Imax sequences in <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em> or Tarantino’s 70mm roadshow for <em>The Hateful Eight</em> and short on what was so promising in their early works: a real engagement with storytelling and character.</p>

<p>The whole film industry seems on the edge of catastrophic changes and <em>Tangerine</em> is one of the harbingers of that welcome disaster. It’s an example—for anyone with the foresight to see—of what it’s possible to do with nothing more than a couple of jacked up iPhones and a good idea. </p>

<p>And, of course, prodigious talent as well.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>