<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-24T22:55:49Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Founder</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/24/the-founder.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheFounder" />
    <published>2017-01-24T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-24T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/24/the-founder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’m a middlebrow kind of guy, generally. I’m perfectly happy with consuming media that has no greater ambition than to entertain or tell a good story. That’s not a statement of advocacy, just a fact. And because of that fact, your projects tend to hit my sweet spot. </p>

<p>Whatever greater lessons exist in the subtext of this film—the rise of corporatism and it’s corollary: the decline of mom and pop enterprises in the latter half of the twentieth century—what the <em>The Founder</em> does remarkably well is tell, in a simple but compelling fashion, the story of the rise of McDonalds from a single roadside diner to a multi-billion dollar corporate behemoth.</p>

<p>Ray Kroc (Michael Keaton who continues his phoenix like re-emergence onto the A-list) is a character whose through line is an absorbing, cautionary tale about how innovation and small scale entrepreneurs can fall prey to corporate appropriation. From humble beginnings he became the singular avatar of all that is wrong with late-stage capitalism. Watching him evolve from a slightly shady travelling salesmen to an utterly heartless CEO is both appalling and also completely fascinating—and a lot of that is down to how effortlessly Keaton shepherds that transition. He portrays Kroc as a folksy monster, so that each step in his metamorphosis is tinged with a casual, almost banal, amorality. We get to watch how increasing wealth and power expose the essential weaknesses of his character, while also being given a pretty good primer on how we went from single owner diners and department stores to ubiquitous franchise restaurants and box stores the size of city blocks.</p>

<p>But all of this is background, and none of it is essential to engaging with the film. Just watching Ray navigate his way to the top, over and through anyone foolish enough to get in his way, is what makes <em>The Founder</em> compelling. And Ray leaves a long list of casualties in his wake. </p>

<p>There are almost always a bevy of quality, understated performances in your films, and <em>The Founder</em> is no exception. Laura Dern, John Carroll Lynch, and B.J. Novak all have small, but pivotal, roles. But for me the real revelation was Nick Offerman as one of the two McDonalds brothers. He was quietly brilliant, subtly projecting both competence in his area of expertise, and utter befuddlement with the ethically bereft shenanigans Kroc perpetrates.</p>

<p>Some of what I admire about your filmography is the regularity with which you produce what people often refer to as Oscar bait. What that seems to mean is films with a complex central characters located in interesting historical settings, married to strong scripts and quietly effective direction. The kind of films that put story front and centre, rather than submitting to auteurist tendencies (your ongoing relationship with Tarantino being a profound exception).</p>

<p>As with <em>Gold</em>, <em>The Founder</em> is meat and potatoes film making. The emphasis on the basics of storytelling—a good script, coherent plot, smart casting—is a refreshing shift from a landscape filled with creators that sometimes seem to have lost sight of these fundamentals. This is not a film that seeks to innovate or break new ground, but it’s absolutely a film that succeeds in its ambitions, however straightforward they might be.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Best of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/24/the-best-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheBestof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/24/the-best-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The big green beast turns 60 this year, unleashing a new version of the Japanese monster on May 16th. In anticipation, Kelan Young goes on a reviewing rampage, looking back at some of the best – and most overlooked – entries in the storied series. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Captain America: Civil War is the Best (and Worthiest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/23/captain-america-civil-war-is-the-best-and-worthiest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CaptainAmerica:CivilWaristheBest(andWorthiest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-23T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-23T04:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/23/captain-america-civil-war-is-the-best-and-worthiest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If all my years of high school English taught me anything, it’s that a good essay should start off with a loud, emphatic statement that will draw a reader in. So, here we go:</p>

<p><em>Captain America: Civil War</em> is without a doubt the best movie of 2016.</p>

<p><em>Civil War</em>? A superhero movie? For best picture? Blasphemy! Shame! Who does this guy think he is? Did he even see <em>Moonlight</em>, <em>Manchester by the Sea</em>, or <em>La La Land</em>? </p>

<p>My answer is simple: it doesn’t matter. I didn’t <em>want</em> to choose <em>Civil War</em> as my top pick. I wanted to pick a film that is universally deemed to be worthy. I know the kind of stigma that comes with suggesting a superhero film can be an expression of cinematic art, let alone the best one in a given year. It might seem juvenile, unrefined, and in keeping with a person who hasn’t experienced, nor isn’t capable of understanding, the depth that critically appreciated films usually possess. But that’s what makes my pick so compelling. Every time I sat down to construct a narrative around one of those other movies, my true feelings about <em>Civil War</em> kept getting in the way. The more I pushed them down, the louder they got. So, rather than fight my feelings, I decided to let them out. I decided to do what a critic does best; defend the shit out of my position. </p>

<p>To understand why I chose <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> as my #1 pick, you have to take a look at the cinematic landscape of 2016 as a whole. Much can be said about the caliber of movies that came out in 2016, but there is no doubt that it was the year that comic book adaptations reigned supreme. </p>

<p>From the Merc with a Mouth to the mind-bending theatrics of Doctor Strange, 2016 slapped on a pair of spandex more often than not –six times to be exact. And even though I adore superhero films, even <em>I</em> got fatigues by the rate at which these blockbuster were released. I began to notice that these types of movies weren’t being made for fans anymore, but, rather, for profit, which meant that timelines were rushed and quantity was chosen over quality. I mean, just look at what happened to Suicide Squad.</p>

<p>So what makes <em>Civil War</em> different? It’s just a blockbuster filled with colourful people in colourful outfits. Besides all the cool superpowers, what was so special about it that it warrants this prestigious designation? At the end of the day, aren’t all superhero movies the same?</p>

<p>The difference is that <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> stays true to itself with the sort of light-hearted action we’ve grown to love from the Marvel Cinematic Universe, but contrasts it with a deep and emotional story that is a culmination of tensions that were put into motion after the first <em>Iron Man</em> all the way back in 2008. </p>

<p>Was Marvel planning a film adaption of the Civil War storyline eight years in advance? Did they purposely develop Captain America and Iron Man for this very moment? I don’t know. All I know is that when they finally faced off, it didn’t feel unexpected.</p>

<p>At its core, <em>Civil War</em> is a story about political divisiveness. After years of funding and manufacturing top-of-the-line weapons, Tony Stark hits a moral low as he finally sees that no matter how hard he tries to vanquish his demons and make a positive difference in the world, he’s innately reckless and needs to be policed. This is in direct opposition to Steve Rogers’ political leanings; Steve has seen firsthand the type of corruption that comes when a government amasses too much influence; he’s seen absolute power corrupt absolutely. Despite sometimes being reckless in the way he conducts himself and his team, Steve knows the intervention of bureaucrats will only result in more subtle forms of recklessness. </p>

<p>The showdown came about seamlessly. It was like the final domino being added in a long line of dominoes, just waiting to be knocked over. And the fall of those dominoes, when it finally came, was mesmerizing.</p>

<p>That chain of events left me gutted. During the climax that reveals Bucky Barnes culpability in the death of Tony Stark’s parents, I was hit with something that I’ve never been exposed to while watching a superhero movie: profound sadness. To the point where I was dreading that these two beloved characters might actually kill one another. I was emotionally invested and completely caught off guard. I can usually predict the outcome of a comic book film, but I wasn’t expecting the dark and dramatic turn of events that occurs at the end of <em>Civil War</em>. Fighting over politics is one thing, but discovering that the man you’ve fought beside against aliens and sentient robots has been hiding a secret of this magnitude is some Jerry Springer shit that is too raw to ignore.</p>

<p>But <em>Civil War</em> isn&#39;t a two-man show. It’s an all-star team-up that brings in even more superheroes than <em>The Avengers</em>. It features supporting characters who have headlined (and will soon headline) their own movies, and, as every critic knows, too many powerful personalities in one movie can break it. But this wasn’t the case with <em>Civil War</em>. The filmmakers were fully aware of the clout that each character possessed, and used them to the best of their abilities. They had confidence in the story they wanted to tell, and didn’t let anyone get in the way of it. The integration of highly-anticipated heroes like Black Panther and Spider-Man was handled with total precision. Everyone had their time to shine, and when it was time to refocus, the supporting cast disappeared into the background. <em>Civil War</em> struck the perfect balance between character and story.</p>

<p>By the time I finished watching <em>Civil War</em> for the first time, I was in a buzz. I didn’t just witness a moving drama, but a hilarious comedy and thrilling action flick, too. I still can’t comprehend how blockbuster spectacle with such a diverse cast could feel so organic, so <em>real</em>. I was beaming with emotion. This isn’t just another addition to Marvel’s Cinematic Universe—it’s a piece of art, a film that transcends its own genre. </p>

<p>And that’s why <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> is without a doubt the best movie of 2016. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Split</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/20/split.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Split" />
    <published>2017-01-20T15:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-20T15:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/20/split</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Like most M. Night Shyamalan movies, the true purpose of <em>Split</em> isn’t revealed until the final moments of the film. But this time it’s not some wild plot twist or magical coincidence. No, it’s something much different. Something totally removed from the narrative of the film. Something so cynical, so lazy, that as the credits began to roll I felt like the victim of a cruel prank. </p>

<p>(For those of you who care to experience the prank firsthand, stop reading now; spoilers ensue.)</p>

<p>I hate to escalate things like this, Jeff. It feels like I’m ratting out a classmate to the school principal. But, as the head honcho, the buck stops with you. At least it <em>should</em>. And I’m writing to plead with you: make this stop. </p>

<p>No, I’m not talking about <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/8/m-night-shyamalan-the-final-blockbuster-auteur.html">M. Night Shyamalan’s career</a>. Believe me when I say that I take no pleasure (as many would) in chipping away at what remains of his reputation. But it’s impossible to talk about this film – and what happens in its final few seconds – without talking about the man and his career. Which is fair, I think, because thing that happens at the end is explicitly about him and his career. Not the story, not the characters—<em>him</em>. </p>

<p>I’ve been neither a devotee nor hater of Shyamalan’s work. <em>The Sixth Sense</em> didn’t surprise me much (which is bad news for a film that exists only to surprise) and I’ve always been befuddled by the appeal of <em>Unbreakable</em>. In my casual estimation, his best film has been <em>Signs</em>, which genuinely frightened me, and I’m even willing to defend <em>The Village</em>. I couldn’t bring myself to despise <em>Lady In The Water</em> the way most people did, and <em>The Last Airbender</em> was atrocious in such a familiar way that it was hard to pin the blame entirely on the director. So I’ve always been willing to give Shyamalan another chance. Just like you, apparently. I think it’s his unfulfilled potential that fascinates me; he always seems just a few steps away from doing something great. There is something about his eagerness to manipulate the audience that I find admirable; why else do people go to the movies? </p>

<p>So I was quite excited to see <em>Split</em>. The premise was classic Shyamalan: girls kidnapped by a weirdo with multiple personalities; one of those personalities may or may not be a demon (or something). Fun, right? But instead—</p>

<p>Maybe my memory of his previous films has gone foggy, but, with <em>Split</em>, he seems to have regressed as a filmmaker. There are individual shots that are self-consciously cool, images that would look great on <a href="https://twitter.com/OnePerfectShot">One Perfect Shot</a>, but a film is not a series of images, it is the aggregate of those images, and the real artistry of a movie is how those images interact and give meaning to one another. Shyamalan is like a foreigner who has learned the native language one word at a time; he possesses an impressive vocabulary, but has no sense of grammar or structure of verb tense. Indeed, there are sequences in <em>Split</em> that unfold in such an illiterate manner that they seem like the work of a student filmmaker; someone just learning what a camera is supposed to do, how information is supposed to be conveyed.    </p>

<p>But that sort of sloppiness can be easy to overlook if a film’s purpose it true. Unfortunately, Shyamalan’s illiteracy extends to the morality of the film, too. Here we have a thriller about semi-naked teenage girls held hostage by an eccentric maniac, and, rightfully, Shyamalan indulges playfully in the tropes of that sub-genre. But <em>Split</em> is also a movie that references, multiple times, child sexual abuse. And, in one horrifying scene, even shows us the disturbing prologue of a five year-old girl’s sexual encounter with an uncle. It’s a sequence that plays out in typical thriller fashion, a slowly-dawning discomfort that builds to repulsion, and, I’ll admit, it’s very effective—but the problem is, this isn’t <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/11/manchester-by-the-sea.html">a quiet drama about the consequences of trauma</a> or <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/18/moonlight-is-the-best-and-brightest-film-of-2016.html">an empathetic character study</a>, it’s a Hollywood movie about a whimsical serial killer with super-powers. I don’t mean to imply that such topics should be off-limits to certain filmmakers or untouchable in the context of a certain genre, but I simply felt like the film, up to that point, hadn’t earned the right to use such dark issues to advance its plot, and there was, therefore, something utterly tasteless about it all. </p>

<p>Worse yet, all of those muddled principles are amplified in the climactic confrontation between killer and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_girl">Final Girl</a>. I’m assuming you’ve seen the film, so you know the scene I’m talking about: our protagonist is cornered by the lunatic, she’s about to be eaten or whatever, and he manages to tear her shirt off, revealing numerous scars on her abdomen and shoulders, the handiwork of her abusive uncle. The lunatic pauses, and then plainly states (as everything in an M. Night Shyamalan screenplay is stated) that, like him, her victimhood makes her powerful. Which I guess isn’t a <em>totally</em> reprehensible ideological stance, except that she has no agency in demonstrating her power as a survivor, she just sits there passively, observed, judged (with her shirt torn off). Yet another “strong female character” who is only strong because the male antagonist acknowledges that she’s not weak. For me, that nuance drained the film of the moral credibility with which it was attempting to give depth to all the slasher-flick goofiness. </p>

<p>I mean, Christ, I’ve had worse times in movie theaters. And despite all of this, as the last act wrapped up I was willing to give <em>Split</em> a couple of stars (one each for James McAvoy and Anya Taylor-Joy, to acknowledge the efforts they make to overcome the facile, sometimes laughable screenplay). But then—those last five seconds of the film, the big secret revealed, and it turns out that this entire thing was, quite literally, a set-up. Not a narrative set-up, mind you. A fraud, a con. </p>

<p>Here’s how the whole thing wraps up: we find ourselves in a diner; a television blares, and we learn, from a line of dopey newscaster dialogue, that the killer, who remains uncaptured, has been nicknamed The Horde; we pan slowly down the lunch counter, where, sitting there on a stool, enjoying a club sandwich and hot cup of coffee, is David Dunn, aka. Bruce Willis, the unbreakable hero of Shyamalan’s long-ago hit <em>Unbreakable</em>, who, we must assume, will now do battle with the villain we have been following throughout this film. Which means that <em>Split</em> is not actually a movie at all; it’s the backstory for another movie that does not yet exist, that, having paid fifteen bucks to watch this one, you may or may not care anything about. </p>

<p>That the characters in <em>Split</em> have suffered and died merely to enable this clash is sort of depressing, isn’t it? What does any of it mean? Is this simply how popular entertainment works, now? The serialization and continuation of everything. No endings, anymore? Just teasers for the next, better chapter? Is <em>Split</em> the embodiment of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H18RUB1cxfI">Fuck You, It’s January!</a>?</p>

<p>Clearly this pissed me off, Jeff. But I wonder, now, about my own culpability in this culture of unoriginality. My complicated nostalgic attachment to comic book movies is well-documented. And I’ve often defended the stingers in those films as akin to the previews you find in the back of comic books that show the next month’s cover. But this felt bigger than that. More intrusive. A desperate attempt by the director to remind us that he once made films that were more interesting than this one. </p>

<p>But, okay—<em>one</em> star. To keep with the theme of multiple viewpoints occupying the same body, I’ll give <em>Split</em> one star on behalf of my self-doubt.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Elle is the Best (and Angriest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/19/elle-is-the-best-and-angriest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ElleistheBest(andAngriest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-19T05:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-19T05:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/19/elle-is-the-best-and-angriest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Given the dumpster fire of misery and regression that was 2016, you would think my pick for the year’s best film would be something optimistic or uplifting – anything to temporarily forget that we probably won’t be writing about our favourite films of 2017 next year because we’ll have all been accidentally nuked by a blob of talking nacho cheese that likes to throw tantrums on Twitter. </p>

<p>There is one bag of flaming dog shit 2016 left on my doorstep that I’m still not over: watching men who harm women tap dance away from any accountability or consequence. Oddly enough, the media and punditry’s pious lectures on justice, the presumption of innocence, or the ‘proper’ way for sexual assault victims to behave, did not help – too much hysterical rage taking up space in this little ladybrain, perhaps. What has remained stuck in my brain? That you can choke your dinner dates for years and walk away free because their behaviour matters more than yours; that a judge in the 21st century will still openly wonder why a rape victim didn’t just keep her legs together, or worry that prison will ruin a rapist’s athletic career.  So for me, the best film of 2016 was one that embraced female anger without trying to assuage it, dismiss it, or scold it, and one that didn’t concern itself with whether or not I felt better or hopeful at the end. </p>

<p>Paul Verhoeven’s <em>Elle</em> opens with the protagonist, Michèle, being raped by an intruder in her home. She is what we are told is a ’perfect‘ rape victim; attacked by a random, masked bogeyman who broke into her house. But then she goes and fucks it all up by not behaving as we are told a rape victim should. She doesn’t curl up into a ball and weep, nor does she seek help. After her intruder leaves, it’s just another evening of tidying up, bath time, and take-out. Michèle approaches the aftermath of her assault with a sense of icy calm, her expression perpetually unreadable, and there is never any explanation offered for her actions, even as they get progressively more twisted. </p>

<p>Calling <em>Elle</em> the angriest film of 2016 might actually be a point of contention. On the surface, it isn’t a very angry film at all. The rape in the opening scene quickly becomes less of a focal point than Michèle’s workplace tensions, family crises, and the mysterious trauma in her past. If anything, she seems to be consumed with glossing over the terrible things that happen to her, and you forget it’s actually a revenge film until right at the end. Michèle gives nothing away. Her anger doesn’t explode in fits of screaming and tears; it simmers away under her cool exterior, occasionally bubbling to the surface with a sarcastic joke or petty, passive-aggressive dig at her family and friends. A good tagline for the film might be, “Michèle doesn’t get mad, she gets even,” but if you look a little closer, you see that she is furious, and it didn’t even begin with her rape; the fury has been building in her for years, but she will get mad (and even) on her own terms. Once you stop being distracted by how she did or didn’t behave after her attack, Michèle’s rage becomes more and more palpable. When she does finally avenge herself, it isn’t in an operatic, Lady-Vengeance-esque way; she acknowledges her triumph with a quick, slight smirk, and that’s it. Those more used to expressing their anger loudly, through poorly rhymed slogans or social media diatribes, might not understand this. Others, whose anger is quieter but every bit as potent, will get it at once. Anyone who has ever swallowed their anger because they simply lack the patience to allay the discomfort angry women seem to provoke, or would just rather not hear, “Hey, hey, calm down, lady,” one more time, will love Michèle for it.  </p>

<p>In addition to being the angriest film of 2016, <em>Elle</em> is also relentlessly hostile to its audience, which is kind of perverse, but also pretty cool, in that it offers no explanations or excuses for anything. You are not required to empathize with or relate to Michèle; in fact, she is distinctly unlikeable, and that is exactly why wondering who her rapist is gradually takes a back seat to wondering if Michèle isn’t completely nuts herself. We stop asking, “Who is he? Why did he do this to her?” and focus on, “What the hell is <em>she</em> doing?!” which, at some point, hopefully, will result in a light bulb moment for the viewer. </p>

<p>When it comes to the treatment of sexual assault victims and the perpetuation of rape culture, I doubt I’ll have reason to be less angry in 2017, or any time soon, but <em>Elle</em> served as a kind of catharsis for me, even though there is no moral to the story, no lesson to be learned. I mean, you could tout the film as a reminder that there is no such thing as a perfect victim or something. Or not. Like Michèle, it really doesn’t give a fuck what you think. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Moonlight is the Best (and Brightest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/18/moonlight-is-the-best-and-brightest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MoonlightistheBest(andBrightest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-18T04:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-18T04:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/18/moonlight-is-the-best-and-brightest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Usually when someone references the Roger Ebert quote “...for me, the movies are like a machine that generates empathy...” they’re applying those words to a movie that fails to reach that standard. In the case of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/11/3/moonlight.html"><em>Moonlight</em></a>, it seems that Ebert time-travelled forward, saw this film, and then had his eureka moment. </p>

<p><em>Moonlight</em>, like Picasso’s <em>Guernica</em>, or Kenji Mizoguchi’s <em>Sansho The Baliff</em>, evokes the universal while engaging in a granular depiction of the specific. Chiron (<em>Moonlight</em>’s singular protagonist—although he is played by three different actors) is inextricably linked to particular times and places and has a specificity that feels utterly genuine. Yet the movie somehow managed to unearth memories from <em>my</em> life, some of which are over forty years old.</p>

<p>There is a brief scene early in the film where Chiron—called Little in this preadolescent iteration of his character—is sitting across a breakfast table with Juan (a tremendous and atypical depiction of a drug kingpin by Mahershala Ali) and his partner Theresa. In the scene a child essentially asks a drug dealer “what does faggot mean?” Jesus. Juan’s answer was compassionate, yet still clearly the product of someone who understands some hard truths about how the world works. The film could have ended there and I would have walked away thinking how lucky I was to have seen this fifteen minute work.  </p>

<p>Because while I’m neither African American, nor gay, nor was I raised in the projects of Miami, that specific moment paralleled a profound experience in my own life that, looking back, was entirely formative. And perhaps, more crucially, <em>Moonlight</em> changed what that memory meant to me.</p>

<p>I was congenitally ill-equipped to navigate the byzantine and often cruel politics of childhood. While I was a bright and generally happy child, I just didn’t understand the larger game. In fact I wasn’t even aware I was playing the game. So one morning, the day after the umpteenth time I was chased home by a rock-throwing mob, I sat eating my cereal. As the usual dread grew a lump in my stomach, I asked my Mom a straightforward question: “is there something wrong with me?”</p>

<p>That my Mom didn’t have a pithy answer is just one of the fundamental differences between life and the movies. Although I’m pretty sure I remember a look of pity, mixed with despair. That was a look that I would see on her face more than few times in my life. </p>

<p>If this all seems a little autobiographical it is only to illustrate how effectively <em>Moonlight</em> dug around in my psyche. This film got to me in a way few films ever have. It was an unsettling experience, but in the best kind of way.</p>

<p>In most cases that would be enough for me to champion this film, but it is surprisingly not the aspect of <em>Moonlight</em> that has taken up the majority of my inner dialogue regarding this piece of fucking capital A art.</p>

<p>As effective as <em>Moonlight</em> is at creating connective tissue between the audience and the characters, what was most profound about the film was how it underlined the differences between my life and Chiron’s; that my small circle of experience will never encompass what it was like for him to grow up in circumstances I couldn’t begin to imagine. It is here that the specifics of his existence, so artfully wrought, make clear the importance of caution. Each frame of this film underscores a life fraught with obstacles and Gordian knots that probably would have crushed me long before I reached a place where I was even marginally capable of navigating them.</p>

<p>As a consequence of this, the most important thing I took away from <em>Moonlight</em> was a powerful reminder of the vast chasm between my lived experience and that of any other human. That while I may have glimpses into certain shared experiences, it is far removed from understanding the totality of other people’s history. That truth should leaven any sweeping pronouncements any of us make about understanding and empathy. To do otherwise is like living in a house balanced on a single twig.</p>

<p>Precipitous to say the least.</p>

<p>In the same way I will never be able to truly empathize with what it was like to cower under the falling bombs as the Stuka’s obliterated <em>Guernica</em>, nor will I ever really truly appreciate the existential sorrow of peasant life in feudal Japan, my understanding of Chiron’s life is filament thin. The most any film, or person, can hope to do is create and fleetingly sustain moments of tenuous connection. Any other claims are specious and fundamentally disrespectful.</p>

<p>That those two seemingly contradictory messages—that we all share some commonality but it is our differences that shape us and our relationships to one another—can exist, in exquisite tension, in one transcendent film is why <em>Moonlight</em> is, by far, the best film of 2016.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Arrival is the Best (and Profoundest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/17/arrival-is-the-best-and-profoundest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ArrivalistheBest(andProfoundest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-17T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-17T05:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/17/arrival-is-the-best-and-profoundest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Warning: spoilers ahead.</em> </p>

<p>A hundred years from now, will 2016 be remembered as the sociopolitical inflection point that it right now seems to be? Certainly the spate of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/national/police-shootings-2016/">horrific crimes</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Trump_presidential_campaign,_2016">societal regressions</a>, <a href="https://www.mercycorps.org/articles/iraq-jordan-lebanon-syria-turkey/quick-facts-what-you-need-know-about-syria-crisis">humanitarian crises</a>, and <a href="http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/bright-lights-starring-carrie-fisher-and-debbie-reynolds-2017">celebrity deaths</a> has justified many claims that it was the worst year ever. Such broad statements, however, discount all the great stuff that was produced throughout those twelve months: culturally significant pop albums like Beyonce’s <a href="http://www.beyonce.com/album/lemonade-visual-album/">“Lemonade”</a>; ground-breaking films like Barry Jenkins’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/11/3/moonlight.html"><em>Moonlight</em></a>; pioneering novels like Katharena Vermette’s <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/arts/books-and-media/book-reviews/review-katherena-vermettes-the-break-is-an-astonishing-act-of-empathy/article32021013/"><em>The Break</em></a>. Indeed, there was much great art created in 2016. Enough to balance out all the disheartening atavism? Perhaps that’s a question best leftto historians. </p>

<p>My favourite film of the year was the one that, in the midst of what seemed like the global collapse of common sense and dignity, affected me most deeply on a personal level. Which makes sense, I think. When the wider world becomes impossible to comprehend, one turns inwards. And my experience with this particular film was very intimate, very internal. In the hours after I left the theater I felt possessed – much like the film’s main character – of a radical new way of understanding the world. The people I observed in the aisles of the grocery store appeared more substantial to me; the empathy I felt for them as they browsed granola and orange juice and reprimanded their dawdling children was hugely amplified; the anxieties of my life seemed abstracted, shrunk down, drained of their power to oppress me.  </p>

<p>Yes, it’s true—this was what I experienced after watching an alien invasion movie filled with giant spaceships and roaring jet fighters and trigger-happy generals and, as it always seems to be these days (in movie as in life), the fate of the world hanging in the balance. </p>

<p><em>Arrival</em> is, first and foremost, a film of ideas. Some might find it cold, and I don’t blame them for being put off by the purposeful complexity of the story. The movie is a cryptogram, just like the weird alien ink-squiggles that the protagonist, linguist Louise Banks (played by Amy Adams), is tasked to translate. But however esoteric the narrative might be, the Big Idea that reveals itself at the end of the film has haunted me ever since. I think about it almost every day.  </p>

<p>That Big Idea is best expressed by summarizing the dilemma faced by Louise when she finally learns the truth about the byzantine alien language: would you know unimaginable pain in order to know unimaginable joy? </p>

<p>Of course this simple summary gets the chronology of the story wrong, but that’s in keeping with the film’s tricky treatment of passing time (which is not simply a storytelling conceit, but a brilliant expression of that core philosophical question itself). Here’s how it works within the narrative construct of the film: Louise knows joy, first; she has a daughter whom she loves, who, we learn in the very first minute of the film, dies of an untreatable disease at the age of ten. What we don’t know until later is that these are <em>not</em> flashbacks; this birth and death have yet to occur. And so, at the end of the film, she must choose whether or not to conceive this doomed child; whether to experience that decade of joy, knowing fully what awaits her at the end of it. All of the alien encounter stuff is merely prelude to the <em>real</em> beginning of Louise’s story. See the film a second time and you’ll be shocked to realize that she pretty much states this explicitly in her <em>very first</em> line of voice-over dialogue: “I’m not sure I believe in beginning and endings…”</p>

<p>This misdirection might not seem terribly sophisticated; in truth, it’s a total contrivance. But the way that contrivance is revealed – in subtle, sublime iterations – is masterful. Even the opening shot of the film offers clues: at the edge of the frame, the wine glass sitting on the table tells you everything you need to know about how everything will end (or begin). There is no close-up, no insert. You could watch the film a hundred times and miss that wine glass ninety-nine of them—but when you <em>do</em> see it there is an inevitability to the realization that comes remarkably close to simulating the experience of understanding the aliens’ circuitous, temporally-complex language.  </p>

<p>Tricking an audience is simple; implicating them in their own delusion requires the touch of a master filmmaker. And since director Denis Villeneuve has now <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/1/12/sicario-is-definitely-the-best-film-of-2015.html">topped my list two years in a row</a>, I suppose I can comfortably say that I consider him a master. </p>

<p>There is so much more to <em>Arrival</em> than the big plot twist, though: Johan Johansson’s <a href="http://songexploder.net/arrival">moody, methodical score</a>; the functionally brutalist production design by Patrice Vermette; the exacting, engrossing performances from the entire cast (even Forest Whitaker and his Afrikaner-by-way-of-Southie accent); Bradford Young’s cinematography, which is stark and epic as military choppers approach the ovoid monoliths, then soft and gauzy in moments of domestic parental bliss, feels like some divine commixture of David Lean and Terrence Malick.  </p>

<p>Yes, all this top-notch craft makes for a good night out at the movies. But what turned that good time into a moment of spiritual ecstasy for me wasn’t the craft, or the political message, or the mirrors and false floors and trapdoors of the plot. It was, instead, those most basic elements of filmic language, which, together, made that central theological question – the impossible sameness of joy and anguish –  real to me. </p>

<p>It was the images and the sounds.  </p>

<p>Simple images that evoked whole oceans of feeling: a newborn baby’s tiny fingers; a child running through tall grass; a little girl laying in bed with her father, reading a story. All set to a simple piece of music by composer Max Richter that is the very definition of bittersweet: looping, elegiac, unrelenting strings that seem the sonic manifestation of all the sorrow and happiness Louise feels throughout the film. The merging of those two elements devastated and elated me. They spoke to my greatest hopes and greatest fears. It made the film seem like it was made just for me, like it was released into theater just so that I would see it and finally come to understand how treacherous the world is and how blessed I am to know such happiness in the midst of it.  </p>

<p>My God, how unexpected to be filled with such spiritual sentiment after seeing a big-budget sci-fi flick! Or maybe not. Maybe I should have expected it. The scientific premise of the film is that language has the capacity to rewire your brain, and therefore to alter your perception of reality. Louise, after working for months to decipher the alien glyphs, now sees cause and effect as the enlightened extraterrestrials do: not as sequential, linear moments, but as part of a whole; Time as an overlapping, perpetual, redundant variable. One imagines that she might find herself in a grocery store, like I did after leaving the theater, and be able to observe the people around her not just in that one moment, in that one place, but, simultaneously, as every iteration of themselves that they <em>have been</em> and <em>will be</em>: a baby, a child, a teenager, an adult, a parent, a grandparent. And to consider, too, every single ordeal and adventure and moment of bliss and heartbreak each of those versions has experienced. She would thereby know them more deeply than I ever could; more deeply than they know themselves.  </p>

<p>We have been trained, over decades, to expect certain things from films like this. To have one’s expectations recalibrated the way that <em>Arrival</em> recalibrated mine is a special occurrence. And for that reason is it, undoubtedly, the best (and most profoundest) movie of the year. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Swiss Army Man is the Best (and Ballsiest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/16/swiss-army-man-is-the-best-and-ballsiest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SwissArmyManistheBest(andBallsiest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-16T11:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-16T11:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/16/swiss-army-man-is-the-best-and-ballsiest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Go ahead, say it. I know what you’re all thinking: only a juvenile jackoff would seriously go to bat for <em>Swiss Army Man</em> as the best film of the year. Normally, my tastes are disconcertingly populist. I’m the guy who regularly defends the Oscars’ <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/2/the-artist.html">Best Picture winners</a> as the <em>actual</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/9/12/argo.html">best pictures</a> of the year. Then along comes <em>Swiss Army Man</em>, rocking a painfully low 48% from Top Critics on Rotten Tomatoes. It might be the most poorly reviewed film I’ve ever thought was truly great. </p>

<p>But popular opinion be damned, I’m going all-out artsy-fartsy with my pick.</p>

<p>Actually, let’s talk about that term for a second. “Artsy-fartsy” is the sort of lazy, dismissive label your uncle uses to describe black and white movies with subtitles. No one takes the term seriously because, well, it rhymes, and makes no sense, and makes the person using it sound much dumber than whatever they’re trying to condescend. But I have a feeling co-directors Daniel Kwan and Daniel Scheinert (collectively credited as “DANIELS”) got drunk and tackled the notion of “artsy-fartsy” as a dare—one they took dead-serious. In doing so, they somehow managed to create the most audacious, endearing, entertaining, life-affirming, and unconventional film of the year. </p>

<p>Yes, the movie about the farting corpse. Not the movie with <em>a scene</em> that features corpse-farts (which would be normal-ish), but the movie whose very plot is <em>fueled</em> by farts. It&#39;s worth focusing on, too (this isn’t <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-38037187">Parliament</a>, after all, and I’m sick of reading lukewarm <a href="http://variety.com/2016/film/reviews/swiss-army-man-film-review-1201685807/">reviews</a> that send me to the dictionary just the writer can avoid typing that four-letter word). Farts aren’t just played for laughs in <em>Swiss Army Man</em>—they’re the whole point. The film takes body humour to such absurd lengths in order to reach an insanely ambitious goal. “We want to make a movie where the first fart makes you laugh,” the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MyPbLmXYxTs">original pitch</a> went, “and the last one makes you cry.”  </p>

<p>Well, fuck. Mission accomplished.</p>

<p>The very first shots of the film announce the filmmakers’ creativity, humour, and knack for concise storytelling. Garbage origami floats on the ocean, with pleas for help scrawled upon each (too cutely) crafted vessel. Paul Dano, in full <em>Castaway</em> mode as Hank, is about to hang himself when he notices a body wash upon the shore. He races towards the corpse, nearly hangs himself in the process, and attempts to will the body back to life with frantic pleas and mouth-to-mouth resuscitation. But instead of the body gasping for air (as we see in every other film), the body releases a windfall of flatulence (sorry—<em>farts</em>). It’s funny, and then it gets silly, and by the time Hank is riding the body like a fart-fuelled jet-ski across the ocean, it goes full-on insane. All this, remember, before the film’s opening title even hits the screen.</p>

<p>I’ve never fallen in love with a movie so hard and so fast.</p>

<p>Usually, when an outrageous moment is used to describe a film, it comes at the end: the movie where the guy cuts off his own arm; the movie where people are sewn together ass-to-mouth. I went into <em>Swiss Army Man</em> assuming that the ending had been spoiled for me, and found myself elated to only be at the beginning of a bizarre journey. And in holding on for the ride (unlike many of you who <a href="http://variety.com/2016/film/news/daniel-radcliffe-farting-corpse-swiss-army-man-1201686756/">walked out</a> at the Sundance premiere), I leapt head-first into a world of magical realism, leaving behind the twin bouncers, Why and How, who usually work the door of my critical faculties. </p>

<p>It’s a testament to the commitment of the film’s directors and actors that the allegorical lyricism never crosses into all out fantasy; they are constantly challenging you to take the premise seriously. The film never privileges Hank’s perspective, isolating our first glances of Manny’s gurgling and twitching body from our hero’s perspective. To keen observers, this removes any anticipation for a<em>Fight Club</em> twist that would have us re-watch the film knowing that Manny’s bizarre re-animation (played with uncanny perfection by Daniel Radcliffe) was all in Hank’s mind. It is, obviously, and it isn’t, amazingly, and by striking that impossible balance the film also manages to cheat death. </p>

<p><em>Swiss Army Man</em> holds its spell by embracing the fact that it is, undeniably, a <em>film</em>: unnaturally beautiful lighting, over-the-top sound design, hand-crafted sets within the set, comically dangerous stunts, slow-motion and speed ramps for emphasis. Even the music during the montage, which gives me goosebumps every time I hear it, features the characters singing along to the wildly catchy lyrics “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fh8qNRp55rQ">Pop popcorn, pop popcorn, pop popcorn</a>)”. The characters breach the fourth wall just enough to share our space, but never wink (or, in Manny’s case, even blink) at the film’s design by betraying our belief in this hairy-assed fairy tale. The film is pure cinema, and delightfully puerile. Watching it is akin to falling into someone else’s dream, where every subconscious insecurity and eccentricity is amplified into ludicrous detail, but also kind-hearted and familiar enough to insist that your presence is welcome. As Hank might say: a movie that doesn’t hide its farts has nothing to hide. </p>

<p>It would be groan-inducing for me to extrapolate layers of meaning from the film’s surface obsession with body functions (poop, masturbation, erections) and mental malfunctions. This focus is a natural extension of DANIELS bewildering and beautiful <a href="http://www.danieldaniel.us/">music videos and short films</a>. Plus, I think the film’s thesis is best summed up by Manny, delivered with childish naivety in what has to be the best and most unconventional performance of the year: “Maybe we&#39;re all just dying sacks of shit, and maybe all it&#39;ll take is one person to just be okay with that, and then the whole world will be dancing and singing and farting, and everyone will feel a little bit less alone.”</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>O.J.: Made in America</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/16/oj-made-in-america.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=O.J.:MadeinAmerica" />
    <published>2017-01-16T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-16T05:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/16/oj-made-in-america</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>When you’re too close to a situation, or you’re unable to see things objectively, it’s important to gain some perspective. Oftentimes, changing the angle of something can, for better or worse, alter your relationship to that thing. For instance, your job involves filming from a high vantage point, to quite literally show us the bigger picture. When that picture involves race, fame, justice, and the most high-profile double murder case of the 20th century, it would be absurd to even attempt to achieve the kind of space and time needed to view it without hyperbole or prejudice.  But if you have ESPN’s epic <em>30 for 30</em> banner, documentarian Ezra Edelman, and close to 8 hours to explore a subject as toothsome as O.J. Simpson, anything is possible.</p>

<p>Maybe you were like me. Maybe you thought you knew everything you needed to know about O.J. Simpson, a famous athlete and actor made infamous by his role in the murder of his ex-wife Nicole Brown, and waiter Ron Goldman. For several years it was almost impossible to escape the spectre of what became known as “The Trial of the Century”. Having lived through the surreal experience once was enough. And if <em>O.J.: Made in America</em> was just about the trial, it might not have made the impact that it has with audiences and critics alike. </p>

<p>Edelman views O.J. through the prism of race, specifically in Los Angeles, and specifically within the last several decades beginning with the African-American diaspora from Jim Crow States to Southern California in the early 20th Century. Though California was desegregated, it was not without a deeply entrenched racial divide between its black citizens and overwhelmingly white law enforcement. For (predominantly white) people who still, two decades after the case, cannot understand why African-Americans were cheering in the streets when a clearly guilty O.J. was acquitted, this overlooked backstory is imperative. But if it was just about race, <em>O.J.: Made in America</em> would be compelling—but not necessarily vital.</p>

<p><em>O.J.: Made In America</em> weaves race, celebrity, domestic violence, entitlement, media, and the law together to form a narrative thread that is ultimately about more than O.J. It’s about us. Edelman manages to humanize all the players in a way that no one has yet been able to do successfully. His remarkably candid interviews with people like Marcia Clark, Carl Douglas, Mark Fuhrman and members of the jury, the Goldman and Brown families, and others close to O.J., give us insight into how much—if any—impact the passage of time has had. The breadth of archival footage is married to a score that is at times portentous, at times arch, and consistently enhances the tone of the film, which manages to transcend the medium to stand alone as a work of art. </p>

<p>Broken up into five distinct episodes, <em>O.J.: Made in America</em> starts with a look at O.J. as a rising star athlete on the USC football team. Your camera pans over the stadium which butts up against the community of Watts, forever known for its 1965 riots which began as a response to police brutality. We learn that O.J., unlike other black athletes at the time—Cassuis Clay (Muhammad Ali), Lew Alcindor (Kareem Abdul-Jabbar), Tommy Douglas, Jim Brown, Bill Russell—was uninterested in the Civil Rights struggle, or in advocating for anyone but himself. He once famously said, “I’m not black, I’m O.J.”He was interested in fame, and was seduced by 
elite white society. And by the end of his professional football career (and this first episode) he was an unhappily married man in love with an 18 year-old waitress named Nicole Brown.</p>

<p>The second episode paints a picture of two separate worlds: the wealthy, privileged world of O.J.’s Brentwood (a suburb of Los Angeles you show us by soaring seductively over its stately manses, manicured lawns and golf courses), and the world inhabited by black L.A. – one of random beatings, property damage, and infringements of basic rights at the hands of police officers. Inserted into this, threatening O.J.’s reputation as a “nice guy” who invites cops over for barbecues, is a chilling 911 call from a severely beaten Nicole. But there is a different set of rules for a beloved sports icon than there are say, for Rodney King, whose beating at the hands of cops ignites the tensions of smouldering resentment among the black community resulting in the L.A. riots of 1992.</p>

<p>It isn’t until episode three, over three hours in, that we learn of the murders of O.J.’s now ex-wife Nicole Brown, and her friend Ron Goldman, who happened to be at the wrong place at the wrong time.  You glide slowly over present-day Los Angeles freeways, which are almost strangely idyllic, especially when juxtaposed against some of the most surreal footage ever filmed, the infamous white Bronco chase. Here Edelman turns the events of June 17th, 1994 over to the people who lived it: the SWAT team who surrounded OJ’s Rockingham estate; the cops and EMTs waiting in his house; Officer Lange who spoke to O.J. while he was in the Bronco threatening suicide; and Zoe (formerly Bob) Tur, the helicopter pilot who filmed the entire thing. Edelman frames the events of that day in the context of an accidental pop cultural phenomenon. He manages to recapture the thrill of watching it for the first time but he wraps it in an uneasy nostalgia. Our morbid fascination with celebrity and death has become entertainment. </p>

<p>Episode four concerns itself with the trial, and Edelman makes the decision to show some of the crime scene photographs. These photographs have not been widely released before, and the response they illicit is visceral. By this point Edelman has made Nicole a whole person, a wife, a sister, a daughter, a mother, a friend. We’ve seen excerpts of her journals, we’ve seen footage of her swinging contentedly in a hammock with her daughter, Sydney, and pictures of her arm in arm with her parents. Ron Goldman is remembered by his father, and in pictures, and is given the kind of dimension the media circus never afforded him during the trial. Showing the crime scene photos doesn’t feel sensational, or exploitative. On the contrary, their inclusion feels necessary. They cut through the white noise of the trial that two-plus decades on continues to be deafening. </p>

<p>The final episode prepares us for the verdict and Edelman amps up the intensity with footage of the L.A. police force bracing for the worst. He shows us the stark difference of the reactions between white and black communities when O.J. is acquitted. He speaks to the members of the black clergy who opened up their houses of worship to O.J., and he shows us O.J.’s once beloved community of Brentwood where he has become a pariah. In the years following the civil trial, O.J. must pay the Goldman family $33 million dollars, and we see a man quickly descending to rock bottom. He loses his home, moves to Miami, has difficulties raising his children. He fills his days making tasteless reality television, and his nights with cocaine and wannabe porn stars. By the time O.J. ends up arrested for trying to steal back his own memorabilia and sentenced to 33 years in prison, he is a broken man. Edelman makes sure this downfall is not played for cathartic effect, he does not want us to feel relief in O.J.’s fall from grace. And miraculously, we don’t.</p>

<p>Throughout the film, your camera pans over different neighbourhoods, over buildings like the L.A. Courthouse, Nicole’s home, and streets where rioting and celebrating took place. These places were ordinary until a strange event made them extraordinary. The effect is haunting. We see these places differently now, than we would have five, ten or even twenty years ago. The O.J. Simpson trial changed the way we view fame, race, sports heroism, marriage, and domestic violence. It changed the media and the way the business and ethics of news is conducted. It changed us. Perhaps that is why this over seven hour film is absolutely riveting, and utterly fascinating in its depiction of an exceptional young black man in the context of a deeply divided America, and a world where privilege trumps morality. </p>

<p>Time has given us the perspective we needed to see things more clearly and confront an uneasy yet stark reality. The question of “who made O.J.?” is not unanswered by the end of this magnum opus. The answer is simple; we did.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Live by Night</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/13/live-by-night.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LivebyNight" />
    <published>2017-01-13T11:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-13T11:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/13/live-by-night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Show don’t tell. That’s the first commandment of screenwriting. Why say something when you can show it in any number of exciting ways? That’s why visual storytelling has always been so popular, from the first cave drawings to today’s bombastic, special effects-heavy superhero films. But as thrilling or breathtaking as a film might look, without a solid story as its foundation, it becomes nothing more than eye-candy and empty calories. </p>

<p><em>Live by Night</em>, based on Dennis Lehane’s novel, is Ben Affleck’s latest, and it reminded me a lot of the actor himself; handsome enough, sure, but a little light on substance. I have more regard for Ben’s skills as a director. <em>Gone Baby Gone</em> and <em>Town</em> were both well-crafted, brilliantly acted thrillers. <em>Argo</em> was a <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/9/12/argo.html">pitch-perfect</a> period-piece that sent up both Hollywood and Washington (though it doesn’t hold up so well under repeat viewing). <em>Live by Night</em> is a gangster flick that looks better than his other three films, but doesn’t match their level of storytelling. It’s a very pretty face trying – and almost succeeding – to distract us from its plain-Jane narrative. </p>

<p>The film gets off to a cracking start as we learn that Affleck’s Joe, a veteran of the First World War, robs Boston’s banks, not because he’s a gangster, because he’s an <em>outlaw</em>. An outlaw with a police chief father who disapproves of his off-the-boat Irish girlfriend who also happens to be a real gangster’s moll. It’s this Irish mob boss, Albert White, and his feud with an Italian mob boss, that sweep Joe up in a decade’s worth of rum-running, gambling, and double-crossing in Prohibition-era Florida. </p>

<p>Your job is to help the director plan his vision of the film shot by shot, sketch by sketch. And it doesn’t take very long for your work to come to life. In an effort for him and his girlfriend to make a clean break from Albert White, Joe and his gang plan one last heist, but it goes awry. A succession of quick cuts shows us a foot on the pedal of the getaway car, a shotgun blast, the car slamming into another car, the steering wheel, a cop! It’s edge-of-your-seat exciting, ending in a great tableau of an upended car on fire in a lake, with Joe standing in the background. If only the rest of the film sustained this level of symbiosis between visuals and narrative. </p>

<p>But there are moments. Mostly from the exemplary cast Affleck has assembled. A trick he employed in <em>Town</em> and <em>Argo</em>, two films he both directed <em>and</em> starred in, was to surround himself with far better actors than himself and take on the less showy role. Unfortunately he gave himself the lead here, and <em>Live by</em> <em>Night</em> suffers for it. In his hands, Joe never becomes more than the prototypical “gangster with a conscience”. Sorry, <em>outlaw</em>. I kept wondering how an actor like Leonardo DiCaprio, or Christian Bale might have given Joe some layers, or at least a fighting chance in keeping up with Brendan Gleeson as Joe’s dad, Sienna Miller as his trashy girlfriend, Matthew Maher as a creepy KKK sociopath, Chris Cooper as the sympathetic police chief, or Elle Fanning (in easily the best role of the film) as Cooper’s disgraced flapper daughter. The fault might be that the characters are so flimsily rendered in the first place that it took incredible actors to bring them to life. Poor Zoe Saldana deserved a meatier role. As Joe’s Cuban wife, she is given little to do but look pretty. </p>

<p>And oh, does this film look pretty. One of the best things about <em>Argo</em> was its fanatical devotion to period accuracy (an ashtray in every scene!), a trait <em>Live by Night</em> shares. From the sumptuous Art Deco surroundings, to the sensual fur, satin and linen costumes, and the South Florida hotels, diners and speakeasys so palpably humid, Affleck’s attention to detail is commendably obsessive. He frames his shots carefully – a droplet of blood falling into a crystal tumbler, an eye-sized bullet hole in a car window framing a freshly shot eye – that they almost feel like panels in a graphic novel. I give kudos to you for giving him the blueprint to make these scenes a reality. </p>

<p>At its best, <em>Live by Night</em> recalls other gangster flicks like <em>Road to Perdition</em>, <em>Carlito’s Way</em>, and <em>The Untouchables</em>, but it fails to sustain their level of gravitas. The film’s rhythm stops and starts, its better characters aren’t around long enough, and the tone never finds its sweet spot. You drew out this movie, and Affleck rendered it beautifully, but this is one of those times I wish I’d read the book instead.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>