<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-02T10:38:23Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lights Out</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/2/nerve.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LightsOut" />
    <published>2016-08-02T06:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-02T06:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/2/nerve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If you’re reading this, you’re committed to having kids soon. As your past self, I assume you’re still worrying about the kind of societal pressures your kids will face once they reach their formidable teenage years. I sure as hell am at age 23 – especially having just walked out of <em>Nerve</em>. </p>

<p>Today, I see the rise of mobile apps like Snapchat and Pokémon Go and witness what adolescents need to be doing in order to fit in. Back when we were in high school, a student wasn’t even spoken to if they didn’t have a shiny flip phone to text all your friends during class; and considering that we didn’t have a phone until grade 12, the first three years of high school were just peachy, weren’t they? That was the extent of what we had to deal with. Today, there are a whole slew of apps that determine how well teens rank in popularity — and what they do on those apps determines the hallway fame they so desperately crave.</p>

<p>That’s the concept behind <em>Nerve</em>, a thriller starring Dave Franco and Emma Roberts. In <em>Nerve</em>, if you don’t remember, teens are flocking towards the latest digital craze, a new app called Nerve that takes truth or dare to a whole other level. In the game Nerve, you decide whether you’re a ‘Watcher’ or a ‘Player’. Watchers set dares for Players to accomplish. If Players successfully complete the dare, they’re rewarded with a cash prize. The tougher the dare, the higher the cash value. </p>

<p>The premise is simple, solid and impactful. <em>Nerve</em>, in my opinion, is 2016’s sleeper hit. </p>

<p><em>Nerve</em> is essentially one giant PSA for teens to stop seeking admiration online, but it tackles the subject in a very subtle manner. <em>Nerve</em> provides suspense, humour, mystery, and entertainment. Rather than pandering to a youthful demographic, like Hillary Clinton trying to ‘Whip’ and ‘Nae Nae’ in what has to be the most cringe-worthy Ellen segment, ever, <em>Nerve</em> sticks to the script and focuses on being a movie first, and a message, second. </p>

<p>A movie that sends a message is one thing, but a movie that provides entertainment and sends a message is a star in my book.</p>

<p>As we progress further into <em>Nerve</em>, we begin to see the dark side of the internet. The side of the internet that feeds off the misery and pain of others. One such moment is when Dave Franco’s character, Ian, is dared to dangle from a construction crane — with one hand. As a human being with pretty stand-up morals, I was very much against Ian going through with the dare, but as a moviegoer, I was on the edge of my seat. The theatre was pin-drop silent during this scene, with the only noises being faint gasps and squirms. </p>

<p>It’s these type of scare tactics that help <em>Nerve</em> get their point across. We’ve all seen the strange and extremely <a href="">dangerous</a> online trends that people participate in to obtain their 15 minutes of internet fame. Dangling off a crane doesn’t seem so out of the ordinary when put into perspective — which is terrifying and thought-provoking. Since we get to know Ian during our time viewing <em>Nerve</em>, the thought of him dying terrifies us, but when we see some teens doing something similar on our Facebook feed, we laugh it off as a bunch of dumb kids doing dumb shit. </p>

<p>Why don’t we have the same breath-held reaction as we did in the theatre? Why are we encouraging their behaviour by sharing the content? Are these kids really stupid or desperate for some type of belonging? </p>

<p><em>Nerve</em> paints an alarming picture of the fate of our world as online trends get more inclusive and sharing our lives through our phones gets more and more normalized. </p>

<p>I know you’re worried about the type of dangers that await your offspring, and truth be told, there isn’t anything you can do to stop it. Every generation will bring new challenges. You will just have to try your best and pray to your Supreme Leader Trump that nobody creates an app like <em>Nerve</em> in real life.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Rashomon Effect</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/27/the-rashomon-effect.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheRashomonEffect" />
    <published>2016-07-27T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-27T06:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/27/the-rashomon-effect</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The Rashomon Effect<br>
<em>The Rashomon effect is contradictory interpretations of the same event by different people. The phrase derives from the film Rashomon, where the accounts of the witnesses, suspects, and victims of a murder and possible rape are all different.</em></p>

<p>Since I have a little bit more to say about <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html">Jared’s piece</a> I’ll start with that, and then I’ll have a run at <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong.html">Christopher’s take</a>.</p>

<p>I find it both fascinating and crazy frustrating that two people can experience the same film in such entirely different ways. And while I certainly think that the circumstances surrounding the experience—the theatre, the individual’s state of mind, beer or no beer, the relative quality of the popcorn—all matter to one degree or the other, I still believe we would have probably ended up in roughly the same place regarding <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/23/de-palma.html"><em>De Palma</em></a>.</p>

<p>One of the reasons for that is pretty obvious. We all live in our own bubbles of consciousness, our own little universe. We see the world from a fundamentally subjective viewpoint that is utterly distinct from any other, so inevitably any common experience—when held up in comparison—will be out of sync.</p>

<p>Given that inevitability, it is kind of wondrous that any of us manage to communicate at all. But we do, and for the most part we find enough common ground that we can share, with varying degrees of coherence, our worlds. Where this all becomes interesting to me is when two interpretations of the same experience vary so completely, especially when the people involved (in this case  and I) share a lot in common.</p>

<p>We’re both white males, both fairly astute, both committed to the idea that film is worth the time and energy to try and appreciate beyond simple consumption, and we both think <a href="">Denis Villeneuve’s</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/10/26/sicario.html"> Sicario</a> is at, or near, the apex of a particular type of filmmaking. We share a common culture and seem to have similar points of reference. But our experience of the same film, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/23/de-palma.html"><em>De Palma</em></a>, couldn’t have been more different.</p>

<p>Some of that difference is baked in, but it is the degree to which we differ that is what I find so fascinating, and is the primary reason why film criticism, or cultural criticism of any stripe, is sometimes so valuable. It is those differences, and how coherently they are expressed, that help bracket a film, that creates a context for others to see what is, or isn’t, intrinsically valuable about a particular work. That we can manage to express our experiences and POV in a way that is comprehensible to others is miracle enough, but to be able to overlay that with an analysis that can sometimes enhance someone else’s experience is really something special.</p>

<p>There are probably as many reasons as there are De Palma films for why we differ so completely in this case, but I think there is one specific difference that is built on a first principle. Our perception of De Palma as both filmmaker and human is diametrically opposed. You see a ‘charismatic guy sitting in a chair’ whereas I see a broken old man. You see ‘an artistic complexity and ambition of vision’ whereas I see a fundamental emptiness of spirit compensated for by technical sleight of hand. And the most baffling of truths in all of this is that I suspect we are both right—as much as that means anything at all.</p>

<p>That is why all this writing and talking and listening and arguing matters. Every time I take on board someone else’s view of a shared experience, my own little universe gets slightly bigger.</p>

<p>Every time I’m required to re-examine and re-evaluate my own experience because someone differs with me, it means I’m less likely to get stuck in the mire of my own neural pathways. And for me that is pretty much what life is—the evolution of your own pocket universe. And what that universe looks like, how fecund or arid it is, comes down to a person’s capacity and willingness to engage with viewpoints that contrast with their own. </p>

<p>Which brings me round to Christopher’s piece and how I think that he is very correctyet , I would add one caveat. Since one of the things about what we do at DCAC is to write to specific cast members, I sometimes find that I’m thinking more about the filmmakers and less about potential audiences when I write. And while I hardly expect what I’m writing to be read by its intended recipient, it stills strikes me as a valuable exercise for one very specific reason. What we do, what all film and culture is really about, is this ceaseless back and forth, this exchange of opinion, knowledge, creativity, criticism and most importantly, our specific experiences interacting with some or all of the above.</p>

<p>So maybe I’m less clear about the boundaries than you are, Christopher, but perhaps that is as much to do with my tendency towards the autodidactic as anything else. What I do agree with is maintaining the balance point between literary onanism and pertinent self-reference (for instance—using terms like onanism). The problem being, even the line between excess and useful is almost entirely arbitrary, and has as much to do with the reader as it does the writer.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, I will never stop being surprised that everyone doesn’t see the world the way I do, but I also will never stop trying to find ways to clearly articulate what it is that I think and feel about the culture I experience. And in the end whether we agree or not is utterly inconsequential, because what matters is that we can manage to express those differences in ways that change the colors in someone else’s world, even just a little bit.</p>

<p>So, thank you both for doing a little bit of painting.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>There Are Two Ways to Judge a Film. And the Other One is Wrong.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ThereAreTwoWaystoJudgeaFilm.AndtheOtherOneisWrong." />
    <published>2016-07-27T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-27T03:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Let’s talk about the nature of criticism and the role of a critic.</p>

<p>There are micro conditions (popcorn quality, sleep deprivation, theatre setting) and macro conditions (time of year, proximity to similar releases) that affect our reaction to a film. We’re human, and reviews shouldn’t be written like a multiple choice exam. But there is a necessary balance between cold-hearted calculations and masturbatory extra-textual analysis. </p>

<p>Our job as critics is not to dive inward and explain why a certain moment at our junior high dance made us feel a certain way about a certain scene. The more you try to decode your subjectivity, the more you abdicate your role as a critic. You become an investigative reporter on your own emotions, and the result (while often pleasant to read) is ultimately only relevant to a single viewing experience. If you’re always interrogating your personal history and circumstances in relation to a film, then you’re still just reacting to films. You’re not being a critic. </p>

<p>No one is asking you to divorce yourself from your subjectivity (<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html">that which makes your perspective unique</a>), but you do have a responsibility to control it. In fact, you <em>have</em> to if you want to build trust with your audience. </p>

<p>There’s a reason professional critics are creatures of routine. They usually sit in the same theatre seats, arrive at approximately the same time before a screening, and get used to the hallow of empty press screenings or the over-enthused energy of advance public screenings. Like a professional athlete, you need to learn how to tune out as many distractions as possible. And the more you’re able to do that without losing your talent and energy, the more you become a star. Everything else is bush league.</p>

<p>We’ve all seen YouTube videos of dazzling plays by junior athletes, or marveled at impossible trick shots. The same can be said about amateur critics who give blistering sarcastic reviews or blow up with emotion praising a new franchise film that gave them a reason to live again. But professionals provide us something else. The roll of the critic is to stick handle personal emotions with finesse and beauty, without ever forgetting that there is a goal in mind. The audience wants to walk away knowing the score – otherwise it feel like watching a skills competition or backyard practice.</p>

<p>In that spirit, major film festivals and the awards season are akin to the playoffs. The stakes are high and pressure is ever-present. Everyone is prone to over-praising certain moments or pilling on t under-performers. So should a critic’s job be to judge every film by these extra-textual conditions? Are those the critics you trust when trying to decide where to spend your time and money as an audience member? If a bad burrito gave a blogger indigestion before a screening, is it your responsibility as a reader to separate out that stink from his review? </p>

<p>The best critics of our time understand how to make an experience relatable to an audience. They look at art and engage a special set of skills to blend formal analysis with personal context. And the ones we dismiss outright are usually the ones we know can’t trust their own reactions because they are too easily influenced by circumstance. Their contribution to the larger cultural discussion becomes muted, andeven less benefi over time. </p>

<p>All this to say, I still can’t decide if I want to watch the De Palma documentary.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lights Out</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/26/lights-out.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LightsOut" />
    <published>2016-07-26T19:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T19:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/26/lights-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Lights Out</em> is adapted from a well-regarded short film of the same name. </p>

<p>…and in that statement lies the central difficulty that plagues this inconsistent, only occasionally interesting film: how do you manage to expand a perfect little three minute short into a feature length film.</p>

<p>In some ways you succeeded. There is some real depth of character here, with a couple of performances that hint at a rich backstory. However, what you didn’t manage to develop—and this is crucial to a film that mixes the supernatural with the mundane—is a compelling mythology.</p>

<p>Effective horror depends upon creating a world that allows and encourages the suspension of disbelief. For a film to really crawl into your head, it must convince the you that the monster, whether it’s a relentless xenomorph, a young child inhabited by a devil, a pagan harridan preying upon an isolated New England family, or even a robotic assassin, is grounded in a reality that is credible in the context of the central concept. </p>

<p>To achieve this without bogging the film down in endless, dry exposition is difficult. In <em>Lights Out</em> you manage, for the most part, to avoid the dreary exposition. But you didn’t manage to create a mythology that felt like anything other than a cut and paste horror franchise origin story. Your monster had no depth, and because of that everything else felt kind of weightless. </p>

<p>Often the most tragic element (and therefore most compelling) of horror films is how the creature came into being, but if you fail to convey that in a plausible way, it undermines what gives these kinds of film their visceral power. One of the better examples of this is <em>Ringu</em>, a Japanese horror film from 1998 (a film which <em>Lights Out</em> shares more than a little DNA with, especially visually). In <em>Ringu</em> we’re given evocative hints about how the demonic apparition came to be, and moreover we are led to feel more than a little compassion for the creature. This doesn’t happen with the fumbling and perfunctory attempts that <em>Lights Out</em> makes at creating a similar mythos.</p>

<p>There are some effective visual conceits throughout <em>Lights Out</em> that involve light and the absence of it, but too often the story seems pushed into corners to accommodate these sequences. And while the performances range from solid to exceptional (Maria Bello’s interpretation of a mentally disturbed mother is unsettling in its authenticity) the contrast between them and the cobbled together feeling of the creature’s backstory only serves to highlight the film’s central weakness.</p>

<p>Where <em>Lights Out</em> works best is in set pieces common to this genre. There are a couple of scenes involving Maria Bello and her young son, as well as one other unseen participant that are masterfully blocked to maximize tension. In these moments <em>Lights Out</em> creates a sense of dread that is not just about the shock of the reveal, but also about how something in the dark can be whispering your death into the ear of someone who you expect to protect and nurture you.</p>

<p>If the whole film had lived more fully in these moments, if you had managed to ground something fantastic in something that felt convincing, <em>Lights Out</em> would have been something more than an occasionally watchable genre film. </p>

<p>Horseshoes and hand grenades.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My De Palma is Better Than Your De Palma</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MyDePalmaisBetterThanYourDePalma" />
    <published>2016-07-26T12:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T12:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>This is a thing I’ve long wondered about criticism in general and film criticism in particular: how can one disassociate the experience of art with the object of art itself? </p>

<p>No one reads a book or listens to music or watches a film in a total vacuum of objective critical focus. These are entertainments, and the whole notion of entertainment is to distract or edify or otherwise conjure good feelings inside one’s brain and/or heart. A book that you read on a beach in Mexico during a much-needed vacation from the crushing responsibilities of your professional life is experienced in a very different way than the book you read in fifteen-minute iterations over the course of a month on the bus that carries you each day to and from the crushing responsibilities of that professional life. A song that you first hear faintly playing in the background at a friend’s barbecue certainly affects you in a different way than the song that was playing at your junior high mixer when you looked across the gymnasium and saw Jessica Harbicht slow-dancing with Eric Forbes and <em>his hands</em> were <em>in her back pockets</em>! </p>

<p>And films. Films are the worst. Particularly when you see them in theaters. Because orbiting around the theater experience are numerous considerations: arrangements to be made (with friends, Tinder dates, babysitters); snacks (salty, sweet, unhealthy, <em>extremely</em> unhealthy); and, worst/best of all, other people sitting around you, each having their own unique moviegoing experience. </p>

<p>We like to think, as aficionados, that our arcane knowledge trumps our subjectivity—that somehow our understanding of, say, Auteur Theory or Apparatus Theory, or our devotion to Pauline Kael or Andrew Sarris, colours our ability to rationally judge an experience more than, say, whether you were able to time your arrival at the front of the concession to coincide with a freshly-popped batch of popcorn, or whether you got stuck with one of those limp three-quarters-full bags that has been sitting under a heat lamp for twenty minutes and turns out to be, once you dig to deeper strata, mostly composed of broken, burnt bits scraped from the bottom of the machine hours earlier. I can’t understand how a person can <em>honestly</em> say that the middle act of <em>Interstellar</em> is too self-serious and meandering when there’s a chance they might have been eating a bag of popcorn like that.</p>

<p>So what can I tell you, Tim, of my experience watching Noah Baumbach and Jake Paltrow’s documentary, <em>De Palma</em>, that isn’t deeply influenced by the physical conditions of my immediate environment and precise circumstances of my life in that particular moment of time? </p>

<p>I arrived at the VanCity Theater in Vancouver in a state of existential unease. The kind that is unique to business travel, wherein one is simultaneously relieved to be away from the routine of the 9-to-5 workday – the small talk with colleagues, the big talk with bosses – and also perturbed by the uncertainties of the foreign workday that awaits: the new people to make small talk with, the big talk one must inevitably engage in to justify the cost of cross-continent plane fare and deluxe accommodation. Not to mention the part where one misses one’s family and resents being taken away from them, yet simultaneously feels guiltily glad to be away from them and have a bit of freedom to, say, eat an entire pizza for dinner and then go to a movie alone.</p>

<p>The VanCity Theater is an exceptional little place. It’s not one of those old repertory cinemas with an ornate marquee, columns and lintels, velvet curtains and vintage, musty odors. They <em>do</em> have a little exterior ticket window, and the interior is laid out like the lobby of a hip hotel, all plain white walls, tall windows, café tables and couches. I arrived early enough to buy a beer and a package of licorice and lounge around for a while. The others waiting in the lobby with me were so typical of the demographic you might imagine to be loitering in the lobby of a nifty modern theater in Vancouver that it seems somehow cruel to describe them in further detail other than to say they were wealthy and middle-aged and predominantly white.  </p>

<p>When the doors eventually opened, we poured in and selected our seats a respectful distance from one another, passing the last few minutes before showtime watching the screen upon which an upcoming retrospective on mid-century Cuban cinema was being promoted. The place smelled like a classroom. The seats were soft and deep and ergonomically supportive. My cold beer sat sweating in the cupholder, waiting. This, the beginning of things. </p>

<p>I was overcome with such a sense of peace and excitement in that moment of prologue that I felt it physically; like there was a nozzle in my chest and someone had attached a hose and released into my body a hissing blast of ice-cold helium. The iris closed and blacked out the whole complicated fractal spread of my life – the myriad responsibilities both professional and personal and the myriad fears and anxieties attached to each of them – and I was <em>there</em>, in the theater, <em>present in the cosmic moment</em> in that Zen Buddhist way that self-help books about mindfulness try (and fail) to teach you how to conjure at will. </p>

<p>So, Tim, here’s the essential question I want to ask you:</p>

<p>Was <em>De Palma</em> a sublime moviegoing experience because it was a terrifically constructed and materially fascinating film which in its deceptive simplicity – basically just a single-take of a charismatic guy sitting in a chair in what appears to be his dining room, chatting unreservedly about his long and controversial career – is able to convey an artistic complexity and ambition of vision that on the surface of Brian De Palma’s <em>actual</em> films is difficult to identify (and maybe, in some cases, completely invisible)? </p>

<p>Or was the sublimity I experienced an effect of my mood, and of my physiological reaction to the hoppy IPA and perfectly supple licorice whips and the library-like quiet of the lobby and my desperate need, that particular evening, to remove myself from the world?</p>

<p>What we often pretend at, in criticism, is that we are not people, but rather these free-floating consciousnesses—bodiless intellectual machines that can process the pure data of a Thing and output an absolute empirical answer about whether or not that Thing sucks or is awesome or is just kinda okay. But movies – even analytical documentaries like this – are not expressions of pure intellectual substance. And people – even knowledgeable, tasteful people like me (self-proclaimed) – have memories and desires and are subject to unknowable subconscious prejudices. </p>

<p>The answer to the question I’ve asked above (which I’ll admit I don’t know) probably goes a long way to explaining my <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/3/iron-man-3.html">own</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/8/thor-the-dark-world.html">curious</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/30/x-men-days-of-future-past.html">reaction</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/7/27/the-dark-knight-rises.html">to</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/18/captain-america-civil-war.html">superhero</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html">movies</a>, as well as the dissonance many critics feel between their immediate instinctive response to a film and the broadening (or shrinking) of perspective they experience after the passing of a few days or weeks or even years (after that time has passed, they must reconcile their memories of that film with their experience of seeing it, which has been amplified or shrunken by their autobiographical memory). </p>

<p>When the end of the year arrives and we start compiling our lists of the best films of the year, <em>De Palma</em> will be at the top of mine. Perhaps by then I may have a sense that it wasn’t <em>objectively</em> the best motion picture released in the last 12 months. But our favorite things are never objective. They <em>belong</em> to us. We possess them, and we do so because they are meaningful beyond the simple diegetic expression of what we have seen onscreen and heard on the soundtrack. Our favorite movies mean something—not just because they are good, but because, in some way, they made our lives good, too.</p>

<p>For those two hours in Vancouver, at a time when I desperately needed it, <em>De Palma</em> made my life better. Which, on its own, is no criteria by which anyone should decide to rush out and see it. But is reason enough for me to judge it, empirically, unfairly, but totally accurately, a five-star film. </p>

<p>For whatever that’s worth. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/21/absolutely-fabulous-the-movie.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AbsolutelyFabulous:TheMovie" />
    <published>2016-07-21T10:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-21T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/21/absolutely-fabulous-the-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There was a time, in the early aughts, when <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/writers/dig/">Di</a> and I worked together at a video store almost every day. And we watched a <em>lot</em> of Ab Fab. It would remind us both of your heady days: when terrorists were Germans played by Alan Rickman, tall buildings exploding were considered cool (not PTSD triggers) and broad caricatures of gay men, minorities and the elderly and infirm were just fine, if done with one’s tongue sufficiently embedded in one’s cheek.</p>

<p>But man, that was then. <em>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</em> feels like a remake of Gilligan’s Island made 20 years after the fact—and without the irony. There is nothing about this film that manages to successfully remodel what made Ab Fab so delightful: two utterly unrepentantly selfish women, with almost no redeeming features, ingesting every legal and illegal substance known to man or woman. There really was no message, it was just this rolling train wreck populated by Jennifer Saunders and Joanna Lumley, and the whole joy was watching that very train wreck end exactly where it was aimed from the giddyup.</p>

<p>But for more reasons than I can fit in this space the film can’t reproduce that particular point in time and these characters, Patsy and Edina, can’t evolve without distorting them out of all recognition. The things that made them funny: their casual and unrepentant racism, the class snobbishness, their happy immersion in the worst sort of consumerism and their complete lack of interest in the welfare of Edina’s child (and in this film Edina’s grandchild—a character that is a perfect example of the kind of egregious tone deafness this film too often indulges) just aren’t funny anymore. This isn’t because either women is any less sharp or capable but what their characters are, at their core, is now so unpalatable that it has moved from being outrageous to simply unacceptable.</p>

<p>Structurally <em>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</em> also suffers from what any number of television show/feature film conversions suffer from—it feels like a single half hour episode stretched out over 90 minutes. Every scene is more or less a couple of jokes attached to whatever the particular premise for that sequence is, without any real through line, so instead of a feature length film it feels like a clip show of the more mediocre episodes. The material and pacing are stretched so thin that the thing that made Ab Fab so special—this inevitable, meteoric rush to disaster—is diluted to the point where it feels plodding. </p>

<p>I tend to think the only way this film could have worked is if they had played it utterly straight and gone super dark. Because for better or worse, the subjective distance between your blinkered innocence and the world today is far more than just a couple of decades. So these people whom we could once laugh at from a comfortable distance have become our modern day boogey(wo)men—not laughable, but simply targets of derision and contempt.</p>

<p>Some things are of their time and <em>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</em> is definitely an artifact that only really makes sense when wrapped in your warm, slightly ignorant, embrace.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ghostbusters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/20/ghostbusters.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Ghostbusters" />
    <published>2016-07-20T09:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-20T09:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/20/ghostbusters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>First year Film Studies taught me that you are a metaphor for the things that trouble our collective psyche. Obsession with female purity, threatened masculinity, you’re stand-ins for all of it. Often, the protagonists’ quest to rid themselves and the world of your presence represents a desire to exorcise the more unsavoury aspects of ourselves and our societies. Then Internet trolls remind us of all the shit we foolishly think we’ve resolved and buried, and it’s obvious you aren’t finished haunting us. </p>

<p>I knew I was going to enjoy Paul Feig’s <em>Ghostbusters</em> reboot long before I saw it. I’m not overly familiar with the original, but I’d give a 90-minute static shot of an oscillating fan two thumbs way, way up if it made sad men-children on the Internet as apoplectically furious as <em>LadyGhostbusters</em> has. Watching the film was actually a weird experience; it was formulaic, but also not. I guess I’m just not used to seeing this many women in a movie that doesn’t have any wet clothing or period jokes. Our heroines may get drenched in ectoplasm, but they don’t even smear it over their chests coquettishly - it was all very new for me. </p>

<p>I’m just kidding, <em>Ghostbusters</em> is a very clever and funny film. With four of the funniest women on the planet at the helm, all the one-liners, punchlines, and slapstick gags land with near-impeccable precision. I also admire the more activist aspect of the narrative, especially given the shitstorm of sexist temper tantrums that seem to have dogged the film at every turn. </p>

<p>When your corps of spooky spectres include men who chained their daughters up in cellars, and a large, white, puffed up, angry male, full of hot air, that literally tries to suffocate women, it isn’t hard to tell what Feig is getting at. By aiming their proton packs at all of you, our heroines aren’t merely busting ghosts, they’re out to exorcise The Patriarchy itself. Rather than ignoring the haters or bothering with all that ‘rising above’ crap, Feig and his cast harness all that vitriol, throw it right out in front of them, and then take aim. And they do not miss. The film further broadens its scope in order to call out institutionalized sexism in science and academia, and pokes fun at the way in which we gloss over the depravity and misogyny of history’s Great Men. Is it a tad ham-fisted and on the nose? Sure, but also pretty damn satisfying.</p>

<p>Still, <em>Ghostbusters</em> falls short in one glaring way. I was expecting the team to be comprised of four scientists, not three white scientists and a black woman who has to constantly defend her presence among them. And this has nothing to do with the fact that Leslie Jones is my very best friend (she just doesn’t know it yet). I was sorely disappointed by the way in which her character, Patty, is set apart from the other three. Their credentials and expertise are evident from the get-go; Patty, on the other hand, struggles to make space for herself and her awesomely encyclopedic brain. She has to constantly remind her teammates, “Hey, I’m smart, too!” while they stare back at her uncomprehendingly. For all the ghosts blasted away, one spectre unfortunately lives to see another day. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Free State of Jones</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/11/free-state-of-jones.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=FreeStateofJones" />
    <published>2016-07-11T06:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-11T06:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/11/free-state-of-jones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What <em>Free State of Jones</em> gets right is the details. For instance, Matthew McConaughey’s prosthetic teeth are truly repugnant, as was the style of the time. Grey-yellow and rotting, they certainly mirrored the society that spawned McConaughey’s Confederate deserter, Newton Knight—as well as establishing a clear sense of time and place</p>

<p>These little touches, from the flintlocks to the spiked necklaces that runaway slaves were forced to endure, all speak to a commitment to detail necessary these days to sell any period piece, particularly one so well documented as the American Civil War. </p>

<p>Where <em>Free State of Jones</em> falls short is in the more ephemeral aspects of a story that tries to present a revisionist history of the Southern experience. Knight (and tell me that isn’t a surname that has some specific weight for a white Southerner) led an internal revolt in the Confederate South during the Civil War. After deserting his unit and returning to his Mississippi home, Knight is confronted by the deprivations inflicted by the local Confederate detachment. Soon he is leading a ragtag militia of escaped slaves, local farmers and fellow deserters.</p>

<p>Hollywood is facing some difficult choices these days—most of which are of their own making. Audiences less and less interested in watching films where white males are doing the Moses thing—leading the poor and disenfranchised to a new world. So casting McConaughey as an enlightened sharecropper might have made sense ten, maybe even five, years ago, but now it feels tone deaf and out of step (especially when compared to something like the-soon-to-be-released Sundance darling <em>Birth of a Nation</em>).</p>

<p>It’s not that the story isn’t intrinsically interesting, but <em>Free State of Jones</em> is never agile enough to thread the sort of needles necessary to avoid feeling mawkish and retrograde. The spotlight that follows Knight throughout the film means that too much of the story revolves around his redemption and not nearly enough on those for whom the whole exercise is much more than an abstract moral choice. </p>

<p>There were any number of characters that would have been equally compelling and also would have presented a fresh perspective. Newton’s complicated domestic circumstance—his estranged wife returning years after he had been living common law with a former slave—presented an excellent jumping off point for an entirely different version of this story. Either one of their POV’s would have presented some fascinating narrative opportunities. </p>

<p>Instead what we got was a kind of paint by numbers script, which includes a needlessly complicated framing device involving a 20th century trial. The whole thing felt threadbare and tacked on. </p>

<p><em>Free State of Jones</em> finally devolves into a series of tableaux that attempt to describe the Reconstructionist Southern experience for people of color—all the while staying firmly affixed to Knight and his more mundane domestic tribulations.</p>

<p>If there had been more of a commitment to the ugly, difficult truths that your work represented, <em>Free State of Jones</em> may have managed to break from the mold it otherwise so thoroughly inhabited. Instead its entirely cosmetic approach to complex issues failed to rise to your exacting, if unattractive, standards.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>M. Night Shyamalan: The Final Blockbuster Auteur</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/8/m-night-shyamalan-the-final-blockbuster-auteur.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=M.NightShyamalan:TheFinalBlockbusterAuteur" />
    <published>2016-07-08T07:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-08T07:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/8/m-night-shyamalan-the-final-blockbuster-auteur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve got some bad news for you. If you grew up hoping to be the next Hitchcock, Spielberg, Scorsese, or Tarantino – a director so bankable that your name alone could sell a film – those dreams died 1999. Simply put: if you didn’t make a name for yourself by the end of the Millennium, you officially outlived the era of Blockbuster Auteurs. Membership is officially closed. Sorry.</p>

<p>The end came unexpectedly. In fact, in 1999, anything seemed possible. Two parallel phenomena were sweeping Hollywood, both in the ever-maligned horror genre. First, <em>The Sixth Sense</em> burst into theatres as a crowd-pleasing critical darling. Through sophisticated tension, careful visual construction, and a delicious twist ending, writer-director M. Night Shyamalan was instantly heralded as a master architect of suspense. His barely-seen previous films (a family comedy starring Rosie O’Donnell, and a comedic coming-of-age story starring himself) were somehow irrelevant; <em>The Sixth Sense</em> proved that he was a director to watch out for. His unusual name became a talking point—not just among cinephiles, but by average movie goers who couldn’t wait to see what he’d do next. </p>

<p>On the other end of the spectrum came <em>The Blair Witch Project</em>, a gimmicky premise that was somehow turned into a bona fide blockbuster (and still the most profitable independent film of all-time). The found-footage film arrived at a perfect moment: the Internet was accessible enough to spread the word, but not sophisticated enough to de-bunk the hoax. The film’s success was predicated almost entirely on the chance that it might, maybe, who knows, <em>actually be real</em>. But for aspiring filmmakers, what it really meant was that anyone with a camcorder could potentially make a name for themselves. </p>

<p>It was a glorious time. </p>

<p>And then something happened. <em>X-Men</em> was released in 2000 and introduced a new, more socially-relevant, more earnest approach to blockbuster filmmaking. That success bred <em>Spider-Man</em>, and eventually a re-booted Batman series. Each of these films were directed by lauded filmmakers: Brian Singer, Sam Raimi, and Christopher Nolan, respectively. And in this unholy marriage of unique voices and familiar properties, a new formula for Hollywood success was born. </p>

<p>On the other end of the spectrum, it was a race to the bottom for low-budget break-out success. The wild rates of return experienced by the <em>Saw</em> and <em>Paranormal Activity</em> franchises made skittish studio executives gitty over mainstream genre exercises. And slowly but surely, the mid-range budgets that visionary directors normally found to grow the scale of their films and audience started to disappear. The gamble on talent became too rich for Tinsletown. </p>

<p>So by the end of the decade, the name of the director quickly took a backseat to the property being developed. Like Disney animation or MGM musicals, the brand of the studio replaced the brand of the director; the producers, and their long-term corporate expansion plans, became the visionaries who drove the storytelling. And now, in all the years that have passed since 1999, not a single new blockbuster director has emerged as a marketable talent for the average movie-going public to recognize and galvanize behind. </p>

<p>It sounds hard to believe, I know. But Peter Jackson brought us <em>The Lord of The Rings</em> in 2001, only after directing five other films. And though his LOTR trilogy was a massive success, his follow-up in 2005, <em>King Kong</em> (another established property), failed to pave the way for any bold or original future works. Even Michael Bay – a polarizing figure in cinema but undeniable audience magnet – shifted into franchise filmmaking with <em>Transformers</em>. Of course, other legacy name-brand directors like James Cameron, Tim Burton, and David Fincher continued their output, but no new names have been added beneath them on the list. Not a single Millennial director has captured the world’s attention the way M. Night Shyamalan last did.</p>

<p>Should we blame Shyamalan for this? Did he really burn his studios so badly with his subsequent string of mega-flops that they will never again try to build their brands on the back of a director? True, by the time he released <em>Lady in the Water</em> in 2006, his name was more of a liability than selling feature. But does that really explain why someone hasn’t taken up the mantle?</p>

<p>You might argue a case for a few names in comedy: Judd Apatow, Tyler Perry. But both come with big caveats. Apatow works more as a producer than director, and good luck getting your mom to name a film that Apatow has directed (my personal barometer for cross-over success). Perry is more of a niche success, like Wes Anderson, P.T. Anderson, The Cohen Brothers, or Woody Allen, even though starring in many of his films gives him better name recognition. After that, we get to names like J.J. Abrams, who works almost exclusively with other people’s franchises (<em>Mission: Impossible</em>, <em>Star Trek</em>, <em>Star Wars</em>). And those other unique voices we might have held out hope for? Ryan Johnson, Ryan Coogler, even Zack Snyder? They, too, find themselves at the mercy of the mega-franchise. </p>

<p>It’s sad. Devastating, really. We hear anecdotal stories all the time about directors like Steven Soderberg wanting to quit the business. But the theatres still fill up, and the studios are making more money than ever. So why do so many famous filmmakers paint a doom and gloom picture of a life making movies? It’s simple, really. And in a sense, it all comes back to M. Night Shyamalan. The man who re-invigorated Hollywood’s appetite for big budget auteurs may have also brought about their demise. How’s that for a Shyamalanian twist ending? </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Independence Day: Resurgence</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/6/independence-day-resurgence.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=IndependenceDay:Resurgence" />
    <published>2016-07-06T05:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-06T05:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/6/independence-day-resurgence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The way Hollywood spends money is a growing matter of contention. I don’t just mean which states and countries get productions based on tax credits and exchange rates, but what <em>types</em> of films get greenlit in the first place. Much has been said about how the middle has fallen out of cinema – you’re either making an independent film for less than $5M and hoping for a modest return, or you’re pumping up a $150M tent-pole production with a P&amp;A budget (prints and advertising)that <a href="http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/200-million-rising-hollywood-struggles-721818">doubles down on that investment</a>. In other words, for every <em>Independence Day: Resurgence</em>, the world is getting anywhere from five to 50 <em>less</em> mid- and low-budget films. </p>

<p>How’s that for an apocalyptic scenario?</p>

<p>The business appeal of doing something like <em>Resurgence</em> is pretty straight-forward. In theory, all these reboots, remakes, sequels, and adaptations already have built-in brand recognition that will ease entry to the market place. But familiarity can quickly turn into fatigue, and when a recycled business model becomes transparent, audiences usually wise-up. And boy, were eyes wide open for this planet-sized cash grab.</p>

<p>Still, I entered the cinema on my own terms and in good faith. I naively hoped that this new film could recapture some of the thrill I felt as a 13-year-old seeing <em>Independence Day</em> in 1996. Plus, <em>Jurassic World</em> proved that following up a mid-90s mega hit could nail the sweet spot of nostalgia and new appeal. But while Chris Pratt brought that extra element of rising star appeal to the dino-sequel, <em>Resurgence</em> had a Will Smith-sized void in that department (apologies to non-Thor Hemsworth). I couldn’t help but wonder – was it a budget thing?  </p>

<p>You’re not the right person to ask, I know. People like you are tasked with controlling dollars on the ground during production, which may also be problematic. You were no doubt given a blue print for not only what’s been spent in the past, but what is a reasonable rate of return for investments in the future. Blowing up a scaled-down exact model of the White House, for example, proved to be an extremely wise bang-for-your-buck investment back in 1996. When <em>Independence Day</em> hit theatres, that trailer image electrified audiences and made the film a must-see. There was still a novelty to end-of-the-world films, which hadn’t yet saturated the market (<em>Armageddon</em> and <em>Deep Impact</em> took care of that a couple years later). So what’s the big money shot this go around? The gag of just barely bending the flag atop the White House is pretty much the only unique image that comes to mind – and that was barely worthy of a smirk. </p>

<p>In a world where “we’ll fix it in post” has gone from being a punchline to standard operating procedure, there was a lack of tangible investment in this film – both physical and emotional. We’ve seen so many cities crumble on screen with so little consequence, studios forget it’s not a one-for-one exchange: ticket prices aren’t based on the number of buildings that crumble.</p>

<p>I don’t know what it would have cost to make a film where we give a shit what happens, but it’s a whole less than this.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>