<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-22T16:16:21Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Maze Runner: The Scorch Trials</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/22/maze-runner-the-scorch-trials.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MazeRunner:TheScorchTrials" />
    <published>2015-09-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/22/maze-runner-the-scorch-trials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There isn’t much you can do to save a film if the script is poor—but every once in a while a film will possess qualities that can help mitigate the weakness of the source material. For instance, with an action driven, post-apocalyptic tale like <em>Maze Runner: The Scorch Trials</em> you can hide a lot of bad with inventive production design.</p>

<p>If the visual elements that inform a world are compelling and well executed they can help take the audience’s attention away from gaping plot holes, generally poor performances and a story that loses its way in the second act. And while your production design on <em>Scorch Trials</em> doesn’t raise it above competent it does save it from being a complete waste of time.</p>

<p>Your work on this film—from the creatures that inhabit the burnt out hell hole that Earth has become, to the design of the government’s special forces uniform—was outstanding. It is a difficult thing to create the details of an imagined world, to strike a balance between plausibility while still remaining visually compelling. Somehow you managed to walk that line throughout this otherwise forgettable mess of a film.</p>

<p>In the same way that every clichéd character in this film meanders aimlessly through the umpteen nameless, deserted cities that dot the landscape of this world, the plot follows the same path. There was never any kind of internal logic established that went beyond a kind of Pavlovian response to stimulus. The characters are saved by a mysterious group that is not at all what it seems—so characters flee into <em>The</em> <em>Scorch</em> (a term that rocketed pretty quickly from mildly hyperbolic to annoying by dint of overuse). Characters are threatened by (super creepy and well articulated) mutants—they flee. Characters are also chased by mysterious government agents with opaque motivations—yep, more fleeing. Finally the characters end up at an ostensibly mythic sanctuary and are betrayed by one of their own (which normally would be a spoiler but that piece of plot was so telegraphed, and telegraphed so early, that it was nothing but inevitable—yawn). </p>

<p>This kind of plot can actually work just fine, if it is handled correctly. But since no one in this film is anything other than a ‘character’—who is going to give a damn about what happens to any one of them? That is not only a failure of the script but of performance as well. No one in this film, not even Patricia Clarkson (all hail), gives us anything at all to hang on to. The direction, aside from a couple of lovely images involving characters in silhouettes trudging through the waste, is pedestrian at best. The whole project has the feel of either a paycheck generator or people padding their resumes. It seems that no one is actually engaged with the material beyond a baseline kind of expediency.</p>

<p>Well, almost no one. You managed to bring something to the table, Dan. And all of us who sat through <em>Maze Runner: The Scorch Trials</em> thank you for your effort. The visual landscape you articulated made the unbearable slightly more bearable and gave me something positive to write about instead of simply pouring venom onto the page.</p>

<p>Thanks again.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mistress America</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/4/mistress-america.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MistressAmerica" />
    <published>2015-09-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/4/mistress-america</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Mistress America is one of those films that left me grinding my teeth in frustration at the waste of intelligence that, for me, is intrinsic to your work. There is something base in commidifying the banality of your own existence. Moderately clever, over-educated people bereft of any real meaning in their life magicing up this daily theatre of the absurd, mostly in an effort to insulate themselves from existential despair, makes for some pretty shite filmmaking.</p>

<p>Look, it is clear that I’m hostile to your aesthetic sensibilities, making it difficult for me to address this film in a way that isn’t going to reek of contempt. It may be that I’m missing something significant in <em>Mistress America</em>, some subtle nuance that is obvious to others. But to me this film was so utterly tone deaf, so buried in its own navel, that I could not find a moment that redeemed it.</p>

<p>With one exception.</p>

<p>Early in <em>Mistress America</em>—before the descent into a literal farce that occupies the last third of the film—there is a scene where the failed Manic Pixie Dream Girl Brooke (that’s you Greta) and the naïve freshman ingénue Tracy (your soon to be step sister played by Lola Kirke) are having a drink in a dive-y Manhattan bar. A former schoolmate of Brooke’s recognizes her and comes over to the table. Initially Brooke seems delighted, perhaps expecting some sycophantic murmurings. Instead the mood shifts abruptly when Brooke’s former classmate details some particularly cruel behavior she had suffered at Brooke’s hand—behavior that apparently spanned the whole of the former classmate’s high school experience. It is a really lucid and well-articulated scene where Brooke is faced with the distance between her perception of herself and the reality of who she really is.</p>

<p>If the whole film had been in that key this would have been a more interesting experience. Instead that moment and all its implications are disappeared like a mouthy protester in a banana republic—never to be seen again. After that the film descends into a messy parable about the ethics of using the personal experience of others as a career booster for your burgeoning writing career. </p>

<p>Tracy, having been taken under the fluttery and inconstant wing of Brooke, uses the low comedy that she witnesses as a springboard to minor literary success. This, of course, leads to a contrived rift between her and Brooke, who after spending a good two thirds of the film drenched in an endless and very public self-revelation, suddenly takes exception to the details being shared with some first year lit students.</p>

<p>The only other contact Tracy has in New York (she has just arrived as a college freshman) is among the many clichés that dot the landscape of this film—the Woody Allen–esque, bird-necked Lothario, played fitfully by Matthew Shear. There is also the regretful hedge fund manager and his self-admitted golddigger of a wife, as well as the usual assortment of wind up dolls that often populate Baumbach’s films. There isn’t a character in this film that doesn’t scan as a ‘character in a film’. <em>Mistress America</em> rarely escapes from its own cleverness. </p>

<p>Hasn’t this kind of particularly New York-centric dramedy passed its expiration date? <em>Mistress America</em> feels listless and played out, and most of all irrelevant. The performances are both somehow manic and flat and the whole exercise seems small-minded in its obsession with people who can’t decide which of thirty-five different options of ice cream they might choose, especially when so many of their fellow New Yorkers would be happy with any one of those cones.</p>

<p>Or maybe it’s just me.</p>

<p>Nah.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The End of the Tour</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/27/the-end-of-the-tour.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheEndoftheTour" />
    <published>2015-08-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/27/the-end-of-the-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Much of your work was about finding a pathway through pop culture’s bracken of ironic remove. You seemed to have been searching for an authenticity, in both high and low art, which somehow wasn’t poisoned by sentiment or nostalgia—and subsequently free of the kind of base commercial motivations that render so much of today’s cultural output as purely transactional. </p>

<p>This balance point also seems to be something that is both as desirable and fictional as a Unicorn.</p>

<p>The search for that mythic sensibility—neither a myopic and whiny longing for a non-existent canon, nor a surrender to the seeming inevitability of the flat-lined ironic gaze, where everything is equally banal and therefore without any real value—is perhaps as close to a Grail quest as is culturally possible these days. And it is just as existentially fraught.</p>

<p><em>The End of The Tour</em> –a film that chronicles Rolling Stone reporter’s David Lipsky’s four days with you during the end of the Infinite Jest book tour—also seems to be reaching towards that goal as well. And for the most part the film <em>is</em> executed with a surefooted, deliberate tone that feels authentic, without falling into a bro-ish deification of you and your works.</p>

<p>In this cultural moment—where diversity and questions about the status quo are pre-eminent, and rarified conversations about ‘what it all means’ seem tone deaf—that we are given a film that features two of the palest, malest, most privileged of the pasty, white, East coast intelligentsia (you grew up in the Midwest but are the epitome of an East coast, Ivy league intellectual in so many ways) is not lost on anyone paying attention. But that it works at all (and it does—far more often than not) on any level other than self-parody, is a testament to the universality <em>The End of The Tour</em> touches upon—and the utterly compulsive power of your prose.</p>

<p>Much of this film, and especially Jason Segel’s uneven but admirable run at your persona, is verbatim from Lipsky’s book (<em>Although of Course You End Up Becoming Yourself</em>) about those four days in 1996. It is a charming and irritating and sad and sometimes profound conversation between two men, and the occasional other, that takes place in the arid sterility of a Midwestern winter. Your house, anonymous coffee shops, a book store, a lecture hall, a rental car; all of these ordinary and otherwise nondescript settings juxtapose in remarkable ways with what is some of the most fascinating two-dudes-talking dialogue since <em>My Dinner With Andre.</em></p>

<p>Jesse Eisenberg inhabits the role of Lipsky. Tonally he is a perfect balance between supplicant and reptilian careerist. Late in the film, you and he having seemingly reached some sort of détente, Lipsky is left alone in your house while you attend to carving the car out of a late winter snowfall. Lipsky then proceeds to rifle through your personal possessions in a way that is both reverential and completely crass. It is as if he has found the bones of a saint and can’t decide whether to sell them to the highest bidder or just keep them to himself and build a shrine in his basement.</p>

<p><em>The End of the Tour</em> is inevitably tinted by melancholy. It only very briefly alludes to your suicide in 2008 but that tragedy stills informs each frame of this film. To catch even a reflection of the kind of mind you possessed is a privilege. But to know that what you will share with the rest of us will have to be mediated through your existing works, and the imperfect memories of others, means that no matter how good a film <em>The End of The Tour</em> is, it probably leaves the most important parts out. </p>

<p>I, for one, would give a lot to read your review of this film. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>American Ultra</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/17/american-ultra.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AmericanUltra" />
    <published>2015-08-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/17/american-ultra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There is an old adage: “a carpenter is only as good as his tools”. If anyone knows the truth of that saying, it is you. Sometimes you get precision-tooled equipment: pristine and flawless, stainless steel and factory fresh. Other times you have to make do with a single, rusty, duct taped POS hammer someone scrounged from Grandpa’s garage. Unfortunately the latter circumstance was the case with <em>American Ultra</em>.</p>

<p>Jesse Eisenberg is a lot of things. What he is not is a convincing simulacrum of Matt Damon. And that is what <em>American Ultra</em> required—inasmuch as it is a direct homage to, or pastiche of, the <em>Bourne</em> franchise. There once was a time when you could manage to work around an action star that was less than physically capable. Roger Moore made a career out of it. These days though, audiences are too film literate to let you get away with long shots, cutaways and POV trickery. For the most part they want to see the star get dirty.</p>

<p>If this was different kind of film, if it was less grounded in ‘reality’, if there was more CGI and it was a little more elevated —like <em>Scott Pilgrim</em>, for instance—it may have worked. But <em>American Ultra</em> is not that. It is thematically and structurally a direct heir to Doug Liman’s <em>Bourne Identity</em>, the first film in the Bourne Trilogy (the pissant little town Eisenberg’s character, Mike Howell, is trapped in is called <strong>Liman</strong>, in case there was any doubt). And that means no super powers and no obvious CGI. It requires a lead that can get up close and personal.</p>

<p>Eisenberg, who plays a sleeper CIA operative unaware of his past, is just not up to the task. There is a reason the people that are usually the leads in these kinds of films are who they are. Daniel Craig, Gina Carano, Matt Damon, anyone in the <em>Raid</em> films, are all cut from the same cloth. Even someone as diminutive as Chloe Moretz (<em>Kick Ass’</em> <strong>Hitgirl</strong>) was convincing because she is physically capable. Ultimately, the kind of veracity a film like needs to ground it never emerges because Eisenberg is unpersuasive as an awakened CIA killbot.</p>

<p>As far as the rest of the cast goes, it is a mixed bag. Kristin Stewart does what she can as Eisenberg’s CIA handler/girlfriend but her character is underwritten and fuzzy in her motivations. Topher Grace seems to have gotten a different script than the rest of the cast, as his evil CIA bureaucrat is less Chris Cooper/Brian Cox and much more a cartoonish parody. Bill Pullman is perfect in his brief appearances, mostly because he is almost catatonic in his reserve—something this film could have used a lot more of.</p>

<p>Stewart is fine in her scenes and the staging and camera work isn’t bad, but it becomes obvious that Eisenberg can’t do the kind of close in work necessary to give the film the kind of intimate physicality it requires. Too many times when some complex interaction occurs, the camera pulls away or sits over Eisenberg’s shoulder—tricks that are used to insert stunt doubles. One of the effective conceits of the Bourne franchise and the new James Bond films is whenever possible, Craig and Damon are central to the action. You believe these actors can do what we are being asked to believe they can do, which makes a significant difference in the level of audience engagement and heightens the stakes enormously. </p>

<p>The best example I can think of is the first set piece in <em>The Bourne Identity</em> when Damon disarms two Swiss policemen and then renders them unconscious. The sequence is a wide shot, well lit, with some cuts, and it is clearly Damon himself who is engaging in the sequence. The mirror of that scene occurs towards the end of the first act of <em>American Ultra,</em> when a two-man team is sent to eliminate Eisenberg’s character. This sequence is poorly lit, choppily edited and it is not at all clear who is doing what to whom. Most importantly it does not establish Eisenberg as someone who is convincingly dangerous, and if we don’t believe that, then the movie’s central premise is fatally undermined.</p>

<p>It must have been a bit frustrating when you realized your toolkit was so limited, that you would have to make do instead of building something great. You’ve done good work elsewhere (<em>Mission Impossible: Ghost Protocol</em>) so I tend to think this was less the craftsman and more the tools. Maybe next time you will have what you need to build something truly superior. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Man from U.N.C.L.E.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/16/the-man-from-uncle.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheManfromU.N.C.L.E." />
    <published>2015-08-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/16/the-man-from-uncle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Man From U.N.C.L.E.</em> is touted as a stylized spy flick—and it is—but not to the degree I was hoping it would be. Between a deceiving trailer and visual effects inconsistencies, <em>Man From U.N.C.L.E</em> went from being a great film to just being good. </p>

<p>Visual inconsistencies? How dare I. With films like <em>Avengers: Age of</em> <em>Ultron, San Andreas</em> and <em>Jupiter Ascending</em> as digital feathers in your respective caps, visual effects shouldn’t have been the problem. So what was?</p>

<p><em>Man From U.N.C.L.E.</em> is a cinematic adaption of the popular 60’s TV show of the same name. It follows CIA and KGB agents Napoleon Solo and Illya Kuryakin, bitter enemies of the Cold War-turned allies tasked with stopping a nuclear threat by a mystery terrorist organization. Many spy/agent TV-shows from yesteryear have been adapted as modern-day action/comedies; <em>Get Smart, A-Team,</em> and <em>21 Jump Street</em> to name a few. But <em>Man From U.N.C.L.E</em> chose to stick to the cold-war era rather than rejig the plot to fit a 21st century setting. And you guys did a great job of recreating the look and feel of that time. But it wasn’t enough. <em>Man from U.N.C.L.E.</em> doesn’t have the kind of spark to make it a stand out. Instead of spiffing up the landscape, it merely built another duplex. </p>

<p>In the trailer, audiences are exposed to the car chase between Illya Kuryakin and Napoleon Solo. The highly stylized chase is sex for the eyeballs; sped-up and obvious that it was created on a computer screen. Very <em>Sky Captain and the World of Tomorrow</em>. The emphasis on how deliberate it is helps position <em>Man From U.N.C.L.E.</em> as a quirky, retro spy movie. That was the spark. If that theme were used throughout, I wouldn’t be writing this letter. Unfortunately, that scene occurred within the first 30 minutes and that was it. There were plenty of chase scenes after that but none featured that same visual representation. Why the inconsistency? That is what bothered me about <em>Man From U.N.C.L.E.</em> Expectations are raised in the trailer, but the film never delivers on that promise. In fact, the bulk of the visual effects are in the opening and end credits. </p>

<p>Still, <em>Man From U.N.C.L.E.</em> has its own charm. It is funny and entertaining. Probably because we’re watching a British actor play an American, and an American actor play a Russian (forced accents FTW). But if audiences are expecting an aesthetically breathtaking movie by you, the fine folk at BlueBolt, Cinesite and RISE, only to have the sweet stuff shown during the first 40 minutes, they’ll likely be a little disappointed.  </p>

<p>I know many of these decisions weren’t yours to make. All three of you played an integral part in this creation, but unfortunately your contributions were kind of wasted. If you were left in charge of the creative treatment, I’m sure the finished product would have been a whole lot different.</p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong><br>
Ankit</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fantastic Four</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/16/fantastic-four.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=FantasticFour" />
    <published>2015-08-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/16/fantastic-four</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I would be lying if I said I didn’t see this coming. Your <em>Fantastic Four</em> has lived under a pall of doom (pun-intended) since its conception. And it has certainly fulfilled all that negative promise—not only is it tanking at the box office but it’s currently standing at 9% on Rotten Tomatoes. That failure, in turn, has engendered a lot of <a href="http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/fantastic-four-blame-game-fox-814764">nasty finger pointing</a>. </p>

<p>On Thursday you went nuclear with this <a href="http://www.joblo.com/movie-news/josh-trank-disowns-fantastic-four-via-twitter-claims-studio-interference-322">tweet</a>, in essence disavowing the film. Whatever ended up on the screen, you wanted everyone to know that it wasn’t representative of the film you wanted to make. Since the release there have been a more than a few stories about how early and often the studio stuck its finger in your pie. 20th  Century Fox ostensibly scrapped three agreed upon action sequences as well as removing the final edit from your hands. So it may well be that this version of <em>Fantastic Four</em> isn’t really yours. </p>

<p>What is it then?</p>

<p>Mostly it’s an incoherent mess. The film manages to avoid anything resembling excitement in its meandering travels. The characters are wafer-thin, and the performances range from surprisingly muted (Miles Teller) to stilted (Kate Mara) to occasionally charming (Michael B. Jordan) to nearly invisible (Jamie Bell).</p>

<p>The plot is a Frankenstein’s monster: pieces of the foundational story grafted haphazardly onto whatever the studio decided to replace it with. It has no flow and makes no sense. Secondary plots appear and disappear like soap bubbles, and whatever motivates the characters seems as much a mystery to the actors portraying them as it does to the rest of us.</p>

<p>Visually this monstrosity bears no resemblance to your nuanced work on <em>Chronicle</em> (the surprise indie hit that got you this gig in the first place). Where <em>Chronicle</em> was a film that was made for twelve million that looked like it cost a hundred and twenty, <em>Fantastic Four</em>  looks like the reverse. It’s poorly lit, the staging is clunky, and the CGI would have been laughable in the first <em>Spawn</em> movie. </p>

<p>Part of the problem assessing this film lies in trying to figure out what parts are yours and which parts were reshot by the studio. Fully 1/3 of this film is studio reshoots and that is by 20th Century’s admission, which means it is probably closer to 1/2. The whole film is riddled with the kind of inconsistencies this sort of meddling produces. Just watch Kate Mara’s wig as it appears and then vanishes in the same scene. This occurs in at least two different sequences in the film.</p>

<p>There was a brief, promising moment midway through the film just after the titular four have returned from the mysterious Planet Zero. All four of them have been exposed to an unnamed radiation/goop that conferred (inexplicably, but by then I had given up hope anyway) different powers on each of them. </p>

<p>Here you managed to do something really interesting (I assume this was you since the ambiguous consequences of obtaining superpowers like these was the theme of <em>Chronicle</em>); I didn’t see it coming, but the transformation sequence was darkly effective. The physical changes each one of them suffers through are played as Cronenberg-esque body horror. It was absolutely chilling. If the rest of the film had operated anywhere close to that level, it would have been remarkable.</p>

<p>Whoever is ultimately to blame—and I tend to think there is more than enough to go around—what I am most concerned about is whether or not this whole experience has undermined your credibility (or simply eaten your soul) to point that you’re effectively finished as a filmmaker. </p>

<p>That would be a shame. If nothing else I hope (probably in vain) that the studios will understand the consequences of hedging their bets. If you hire an auteur, then give him enough rope to hang himself. Because the short leash doesn’t serve anyone’s interests.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Vacation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/11/vacation.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Vacation" />
    <published>2015-08-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/11/vacation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Your work transcends eras and demographics, so it’s fitting that you’re involved in the remake of an 80s classic near and dear to my heart. When I was six years-old, Devo was my favourite band. I loved to pogo along to “Freedom of Choice”, and today, as an adult, I love clever lyrics like, “Freedom of choice is what you’ve got / Freedom from choice is what you want.” You and your hazmat-suited, energy-domed bandmates wrote anti-establishment diatribes disguised as catchy, new-wave pop. </p>

<p>You’ve worked on everything from <em>Pee-Wee’s Playhouse</em> to <em>21 Jump Street</em> to just about every Wes Anderson film, and now the <em>Vacation</em> reboot. There is even talk that <a href="http://time.com/3556593/wes-anderson-mark-mothersbaugh-theme-park/">you and Wes Anderson are going to open up a theme park</a> of your own in your hometown of Akron, Ohio. Considering that the idea that spurned the creation of Devo was De-evolution - the regression of mankind and the subversion of the American way of life – I’m guessing your target demographic won’t be families like the Griswolds. </p>

<p>Like its 1983 predecessor, <em>Vacation</em> is an R-rated comedy. As a kid, I knew those “mature audiences only” warnings were tongue-in cheek. There is very little about the <em>Vacation</em> movies that could be considered mature, and that’s what made them so much fun. When I was 10, I related to the Griswold kids, Rusty and Audrey, who had to endure the hell of road-tripping with their lame parents. As adults, my husband and I ritually watch <em>Vacation</em> before we go on holiday. It’s a silly reminder that no matter how bad our trip might turn out, it won’t be <em>Griswold</em>-bad. I was worried that this new iteration might sour the franchise again (ahem, <em>Vegas Vacation)</em>, but it manages to hit the same absurd, juvenile, and hilariously uncomfortable marks as the original. And, like the 1983 version, this <em>Vacation</em> is better enjoyed as the sum of its parts rather than as a whole. </p>

<p>Rusty Griswold is now a husband and father who longs to bond with his kids and to reignite the passion in his marriage. But because he is a Griswold, his idea of a quick fix is to take the family on a road trip to Wally World. The film opens with Lindsay Buckingham’s “Holiday Road” and the titles roll over a montage of awkward family vacation photos, reassuring us that the elements we loved about the original film will be updated accordingly. “Holiday Road” is covered a few times (once as a dirge), but many of the songs you include are integral to the plot (“Kiss From A Rose” and “Summer Breeze”) while others are pitch perfect additions (“Crown on the Ground” and ”Still Not A Player”).</p>

<p>There are many elements that harken back to the original film. Popular comedians in bit parts, a dysfunctional vehicle, uncomfortable family reunions, and it all meshes well with this vision of the 21st-Century Griswolds. The kids – overly-sensitive teen James and his sociopathic little brother Kevin – have more to chew on than their counterparts. The parents, played by Ed Helms and Christina Applegate, naturally channel that lovably moronic Griswold sensibility. Applegate is given far more to do than Beverly D’Angelo ever was, and she steals almost every scene she’s in. As much as I love the long-suffering Ellen, Applegate’s “Do-Anything” Debbie is a refreshingly feminist, take-no-BS matriarch. </p>

<p>Watching last year’s Oscar telecast, I got super excited about seeing you onstage during the musical number for “Everything Is Awesome” (which you produced). The exact opposite of that Oscar-night excitement is what I felt near the end of <em>Vacation</em>’s second act, when Chevy Chase shows up, reprising his role as the bumbling Clark Griswold. His tired shtick evokes little more than pity-laughs from those of us old enough to remember when he was still funny. It’s easy to see why, during their blessedly brief cameo, D’Angelo looks like the proverbial deer in headlights. I guess three-plus decades of dealing with Chase’s shrinking talent and massive ego will do that to a person. I hope that this dutiful nod to the <em>pater familias</em> means that we won’t have to endure more awkward visits with Grandpa Clark should the franchise continue. Like Devo’s unnecessary 1984 cover of “R U Experienced?”, some things are better left in the past.</p>

<p>Nostalgia trips are fun up to a point, but they can quickly veer into self-indulgence. <em>Vacation</em> takes what we loved most about the original and drives it into this century. But it flails when it tries to preach about spending time with family and working hard to maintain your marriage. Sure, those things are important, but that’s not why we watch a <em>Vacation</em> movie. </p>

<p>The Griswolds just want to live the suburban dream of a picture-perfect family, secure job, and well-deserved annual holiday but they are thwarted at every turn. It seems they’ve embraced your theory of De-volution, but because they are Griswolds, they have done so completely by accident.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Southpaw</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/8/southpaw.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Southpaw" />
    <published>2015-08-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/8/southpaw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The truly great boxers are possessed of a very specific set of skills. Marvin Hagler, Ray Leonard, Ezzard Charles, all of these men were blessed with a remarkable combination of speed and power as well as a dancer&#39;s elegance. So it was something of a surprise to see Jake Gyllenhaal exhibit that same kind of rare physicality in <em>Southpaw</em>. His performance, both in the ring and out, was mostly remarkable.</p>

<p>You also had all of those technical skills, Roy. The power, the quickness, the casually luminous athleticism that all exceptional athletes possess. But in the same way this film was potentially brilliant—it had a solid cast, beautiful cinematography, and a director who had previously produced superior work—your career and <em>Southpaw</em> share a sad confluence. In both cases all those ingredients never added up to more than the sum of their parts.</p>

<p>The script dutifully checks the appropriate boxes—riches to rags to redemption. Everyone from the deeply flawed trainer to the avaricious promoter had their requisite moment. Characters were definitely at the disposal of the plot, a circumstance that inevitably leads to a lack of emotional engagement with the audience. Rachel MacAdams was underutilized and she disappeared from the film far too quickly. There were any number of characters that simply show up as required. Disillusioned daughter—check. Kid from the wrong side of the tracks that echoes the protagonist as a troubled youth—check. At least the daughter doesn’t get eradicated, offstage, and then dismissed with a single sentence when her purpose has been served. These characters/plot devices appear and then, when convenient, do a quick fade. As a result of this kind of utilitarian construction, nothing about the script felt organic or even mildly surprising.</p>

<p>Gyllenhaal carried every moment he was on screen, which thankfully was most of the film. His portrayal of Billy ‘The Great White’ Hope was nuanced and, when the script allowed, riveting. Not only did he nail the physical aspects of the character but he painted a convincing portrait of how elite athletes are often congenitally ill equipped to deal with the mundane realities of daily life—that if they are stripped of their support structures they are often revealed for the literal babes in the woods that they are. It is Billy’s journey from child to something akin to a responsible adult that is the backbone of this movie, and that journey had moments of real pathos.</p>

<p>The boxing scenes were competently filmed and lucid in their construction. The climactic fight, particularly, was elegantly crafted, but somehow empty of any real emotion. And that is perhaps the problem with the film. Antoine Fuqua is a remarkably adept technical director. His films look beautiful, they generally move at a good clip and there is very little that could be labeled as extraneous. But it seems to be the case that the early promise of a film like <em>Training Day</em> owed as much to a great script by David Ayers and a brilliant performance from Denzel Washington as anything else. Nothing Fuqua has done since has come close to the spiky greatness of that superb film.</p>

<p><em>Southpaw</em> is a film that contained all the moving parts for something special but the conventional nature of the script and a seeming reluctance to step outside of any of the usual tropes hamstrung the whole enterprise. I’m not sure if that is the result of caution on Fuqua’s part or simply the weakness of the material but the film never managed to create the heightened emotional beats that similar films, like <em>Warrior</em> or <em>The Fighter,</em> evoked.  </p>

<p>As with the difference between a great fighter and merely a good one, a great film is possessed of an ineffable quality that a good film simply lacks. This quality is beyond technical prowess or even the talents of everyone involved. You know this better than most, Roy, partially because it was something that occasionally eluded you in your career. Your talent was superlative but you sometimes failed to rise to the moment—you seemed to lack the capacity to transcend your admittedly infrequent limitations. <em>Southpaw</em> also never quite manages that transcendent quality either; and as a result is, in its best moments, just a good film.</p>

<p>But not a great one.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Amy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/8/1/amy.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Amy" />
    <published>2015-08-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/8/1/amy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>This is the verbatim conversation <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/writers/timm/">Tim McEown</a> and I had on July 23, 2011:</p>

<p>Me: Amy Winehouse died.</p>

<p>Tim: How?</p>

<p>Me: Rescuing kittens from a burning building. How do you think?</p>

<p>Tim: Wouldn’t that have been awesome though? Then she’d be remembered as a hero.</p>

<p>Me: Instead of a cliché.</p>

<p>Yes, that was cold. But, to be fair, no one was surprised by the death of Amy Winehouse. She was a brilliant young singer/songwriter blessed with a soulful voice—and it just so happened that her immense talents were matched by her inner demons. It’s a story as old as pop music itself: a troubled singer becomes an overnight sensation, can’t handle the pressure, and succumbs to drugs, alcohol, unhealthy relationships, and eventually dies too young. </p>

<p>We’ve seen the scenario played out so many times –  Jimi, Janis, Jim, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html">Kurt</a>, etc.– that it’s almost impossible to feel much more than a passing, “damn, what a waste”, before clicking on to the next story. In his documentary, <em>Amy</em>, director Asif Kapadia manages to strip away the layers of what the public knew of Amy Winehouse – the bruises, the streaked makeup, the slurring hot mess – to show a sweet, witty, and remarkably self-aware woman. </p>

<p>Kapadia amassed an exhausting amount of footage – candid home movies, interviews, live performances – and opens his film in 1998. A 14 year-old Amy sings “Happy Birthday” while twirling a lollipop. Her gift is undeniable. Kapadia manipulates the footage, zooming in, slowing it down, and show us how she grew into such a confident performer. We see her notebooks and watch her lyrics appear in cursive while she sings them. The interviews with her friends, family, bodyguards, managers, and ex are all audio tracks, which keeps the focus entirely on Amy. Kapadia’s approach is fully aware of the irony behind the camera’s fascination with her, and how it became an instrument of both her rise and fall.</p>

<p>And while we’re on the subject of irony, “Rehab”:..</p>

<p>You were Amy’s biggest hit. But you were also the albatross around her neck. A catchy, Phil Spector-inspired chastisement to the doubters in her life, you skyrocketed her to fame with a cheeky hook that in retrospect seems like a cry for help. “They tried to make me go to rehab but I said no, no, no.” Amy sings you in one of the film’s best montages: on Leno, on Letterman, on increasingly larger stages, on the car radio in New York City. This could have been the sappy <em>VH1 Behind the</em> <em>Music</em>-style crescendo, the rising star sequence that leads to the overwrought “and then the unthinkable happened”-moment. But Kapadia doesn’t go there. As he did so masterfully in his documentary about Formula 1 driver Ayrton Senna, Kapadia manages the feat of actually making us forget, at least momentarily, that Amy (and Senna) died. </p>

<p>Externally, the Paparazzi pursued Amy relentlessly, stalking her at literally every turn. Internally, she faced constant pressure to keep performing despite her health being at risk from both addiction and years of bulimia. After nearly OD-ing, Amy and her husband Blake’s Sid &amp; Nancy-like desire to come off drugs together highlights how co-dependent they were. At one point during a tenuous attempt at recovery, Blake teasingly goads her to change your lyrics, and she responds, weakly: “I don’t really mind it here.” </p>

<p>Later, it becomes clear that your lyrics, “I ain’t got the time, and if my daddy thinks I’m fine,” aren’t just brassy pop sentiment—Mitch, her dad, goes so far as to stalk her for his own documentary, bringing a TV crew to St. Lucia where she has been trying to clean up. It becomes increasingly uncomfortable to watch Amy struggle to please everyone but herself.</p>

<p>These scenes, and those of her barely able to remember your lyrics while swaying onstage, are stomach churning. Because by now we’ve seen the <em>real</em> Amy. The one who was devilishly funny and wise beyond her years. The one who loved her friends and family. The one who loved making music, and the one who was frightened of becoming famous because she knew what it would do to her. </p>

<p>Kapadia shows us the Amy behind the trainwreck tabloid escapades. She becomes someone we want to root for. And not just because of her million dollar pipes. <em>Amy</em> is gutting because it <em>isn’t</em> the story of yet another star gone too soon; her struggle with mental illness and recovery was very real, and no less difficult because of her celebrity. Addiction doesn’t care if you’re famous.  </p>

<p>You were Amy’s biggest song but you certainly weren’t her best. Still, you will live on, mostly as a macabre joke sung by a reluctant pop star. But <em>Amy</em> reminds us that Amy wasn’t a punchline. She was a person.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pixels</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/7/28/pixels.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Pixels" />
    <published>2015-07-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/7/28/pixels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist: Adam Sandler is the Antichrist; Adam Sandler is the Antichrist; Adam Sandler is the Antichrist.</p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist—Adam Sandler is the Antichrist—Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. </p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist—Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist.</p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. ADAM SANDLER ADAM SANDLER ADAM SANDLER ADAM SANDLER ADAM SANDLER ADAM SANDLER…is the Antichrist. </p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. No really, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. </p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist—Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. </p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist </p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. </p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist—Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Adam Sandler is the Antichrist, Adam Sandler is the Antichrist.</p>

<p>Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist Adam Sandler is the Antichrist. Tsirthcitna eht si Reldnas Mada. Tsirhctitna eht si Reldnas Mada. Tsirhctitna eht si Reldnas Mada. Tsirthcitna eht si Reldnas Mada. Tsirhctitna eht si Reldnas Mada.</p>

<p>All work and Adam Sandler make Tim a crazy boy. This was in all ways a dreadful, flaccid film and I’m sorry for all of us it exists.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>