<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-23T09:18:22Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Race</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/23/race.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Race" />
    <published>2016-02-23T04:05:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-23T04:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/23/race</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The timing of Stephen Hopkins&#39; <em>Race</em> is perfect. The Jesse Owens biopic comes out during Black History Month, just in time to commemorate the 80th anniversary of the 1936 Olympic Games in Berlin, where Owens won four gold medals and, so the story goes, took a stand against the racial politics of the Nazis and showed Adolf Hitler exactly where to stow it. Constructing a myth is a lot like editing a film; you have a particular narrative in mind, and you comb through piece after piece of material, keeping everything that best supports your vision, and discarding everything that is extraneous or irrelevant to it. So it’s no surprise that <em>Race</em> also conveniently alters or discards what is inconvenient and unflattering. But it is disappointing. </p>

<p>Covering the beginnings of Owens’ career is a tedious journey to follow. Owens is shown making a name for himself in college athletics through a series of track meets that quickly become repetitive. Much of Owens’ struggle is depicted through the lens of his relationship with his coach, Larry Snyder. The most compelling part of Owens’ road to the Berlin Olympics are the conflicting pressures placed on him as an athlete representing the United States of America, as a black American, and as an individual whose own ambitions are overshadowed by what his country and community demand of him. But we get maybe two or three scenes that really delve into that aspect of Owens’ life. Mostly, it isn’t so much the Jesse Owens story as the story of how Jesse Owens helped his white coach get his groove back. For a film professing to pay homage to a prominent individual in the annals of Black history, I probably don’t need to spell out why this is problematic. </p>

<p>While the film’s pacing was way too slow off the blocks, you saved it in the final act. The plot finally hits its stride when we arrive in Berlin. There is little suspense, as we know how Owens fared at the games, but there is enough drama and intrigue there for three feature films. There is something for everyone at the Berlin Olympiad; history buffs can boo and hiss at Joseph Goebbels, film geeks can boo and hiss (or not) at Leni Riefenstahl, and sports movie enthusiasts are treated to highly engaging, kinetic race sequences. You establish a good rhythm going back and forth between the athletic sequences and the quieter scenes that establish the personal and political challenges faced by the athletes and Olympic officials, creating a compelling snapshot of a world on the brink of war. </p>

<p>While your editing ultimately shines, it’s the other more insidious narrative ‘editing’ I just couldn’t stomach. The plot makes a big deal out of the widely mythologized snubbing of Owens by Hitler. There have been numerous eyewitness accounts since 1936 disputing the claim that Hitler deliberately snubbed Owens at the Berlin Olympics – most importantly, Owens’ own account. According to him, the head of state who actually snubbed him was President Roosevelt, but I suppose that would be one of those uncomfortable, inconvenient snippets best left on a proverbial cutting room floor. When paying cinematic tribute to an individual, why stop at altering (if not flat-out disregarding) said individual’s own stated truth? </p>

<p>In <em>Race</em>, the audience is sold quite the bill of goods. The film is touted as celebrating Jesse Owens’ achievements within the greater context of Black history. However, narrative focus is split among four characters, and only one of them is Jesse Owens. Or black. Far too much time and attention is spent privileging the perspectives of white supporting characters. What makes things even worse is that their actions and motivations are themselves based on highly contentious accounts (I wanted to use the term ‘whitewashing’ but figured it might be too on the nose). If it was uncomfortable to sit through the glowingly flattering portrayal of Leni Riefenstahl, it was downright galling to watch the depiction of American Olympic Committee head, Avery Brundage, as an upstanding, idealistic champion of human rights when he was actually a vocal anti-Semite who made nice with Nazis to further his own ambitions. </p>

<p>Ironically, <em>Race</em> is a painfully accurate Jesse Owens biopic. Not as the story of an exceptional Black American athlete, but as the story of an exceptionally talented individual used by a mythmaking apparatus as a stand-in for an ideal. His actual life story proves less important than the narrative shaped to propagate a particular set of nationalist myths, in 1936 and once again in 2016.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Straight Outa Compton</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/23/straight-outa-comptopn.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StraightOutaCompton" />
    <published>2016-02-23T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-23T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/23/straight-outa-comptopn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>“You are now about to witness the strength of street knowledge.”</p>

<p>That’s the first line of the first track of N.W.A.’s debut album, from which your screenplay takes its name, and it is undeniably a call to arms. Whatever opinion you might have about the album – that it’s a true-to-life document of the sociocultural climate of inner-city Los Angeles in the 1980s, an artistic feat that revolutionized modern pop music, or a glorification of misogyny and violence – one thing is for certain: it’s fuelled by the complicated, brutal, erosive real-life experiences of its creators. It’s fuelled by <em>street knowledge</em>.  </p>

<p>So, after thinking for a while about the movie <em>Straight</em> <em>Outta</em> <em>Compton</em>, I am left wondering how a story that was inspired by such righteous anger and unpleasant truth could be delivered in such a shallow, banal, untruthful manner.</p>

<p>It’s a film fuelled by the <em>opposite</em> of street knowledge. What’s missing, ultimately, from your screenplay, is a sense of danger, of fearlessness, of purpose—a desire to incite thought and feeling and resolution. Instead, <em>Straight</em> <em>Outta</em> <em>Compton</em> is the kind of middle-of-the-road, play-it-safe, milquetoast pop-culture product that N.W.A. built their reputation by undermining. Which is more than just ironic. It’s <em>tragic</em>. Your film, in attempting to build a monument to the legacy of N.W.A., has compromised it instead. </p>

<p>I’ll be honest. I left the theater after seeing <em>Straight</em> <em>Outta</em> <em>Compton</em> . The people I’d gone with seemed to have enjoyed it, too. How could we not? It’s a feel-good music biopic that luxuriates in all the satisfying tropes of the genre: artist(s) come from disadvantageous circumstances, overcome adversity, prove naysayers wrong, overindulge in fame and success, learn lessons, overcome adversity once again, cement legacy, the end.</p>

<p>Like eating fast food, there is a certain base-level caloric satisfaction one receives from such intakes. The film is competently made. The performances are decent. It’s well-shot. But the story of one of the most contentious, important, divisive music groups of recent history deserves more than mere competence. Having had time to contemplate, I feel this strange sense of anger towards this film. I’m angry that it tricked me into thinking it had fulfilled its <em>raison</em> <em>d’etre</em> – to tell the story of NWA – when in fact is was the most hollow, meaningless, cloying, deceptive moviegoing experience I had all year. </p>

<p>And here’s the thing: N.W.A.’s success was about more than just talent, or the luck of being in the right place at the right time. It was about hard work. It was about trying and failing and trying again; doing the <em>hard</em> thing instead of the easy thing. You did the easy thing. You wrote a by-the-numbers screenplay that is, as both historical document and artistic expression, a compromise. </p>

<p>The whole production feels like an act of cowardice. It’s built upon a blueprint that offers ample opportunity for great risks to be taken (and great rewards to be reaped), but at each and every one of these opportunities your screenplay plays it safe. No, it’s more than just playing it safe. It obscures the truth in order to hide the story’s sharpest edges. It uncomplicates racial and cultural dynamics with a simplistic (almost propagandic) thematic focus. </p>

<p>But how can any of this be your fault? Sure, you wrote the screenplay. But you clearly weren’t writing for the audience. You were writing for the producers of the film, and there is no room to misinterpret your intentions: to deify them. </p>

<p>Those producers? Dr. Dre, Ice Cube, and Eazy-E’s widow, Tomica Woods-Wright. They have become the powerbrokers that they once rebelled against. Willing to protect their reputations (aka. their business interests) at any cost...</p>

<p>But. </p>

<p>Wait. </p>

<p>I feel like I need to think this through a little further. </p>

<p>Why am I so angry? Why does this offend me so much? Aren’t glossy, hollow, aggrandizing biopics as much a Hollywood tradition as bible epics and romantic comedies and superhero franchises? Why shouldn’t African American cultural icons receive the same varnished, agitprop treatment that white figures like Johnny Cash, Jerry Lee Lewis, and Steve Jobs have? In a year when the #OscarSoWhite movement has garnered more attention than the nominees themselves, what does it mean that I am all twisted up about the exaltation of this generation’s black leaders and the institutions they’ve created? Why did the inaccuracies and generalities of <em>Straight</em> <em>Outta</em> <em>Compton</em> incite more distaste in me than films like <em>The Social Network</em> or <em>Walk</em> <em>The</em> <em>Line</em>? Because it wasn’t dark enough, wasn’t gritty enough? And why on earth, of all the people to whom I could have written this outraged letter, did I choose the white lady who wrote one of the earliest drafts of the screenplay?</p>

<p>y reaction to this movie might be proof of the very need for movies like this. Perhaps, to be meaningful, to have real social impact, African Americans films don’t have to categorically be dark, gritty, brutal, ruthless, or fuelled by my white-guy’s detached academic notions of what street knowledge is. Maybe <em>Straight</em> <em>Outta Compton</em> is actually the story of how street knowledge made its way into the corridors of power. Making this kind of generic, revisionist-history biopic is, itself, an act of revolution akin to the album that inspired it.  </p>

<p>Dre and Cube certainly aren’t in Compton anymore. They’re part of the establishment, they’ve joined the system. They have the political and financial influence to produce films about themselves. And that might not be a bad thing—even if it produces bad movies.  </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Witch</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/19/the-witch.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheWitch" />
    <published>2016-02-19T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-19T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/19/the-witch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You and your director (Robert Eggers—a name which everyone should pay attention to) have crafted a film worthy of early Kubrick. <em>The Witch</em> is a superior piece of filmmaking. The whole experience was a pleasure, both aesthetically and intellectually.</p>

<p>And it’s also scary as shit.</p>

<p><em>The Witch</em> is a self-assured, mature piece of film craft. Your use of natural light gives the story the kind of pastoral naturalism that contrasts perfectly with the film’s supernatural underpinnings. Despite the rigor of your cinematography (echoing not just Kubrick, but the compositional perfection of Bergman’s <em>Seventh Seal</em>) it is a quiet, understated formalism. Your work is always at the service of the atmosphere of subtle dread that builds over the course of the whole film. The muted tones of autumn and early winter also evoke a patient, inevitable corruption; and the living avatar of that corruption lurks somewhere in the deep woods. Your camera intimates a mood of isolation—these people do not belong in this world. </p>

<p>And who are these people? A family living in self-imposed isolation in 17th Puritan New England, who left the safety of colonial life, largely because it didn’t meet their exacting religious standards. This gives the audience a sense of how utterly committed they are to a particular worldview, and it’s that myopically constricted commitment that serves them up as fodder for the entity that preys upon them. They are as lambs to slaughter just as much because of their blind adherence to their creed as the malevolence of their tormentor.</p>

<p>The performances are all remarkable, each member of the cast in lock step with the other. The dialogue, enriched by having been pulled from primary sources of the period, is both evocative and filled with a kind of nuanced foreboding. It would be almost unfair to single out one player over another since this film, small as it is, had no room for a mediocre performance. But Anya Taylor-Joy as Thomasin, the daughter teetering on the edge of womanhood, was particularly compelling. If any single character carried the weight of the narrative it was she, particularly as the film slid towards it’s foreordained conclusion. This film is utterly Calvinist in its inevitability, yet it never succumbs to the kind of narrative inertia a lot of films like this suffer in their final act. This is largely because the tension has less to do with what will happen and more to do with a more nuanced struggle about where your loyalties lie: to your family, or to your deity.</p>

<p>At its core <em>The Witch</em>  is a superior example of gothic horror in the same rarified category as Del Toro’s <em>Devil’s Backbone</em> or <em>The Orphanage</em>. It creates and sustains a level of dread that remains long after the film ends. If you have ever felt an atavistic shiver trying to look into the depths of a tangled wood in the early evening, just imagine that moment stretched out over almost two hours—that’s what you have created for your audience.</p>

<p><em>The Witch</em> reminded me how small-budget, low-tech filmmaking can produce superior work when it’s informed by exceptional performances, a strong script, a disciplined and clear-eyed director and captured images that build a fully rendered, fully inhabited world. This is one of the best films I have seen in a year filled with some exceptional work.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hail Caesar!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HailCaesar!" />
    <published>2016-02-19T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-19T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If there’s a crewmember of <em>Hail Caesar!</em> who exemplifies this film’s beating heart, it’s you. In the same way that certain Coen Brother’s films are like a Rube Goldberg device designed by MC Escher—exhausting to even think about—the hairstyles you designed for the film are equally byzantine and endlessly complex. They are elaborate, terraced constructions that capture a paradoxical authenticity; they foster the illusion that you are copying an original that <em>never actually existed</em>. </p>

<p>To watch <em>Hail Caesar!</em> is to fall through a wormhole to an alternate 1950’s Hollywood. Which, to be clear, is a charming place to be. The Coens have created an elaborate confection that is both a parody of itself and still deeply in love with the very thing it is poking fun at.</p>

<p>There are singing cowboys, Roman Centurions, Communist, Dames, a square jawed hero racked by uncertainty and, of course, Seamen everywhere. Nothing is sacred to the Coens—which is demonstrated in a sharply rendered set piece involving a priest, a rabbi, a pastor, and a patriarch walking into a room. </p>

<p>But the hair. My god, the hair in this movie. George Clooney with his Roman bowl cut, Josh Brolin with his magnificently brylcreemed pompadour, Tilda Swinton’s behatted magnificence as well as Alden Ehrenreich’s monumental spit curl, Scarlett Johansson’s hair that never gets wet (despite her turn as a faux Ester Williams) and Channing Tatum’s godlike swoop. All of this in aid of creating a place and time that feels absolutely genuine in its artifice.</p>

<p>Josh Brolin’s Eddie Mannix is the centerpiece of this film. He is a fixer for Capitol studios, spending his days and nights at the center of an endless storm of fuck-uppery: actresses having children out of wedlock; stars being kidnapped by disaffected communist screenwriters; gossip columnists attempting to leverage scandals; and then he also makes sure that the machinery of the moviemaking process remains well oiled, both metaphorically and literally.</p>

<p>There’s even an overt Christ metaphor that shadows Eddie like his ace secretary Natalie (a great performance by Heather Goldenhersh) but I suspect what the Coen’s are actually getting at is something a little more complicated.</p>

<p>If this film is attempting to do anything more than entertain, it seems to be an expression of the inherent ambivalence of the Coens’ relationship with the studios, and Hollywood in general, both past and present. They love what it could have been, or what it might still be, but they are clear-eyed about what it actually is. In the same way that <em>Birdman or (The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance)</em> is about how small-minded egomaniacs are nonetheless capable of producing great art, almost by accident, <em>Hail Caesar!</em> is a complicated love letter to the unpleasant but captivating characters who often populate the movie making industry.</p>

<p>While religion is often a screen for some of the most unpleasant of human behavior, the idea behind it still remains appealing, even if it is perverted at every turn—much like Hollywood. And it is in this small valley between the aspirational and the real that <em>Hail Caesar!</em>  plants its gaudy flag. And you and your magnificent creations helped to make sure that it is a valley populated by men and women with hair that we can all only dream of, Donna. And for that, I salute you.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Racing Extinction</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/17/racing-extinction.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RacingExtinction" />
    <published>2016-02-17T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-17T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/17/racing-extinction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re almost as famous as the dinosaurs you so righteously wiped out. The extinction you caused was severe – roughly 80% of the species living on Earth at the time didn’t make it. But nobody blames you.. We accept that  you were nature playing its course. You were an abnormality of probable odds. If you had crashed into some space debris before entering our gravitational pull, you could have been thrown off course and everything would have been different. The chances of an asteroid your size hitting Earth again are almost impossible, but that won’t stop us from entering the planet’s next extinction level event. In fact, we’re in it now. We are that event. We humans have become you, the asteroid.</p>

<p>That’s a pretty bold claim, but after watching <em>Racing Extinction</em>, it’s a harsh reality I had to face. <em>Racing Extinction</em> is an Oscar-nominated documentary (Best Original Song) that highlights the immense global destruction humans are selfishly causing—from selling endangered animals on the black market, to wiping out species by destroying natural habitats, to acidifying our oceans via carbon dioxide. If we scale Earth’s existence down to a 24-hour clock, as seen in <em>Racing</em> Extinction, humanity only appears a few seconds before midnight, and in the few seconds, we’ve promptly fucked things up. </p>

<p>We’re often quick to dust environmental impact off our shoulders; we see it as a small price to pay for modern luxuries. This is alarming considering not only are we the ones causing another extinction—we’re also the only ones who can stop it. So, unless dolphins finally get tired of our shit and revolt out of the oceans and fix the world, it’s up to us to become aware of our footprint. Which is why I believe everyone should take an hour and twenty minutes of their week to watch <em>Racing Extinction</em>. </p>

<p>We’re not a sudden force of nature. We’re not an improbable cause like you. We’re unconsciously, yet consciously bringing about our end in increments. In the back of our minds, we know all the wrong we’re doing, but we choose to suppress it. For those who do know what we’re doing and choose to accept it, only a handful of them are actually willing to put the first foot forward and make a change. I’m writing this letter but I certainly haven’t done anything of value to save the planet after watching <em>Racing Extinction—which is awful because _Racing Extinction</em> is an excellently crafted documentary. Director Louie Psihoyos does a great job of threading the audience along, informing and shocking along the way. </p>

<p>I was forced to take a hard look at myself and society around me, just like <em>Happy</em> and <em>Zeitgeist: The Movie</em> did; two of my favourite documentaries. And in that hard look, I found the lethargic human in me—the one who’s too used to public transportation and pre-cut chicken breast to want to change. </p>

<p>I, like most humans, am part of the systematic problem. I am gravity pulling you into Earth’s line of sight. I am the college student who knows my paper is due the next morning yet I can’t be bothered to stop watching Netflix. I’d rather face the consequence and justify my actions at a later time than give up what makes me feel comfortable. Humans are a very flawed species; we’re brilliant yet stupid, aware yet oblivious and driven yet lazy.</p>

<p>In other words: do you have a cousin that’s looking to make a rest stop? We might just need another wake up call.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Deadpool</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/12/deadpool.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Deadpool" />
    <published>2016-02-12T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-12T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/12/deadpool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My plan was to address this letter to <em>Deadpool’s</em> title sequence designer<em>—</em>after which I would make some clever comments about how, if nothing else, the film had a kind of internal integrity worth recommending. Then I was going to compare <em>Deadpool</em>’s opening credits—which were absolutely true to the tone of the film throughout—to other, more opaque, and nonrepresentational (to the point of distraction) opening sequences, like David Fincher’s <em>Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em>.</p>

<p>All this was going make the larger point that <em>Deadpool</em>, while essentially being the lucid dream of some really clever, but utterly perverse, 13 year old boy’s id, was at least fundamentally honest about its intentions from the start.</p>

<p>Anyway, that whole conceit kind of swallowed its own tail when I found out that you were a first time director who had largely made his bones as the creative force behind Blur Studios—which, among other things, had fashioned the opening titles for David Fincher’s version of <em>Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em>.</p>

<p>So instead of that I will go with plan B—where I point out that along with the writing team from <em>Zombieland</em> (Rhett Reese and Paul Wernick), you have managed to create a film that is flat out fun to watch. The opening titles skewer the film’s own narrative premises (the usual superhero origin story tinged by dark and gritty regret) without actively sneering at the larger framework (superhero movies in general)—and, in doing so, they announce that the movie we are about to see is as happy to laugh at itself as anything else, while still managing to follow a narrative compelling enough to carry us through the various inevitable discursions. </p>

<p>Oddly enough, the structure of this review has ended up mirroring what <em>Deadpool</em> does so well, which is comment upon its own story as it is occurring. This kind of narrative balancing act is really delicate to maintain—and probably only viable when the story is so boilerplate that it requires very little effort to follow. So while <em>Deadpool</em> the movie is a uniformly fun ride, it really doesn’t hold together under scrutiny. The only way to get anything at all out of this film is simply let it wash over you without spending too much time examining all the moving parts.</p>

<p>This is the kind of movie that probably was going to happen sooner or later—a late period superhero film that lives and dies on the expectation that the various tropes being skewered are so thoroughly inculcated that they don’t need much explanation. <em>Deadpool</em> is built upon the probability that the people watching it are at least moderately familiar with what it’s lampooning, so in some significant ways it is kind of a niche market. Like <em>Zombieland</em> before it, <em>Deadpool</em> is a fine confection—like a really good cheesecake. So if you like cheesecake, you’re good. If you think cheesecake is a pointless, empty collection of fat and calories, I wouldn’t bother.</p>

<p><em>Deadpool</em> has very little to add to a larger cultural conversation and even as a story it is pretty small stakes, but, in this case, these are both definitely points in its favor. Because I think you and your team seem to have remembered something a lot of other people have lost track of—comics and the movies they spawn can be fun just for the sake of it. So thanks for a night of just that, Mr. Miller. And I look forward to whatever you next put your hand to.</p>

<p>As long as it isn’t yourself. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Winter On Fire: Ukraine’s Fight for Freedom</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/10/winter-on-fire-ukraines-fight-for-freedom.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=WinterOnFire:Ukraine’sFightforFreedom" />
    <published>2016-02-10T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-10T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/10/winter-on-fire-ukraines-fight-for-freedom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Normally I’m suspicious of large groups of pale young people gathering together to subvert what they see as a repressive regime. Too often—in a North American context at least—such an insurgency is embodied by Oberlin college students boycotting the campus cafeteria, because they believe serving General Tso’s chicken is a type of <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/news/2015/12/oberlin-protest-dining-hall-food">cultural appropriation</a>. </p>

<p>But in your case, there’s no doubting the righteousness of your cause or the courage you have shown in the face of real adversity. As with the recent Arab Spring (so starkly portrayed in the documentary <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/25/the-square.html"><em>The Square</em></a>—a direct antecedent to <em>Winter On Fire</em>) this is the story of a populist uprising, largely propelled by politically engaged university students. Like the Tiananmen Square protests in 1989 or the Paris riots of 1968, these spontaneous, populist revolutions were in response to politically repressive (or otherwise unresponsive) regimes. All of these movements also began as small, student lead protests, but soon engaged a much broader coalition, from former soldiers, to union members and then schoolteachers, clergy and finally, just plain folks.</p>

<p>Both the Arab Spring and the Ukrainian uprising share one significant difference from both Tiananmen and the ’68 riots: they were largely facilitated by social media platforms like facebook and twitter. This made coordination of protests much more efficient as well as allowing for the widespread dissemination of video. This footage, often shot on mobile phones and mini-cams, was effective in demonstrating how disproportionate and brutal the government response was to what were initially peaceful protests, not to mention providing an enormous reservoir of primary material for the filmmakers. </p>

<p>Much of <em>Winter on Fir</em>e revolves around this primary footage, which is interlaced with after the fact interviews with various participants—and these interviews are often shot in the same locations as the events they are describing. As a documentary <em>Winter On Fire</em> also makes clever use of graphics, specifically CGI maps that help paint a remarkably lucid picture of the geography in question. These maps are effective in helping describe what was a fluid set of circumstances—significant events would occur simultaneously, in complicated urban environments, and they are presented here in a way that was remarkably useful in understanding the larger narrative.</p>

<p>This documentary has an obvious bias and if someone is interested in a more complete understanding of the appallingly complicated clusterfuck that is European-Ukrainian-Russian relations, <em>Winter on Fire</em> is probably more useful as supplemental material than as a primary source. Still, most western viewers will likely side with the protesters. There is a rare kind of clarity to the issues in question, and some of the footage is both horrifying and inspiring: unarmed protesters, often carrying makeshift metal shields, being attacked by government snipers—yet still continuing to move forward. Kids of fourteen or fifteen dressed in makeshift armor, cooking pot helmets and sheets of metal used as ersatz bulletproof vests, all looking like they came from an illustrated version of Alice In Wonderland.</p>

<p>The interviews themselves are filled with real characters. There’s a Muslim cleric who looks like an accountant from Des Moines, an Orthodox priest who I’m not sure is old enough to shave, and a crusty, Andy Rooney-looking, left-leaning, Ukrainian academic who accuses the regime of having “unleashed a bacchanalia of dictatorship”. <em>Winter on Fire</em> is, by turns, an oddly giddy and sometimes tragically serious film. But the real centerpiece is you, the university and high school students that started the whole thing. Engaged, committed, well informed, and serious about your (and your children’s) future, you saw the promise of European economic and cultural membership, and chose, at great risk, and often with mortal consequence, to defy the governments attempts to link the Ukraine with Russia.</p>

<p>To see that kind of commitment is a substantial slap in the face to the surface level and self-interested squalling that often passes for political speech in North America. And it’s particularly damning in contrast with the kind of stupidities that seem to occupy a particular white, upper-middle-class segment of our universities. There is a lot to admire in this film, but nothing more so than kids like you who care enough about abstract concepts like democracy and free speech to risk life and limb in support of them.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pride and Prejudice and Zombies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/9/pride-and-prejudice-and-zombies.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=PrideandPrejudiceandZombies" />
    <published>2016-02-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/9/pride-and-prejudice-and-zombies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I extend to you my deepest admiration for your efforts in the motion picture offering <em>Pride and Prejudice and Zombies</em>, and hope this letter finds you in the pink of health. I had feared the film would cause offense and upset to those who think fondly upon that greatest of literary works wrought so cleverly by Miss Jane Austen, but you will be relieved to hear my fellow filmgoers appeared to find it most diverting. </p>

<p>I must admit to having no real fondness for the work of Miss Austen. While her artful turn at social satire cannot be faulted, I have never managed to rally any real interest in tales centered upon the subject of marriage - be they tales of ladies consumed with the desire to marry, or of ladies chafing obstinately at the prospect of it. By peppering the work with an army of the undead, the film lends a certain bite to the trials and tribulations of the five Bennett sisters with their beauty, bearing, and BRRRAAAAAINS (forgive me).</p>

<p>At first blush, it appears that the bones of dear Miss Austen’s novel have been well-preserved, with entire scenes and conversations between characters bearing a familiar ring. Thrusting the characters into battle with zombie hordes is a rather entertaining means of adding flesh to bone, and a refined, if rather plodding tale suddenly bares its teeth. The sight of well-bred young ladies unsheathing daggers from between the soft folds of their pretty gowns appeared to heat the blood of many a gentleman audience member, a hard thing to begrudge the dear fellows, albeit highly improper. </p>

<p>Just as bland cooking is brightened by the adding of spice and seasoning, I have often felt that <em>Pride and Prejudice</em> would benefit greatly from the addition of subversive behaviours to liven up the interactions between its characters - a ribald word, untimely flatulence... <em>anything</em> that would prevent me from dozing off in the middle of all those tediously repressed exchanges. I must, therefore, applaud the use of violence toward this end. Turning Mr. Darcy’s failed proposal of marriage to Miss Bennett into an antique-smashing dust-up between the two infuses the scene with unprecedented passion – bravo indeed. </p>

<p>Alas, whatever bite there may be at the start, the film is rendered toothless by the finish. The incongruous presence of zombie creatures and well-born country girls up to their corsets in gore is an entertaining novelty at first, but becomes repetitive by the halfway point. I fear the boring, marriage-obsessed plot is ultimately not saved even by a whist party that ends in smashed skulls and guests spattered with the viscera of the undead. That being said, I lend my voice in support of introducing zombies to other well-loved period pieces; <em>Northanger Abbey and Zombies</em> would be marvellous. <em>Downton Abbey and Zombies</em> would, in modern parlance, be simply off the hook. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Brooklyn</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/4/brooklyn.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Brooklyn" />
    <published>2016-02-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/4/brooklyn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What I find compelling about the films you’re involved with is their lucid portrayal of a particular species of love. In <em>High Fidelity, About A Boy, Wild,</em> and now <em>Brooklyn,</em> love is depicted as an effort to pay attention, and to understand without judgment. In the worlds you create, love is about seeing the person in front of you, and accepting that they’re probably as flawed a creature as you.  </p>

<p>This is something John Cusak’s Rob Gordon is slow to learn in <em>High Fidelity</em>, and Hugh Grant’s Will Freeman is perhaps even slower to comprehend in <em>About A Boy</em>. It is a truth that evades Reese Witherspoon’s Cheryl—especially when it comes to herself—for almost the entirety of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html"><em>Wild</em></a>. But in <em>Brooklyn,</em> this truth seems to be integral to Saoirse (sounds like inertia) Ronan’s Eilis from birth. Consequently, the film is far more concerned with the impediments that life throws in front of all of us—in our search for love and belonging—than any kind of interior journey.</p>

<p>Set in the early 1950’s, <em>Brooklyn</em> is very much Eilis’s story. We follow her from her native Ireland, where she is completely unfulfilled, to Brooklyn, New York—and what is essentially a halfway house for young, unmarried women. There she is shepherded by an Irish priest—played benevolently by Jim Broadbent in a role he could have sleepwalked through, but didn’t—until she finds employment in a Macy’s-like department store.</p>

<p>The rest of the film concerns itself with Eilis and her new life—the ups and downs, ins and outs of a young women discovering how the world operates. In many ways, this film is boilerplate in its plot construction, but it is never hackneyed. This is due to the restrained tone (there is never a scene that feels heightened or contrived), uniformly strong performances and the superb attention to detail in the costume and set design. However, what really makes <em>Brooklyn</em> special is Ronan and her tremendous presence. She is a remarkable actress and entirely too self possessed for someone so young. So many moments in this film are carried by a simple gesture or a subtle tell in Ronan’s demeanor. Couple this rare ability with her talent for infusing dialogue with a quiet veracity, and Ronan’s performance becomes something special to watch. </p>

<p>While Eilis’s burgeoning love life is what drives the plot, it is the small, idiosyncratic details that you include that help differentiate this film from a thousand others. The most entertaining of which is Mrs. Keogh—the tyrannical matriarch of the boarding house—portrayed in a marvelously cranky turn by Julie Waters. She is a both a <em>character</em> and the same time a fully realized human being— a feat of writing that is vanishingly rare in any medium. As a result of this kind of nuanced work, moments that could have been heavy handed or overt are given a gentle twist that feels authentic and emotionally honest in a way that you don’t often see, especially in major studio releases. Add to that the absolute fidelity of the visuals to a particular time and place—this <em>is</em> Brooklyn in the early fifties—and you have a film that is far more than the sum of its trailers. </p>

<p>Also, the sharp casting choice of her two suitors—Emory Cohen as Tony and Domhnall Gleeson as Jim—is just another feature in a long list that helps elevate <em>Brooklyn</em> far above the <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/27/far-from-the-madding-crowd.html">Madding Crowd</a>. </p>

<p>It is perhaps surprising to some that <em>Brooklyn</em> is nominated for an Oscar in the Best Picture, Best Adapted Screenplay and Best Actress categories. In many ways this is a small, intimate film without much in the way of overt fireworks. But the craft at work, the script you produced, and the memorable character that Ronan creates in Eilis, make this a special film. </p>

<p>All things considered, <em>Brooklyn</em> is eminently worthy of the kind of recognition it is receiving and a fine addition to an already impressive body of work. Good luck on Oscar night, Nick.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Danish Girl</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/3/the-danish-girl.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheDanishGirl" />
    <published>2016-02-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/3/the-danish-girl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It takes a lot of balls to pull off a transgender character. Any asshole can throw on a wig and a dress and go <em>To Wong Fu, Thanks</em> <em>For</em> <em>Everything! Julie</em> <em>Newmar</em>, but rising above the gimmicks of drag takes a much lighter touch. Especially when differentiating between cross-dressers, homosexuals, transsexuals, intersex persons, etc. One wrong step and the critics will have their knives out. That’s the conventional logic, anyway. But as Eddie Redmayne’s tepid and uninspired performance in _The Danish Girl proves, being bland is a far greater cinematic offence than going over the top.</p>

<p><em>The Danish Girl</em> feels like a film from another time. Not because the story is set in the European high-art scene of the 1920s, but because it treats its subject with such naivety and earnestness that the story itself feels secondary to the premise. Following someone who is born as a man and transitions to a woman is simply not enough to hold an audience’s interest. Twenty years ago, making a film about a transgender pioneer would have certainly ruffled more than a few feathers, and sparked conversations and think-pieces merely by existing. But not in 2015. Not months after Bruce Jenner became Caitlyn Jenner, not a couple years after Jared Leto won an Oscar for playing a transgender woman, and not decades after <em>The Rocky Horror Picture Show</em> crossed over into the mainstream. Novelty has given way to nuance. Substance matters, now more than ever. </p>

<p>Which is why the film’s painfully dull execution felt all the more offensive.  Redmayne opting to take most of his physical cues from a shy Japanese school girl, covering his mouth as he giggles, always averting his eyes, is a choice that I can live with. Accuracy and subtlety aren’t nearly as important as conveying an emotional truth. At times, your coaching helps him do this effectively, like when he delicately lays dresses across his chest or slides on high heels for the first time. These moments were well-choreographed to communicate sensuality and excitement. It was after Einar became Lili that the film started to feel tragically uninspired and predictable.</p>

<p>The story veers towards calamity, and we can see it coming, but instead of providing a deeper exploration of personal dynamics or ratcheting up the suspense, the narrative is pinned down under the weight of the inevitable tragedy, which becomes stifling to watch. By the time we reach the conclusion, rather than feeling surprised or inspired, it felt as if the filmmakers were simply trying to craft a graceful exit. </p>

<p>The film’s saving grace is Alicia Vikander, playing the conflicted but understanding wife, and equally talented (more so, perhaps) painter. She gives each of her scenes a much needed energy and purpose, propelling the story forward and poignantly conveying mood with a simple look or playful gesture. It may be the more thankless and less showy of the two roles, but it’s certainly the more substantial. </p>

<p>After all, it doesn’t matter how a character moves as long as they move <em>us</em>. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>