<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-04T10:14:44Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Truth</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/4/truth.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Truth" />
    <published>2015-11-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/4/truth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I trust you were extra careful with every paper you handled on the set of <em>Truth</em>. Like, anal retentive, triple-check, hyper-cautiously-aware of your responsibilities. Sure, you were only hired as a production assistant, but first-time director James Vanderbilt obviously knows the importance of a solid paper trail after adapting Mary Mapes’ novel, so he must have hired you specifically to make sure everything was by-the-book. Otherwise, you know—the whole project/company/profession could have come crashing down.</p>

<p>No pressure.</p>

<p>It’s this kind of high-stakes attention to detail that sits at the heart of Vanderbilt’s film adaptation of <em>Truth and Duty: The Press, the President, and the Privilege of Power</em>, a first-hand account of the infamous CBS 60 Minutes news segment that questioned President George W. Bush’s military service record. What began as an earnest fact-finding mission about whether or not Bush was given a cushy job with the National Guard to avoid combat in Vietnam turned into a shadowy chess match between obscure sources with even more obscure motivations—one that famously cost host Dan Rather and producer Mary Mapes their careers.</p>

<p>The 60 Minutes segment aired during the 2004 presidential election, and was journalistically justified, in part, by Republican attacks against the service record of Democratic Presidential candidate John Kerry. But, with the help of a sleuth internet community, major questions arose about the authenticity of a key document being featured. The typeface, critics argued, matched those of a 2004 Word processor perfectly, and wasn’t the same as the ones found in most typewriters from 1971. More specifically, a superscript font appeared to be anachronistic. Within days, the story quickly shifted from Bush’s record to that of the news team that broke the story.</p>

<p>Much in the same way that the true scope of this story snuck up on the reporters, so too does the drama in Vanderbilt’s telling. The gravitas of what is happening isn’t apparent early on, nor was it for me as a university journalist student when this incident was first unfolding. After all, the media is famous for aggrandizing their own importance. And in the digital age, it has become fashionable to cheer the demise of the old establishment, even if it’s just to watch it burn. But seeing their credibility go up in smoke is a much more somber experience from the inside.  </p>

<p>What really makes this film work, however, are the more progressive elements of the story—namely, prioritizing Mapes’ story over Rather’s (who, in the public, was the much more prominent player). Experiencing the pile-on from a female perspective adds an intangible strength to the story in which the opposition came directly from the old boys club. Cate Blanchett navigates her role with the dignity you’d expect, and even gets backing from her (non-)trope “supportive husband”. Sure, Mapes’ psychology is a bit reductive (daddy-issues, with some on-the-nose dialogue to hammer the point home), but her professional motivations and methods are less easy to pick apart. </p>

<p>The film is also, thankfully, workmanlike in its approach, devoid of the hyperbolic visual flare that plagued <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/22/the-fifth-estate.html"><em>The Fifth Estate</em></a>, focusing instead on the details. A lot of care went into translating what was on the page onto the screen, which is exactly what a good journalism is all about. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Last Witch Hunter</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/3/the-last-witch-hunter.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheLastWitchHunter" />
    <published>2015-11-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/3/the-last-witch-hunter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>With all due respect, from one writer to another I have to ask: Dude, what the hell?</p>

<p>Even though there are a trio of writers behind <em>The Last Witch Hunter</em>, I’m singling you out because it was your encounter with Vin Diesel, and your shared love for <em>Dungeons &amp; Dragons</em>, that brought this abomination to life. </p>

<p>Yes, abomination. </p>

<p>When I was a child, the fantasy genre was my absolute favorite. I would spend hours creating stories, assigning characters and playing out my creation with assorted G.I. Joes, rubbing red Crayola on my toys if they ‘bled’.  I would play in the bathtub if an ocean setting were required—hell, I would even create TV shows, with episodes and seasons. I literally grew up with this genre. So when I heard Vin Diesel was going to be able to live in his nerd Valhalla, I was a tad jealous. But after viewing <em>The Last Witch Hunter</em>, I was just insulted by the dumbed down, clichéd mess. It’s not just bland, predictable and forced, it’s a haphazard Frankensteining of <em>The Mummy Returns, The Sorcerer’s Apprentice </em>and<em> Halloweentown.</em></p>

<p><em>The Last Witch Hunter </em>is the generation-spanning tale of Kaulder (sounds an <em>awful </em>lot like cauldron), an infamous witch hunter who was cursed with immortality 800 years ago by the evil witch queen. What follows is the tired, old dribble that accompanies all gothic fantasy films. </p>

<p>Kaulder now operates out of modern-day New York as a bounty hunter of sorts, capturing evil witches and sentencing them to imprisonment—and what’s an imprisonment without a secret court of witch elders who handle the sentencing of magical criminals? It’s the obvious choice. </p>

<p>I didn’t even need to watch the movie, let alone the trailer, to figure out that Kaulder would be draped in black and silver, and that most of the scenery would feature cold buildings made out of brick and iron. Furthermore, the reciting of spells had to be the most painstaking load of enunciated vowels strung along with an echoed whisper, ever. I’m thinking of parseltongue from Harry Potter—and I know you were too.</p>

<p>There is zero subtlety here. You have to remind us at every single turn that we are in the presence of witches: potions, magic stones, horned creatures, insect swarms—you pretty much Googled a list of everything related to witchery and crammed it in. </p>

<p>When we are introduced to Chloe’s bar, we aren’t invited into a seemingly normal bar where witches and wizards can sit back, relax and have a pint like us regular folk. No, we’re invited into a secret world where, instead of alcohol, glowing potions are served, and instead of table lights, there are illuminated, wispy clouds circulating above patron’s heads.  </p>

<p>And somehow you had the gall to push it further. Kaulder actually says the word “magic” out loud when he witnesses a spell. Really, Cory? The man has been around for 800 years and is a witch hunter—why the fuck does he have to say “magic” when he sees it? We get it: <em>The Last Witch Hunter </em>is a movie about witches. </p>

<p>The worst part is that I knew it would be bad—yet I still left disappointed. Fantasy fans should be treated to a better representation of the genre in 2015. <em>The Last Witch Hunter</em> was all sorts of toil and trouble.</p>

<p>Sincerely,</p>

<p>Ankit  </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The 16 Sexiest Roles on a Film Set</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/28/the-16-sexiest-roles-on-a-film-set.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=The16SexiestRolesonaFilmSet" />
    <published>2015-10-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/28/the-16-sexiest-roles-on-a-film-set</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I know why you really got into the business. It wasn’t because you’re a masochist for long hours or a sucker for uncertain income. You think film is sexy. Actually, you <em>know</em> film is sexy. And you’re right.</p>

<p>If you’re attracted to a career in filmmaking, it’s only natural that the people in the industry will turn your crank. But beware – there’s a hierarchy of hotness on set.</p>

<p>Here’s a wildly subjective ranking of roles, and what gives them different degrees of bedability. Actors have been disqualified for obvious reasons (they’re all bat-shit crazy).</p>

<p><strong>16. Data Wrangler</strong></p>

<p>Look, somebody had to be last. And let’s face it – most Data Wranglers have their heads buried in a laptop all day and rarely register on set. When you do, it’s usually disastrous. Being the bearer of bad news that a file is corrupt or a card won’t read is the ultimate buzz kill – even if it’s not your fault (and it usually isn’t). Sure, you can sometimes score points with actors by giving them a sneak peak at the digital dailies, but even then you’re just being used. It’s sad to say that the one job on set with zero room for error is not exactly a head turner, but at least you made the list (sorry, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/9/cloudburst.html">Craft Services</a>). </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Arnaud Hemery Data Manager for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/25/lucy.html"><em>LUCY</em></a></p>

<p><strong>15. Production Assistant</strong></p>

<p>You’re not last! It wouldn’t be fair to pick on this job, especially since so many of us have been PA’s at one time or another. Yes, it’s unglamorous and often attracts unskilled go-getters, but stick around because itgetsbetter. People usually have an eye on you (to see if you fuck up), but at least competence will get you noticed. It’s an entry level-job with big-time make-over potential. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Natalie Wood Production Assistant for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/14/downhill-racer.html"><em>DOWNHILL RACER</em></a></p>

<p><strong>14. Dolly Grip</strong></p>

<p>Here’s a job that many people enjoy doing, but few people enjoy watching. Dolly Grip’s win “Most Likely to Flash Plumber Crack”, but are not nearly as likely to get any ass themselves. The process of laying track and guiding the camera is one that requires a lot of focus and steady work, so luckily most Dolly Grips are too busy to care what anyone else thinks. That’s worth something. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Bruce Hamme, Dolly Grip for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/10/prisoners.html"><em>PRISONERS</em></a></p>

<p><strong>13. Props Master</strong></p>

<p>Being a Prop Master is only as sexy as you make it. Depending on the film, you’ll have various chances to show off your good taste and handy skills. The only problem is that once props are loaned out, most of you turn into neurotic headcases trying to keep track of everything; making sure that vintage book pages aren’t torn or that the vase in the background gets back to your grandma safely. Lack of control inevitably loses you points.</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Michael S. Martin, Property Master for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/13/12-years-a-slave.html"><em>12 YEARS A SLAVE</em></a></p>

<p><strong>12. Continuity / Scrip Supervisor</strong></p>

<p>Good continuity is a total turn on, but more in a reliable relationship way. You got here by proving you have a great attention to detail, and as such, are often seated at the right hand of the director to keep an eye on loose strings. Like many relationships, pointing out inconsistencies or faults might be encouraged early on, but you also have to be okay with being regularly dismissed or overruled. It’s a tricky dynamic to have work in your favour.</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Ronit Ravich-Boss, Script Supervisor for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/6/21/thats-my-boy.html"><em>THAT’S MY BOY</em></a></p>

<p><strong>11. Best Boy</strong></p>

<p>Like the Best Man at a wedding Best Boy is a true misnomer (shouldn’t the “best man” be the one getting married?). Second-in-command of either the Grip or Gaffer department, the term dates back to when managers would yell “bring me your best boy!” to come help with lighting or electrical. This official wingman status is often a thankless job, but at the same time, being shown favour on a big set gets you noticed. Plus, some people would probably hook up with a Best Boy just to say they did. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Greg Fusak, Best Boy for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/29/behind-the-candelabra.html"><em>BEHIND THE CANDLEABRA</em></a></p>

<p><strong>10. Line Producer</strong></p>

<p>Though being the money manager isn’t as sexy as it sounds, there’s some true power here, and that’s the basis for most of the appeal. Many of the department heads are likely to cozy up to a Line Producer just to try and squeeze a little extra money their way. Enjoy it. It’s the best play you have. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Sarah Craig, Line Producer for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/7/time-lapse.html"><em>TIME LAPSE</em></a></p>

<p><strong>9. Unit Production Manager</strong></p>

<p>What’s hotter than hiring and firing people? Well, a lot, but this is still a position that demands respect on set. Points are mainly lost by being so removed from the action when the camera’s rolling, usually holed up in a trailer somewhere crunching numbers and fixing schedules. But with the power to make or break many below-the-line careers, it’s no wonder there’s a little strut in your step. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Brian Bell, Unit Production Manager on</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/9/neighbors.html"><em>NEIGHBORS</em></a></p>

<p><strong>8. Assistant Director</strong></p>

<p>There have to be some cheats here, so I’m grouping all you A.D.’s together, even if the difference between a First, Second and Third is rather huge. It goes without saying that your appeal is directly related to your ranking – no one’s getting hot and bothered by a Third A.D. bossing extras around (well, bothered maybe), and Seconds are usually tucked away in the office somewhere (which at least provides an air of mystique). An effective First A.D., however, really has presence on set – even if all the yelling has more in common with a drill sergeant than a rock singer. In fact, using the band analogy, First A.D.’s are more like the drummer – making a lot of noise and keeping the rhythm of the production going. And we all know drummers get plenty of action. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Lauren Wells-Jones, Casual Assistant Director for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html"><em>THE BABADOOK</em></a></p>

<p><strong>7. Make-up Artist/Costume Designer</strong></p>

<p>If there’s a cool kids club on set, Make-up and Costumes are the gatekeepers. You get a lot of face time with the stars and are the hub of production gossip. But the real appeal comes from being so hands on; cozying up with measurements and touch-ups, striking a quick level of intimacy and familiarity the actors. By extension, Make-Up Artists and Costumer Designers are usually approachable and friendly by nature. Both disciplines (combined here for simplicity) are true art forms in and of themselves, where excellence can be rewarded with an Oscar or a spot on SyFy’s FaceOff. That’s hot. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Robin Matthews, Makeup Department Head for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html"><em>WILD</em></a></p>

<p><strong>6. Boom Operator</strong></p>

<p>If you don’t have a sense of humour, you can’t be a boom operator. The big rod you brandish makes you the butt end of easy jokes, but owning that absurdity goes a long way. It’s a low level position, but also the most visible one in the sound department – and the most fit. Keeping your mic out of the frame isn’t easy. Arm strength is one thing, but there’s also an agility required to keep up with hand-held moving action. For that reason, you’re hotter than you think. Plus, who doesn’t love somehow who knows how to work a pole?</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Valeria Ghiran, Boom Operator for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/2/the-artist.html"><em>THE ARTIST</em></a></p>

<p><strong>5. Grip/Gaffer</strong></p>

<p>Another big cheat to combine these two professions, but the same principles of attraction apply to setting up lights and laying cables. These are technical jobs that require both brain and brawn. Both land on a respectable rung of the professional ladder, and watching someone who really knows what they’re doing is always appealing. But really, this ranking is all about the belts. A lot of people wear them, but no one on set owns them like a Grip and Gaffer. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Andy Mountain, Lighting Console Operator for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html"><em>UNDER THE SKIN</em></a></p>

<p><strong>4. Director</strong> </p>

<p>An ego monster by necessity, a director’s magnetism is a real crapshoot. Everyone on set is judging you, and expecting an answer to their question. If you make mistakes, people talk behind your back. If you act like a big shot without delivering world-class goods, word travels fast that you’re an insecure phony. But no matter what people say, you’re endowed with creative control – and that’s impossible to ignore. If you do all your homework, treat people well, and , your sex appeal is second-to-none. But more often than not, seeing the sausage being made is a pretty heavy turn-off.  </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Marc Foster, Director of</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/19/world-war-z.html"><em>WORLD WAR Z</em></a></p>

<p><strong>3. Production Designer</strong> </p>

<p>You could be working anywhere – drafting buildings, designing big brands, creating personal installations – but you’ve chosen to give your talents to film. The wild variety of skill sets most Production Designers and Art Directors possess make you the most interesting people on set. Most of you care as much about Neo-classical architecture as you do contemporary tech interfaces. You might not sweat as much as the Grips and Gaffer, but you don’t need to. Plus, even in jeans and T-shirt, you still seem to dress better than most people on set.  </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Bobby Vanonen, Production Design/Art Direction for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/6/the-valley-below.html"><em>THE VALLEY BELOW</em></a></p>

<p><strong>2. Stunt Coordinator</strong></p>

<p>Not many sets have the luxury of a true Stunt Coodinator (or even stunt performers), but the ones that do – look out. Everyone’s eyes are on your action. It’s a rough and tumble profession, and one that, at its best, risks life and limb for our entertainment (will somebody give you and Oscar category already?). The reason it’s so high isn’t just because of the Ryan Gosling <em>Drive</em> factor, but the stunt makers who have really broken out, from Bruce Lee to Zoë Bell. Even when you’re doubling for a star, you’re the real show on set.</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Brian Smyj, Stunt Coordinator for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/12/the-place-beyond-the-pines.html"><em>THE PLACE BEYOND THE PINES</em></a></p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Cinematographer</strong></li>
</ol>

<p>Was there ever any doubt? If the Director is the singer of a rock band, the Cinematographer is the lead guitar. It’s where the real music comes from, and where fans know to focus their attention. As the architect of light and movement, the Cinematographer (or Director of Photography) has enough help to side step most of the drama that plagues other department heads. And even so, you’re often the hardest working person on set. Most Directors are disproportionately indebted to their Cinematographer, so they can’t begrudge the praise you get. But don’t think they aren’t jealous when an A-list movie star<a href="http://variety.com/2015/film/news/emmanuel-lubezki-wins-oscar-for-cinematography-1201439231/">lovingly uses your nick-name</a> to announce your Oscar win to the world. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Chris Cassidy, Cinematographer for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/26/side-by-side.html"><em>SIDE BY SIDE</em></a></p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Beasts of No Nation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/27/beasts-of-no-nation.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BeastsofNoNation" />
    <published>2015-10-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/27/beasts-of-no-nation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In today’s increasingly fractured media landscape, acquiring great content is more important than ever. DIY distribution companies are popping up like weeds, and film festivals crawl all over each other like roaches fighting for exclusive premieres. And if people like you don’t position a film properly at the outset, it’s almost guaranteed to be a bust.  You only get one chance to launch a film, no matter how big or small the budget. So choosing a Netflix release – rather than a traditional theatrical release – for <em>Beasts of No Nation</em> was certainly a bold move. It made the industry stand up and take notice. The question is, will the public follow, too?</p>

<p>It’s not an easy sell. Idris Elba certainly has his fans, but the film otherwise boasts a cast of mostly first-time African actors. The difficult subject matter of Uzodinma Iweala’s novel, from which the film is adapted, probably didn’t line up any buyers, either. But enough people saw potential in the brutal story of child soldiers in Ghana that the film was financed and completed. </p>

<p>Then along comes Netflix to scoop up the rights before anyone else even had a chance. I couldn’t help but wonder: was going straight to streaming a vote of confidence in the film—or  a cop out ? A bit of both, I can finally say after seeing the film. And probably the right play. </p>

<p>As a consumer (especially one who’s house-bound with two kids), I selfishly applaud the move. The fact that Cary Joji Fukanaga’s follow up film after <em>True Detective</em> didn’t make the Cannes cut certainly didn’t dampen my expectations (especially since the whiff of being an “original Netflix film” may have been too odorous for those upturned French noses), and it was certainly one of the films I hoped to see at the Toronto International Film Festival. But that pending release date, a month later, which would be beamed straight to my home, pushed the film lower on my list of priorities. Which means that I saw the film, like most people, only after it was released to the public. And that’s when the whole distribution strategy started to make sense.</p>

<p>First, the film has a fairly difficult running time of 2 hours and 20 minutes, which is fine for superheroes and sequels, but not so much for films focused on child murder and rape. Though to scare people off with the film’s more extreme elements would be doing it a serious disservice. After all, Fukanaga’s cinematography (yeah, he did that, too, on top of writing and producing the film) has a poetic ease that never aims to shock, even in its most brutal machete-wielding moments. The performances are nicely underplayed, and Elba comes to the role of the Commandant with a certain <em>je ne sais quoi</em> that doesn’t quite demonize his reprehensible character. He treats the brutal violence around him as an avoidable consequence of refusing to follow his rules. </p>

<p>While the film may not have many direct comparisons, it’s probably most easily described as a cross between <em>The Last King of Scotland</em> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/10/5/war-witch-rebelle.html"><em>War Witch</em></a>—neither of which were exactly box-office champions, but both of which made an impact come Oscar season. </p>

<p>In some ways, <em>Beasts of No Nation</em> is destined to suffer a similar fate: it will either be heralded by critics, awards juries, and audiences who are able to see it more easily than the other buzzed-about end-of-year art films, or it will be consciously scrolled over in favour of a hundred other choices that are a little easier for the public to digest. </p>

<p>For your sake, I hope they press play.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sicario</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/26/sicario.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Sicario" />
    <published>2015-10-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/26/sicario</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In a film as morally oblique as <em>Sicario</em>, it is imperative for the audience to have someone to attach themselves to as the story unfolds. Your character, Kate Mercer—a driven but relatively inexperienced FBI agent—is that anchor. When she is seconded to the DOD, ostensibly as an expert in hostage situations, it seems as if she is being given an opportunity to actually make a dent in the upper echelons of the Mexican cartels.</p>

<p>Initially the operation appears pretty straightforward—but it quickly becomes clear to both Kate, and the audience, that nothing is what it seems. </p>

<p>Throughout the film—and this is one of the many devices used to maintain an uncomfortable tension—Kate is constantly frustrated in her attempts to obtain even the most basic information from her new colleagues. This opaqueness, rather than discouraging her, makes Kate more determined to penetrate the byzantine world she has been drawn into. Her persistence is admirable but it is also the lever used to manipulate her. Kate’s principled commitment to her vocation is her Achilles heel.</p>

<p><em>Sicario</em> is a difficult film for a number of reasons. The central theme is the unmitigated disaster that the perpetual war on drugs has engendered in the countries involved as well as the various law enforcement agencies engaged in that never-ending conflict. The policy failure at all levels and the collateral damage those policies inflict on the civilian populations is a given in this film—regardless of the empty bravado of characters like Josh Brolin’s DOD agent and the peculiar Colombian Alejandro (Benicio Del Toro, doing his best work in years). There are no heroes in <em>Sicario.</em> The characters are either morally bankrupt, ineffectual, enmeshed in events beyond their control, or simply too civilized to survive the snake pit that the Mexican/US border has become.</p>

<p>The violence that these policies spawn is present from the beginning of the film and is ubiquitous throughout. And despite Roger Deakins extraordinary cinematography and Denis Villeneuve’s superlative direction, that brutality is nothing but ugly. There are a number of technically superior sequences in <em>Sicario</em> but none of them leave you feeling anything but unsettled. There is never a moment where the violence achieves anything other than multiplying the root difficulties. Each death simply leads to more of the same, whatever the empty ambitions and rationales of the men involved. And it is always a man, and a very particular sort of man, that initiates the violence.</p>

<p>That’s why your character is so important, Emily. Not only is Kate the only women involved who isn’t simply a bystander, but she also comes to stand for most of us; competent, engaged, but out of her depth and completely unable to operate with the casual viciousness required to survive in the moral vacuum these men seem to thrive in.</p>

<p><em>Sicario</em> is what enforcement becomes when separated from the rule of law—a series of vendettas and power plays that see whole families butchered in the name of expedience and the vague goal of some sort of manageable equilibrium. That your character is unable to swim with this particular school of sharks is neither a character flaw nor a weakness, it is simply the consequence of living within boundaries most of us never see a need to test. Kate’s final choice in the film is the only one a moral human could make, yet it is also the reason we may all fall.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Before We Go</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/21/before-we-go.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BeforeWeGo" />
    <published>2015-10-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/21/before-we-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s been a while. About 18 years or so. Hope you’re doing well. I’m happily married, no kids, nice house, great job. Great life, actually. How about you? I’ve often wondered what you’ve been up to. I googled you once, about ten years ago, but came up empty, and I’ve since forgotten your last name. But that one intense and adorably chaste night we spent together is still vivid in my memory. Do you remember it as fondly as I do?</p>

<p>We met-cute at about 2:00 am on a Saturday night in 1997 when you noticed me struggling to escape through a trap door in the basement of the bar where I worked. I was ducking out to avoid a guy I’d been dating; he was incapable of gracefully accepting our break-up. You pulled me out of a literal hole in the wall and recognized me as the bartender who had been shamelessly flirting with you all night. It seemed like fate, so we spent the night wandering the city and falling in the kind of love only early 20-somethings and Hollywood screenwriters believe in (the kind who write movies I usually hate).</p>

<p>As a self-identifying cynic, by-the-numbers romantic movies invariably induce my gag reflex. But my fond memories of our single, cinematic evening together made me fall for the premise of <em>Before We Go</em>. If I hadn’t lived such a similar experience, I’d probably dismiss the film as a blatant rip-off of the <em>Before</em> _Sunrise trilogy, rather than the charming homage I believe first-time director Chris Evans intended it to be. I found myself completely enchanted by the rhythms and complications of two strangers reluctantly falling in love. </p>

<p>When we met we were both 24 years old, and neither of us had been around long enough to have real baggage. But the leads in <em>Before We Go</em> are a bit older and have a lot more to lose, making their night fraught with tension. Nick and Brooke meet as Grand Central Station is closing for the night. Brooke has had her purse stolen, broken her phone, and missed the last train back to Boston. Nick is killing time while he decides whether or not he should attend a wedding reception where he knows his ex will be. Nick offers to help get Brooke back to Boston before 7:00 am, because she has convinced him that her life – and broken marriage – depends on it. While they spend the next several hours trying to get Brooke back home, they bare their souls to one another, and make some serious life decisions in the process. </p>

<p>Let’s face it: if I looked like Rhea Pearlman, you might not have been so eager to pull me out of a beer chute to spend a chilly night wandering through the streets with me. And if you looked like Danny DeVito, I probably would have crawled back in that hole. The plot of <em>Before We Go</em> hinges on the believability of two people being attractive enough to actually fall for each other so quickly. Chris Evans is Captain America and Alice Eve is a petite blue-eyed blonde with girl-next-door written all over her. They’re good-looking, but not in the usual, unbelievable Hollywood way. A lot happens to these two in a scant five hours, but both actors sell the narrative convincingly. You have to really root for these crazy kids in this mixed-up world, or the whole thing doesn’t work, and I <em>wanted</em> to believe that they could fall in love, so the willing suspension of disbelief wasn’t especially hard to muster. Sound familiar?</p>

<p>Evans and Eve are well-paired here, and handle the dialogue-driven film with natural ease and subtlety. Both characters are given equal weight and depth, with neither falling into rom-commy conventions. This makes scenes like the ones where they employ New York City’s dwindling phone booths as “time machines” – where they can talk to their future and past selves – seem more endearing than corny. Evans recognizes that the strength of this film is in the performances, and he doesn’t try to make Manhattan into <em>Manhattan</em>. There are no adoring montages of the city, no unnecessarily complicated shots. This story is about two people, and could have been set anywhere. Like, say Ottawa, in November 1997.</p>

<p>We stayed in contact after you returned home to Toronto. We got back to our regular lives. But after a while it seemed forced, didn’t it? Plans to meet up fell apart—you were busy with school, and I decided to try again with an ex. I think we both knew that wanting to recapture the magic of that one sublime night was futile, and would risk sullying its memory. <em>Before We Go</em> manages to harness that magic and trap it in a bottle at the perfect moment. </p>

<p>I admit, it was difficult for me to approach this film with a critical eye. As much as I’m proud of being able to keep my emotions in check (even, sadly, when it’s to my detriment). Sometimes I can’t help but let reason take the back seat. Nostalgia played a big part of my engagement with <em>Before We Go</em>, but I wasn’t blinded by it. From time to time, letting go of my acerbic tendencies and indulging in my sappy, romantic side pays off. </p>

<p>Thank goodness or I’d still be stuck in that trap door. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/20/pan.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Pan" />
    <published>2015-10-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/20/pan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In all fairness, you can’t defend a choice that was made for you posthumously. Nevertheless,  your involvement with <em>Pan</em>—however tangentially, and seemingly in opposition to what you stood for as an artist—is a metaphor for everything wrong with this ill-conceived mess of a movie.</p>

<p>And that’s a lot.</p>

<p>I had my first misgivings about this wannabe origin story for <em>Peter Pan</em> when, walking into the screening, I noticed the poster proudly proclaiming “<em>From the studio that brought you Harry Potter</em>”. That’s right; Not the director. Not the writer. Not the producer. Hell, not even the generic we’re-out-of-all-the-other-options catch-all, “creators”. When the main driving force behind a film’s creation is the entity responsible for financing, packaging and distributing, and then repackaging and redistributing the product ad nauseam, you know exactly what they’re going to go for: a sure bet.</p>

<p>And in Hollywood, the only sure bet is to copy what has come before. Play things as safe as possible in a desperate attempt to use nostalgia as a business plan. Everything you railed against, Kurt.</p>

<p>What we get is supposedly the untold origin of Peter Pan, because, as the opening voiceover informs us, “Sometimes, to truly understand the end, you must know the beginning.” Right.</p>

<p>I read that as; “Sometimes to create a franchise, we need to make a convoluted mythology that rips off previous, better works in a lazy attempt to reap profit.” Sure, many great works of art have been assembled from the structures and details of what came before. You even said as much about your seminal <em>Smells Like Teen Spirit</em>, claiming it was your attempt to write a Pixies song. You mimicked their style and structure to make your own song. </p>

<p>That worked. This doesn’t.</p>

<p>Let’s break down the aforementioned Harry Potter kinship, shall we? The abandoned child, his horrible upbringing (one could claim this has a Dickens influence to it, but who are we kidding here?), his mysterious “destiny” that will be revealed to us – but not too fast, as there are future films to be made.</p>

<p>In <em>Pan</em>’s one fun bit, the orphanage has secretly been selling boys to the pirates who arrive via flying sailing ships and bungee jump through the roof and steal children right from their beds. It’s an exciting image that also taps into that basic childhood nightmare logic, and is something <em>Pan</em> desperately could have used more of.</p>

<p>The inventiveness mainly stops there, and unfortunately, another main influence for <em>Pan</em> is <em>Star Wars</em>. No, not the good ones. The Prequels. Having died in 1994, you mercifully did not have to watch George Lucas do his best to undo everything audiences loved about his franchise. Yes, <em>Pan</em> introduces all the future major players with the subtlety George Lucas used when Obi-wan Kenobi told Anakin Skywalker, “Someday, you’ll be the death of me.” Even though Hugh Jackman’s Blackbeard is <em>Pan</em>’s central villain, there’s room to force in Captain Hook as a pal Peter makes working in Blackbeard’s mines, searching for <del>unobtainium</del> pixie dust. This version of Hook is a wise-cracking rascal with a heart of gold in the mold of Han Solo wearing an Indiana Jones hat. Apparently, writer Jason Fuches thought Harrison Ford’s IMDB page was enough research to create this character. I suppose that idea’s not bad on paper, but since Garret Hedlund plays Hook with all the charisma of a Jai Courtney, we’ll never know if it could work off the page.</p>

<p>How, you might wonder, did you get mixed up in all of this? For some reason, someone, at some point, thought it would be a great idea to incorporate modern alternative and punk songs as anthems chanted by Blackbeard’s slave army. It’s used as diegetic music <em>within</em> scenes. Whenever Blackbeard makes an entrance, soot-covered children and motley pirates shout in unison “Here we are now, entertain us!”. They also shout out “Hey, ho, let’s go!’, because, yes, The Ramones’ also got sucked into this. How? Good question. My best guess is that while hurriedly gathering the books and DVDs to pilfer for story ideas, your CDs accidentally got mixed in, and whoever received everything just went with it, whether it made sense or not. That theory would at least explain why this conceit is used exactly twice in the movie then abandoned.</p>

<p>Maybe director Joe Wright is to blame. While this is a pretty impersonal piece of filmmaking, the addition of these songs—as badly conceived and executed as their inclusion is—seems born from the kind of out-of-left-field approach that would never make it through a committee-driven process. And apart from you and Joey Ramone, I worry that Wright is the other casualty of <em>Pan.</em> Coming in at just under two hours, things move so fast and make so little sense, it feels like a good hour of story was left on the cutting room floor. Maybe Wright’s vision was bigger and bolder and had more nuance. Maybe he wanted Amanda Seyfried to do more than drop Peter off at the orphanage, or have Cara Delvingne to do more than literally pop her head out of a pool and smile, before swimming away. I could try to list every slapped together element in <em>Pan</em> but the plot is such a mess hurtling towards something, <em>anything</em>, that much of it left my mind as I left the theatre.  </p>

<p>What remains is the little good and much of the bad. Performance-wise, Jackman actually brings a surprising amount of depth to Blackbeard, considering none of it seems to have been into the script. As Tiger Lily, here reimagined as a kind of tribal Princess Leia/Arwen/, the biggest impression Rooney Mara makes is in how out of place she looks in an aboriginal tribe. (Note to the casting department: the “Lily” in Tiger Lily’s name does <em>not</em> stand for “lily white”.)</p>

<p>So that’s what your music is being used for in the absence of your control. While I’m sorry I don’t have better news to report, I though you needed to know. And, if there is any sort of bright side, it might be this: as appropriate as it may have been to comment on how <em>Pan</em> has its way with J. M. Barrie’s original source material, at least no one decided to use “Rape Me”.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Goosebumps</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/19/goosebumps%20copy.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Goosebumps" />
    <published>2015-10-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/19/goosebumps copy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I must confess, you never scared me all that much. By the time I discovered R.L. Stine’s work, I was a little too old for <em>Goosebumps</em> (I was all about <em>Fear Street</em> with its dead cheerleaders and terrorized prom queens ). But I understand that you’re one of Stine’s most memorable monsters, so it’s fitting that you were brought back for a night of mayhem in Rob Letterman’s movie adaptation of the <em>Goosebumps</em> books. </p>

<p>I’ve become pretty wary of these increasingly common pop culture revivals, which is a polite way of saying that every time I hear another thing I loved as a youngster is about to be remade (and likely ruined), I die a little inside (see: <em>Jem</em> <em>&amp; the Holograms</em>). I have to say, though, I was pleasantly surprised by <em>Goosebumps</em>. I enjoyed it way more than I thought I would. </p>

<p>In keeping with Stine-ian prose, “cold is the night” when new kid in town, Zach, must team up with new friends Champ, Hannah, and her dad – acclaimed author and reclusive weirdo, R.L. Stine – to save the town of Madison, Delaware, from an army of monsters and freaks led by you. After being cooped up in musty pages of books for so long, you understandably have some energy to burn, and you do some pretty serious damage. It was fun to put myself in your tiny shoes and think about where I would go if I was suddenly unleashed into the world like that. Truth be told, I’d probably break into a bakery or a knitting store and go nuts—not my proudest realization, but an honest one.  But you choose to besiege a high school dance instead, and that’s fine. You do you. </p>

<p>The plot is simple enough to keep younger audience members engaged, and it’s quite entertaining watching Stine and the kids race to get all you monsters back into your books. The effects team makes you and the other terrors look good, but my quibble is that there are just too many of you. I get that having every single <em>Goosebumps</em> monster come alive is a cool premise, but we don’t get to fully appreciate most of your friends. Other than you, we really only get significant time with the Werewolf of Fever Swamp and a band of alarmingly agressive lawn gnomes. Relegating the rest of the roster of rampaging rogues to blink-and-miss-it cameos will likely disappoint old school fans of the books and give neophytes no frame of reference as to why they’re supposed to be excited to see the evil clown or giant praying mantis. </p>

<p>While Zach and Hannah are obviously the main couple in the film, I thought the Stine/Champ pairing emerged as the real team to root for. Their angry-grown-up/goofy-teen schtick is charming and greatly entertaining. If our childhood pop culture favourites must be resurrected, I can definitely see the two them in their own spin-off, should you decide to come back for some more fun. Just don’t mess with my beloved <em>Fear Street</em> books, that’s all I ask.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hyena Road</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/14/hyena-road.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HyenaRoad" />
    <published>2015-10-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/14/hyena-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There it is Paul—that’s the problem right there. Your fingerprints are all over every single aspect of <em>Hyena Road</em>. Maybe if it were a smaller, less ambitious work—say a TV series about a struggling, small-town playhouse in Midwestern Canada—your omnipresence would have made sense. But this is a big sprawling, multi-faceted story with multiple locations and complex set pieces that never reaches the heights it seeks, which strongly suggests you had one too many balls in the air. The result is a competent movie that never manages to rise above that particularly Canadian metric of “not bad”.</p>

<p>This is a story of the convoluted circle-jerk that inevitably results from western military interventions—specifically, in this case, Afghanistan and Canada’s role there. It is a role that is so ill defined that a simple task like getting the titular Hyena Road completed (a highway that is meant to create a transport link in a highly contested region) becomes a surreal exercise in realpolitik. There are so many splintered factions that simply identifying allies and enemies is like playing darts blindfolded: it’s all a vague hope guided by a desire not to put your friend’s eye out.</p>

<p>There is the requisite interaction between soldiers and civilians, each suspicious of (and misunderstood by) the other. There is also a failed attempt to delineate exactly why these relationships really never evolve, something that seems a promising thread, but is abandoned in the increasingly diffuse second and third act. <em>Hyena Road</em> is a weak echo of films like <em>Zero Dark Thirty</em> or even <em>Black Hawk Down,</em> and is too reliant upon nondescript action sequences that lack the kind of visual creativity that those other films possess—so that <em>Hyena Road</em> ends up, in these big moments, feeling like a B-grade straight to streaming flick.</p>

<p>The performances are capable—with the exception of you and your  enigmatic Afghani counterpart Neamat Arghandabi. You both push too hard in scenes that require a nuance this film often lacks.  Rossif Sutherland (son of the good Donald) makes a strong impression as a Canadian Special Forces member—but he and the rest of the cast are really just fodder for a movie that is singularly on point in its message and yet somehow flabby and remarkably un-agile.</p>

<p>I admire your ambition, Paul, but it has apparently gone unchecked. It is a rare creative force that manages to wear so many hats and pull it off. Maybe it would have been hard to get this film made had you not agreed to take on so much, but ask yourself this: what good is it to create something that is the mere ghost of what it might have been? It seems to me far better to scale down the project to something manageable or conversely to maintain the scale but delegate some of the work to others. The only time it makes sense a person to have so many slashes in your titles is when they produce something really exemplary. See: Kenneth Branagh, Christopher Guest, and Charlie Chaplin.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Martian</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/6/the-martian.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheMartian" />
    <published>2015-10-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/6/the-martian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’ve ruined duct tape for me, but in the best possible way.</p>

<p>Let’s back up. </p>

<p>When you read the screenplay for the <em>The Martian</em>, did your skin prickle with goose bumps? It’s a movie that, through a series of noisy calamities, builds to near-unbearable levels of stress. A movie replete with hissing airlocks, whirring gizmos, and the beeps and boops of computers operating on a planet prone to loud and ferocious weather. A sound designer’s dream, I imagine. </p>

<p>A dream that you realize with mighty talent.</p>

<p>From the moment astronaut Mark Watney is violently separated from his NASA crewmates during a storm on Mars, you announce yourself. You’re there when the crew, believing Watney dead, blasts away from Mars in a terrifying roar of rockets. You’re there when we return to Watney, wounded, half-buried, suddenly regaining consciousness amid the cacophony of his spacesuit’s many alarms. When he climbs to his feet and staggers towards the crew’s abandoned habitat (or “Hab”), you’re there again in the crush of his boots on the sand, the creak of his stiff spacesuit as he undresses, the squelch of blood and muscle as he fishes a hunk of space-shrapnel from his own guts with a pair of surgical forceps. </p>

<p>Though extraordinarily visceral, these moments of high-octane catastrophe do not represent your most affecting work in the film. Instead, it’s the way you score Watney’s lonely, day-to-day experience—the steady drumbeat of everyday noises in and around the Hab—that gives the film its emotional momentum. </p>

<p>That momentum builds from moment Watney delivers the first of many frank “lay of the land” talks under the guise of a daily video log. Pale, hoarse, barely holding his terror at bay with a steady offensive of sarcasm, Watney breaks down the numbers: thirty days until the Hab reaches its expiration date, three hundred days until he starves to death, and, most significantly, at least four years until a rescue mission can reach him (<em>if</em> he manages to contact earth). It’s a movie based on ruthless math. And it’s a movie in which adrenalin-pumping disaster sequences are separated by plenty of interstitial time—time that Watney must fill with a plebeian cycle of solving problems, coping with boredom (via an obscene amount of disco music), and laboring through daily chores.  </p>

<p>That’s when you do your best work, Oliver. Not in the emergencies, but in the routines. I empathize with Watney most deeply when he lifts a shovelful of dry soil, hauls a wagon with a squeaking wheel, taps a sign into the ground, runs his fingers across a wall dewed with condensation. When he eats, I hear every gluey mastication, am witness to every gulp. When he writes, I hear the scratch of his marker on paper. When he sleeps, I hear his breaths as though he is laying next to me (be still, my heart!). </p>

<p>All of these sounds are part of my boring old life down on boring old earth, and that’s exactly what makes them so poignant. You manage to infuse these ordinary sounds with a sense of unease, of anxious claustrophobia. Watney’s chewing signals the rapid depletion of his food source. When he writes, it is to record the bleak facts of his situation (more ruthless math). Even the chemical makeup of air moving in and out of his lungs intensifies his peril in the Hab’s fragile atmosphere. By hijacking these banalities and using them as signposts in Watney’s terrifying ordeal, you’ve hijacked <em>me</em> as well. You’ve made me more than a passive observer. Not quite a participant in his struggle, but close. Uncomfortably, unforgettably close.</p>

<p>So, the duct tape. </p>

<p>Each time Watney tears a length of it from a roll, that sharp ripping noise, augmented by the hyper-realistic audio immersion of a movie theatre, triggers within me a series of flashbulb memories, like a song I haven’t heard in years. Wrapping a Christmas package, repairing a punctured tent, labeling a Rubbermaid bin: I’ll never do these things again without recalling, in some distracted part of my mind, the contours of Watney’s nightmarish struggle. </p>

<p>You’ve ruined duct tape for me, but in the best possible way. You’ve made it so much more than a benign object—like eating and writing and breathing, your soundscape has raised this element of ordinary life to extraordinary importance.  </p>

<p>That gives me goose bumps, too.</p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong></p>

<p>Megan </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>