<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-09T22:55:45Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fifty Shades Darker</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/9/fifty-shades-darker.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=FiftyShadesDarker" />
    <published>2017-02-09T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-09T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/9/fifty-shades-darker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You are the last person listed in the crew credits on IMDb. I’ve been there: film production offices where I was expected to “look up to” people who ran the spectrum from mildly douchey to outright sadistic. People in positions of power who got off on lording over us lowly, proletariat scum. I’m addressing this to you because you likely had the least influence on this film. With that distance, maybe you feel the same way about it that I do. Or maybe not. Honestly, I feel like I don’t know anything anymore.</p>

<p>Have you ever walked out of a theater after seeing a film so amazing that it changes you? You proselytize about it endlessly to anyone who will listen, and think, if everyone saw this film, the world would be a different place. I have, many times. That’s why I do this. I want people to understand why I love the films I love, or explain why I think other films don’t work. </p>

<p><em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> changed me. I walked out of theater questioning everything I know, and not just about movies, but about life itself. I sat in my car afterwards and stared at people walking down the street, oblivious to the internal carnage this film had wrought. <em>They’re the lucky ones</em>, I thought, <em>they can still be saved.</em> </p>

<p>Please don’t take this as mere film snobbery on my part. I love many bad films. But this film wasn’t bad. It was awful. It was so irredeemably and intolerably awful that it didn’t make me angry the way bad films usually do. It made me sad. Bereft, even. Often I watch bad films and wonder, “who is this for?” With <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> the answer was clear from the hundreds of women (and six guys), some of whom I saw literally <em>running</em> to get in the theater before the screening began. Following the screening I thought of these people and asked myself, “who am I?” I wondered if there was something wrong with <em>m</em>e that made me hate this film so much while others seemed to love it. What discernible character flaw sets me apart from so many women that can’t get enough of this type of shit? </p>

<p>I really don’t want to take a dig at the people that do love this tripe. We love what we love, and we shouldn’t feel guilty about it or apologize for it. That said, the sheer, palpable force of women around me tittering and swooning as every horrible relationship red flag, and every tired gender stereotype weren’t just reinforced but glorified actually pained me. I get it: it’s fantasy, it’s wish fulfillment. It’s a doe-eyed young woman surrounded by pretty, expensive things who has sex with a hot guy. But that’s what <em>Vogue</em> magazine and porn are for.</p>

<p>Please know, dearest Maggie, that I tried. Having not seen the first film in this series, I knew, thanks to <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/13/fifty-shades-of-grey.html">Christopher Redmond’s review</a>, that this second installment would likely not be very good. But in the interest of professionalism I tried to force myself to be objective. Some familiar names popped up during the opening titles that gave me hope – Marcia Gay Harden, Kim Basinger, Danny Elfman – that maybe this wouldn’t be a complete wash. It didn’t matter. Nothing matters anymore. </p>

<p>Before you mistake me for some kind of prude, I’ll tell you, I grew up on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bleu_Nuit"><em>Bleu Nuit</em></a> and scrambled cable porn, both of which are infinitely sexier than <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em>. I stupidly thought that maybe Kim Basinger’s addition to this film might lend it an air of gravitas. She starred in what is arguably the granddaddy of naughty, soft-core studio films from the 80s, <em>9 _1/2</em> weeks. She and pre-motorcycle accident Mickey Rourke had genuine chemistry, their sex scenes were hawt as hell, and were gorgeously shot. The film was no <em>Citizen Kane</em>, but it was a gritty, titillating exploration of a woman’s sexual awakening. </p>

<p><em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> is positively artless. The sex scenes are robotic, abrupt, and laughably vanilla for a film purporting to glorify the BDSM lifestyle. The accompanying soundtrack is grating, and the cinematography is offensively banal. <em>Lifetime</em>movies aren’t this shamelessly boring. At least they don’t take themselves seriously, and they know exactly what they are. Unlike this drivel that can’t decide if it’s a thriller, a romance, or a third-rate Madonna video. </p>

<p>For every time Dakota Johnson’s Anastasia bit her lip, I bit my tongue twice as hard. I have been thrown out of a theater exactly once before for yelling (1996, <em>The English Patient</em> “just leave her in the goddamned cave!”). I came very close here. This film is just like Christian Grey, its lead male character – a manipulative piece of shit. Every time Christian exhibits borderline abusive behaviour – buying the company Anastasia works for, knowing all of her banking info, demanding she not go on a business trip – Anastasia has a fleeting moment of “hey wait, this is wrong”, which is quickly replaced with a reminder of how rich and hot Christian is, just in case anyone in the audience starts thinking maybe Anastasia should walk the fuck away. If I gave a sketchy ex another chance, and three days in he suggested shoving Ben Wa balls up my hoo-ha to wear to his parent’s fancy party I’d be out the door, but not before shoving them up his ass. Oh, but Christian is <em>damaged</em>, you see, and he’s trying to <em>change</em>. Instead of yelling out “BOOOO!” until I was hoarse, I sat motionless in my seat and screamed silently.</p>

<p>I’m still screaming.</p>

<p>I’d attempt to describe the plot but I’m afraid I’d fall asleep at the keyboard. This film is about one thing: money. It’s a cynical box-office cash-grab timed to coincide with a manufactured holiday. But you’re so low on the totem pole it’s not like you’re expecting any points on the back end or anything. You can walk away from this and go on with your career and eventually, when you rack up a ton of credits, you can drop this one from your resume. </p>

<p>If I could give this film less than zero stars I would. I’m actually tempted to go back and give extra stars to other films I thought were horrible because before <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> I didn’t know what I didn’t know. It has set the bar so low that my faith in myself as a critic has been shaken to the core. </p>

<p>So why waste so much time tearing it to shreds, you might ask? Believe me, my first instinct was to just type the word “FUUUUUCK” a thousand times and submit that as my review. Then I realized that the only hollow joy I might derive from this turd rodeo would be to warn other people away from it. I don’t like to call myself a hero, but if I can save just one person from <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em>, then I’m a goddamned hero.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lion</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/3/lion.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Lion" />
    <published>2017-02-03T07:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-03T07:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/3/lion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The last thing I was thinking about when the credits rolled on <em>Lion</em> was the visual effects. The first was getting out of the theatre before someone saw my two-hour long transformation into a puddle of tears. As I tried to compose myself, hood over my head like a petulant child, I watched the documentary footage post-script during the credits. That sure as hell didn’t help stop the waterworks, but it did keep me in my seat long enough to notice the army of (over 50) visual effects team members under your supervision. It made me think.</p>

<p>Even if only <em>half</em> your team was dedicated to Nicole Kidman’s age denying effects (justified early in the film, but a vain movie star demand after the narrative’s 20 year jump), that still left a whole lot of movie to work on. Surprising since each frame of this film feels natural and grounded. Director Garth Davis, in his feature film debut, opts for balance over flare at every turn in his storytelling. This may be in service of the story, or as a way to counteract the many inevitable and inescapable comparisons with <em>Slumdog Millionaire</em>. Regardless, it’s the right choice, and whatever digital trickery was involved in manipulating the images, it was as seamless as Kidman’s oxygen repelling pores. </p>

<p>That’s enough picking on poor old Nicole. By lending her name and talents to the film (and any reservations about sporting God-awful 80s hair), she no doubt helped sell this story about Australian parents who adopt a homeless Indian child. She and David Wenham, however, rightly play second fiddle to a pair of performances portraying Saroo Brierly – one by seven-year-old Sunny Pawar, and the other by <em>Slumdog</em> alum Dev Patel. After the heart-wrenching first act of the film where Saroo loses his family, the story falls into Patel’s hands, who gamely pulls off the transformation into an Australian surfer bro and Handsome Leading Man. I assume his new muscles or long locks didn’t come from your team, but who knows. They sure looked real, and provided a temporarily (welcomed) distraction from the emotionally loaded narrative in this film.</p>

<p>But as embarrassing as it felt in the moment, I don’t resent <em>Lion</em>’s ability to manipulate my emotions. Every turn felt earned, and the performances never crossed into melodrama. When the story finally resolves in both satisfying and heart-breaking ways, the visual choices made to convey a sense of closure felt simple and inspired. The only places your work may have been prominent were during the Google Map searches that that inspire Saroo’s journey. But even there, technology is always simply an enabler for human connection and never foregrounded for effect. Just the way it’s supposed to be, as I’m sure you’d agree.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>20th Century Women</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/2/20th-century-women.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=20thCenturyWomen" />
    <published>2017-02-02T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-02T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/2/20th-century-women</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I don’t often write my letters to the cast part of Dear Cast &amp; Crew. I find it far more interesting to celebrate (or sometimes excoriate) people behind the camera since these fine folks rarely get their due. But you are different, dear Annette. Or maybe not. Too often you are overlooked when awards season comes around. Sure, you’ve been nominated plenty, and I thought this year you would be a shoe-in for an Oscar nod for this role in <em>20th Century Women</em>. But I think I’ve found the reason the Golden Boy remains out of your reach; you make it look easy. Like most parents of teenagers, I’m afraid we take you for granted. You’re just too damn good. </p>

<p>You are like an experienced sound engineer or lighting tech; you have become a master at your craft. Films rely on people of your calibre to run smoothly. Your work is seamless, appearing effortless. You inject your characters with a singularity so organic that once you’ve taken on a role it’s impossible to imagine anyone else owning it. If it seems like I’m gushing, please forgive me. In <em>20th Century Women</em> you play the head-strong Dorothea, a mom at a loss to understand her teenage son in 1979 Santa Barbara. You were a stand-in for writer/director Mike Mills’ mother, but within the first few minutes of watching you on screen, I felt a creeping sense of familiarity. You were standing in for my mother too.  </p>

<p>Like Dorothea, my mother had me late in life. And like Dorothea, my mother didn’t remarry after my father died. Mum raised me by herself, but she was not alone. She collected people, and our house was never empty. Like Dorothea did for her 15-year-old son Jamie, Mum allowed me a great deal of independence, probably more than I deserved. Some moments in the film seemed ripped from my own life, and you gave me the gift of reliving them through my mother’s perspective. </p>

<p>The film opens on Dorothea’s car on fire in a grocery store parking lot on her birthday. Our family car caught on fire at Loblaws on my 10th birthday, and now I understand how Mum was able to shake it off. Dorothea doesn’t understand her son’s music, but makes the effort to try. My Mum raced out to a house party I was at when I called to check in and told her the noise in the background was The Cult. She was mortally embarrassed when she realized it was a band, and not an actual cult. </p>

<p>The commonality of the struggles of raising a teenager alone have never been illustrated so artfully. <em>20th Century Women</em> gave me a deeper understanding of not just what my mother went through, but what my other single mom friends endure. When Jamie yells at Dorothea, “Mom, I’m dealing with everything right now, you are dealing with nothing!” I actually gasped from shame at having said something so similar to my Mum. Jamie apologizes for Dorothea’s eccentricities much the way I did with my Mum; Jamie, “she’s from the Great Depression” (me: “she grew up during the War”). What Mills does beautifully is provide context for each of his characters by recognizing the importance of their time and place in the world; where they are from, who they are in 1979, and who they will become.</p>

<p>Mills’ background is in advertising and music video direction, and it shows here in the best possible way. Mills incorporates multi-character narration, historical footage, and period-relevant books, music and politics to tell the story of an unconventional family that manages to be both unique and relatable.</p>

<p>Affectations that I dismissed as twee in Mills’ previous autobiographical turn, <em>Beginners</em>, are more mature in <em>20th</em> <em>Century Women</em> and far less mannered. But like <em>Beginners</em>, the cast he assembled here is exemplary. Greta Gerwig as the wounded punk Abbie, Elle Fanning as the wise-beyond-her-years Julie, and newcomer Lucas Jade Zumann as Jamie, have a natural chemistry that makes us root for this unorthodox family. But it’s your scenes with Billy Crudup’s William, Dorothea’s handyman boarder, that I wished would never end. Seeing two amazing actors play people so funny and flawed yet self-aware is a rare treat. When people lament the loss of mid-budget films celebrating real people, they should hold this film up as a champion of the type of story that is both small and universal, where nothing and <em>everything</em> happens.</p>

<p>For a long time I bemoaned the fact that my favourite actor, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/the-giver.html">Jeff Bridges</a>, was infuriatingly underrated. Then he won an Oscar for <em>Crazy Heart</em> in 2010 and now I have to share him with everyone who finally recognizes his brilliance. Like a jealous child, part of me wants to keep you all to myself. But like a proud daughter, I want the rest of the world to reward the incredible work you do making complex characters knowable. I have no doubt your time will come.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>xXx: The Return of Xander Cage</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/1/xxx-the-return-of-xander-cage.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=xXx:TheReturnofXanderCage" />
    <published>2017-02-01T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-01T06:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/1/xxx-the-return-of-xander-cage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As a welder, you’re probably used to people thinking you’re a man’s man. You literally work with your hands to forge steel and bend metal as fire rains down around you. Given the definition of what a man is has changed drastically in the past decade, this stereotype may offend or flatter you. All I know is, the stereotype which has associated itself with your profession was the perfect inspiration behind <em>xXx: The Return of Xander Cage</em> AKA the pinnacle of male-centric entertainment.</p>

<p><em>xXx: The Return of Xander Cage</em>, as the title states, is the return of Xander Cage, former extreme athlete-turned super spy. After faking his own death to live a quiet life, Xander is pulled back into the game after a team of super-criminals steal a piece of tech that can take down every satellite in orbit.</p>

<p>It’s an absurd premise full of babes, bombs, and biceps. Which is why I purposely asked the bossman at <em>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</em> to assign me this movie. I’ve been watching too many Oscar-nominated films during the past couple of weeks and I needed a fantastic mess to cleanse the palate. And a fantastic mess is what I got. </p>

<p>After Xander gets intel from his super sexy informant, he is obliged to pleasure all the women in the room -- at the same time. Cut to morning, Xander stands tall and proud as he stares at the sleeping harem of ladies, undoubtedly exhausted due to a night of unbridled sexxing. A grin appears across Xander’s face as utters the line, “The things I do for my country.”</p>

<p>This scene is only one of the many ridiculous aspects of <em>xXx</em>. Others being: Xander skiing down the hills of a South American jungle, Xander participating in a deep ocean dirt bike chase, and the introduction of Kris Wu’s character, Nicks, a successful DJ whose only job is to drop dirty dubstep beats during high-octane sequences. </p>

<p>It’s all a bit much but luckily, <em>xXx</em>  doesn’t try to make excuses for the type of movie it is. It knows it’s a loud and boisterous film that requires zero brain cells to view. It’s fully aware of its macho reputation and doesn’t try to mask it with unnecessary dramatic elements. </p>

<p><em>xXx: The Return of Xander Cage</em> is filled to the brim with testosterone. It’s an extreme anthem with no discernible reason to exist other than to excite the Neanderthal in all of us. It pokes fun at its own genre and let’s viewers turn off their brains and revel in some pure, unadulterated fun. </p>

<p>I’ll admit that <em>xXx: The Return of Xander Cage</em> is not as refined as other meta-hits like <em>Deadpool or Kingsman: The Secret Service</em>. There’s a ton of dead weight with the large cast. I can count at least four characters who could’ve been edited out entirely without diminishing the final product.</p>

<p>Regardless, <em>xXx</em> is a genuinely entertaining movie and a welcome distraction. With women&#39;s marches and male insecurities occupying the most powerful position in government, there’s no better movie than <em>xXx: The Return of Xander Cage</em> to showcase the laughable nature of male bravado.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Gold</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/31/gold.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Gold" />
    <published>2017-01-31T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-31T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/31/gold</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>For more than twelve years you were the guy that Harvey Weinstein depended upon to find films like <em>Snowpiercer</em>, <em>The Imitation Game</em>, <em>Grandmaster</em>, and <em>Carol</em>. Sometimes you would discover these films fully formed at festivals, others you would be responsible for shepherding them through from script to release. However as TWC is apparently choosing to focus more on television productions this year, they only released <em>Lion</em>, <em>The Founder</em> and <em>Gold</em> for awards season.</p>

<p>Sadly, this is probably responsible for the former in your title. TWC has fallen on hard times because of some recent flops and has had to downsize and change their focus. But what a run it was for those twelve years. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_The_Weinstein_Company_films">filmography</a> you were at least partially responsible for building is filled with with some truly interesting films, ranging from the ridiculous to the sublime.</p>

<p><em>Gold</em> is a bit closer to the sublime than the ridiculous. Matthew McConaughey portrays modern prospector Kenny Wells, who gambles everything on a partnership with geologist Michael Acosta, and the potential of a gold strike in the Indonesian jungle. When Wells and Acosta apparently beat the odds, the rest of film explores exactly how dangerous getting what you wish for can be.</p>

<p>These sorts of films have become synonymous with TWC over the last few years, and while you have taken some grief for their apparent similarities, most of that snark is devoid of any real substance. At worst, TWC’s output always seem to meet a standard of competence and quality that most films would be happy to reach.</p>

<p><em>Gold</em> is a throwback—a star vehicle meant to showcase performance and story. Though it feels slightly out of time in its stripped down, workmanlike approach, this spareness is not a negative. In fact it is one of the strengths of <em>Gold</em> that the technical aspects of the film-making are invisible. As I mentioned in my review for<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/24/the-founder.html"><em>The Founder</em></a>, this is something I’ve come to appreciate in this auteur saturated era.</p>

<p>That this movie is as good as it is has a lot to do with the two central performances. Both Edgar Ramirez (as Acosta, he gives his usual effortless performance), and McConaughey are charismatic, interesting actors. They made it easy to become invested in their story so that we care about what happens to them. That may seem pretty basic, but more films than not fail to even achieve that minimum requirement. The supporting cast was equally effective—particularly Bryce Dallas Howard, who manages to do a fair bit with a role that easily could have read as wallpaper.</p>

<p>There are some parallels to be drawn between a prospector like Kenny and the work that you have done for TWC. Both of you have to wade through mountains of slag and try to find little nuggets of the right hue and sheen. Both are high stakes occupations that are infused with greed and fraud, both major and minor. And both must be ulcer inducing given how rarely your efforts bear the right sort of fruit. And perhaps after twelve years it might be the right time for a change of pace.</p>

<p>I like to think of you sitting in a stylish cottage in The Adirondacks somewhere, running an etsy store that sells vintage posters, sipping an afternoon cocktail. That would be an ending to a film you would probably pass on, but it’s one I wouldn’t mind watching.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>O.J.: Made in America is the Best (and Longest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/27/oj-made-in-america-is-the-best-and-longest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=O.J.:MadeinAmericaistheBest(andLongest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-27T04:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-27T04:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/27/oj-made-in-america-is-the-best-and-longest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There have been a few distinct “where were you when” moments in my 43 years; the attacks on the World Trade Center towers, the fall of the Berlin Wall, O.J. Simpson’s Bronco chase. Some might argue that only the first two were truly life-altering, globally significant events. Until recently, I would have agreed. It wasn’t until I watched _O.J.: Made in America that I reconsidered the impact the O.J. Simpson trial had on our culture, our media, and our relationship with race, fame and entitlement. It seems especially profound since I write this mere days after the most powerful country in the world inaugurated a bigoted, misogynistic, reality television star for President.</p>

<p>When I first heard about Ezra Edelman’s opus I thought it was a joke. An almost eight-hour documentary on O.J. Simpson? Who the hell would want to watch that? Didn’t we already know everything we needed to know? What, if any, new information could we possibly glean from revisiting that sordid chapter in our collective consciousness? Turns out, a lot. So much that while watching it, I had to stop myself from opening my window<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Awv8dySZaHE">Howard Beale</a>-style to yell, “Stop whatever you’re doing and watch this documentary! I’m woke as hell and I’m not gonna take it anymore!”</p>

<p>By some miracle, Edelman was able to take what was arguably the most scrutinized event of the 1990s and create what will henceforth be known as the definitive statement on O.J. Simpson. </p>

<p>But it’s so much more than that. </p>

<p>It’s a treatise on America itself. The country’s love affair with fame, and propensity towards deifying men who can throw further and run faster than average mortals, and its unease with accepting that these false idols are sometimes fatally flawed. Its oversimplification of the racial divide, and the magnitude of dissonance of the realities faced by its black and white citizens. Its pride in the equality of its justice system, and its inability to accept that this system is deeply, possibly irrevocably broken. Its addiction to entertainment and morbid fascination with the lives of celebrities, whom they systematically build up and tear down for sport. </p>

<p>The story of O.J. Simpson could have been told in any number of ways (indeed, 2016 saw another take on this subject in the form of the FX dramatization, <em>The People vs O.J. Simpson</em>, which focused solely on the trial and its larger-than-life participants). The artistry of <em>O.J.: Made in America</em> comes from Edelman’s ability to take a story we’ve heard before and not just make it new, but make it engrossing in its urgency. It challenges our perceived notions, it asks us to reject an entrenched mindset, and yet it never once seems interested in O.J.’s guilt or innocence. </p>

<p>The foundation of this film rests on the impact of the first episode, the first twenty minutes in fact. Without that solid structure, we would have been left with yet another maudlin tell-all at best, or a hollow retrospective at worst. Without this assured jumping off point, it wouldn’t matter if the doc was 8 or 80 hours long, it just wouldn’t work if Edelman had arranged the pieces in any other way. But he does something that is absolutely imperative to justify this framework. He does something that is nothing short of sorcery, something that seemed impossible; he makes us fall in love with O.J. all over again. That in itself is remarkable enough. But he does it <em>after</em> he reminds us of who O.J. is <em>now</em>. </p>

<p>The film opens on a sweeping shot of the Nevada desert, and pans to show us the Lovelock Correctional Facility. We hear O.J. in voice over, “growing up in the ghetto, one of the things I wanted most, it wasn’t money. It was fame”. The film then cuts to footage of O.J.’s parole hearing in which he describes his job as a cleaner in prison, and coaching the prison football team to win the championship. His familiar cocky smile fades to incredulity then to obvious derision when a member of the parole board asks about his first arrest in 1994, for the murder of his wife and her friend. </p>

<p>The gears switch to footage of a young, college-age O.J., the running-back phenom for USC whose 64 yard run in a game against arch-rivals UCLA made him a national star. The shots of O.J.’s college life - an awkward interview with his new wife Marguerite (who describes him as “serious”), stands packed with white faces cheering his name, the footage of “the run” set to a swelling, triumphant score – are juxtaposed against footage of a very different life experienced by blacks in the mid-60s. Though we’ve seen many of these images before – hoses on crowds in Jim Crow states, a little black girl being escorted to a desegregated school by the National Guard (an image that will return in a later episode), dogs attacking Civil Rights protestors – the context has changed. It’s increasingly apparent that the rise of a hero able to transcend race in this climate, who will eventually fly too close to the sun aloft on the rarified air of his own ego, isn’t just inevitable, it’s damn near Shakespearean.</p>

<p>This is ten minutes in.</p>

<p>The next ten minutes shows us the mid-Sixties LAPD, run by Chief Parker, a no-nonsense enforcer known to recruit police officers at Klan rallies. The aggressive presence of the LAPD in predominantly black neighbourhoods leads to the infamous Watts Riot of 1965. Footage of a community at war with the officers sworn to protect it, shows people running from tear gas and a tank, a man with urine-soaked pants being cuffed, a cop kicking a black man in the back, a young black man carrying a frightened elderly white woman to safety. It is stomach-churning, and reminiscent of footage of Nazis’ treatment of Jews in 1930s Germany. That the USC stadium butts up against Watts (a schoolmate of O.J.’s remembers how the university warned students not to visit the other side), is painfully symbolic, it is a literal racial divide. Closing this first twenty minutes is another white voice admitting, “I didn’t think it was a big deal. I didn’t think these people were quote “persecuted”. I was as naive as any other white person.”</p>

<p>The rest of the doc unfolds on Edelman’s expert framework organically, but by this point, he could have spent the next seven hours focusing on a freckle behind O.J.’s ear and I would have been riveted. <em>O.J.: Made in America</em> is long, and intense, and it requires commitment. As a reward for that commitment, it challenged me to juggle conflicting emotions at the same time, and reckon with them. It forced me to confront my own white, Canadian prejudices about race in America and about America itself. The best art often isn’t easy to swallow. It<em>should</em> make us uncomfortable. It <em>should</em> ask difficult questions. That it did all of this and managed to be immensely absorbing and ultimately satisfying is what makes <em>O.J.: Made in America</em> extraordinary.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Patriots Day</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/25/patriots-day.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=PatriotsDay" />
    <published>2017-01-25T04:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-25T04:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/25/patriots-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Script processor, eh? That’s a new one. Hollywood scripts always have readers, writers, and supervisors, but I’ve never seen someone credited with having to “process” it. Makes sense, I guess – the Boston Marathon bombing took place so recently that it’s hard to fathom that there’s been enough distance to fully understand and re-tell that story. Meaning all that responsibility – that need for clarity and conscience – fell on you, poor Jake. So maybe it’s to your credit that <em>Patriots Day</em> isn’t just another opportunistic cash-grab of a true-life tragedy.</p>

<p>Real-life, after all, has become the hot new I.P. for Hollywood adaptations (comic books are <em>so</em> two years ago). In the past few months alone, we’ve had <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/9/23/snowden.html"><em>Snowden</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/9/9/sully.html"><em>Sully</em></a> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/10/6/deepwater-horizon.html"><em>Deepwater Horizon</em></a> recreating big media events from recent years. The latter may be the most relevant, having also been directed by Peter Berg and starring Mark Wahlberg. Though where <em>Deepwater</em> struggled to justify itself by the end, devolving into little more than flames and fury, <em>Patriots Day</em> benefits from clear protagonists, goals, and developments in the story. More importantly, it spends some cursory down time with a number of the victims and key players, fleshing them out before integrating them into the story. And sure, they’re all conveniently cultivating new romances mere hours before a national catastrophe, but I can live with those kinds of filmmaking contrivances. It helped me <em>process</em> the whole thing.  </p>

<p>There was, however, an element to the film that I don’t think even you could have predicted. Or maybe you could, and you pushed for this reaction. </p>

<p>During an interrogation scene with the wife of one of the bombers, <em>Patriots Day</em> can’t hide its all-American erection over the Patriot Act’s power to deny a terrorism suspects their Miranda rights. The way this tactic is justified had the effect of riling up even my meek Canadian afternoon crowd. I could actually hear people cheering under their breath phrases like “that’s what you get!”. Hell, even I felt satisfaction from the power of the state regaining control over the unlawful renegades. It was one of those jingoistic payoffs that feels good in entertainment (like almost every episode of <em>24</em>), but lacks all the sober realities of real life. Like those thoughtful elements that help us process heavy-handed government policies as opposed to letting fear guide our decision making.</p>

<p>But this is a film – not a law class. The only rule is to make the audience feel something, and hopefully provide a better understanding of the world along the way. And I can say, without hesitation, that <em>Patriots Day</em> had the effect of making those fateful days in Boston mean something more to me. Achieving that requires going beyond the obvious plot points on the page, by tapping into something deeper.  </p>

<p>So, good processing (assuming you weren’t just an IT guy or glorified photocopier).</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Founder</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/24/the-founder.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheFounder" />
    <published>2017-01-24T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-24T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/24/the-founder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’m a middlebrow kind of guy, generally. I’m perfectly happy with consuming media that has no greater ambition than to entertain or tell a good story. That’s not a statement of advocacy, just a fact. And because of that fact, your projects tend to hit my sweet spot. </p>

<p>Whatever greater lessons exist in the subtext of this film—the rise of corporatism and it’s corollary: the decline of mom and pop enterprises in the latter half of the twentieth century—what the <em>The Founder</em> does remarkably well is tell, in a simple but compelling fashion, the story of the rise of McDonalds from a single roadside diner to a multi-billion dollar corporate behemoth.</p>

<p>Ray Kroc (Michael Keaton who continues his phoenix like re-emergence onto the A-list) is a character whose through line is an absorbing, cautionary tale about how innovation and small scale entrepreneurs can fall prey to corporate appropriation. From humble beginnings he became the singular avatar of all that is wrong with late-stage capitalism. Watching him evolve from a slightly shady travelling salesmen to an utterly heartless CEO is both appalling and also completely fascinating—and a lot of that is down to how effortlessly Keaton shepherds that transition. He portrays Kroc as a folksy monster, so that each step in his metamorphosis is tinged with a casual, almost banal, amorality. We get to watch how increasing wealth and power expose the essential weaknesses of his character, while also being given a pretty good primer on how we went from single owner diners and department stores to ubiquitous franchise restaurants and box stores the size of city blocks.</p>

<p>But all of this is background, and none of it is essential to engaging with the film. Just watching Ray navigate his way to the top, over and through anyone foolish enough to get in his way, is what makes <em>The Founder</em> compelling. And Ray leaves a long list of casualties in his wake. </p>

<p>There are almost always a bevy of quality, understated performances in your films, and <em>The Founder</em> is no exception. Laura Dern, John Carroll Lynch, and B.J. Novak all have small, but pivotal, roles. But for me the real revelation was Nick Offerman as one of the two McDonalds brothers. He was quietly brilliant, subtly projecting both competence in his area of expertise, and utter befuddlement with the ethically bereft shenanigans Kroc perpetrates.</p>

<p>Some of what I admire about your filmography is the regularity with which you produce what people often refer to as Oscar bait. What that seems to mean is films with a complex central characters located in interesting historical settings, married to strong scripts and quietly effective direction. The kind of films that put story front and centre, rather than submitting to auteurist tendencies (your ongoing relationship with Tarantino being a profound exception).</p>

<p>As with <em>Gold</em>, <em>The Founder</em> is meat and potatoes film making. The emphasis on the basics of storytelling—a good script, coherent plot, smart casting—is a refreshing shift from a landscape filled with creators that sometimes seem to have lost sight of these fundamentals. This is not a film that seeks to innovate or break new ground, but it’s absolutely a film that succeeds in its ambitions, however straightforward they might be.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Best of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/24/the-best-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheBestof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/24/the-best-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What makes a movie &quot;the best&quot; of the year? All depends who you ask – and who you believe. Decide for yourself as our critics each defend the film they believe deserves the high praise for bucking trends, capturing the id, or simply firing movie magic on all cylinders.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Captain America: Civil War is the Best (and Worthiest) Film of 2016</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/1/23/captain-america-civil-war-is-the-best-and-worthiest-film-of-2016.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CaptainAmerica:CivilWaristheBest(andWorthiest)Filmof2016" />
    <published>2017-01-23T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-23T04:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/1/23/captain-america-civil-war-is-the-best-and-worthiest-film-of-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If all my years of high school English taught me anything, it’s that a good essay should start off with a loud, emphatic statement that will draw a reader in. So, here we go:</p>

<p><em>Captain America: Civil War</em> is without a doubt the best movie of 2016.</p>

<p><em>Civil War</em>? A superhero movie? For best picture? Blasphemy! Shame! Who does this guy think he is? Did he even see <em>Moonlight</em>, <em>Manchester by the Sea</em>, or <em>La La Land</em>? </p>

<p>My answer is simple: it doesn’t matter. I didn’t <em>want</em> to choose <em>Civil War</em> as my top pick. I wanted to pick a film that is universally deemed to be worthy. I know the kind of stigma that comes with suggesting a superhero film can be an expression of cinematic art, let alone the best one in a given year. It might seem juvenile, unrefined, and in keeping with a person who hasn’t experienced, nor isn’t capable of understanding, the depth that critically appreciated films usually possess. But that’s what makes my pick so compelling. Every time I sat down to construct a narrative around one of those other movies, my true feelings about <em>Civil War</em> kept getting in the way. The more I pushed them down, the louder they got. So, rather than fight my feelings, I decided to let them out. I decided to do what a critic does best; defend the shit out of my position. </p>

<p>To understand why I chose <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> as my #1 pick, you have to take a look at the cinematic landscape of 2016 as a whole. Much can be said about the caliber of movies that came out in 2016, but there is no doubt that it was the year that comic book adaptations reigned supreme. </p>

<p>From the Merc with a Mouth to the mind-bending theatrics of Doctor Strange, 2016 slapped on a pair of spandex more often than not –six times to be exact. And even though I adore superhero films, even <em>I</em> got fatigues by the rate at which these blockbuster were released. I began to notice that these types of movies weren’t being made for fans anymore, but, rather, for profit, which meant that timelines were rushed and quantity was chosen over quality. I mean, just look at what happened to Suicide Squad.</p>

<p>So what makes <em>Civil War</em> different? It’s just a blockbuster filled with colourful people in colourful outfits. Besides all the cool superpowers, what was so special about it that it warrants this prestigious designation? At the end of the day, aren’t all superhero movies the same?</p>

<p>The difference is that <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> stays true to itself with the sort of light-hearted action we’ve grown to love from the Marvel Cinematic Universe, but contrasts it with a deep and emotional story that is a culmination of tensions that were put into motion after the first <em>Iron Man</em> all the way back in 2008. </p>

<p>Was Marvel planning a film adaption of the Civil War storyline eight years in advance? Did they purposely develop Captain America and Iron Man for this very moment? I don’t know. All I know is that when they finally faced off, it didn’t feel unexpected.</p>

<p>At its core, <em>Civil War</em> is a story about political divisiveness. After years of funding and manufacturing top-of-the-line weapons, Tony Stark hits a moral low as he finally sees that no matter how hard he tries to vanquish his demons and make a positive difference in the world, he’s innately reckless and needs to be policed. This is in direct opposition to Steve Rogers’ political leanings; Steve has seen firsthand the type of corruption that comes when a government amasses too much influence; he’s seen absolute power corrupt absolutely. Despite sometimes being reckless in the way he conducts himself and his team, Steve knows the intervention of bureaucrats will only result in more subtle forms of recklessness. </p>

<p>The showdown came about seamlessly. It was like the final domino being added in a long line of dominoes, just waiting to be knocked over. And the fall of those dominoes, when it finally came, was mesmerizing.</p>

<p>That chain of events left me gutted. During the climax that reveals Bucky Barnes culpability in the death of Tony Stark’s parents, I was hit with something that I’ve never been exposed to while watching a superhero movie: profound sadness. To the point where I was dreading that these two beloved characters might actually kill one another. I was emotionally invested and completely caught off guard. I can usually predict the outcome of a comic book film, but I wasn’t expecting the dark and dramatic turn of events that occurs at the end of <em>Civil War</em>. Fighting over politics is one thing, but discovering that the man you’ve fought beside against aliens and sentient robots has been hiding a secret of this magnitude is some Jerry Springer shit that is too raw to ignore.</p>

<p>But <em>Civil War</em> isn&#39;t a two-man show. It’s an all-star team-up that brings in even more superheroes than <em>The Avengers</em>. It features supporting characters who have headlined (and will soon headline) their own movies, and, as every critic knows, too many powerful personalities in one movie can break it. But this wasn’t the case with <em>Civil War</em>. The filmmakers were fully aware of the clout that each character possessed, and used them to the best of their abilities. They had confidence in the story they wanted to tell, and didn’t let anyone get in the way of it. The integration of highly-anticipated heroes like Black Panther and Spider-Man was handled with total precision. Everyone had their time to shine, and when it was time to refocus, the supporting cast disappeared into the background. <em>Civil War</em> struck the perfect balance between character and story.</p>

<p>By the time I finished watching <em>Civil War</em> for the first time, I was in a buzz. I didn’t just witness a moving drama, but a hilarious comedy and thrilling action flick, too. I still can’t comprehend how blockbuster spectacle with such a diverse cast could feel so organic, so <em>real</em>. I was beaming with emotion. This isn’t just another addition to Marvel’s Cinematic Universe—it’s a piece of art, a film that transcends its own genre. </p>

<p>And that’s why <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> is without a doubt the best movie of 2016. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>