<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-09T22:19:56Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Table 19</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/8/table-19.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Table19" />
    <published>2017-03-08T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-08T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/8/table-19</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I always say there are only three things you really need at a wedding: good food, good music, and a few nice photos for posterity. Mind you, I don’t actually like weddings all that much, and have used every excuse to avoid having one of my own (sorry, Mum).  I’m hardly an authority on staging the perfect nuptials, but I’ve been to enough shitty weddings to weigh in on Jeffery Blitz’s <em>Table 19</em>, which made me resent being invited to the screening to the point where I sat there inwardly screaming, “Why didn’t I just say no and send a gift?!”</p>

<p>The film is like a 90-minute speech by some asshole drunk relative, replete with poorly-timed, out of place anecdotes, delivered before a room full of awkwardly silent guests who take the opportunity to add doggy ear stickers to selfies, or hack away diligently at leathery chateaubriand. In the same way that every couple tries to buck trends or make their wedding somehow unique (they all fail; bah, humbug, etc.), <em>Table 19</em> tries to subvert the conventions of the wedding comedy but it just isn’t happening. Sure, the wedding comedy is a by-rote series of calamities and resolutions, but the fact that I can set my watch by each of them is what makes them work. The pacing of <em>Table 19</em> is off to begin with, so without the usual markers (derailed ceremony, inappropriate revelation during toast, etc.), and with plot points that frequently pull the characters away from the wedding, I often had no idea where in the story’s progression we actually were. </p>

<p>Your music was the only tolerable part of the film, your awesome pop covers the only thing diverting my attention from the numbing sensation of my butt falling asleep in my seat. Child of the 80s that I am, I don’t consider a wedding a success unless I hear at least one Cyndi Lauper song*, and you nailed it. As any good wedding band or DJ knows, wedding music can’t just be a random playlist or string of requests – there is a certain progression required when curating the perfect program that will keep the guests entertained and on their feet  - repetitive, but somehow never stale. <em>Table 19</em> tries to mess with the wedding comedy formula, and much like playing <em>I’ve had the Time of My Life</em> at the beginning of the reception or cueing up <em>Gin and Juice</em> in the background during the father of the bride’s toast, it makes no goddamn sense. </p>

<p>As much as I may not like going to weddings (which I probably won’t have to worry about after any of my altar-bound friends or family read this), I was sorely disappointed here, because I do enjoy a good wedding comedy. I actually like that they are formulaic as hell, so <em>Table 19</em> ultimately suffers from trying to fix something that ain’t broke.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Logan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/3/logan.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Logan" />
    <published>2017-03-03T02:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T02:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/3/logan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Intellectual property (IP) refers to creations of the mind, such as inventions; literary and artistic works; designs; and symbols, names and images used in commerce.</em></p>

<p>IP has taken the place of actual movie stars. Instead of the subtle charisma of a Paul Newman, we have the cheap frisson of yet another rebooted <em>Spiderman</em>. We’ve replaced the creative innovation and the brilliant range of Gene Hackman (Popeye Doyle to Little Bill Daggett and then, finally, Royal Tenenbaum) with clumsy marriages between comic book IP’s and other genres: The Space Opera (<em>Guardians of The Galaxy</em>), Retrograde Orientalism disguised as New Age enlightenment (<em>Dr. Strange</em>), Old School Westerns (<em>Logan</em>), Greek And Norse Myths (<em>The Avengers</em>). </p>

<p>At the core of all of these unwieldy mashups is something that almost always mitigates against growth and evolution—characters that are carved in stone. They are so freighted down by their own backstories—curated and guarded by fervent gatekeepers that balk at anything even mildly transgressive regarding their hallowed IP’s—that the best anyone can hope for is dressed up reiterations of the same kind of stories. And as long as these gatekeepers hold any kind of sway, all we will get is their specific versions of these iconic characters reflected back at us. That is a recipe for creative stagnation.</p>

<p>Make no mistake though, <em>Logan</em> is a fine example of a thoughtful rebranding. It is a meticulously executed, often thrilling example of an innovative marketing scheme overlaid onto an already existing property. Within those parameters, it is entirely successful.</p>

<p>Unfortunately it is, at its heart, an empty exercise.</p>

<p>So much of what hamstrings <em>Logan</em> is the entirely wrong headed idea that fan service is something that should carry any weight at all in the creative process. Instead of adding richness and depth, these character’s slavishly adhered to histories that box them in. Any time they even begin to break into new territory they are immediately pulled back to the safe and familiar.</p>

<p>In <em>Logan</em>’s case, a veneer of R-rated violence and some foul mouthed dialogue from Professor X is a promising departure from the watered down, and often absurdly bloodless, incarnations of the IP. After all, Wolverine is a nigh indestructible mutant, with razor sharp, retractable claws and a skeleton made of unbreakable metal. One love tap would collapse a normal humans orbital bone. And in <em>Logan</em>, the logic of that plays out in some startling visuals. But there is never a moment that the characters break from previous depictions in any real way. And the story itself, once stripped of its blood-spattered window dressing, is utterly same-y. In fact it is very much an extended cut of a scene in X2 where Logan (Wolverine) tries desperately to save some mutant schoolkids from the deprivations of nameless government drones.</p>

<p><em>Logan</em>, despite some hyperbole drenched reviews I’ve read touting it as a best picture contender, is nothing more or less than what Mark Cousins refers to as a bauble. Although a particularly finely wrought bauble. It’s great entertainment, and well worth the money you pay. The performances are uniformly committed and often surprisingly nuanced, especially Stephen Merchant as Caliban—and it’s also a pretty film, and tightly plotted, with few of the usual drop offs in tension that these films often suffer from.</p>

<p>What <em>Logan</em> isn’t, in any real way, is fundamentally different that what’s come before. It’s simply a well constructed example of branding as product. And that means that it will always play out in ways that are utterly transparent and obvious. Even when central characters die there is no real permanence to their ending, because you know that as long as the IP remains fiscally viable another incarnation or reboot is right around the corner. That strips any real emotional depth from the situations these characters face, and dooms them to a kind of mediocrity that seems inescapable.</p>

<p>I like Wolverine as a character, partly because he is one of the few in this milieu that even hints at what the real world consequences would be if a human being was gifted with these kinds of deadly advantages. But unless films like <em>Logan</em> can break free of the requirements that being linked to a marketing scheme and maintenance of the IP as a brand entail, rather than developing an evolving, complex character, they will always be a mile wide and an inch deep, no matter how good they look.</p>

<p>And to me, at least, that is a missed opportunity.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>I Am Not Your Negro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/28/i-am-not-your-negro.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=IAmNotYourNegro" />
    <published>2017-02-28T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-28T04:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/28/i-am-not-your-negro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I could listen to James Baldwin’s words, whether spoken by himself or a perfectly calibrated Samuel L. Jackson, for hours against an empty, black screen. Add to that the masterfully selected archival footage you provided director Raoul Peck, and what you get is a documentary that is near to perfect. But it is a profoundly disturbing and unsettling perfection, because it lays bare the chasm between the aspirations of a nation and its often ugly reality. </p>

<p><em>I Am Not Your Negro</em> is a documentary that consists entirely of words written and spoken by James Baldwin, an African American academic and author who lived and wrote during the most tumultuous period of the American civil rights movement in 1950’s and 1960’s. He was a contemporary of Angela Davis, Huey Newton, Muhammed Ali, Malcolm X., Martin Luther King and Medgar Evers. The framing of the documentary revolves around a thirty page proposal for a book, to be titled <em>Remember This House</em>, that remained unfinished at the time of his death in 1987. The book was an attempt to chronicle the lives and deaths of Evers, Malcolm X. And MLK. The rest of the documentary uses that conceit to tell Baldwin’s own narrative, intertwined with archival footage of the three men in question.</p>

<p>Six years in the making, <em>I Am Not Your Negro</em> is a precise and often devastating deconstruction of the parallel worlds that white and black America have occupied for the entirety of the US’s history. The archival footage of the ugliness inflicted upon civil rights activists, as well as the assassinations of MLK, Malcolm X. and Evers, punctuate Baldwin’s observations about how America created and maintained a two-tiered society that pretended to one set of ideals, but often played out in much more sinister ways.</p>

<p>Born and raised in Harlem, before becoming an expat in Paris, and then finally returning to New York, Baldwin was a man built of contradictions. He was, for all intents and purposes, without religion, yet was both the son of a preacher and a former preacher himself. He was a gay, African American academic and author in a time where even saying that sentence in some parts of the country would court a beating or worse. He debated William F. Buckley to a standstill, and was the inspiration for literary figures like Toni Morrison and Ta-Nehisi Coates. Yet he is, for some, a complete cipher and largely unremarked.</p>

<p>Actively dismayed at the arbitrary and often damaging class distinctions that existed not only within the African American community, but the nation as a whole, Baldwin was, it seems, a cosmopolitan humanist with little of the usual loyalties to the church or established hierarchies. He saw himself as a witness, which meant he never really belonged to any one group but sought to see the larger picture—even while acknowledging that his experience was thoroughly grounded in the particulars of an African American man born near the middle of the 20th century. How could it not be? Baldwin also precisely articulated that it is incumbent upon the people who hold and exercise power as to how this will all shake out—while expressing his belief that the black-white divide is entirely a constructed thing, based on economic and class expediency: “White is just a metaphor for those that hold power”.</p>

<p>Watching this film was an often painful experience, especially when the sneering faces that were actively engaged in the beatings and murder of African American men and women could’ve belonged to an aunt or an uncle or a sister or brother of mine; people that look very much like me doing things that were utterly unconscionable. And overtop all of that was Baldwin’s often prescient observations about how these divides would never be healed without a kind of self-reflection that seems beyond most white Americans. But the brutal poetry of images and words, so completely in tune with one another, is what elevates <em>I Am Not Your Negro</em> above similarly constructed works. Especially since so much of the imagery jumped back and forth between historical and contemporary events-- and underscored how little real difference there was between Selma and Ferguson, the lynchings of young African Americans in the Fifties and Sixties, and their current treatment at the hands of the criminal justice system.</p>

<p>James Baldwin was a man of profound depth and a piercing intellect. He was possessed of a melancholic rage at what he saw every day in his country, but rejected the “white devil” rhetoric adopted by early Malcolm X. Instead he charged the American majority with a simple but difficult task: You say you’re decent, god fearing people, who believe in justice and liberty for all. </p>

<p>Now prove it.</p>

<p>The jury is still very much out.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Cure for Wellness</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/21/a-cure-for-wellness.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ACureforWellness" />
    <published>2017-02-21T04:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-21T04:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/21/a-cure-for-wellness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I know I was supposed to be scared witless by Gore Verbinski’s <em>A Cure for Wellness</em>, and normally I would have been. As someone who is deathly afraid of pigeons, because what the actual fuck are they staring at me like that for, I’m an easy mark for horror movies. But this hot mess of cheap scares and tortured allegory annoyed me more than it scared me. Aside from the fact that the film ends about eight times before it <em>actually</em> ends, the underlying themes and narrative subtext are exasperatingly jumbled. </p>

<p>Your script gleefully plays upon our most common phobias - drowning, darkness, the dentist, geriatric nudity - to tell us a cautionary tale about the dangers of working too hard and being too obsessed with wellness. Or something. After a bunch of eels started slithering around in toilets I had no idea what the hell was going on anymore. </p>

<p>But then another narrative starts to emerge, shaped upon themes of purity and tropes of imprisonment, and things got a little uncomfortable for me. The underlying tale of a set of diseased, deadly beliefs, lurking until regaining their former strength and power, is the real horror here, but it falls flat when you consider the real-life resurgence of the same. </p>

<p>I think your basic underlying premise was this: The film is about Nazism. The evil, dastardly, purity-obsessed Nazis we thought were long gone have been hiding and recouping their strength this whole time, rounding up innocent people and conducting terrible experiments on them before exterminating them and just being generally Aryan and horrid. Normally, there would be much satisfaction and narrative catharsis when the evil Nazis/Nazi stand-ins get their comeuppance, but I just wasn’t feeling it. Were you pointing frantically from the Nazi-esques in your script to the real-life alt-right horror show currently unfolding in our own back yards while screaming, “It’s the same damn thing!”?  Because that is more frightening than your water tank scene, your eel scene, and your aggressive dentist scene. </p>

<p>In the decades since WWII, while we’ve solemnly intoned, “Never again, never again,” we have enjoyed a variety of cultural product where Nazis or Nazi-ish bad guys are dealt with violently and mercilessly. We cheer on the avenging heroes and fervently wish they had been around ‘back then’. Well, Nazi-ish appears to be back in vogue, and today, a film like <em>Inglourious Basterds</em> would probably end with a lecture about the importance of dialogue and respect for the Nazis’ freedom of speech. And perhaps you see the horror in that too. When the protagonist Lockhart confronts Nazi-ish bad guy Dr. Volmer over his Nazi-reminiscent misdeeds against his unsuspecting clientele, the latter purrs, “It was easier this time, with such willing pawns.” </p>

<p>Your Nazi allegory is the truly terrifying heart of the film, and it could have been pretty compelling if you had just focused the narrative around it from the get-go. I guess I just didn’t see the point of all that other crap about the evils of greed, or corporatism, or whatever you seemed to be taking aim at initially. Your story tried to be about too many things at once, or was initially about one thing, then changed its mind and decided to be about something else. </p>

<p>If the horror film is a vehicle through which our deepest underlying fears and anxieties over the state of the world play out, the next four to eight years will likely produce a steady stream of fright-fests featuring vaguely (or blatantly) Germanic villains and monsters, with brave protagonists sending them back to Hell, all like, “Not today, Franz!” But the horror on screen is no longer quite as hair-raising as the real world spectres that return for unwanted and unwelcome sequels (that was not a suggestion to write a sequel to this film. Please don’t).</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The LEGO Batman Movie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/14/the-lego-batman-movie.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheLEGOBatmanMovie" />
    <published>2017-02-14T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-14T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/14/the-lego-batman-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>One of the standouts of 2014’s <em>The LEGO Movie</em> was the uber-catchy original song by Tegan and Sara ft. The Lonely Island, <em>Everything is Awesome</em>. Not to be outdone by a bunch of moody twins and a trio of losers, you tapped into your inner Batman and grumbled out a hit of your own: Who’s the (Bat)Man.</p>

<p>Of course, I don’t really think Tegan and Sara are moody twins nor Lonely Island, losers, I was just inspired by the rock ‘n’ roll personality of <em>Who’s the (Bat)Man</em>. Your song is essentially <em>Everything is Awesome</em>, but the everything is replaced with Batman and that’s perfectly acceptable because Batman <em>is</em> awesome and so is <em>The LEGO Batman Movie.</em></p>

<p><em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> is the widely anticipated spin-off for <em>The LEGO Movie</em>’s standout character, Batman; a self-absorbed narcissist who is the product of every fan’s obsession with him. He’s essentially Christopher Nolan’s husky voiced Dark Knight and <em>How It Should Have Ended</em>’s post-credit Batman. If you’re not familiar with the latter, look it up and see the similarities for yourself. </p>

<p>LEGO Batman is well aware that he’s the moneymaker for DC Comics and he revels in the fact. He’s a celebrity, both as Bruce Wayne and Batman. He’s prone to talking about his chiseled abs and his ability to take down villains without breaking a sweat. He’s the plastic manifestation of pop-culture’s obsession with superheroes which is why he might be the most compelling caped crusader to ever grace the big screen.</p>

<p><em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> could have been whatever it wanted to be and it chose to be an homage to the character’s history across film, TV, and comics. This film is a quirky and hilarious treat for moviegoers of all ages. The children who go to see it will absolutely love the potty-mouthed humour while some of the older crowd will appreciate all the nods to Batman’s past. Although, I would be lying if I didn’t admit that The Joker rubbing his butt on the Batmobile and calling it the ‘buttmobile’ cracked me the hell up.</p>

<p>One instance in which <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> absolutely nails what it is to be a lifelong Batman fan comes in the opener where The Joker is introducing his team of supervillains. He names off the usual subjects like Catwoman, The Riddler, and Bane, but continues to go down the list to even the most obscure and laughable villains such as Eraser, Crazy Quilt, and Condiment King. The scene works on many levels but the kicker was the moment my girlfriend leaned over and asked, “are those all real names?” to which my answer was a gleeful “<em>yes”</em>.</p>

<p>Despite all the meta moments and references to butts, there is a genuinely heartfelt story in <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> that takes Batman through a journey of self-discovery. He actually grows as a character which is the biggest critique against the live-action DC films. It makes me wonder how a movie about plastic toys can draw out more emotion than their live-action counterparts. LEGO Batman is actively saving DC’s ass, which only helps add to his over-the-top persona. </p>

<p>Now more than ever I realize just how important <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> really is. Eight decades is a long time to be The Man, yet Batman continues to evolve and stay at the top of his league. Batman has already secured his spot as the <em>It</em> superhero for the foreseeable future. Sure, people would love to fly around Metropolis like Superman, but it wouldn’t compare to the gravitas that comes with being The Dark Knight. </p>

<p>Even though <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> pokes fun at the character, it does him an even greater service by reminding us about all the times Batman has been awesome.</p>

<p>So, if I may quote some of your lyrics:</p>

<p>Who has the coolest gadgets? </p>

<p>Who has the tricked out ride? </p>

<p>Who does the sickest backflips? </p>

<p>Who&#39;s the manliest man?</p>

<p>You better believe it’s the Batman.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Toni Erdmann</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/13/toni-erdmann.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ToniErdmann" />
    <published>2017-02-13T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-13T04:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/13/toni-erdmann</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Remaking an acclaimed foreign film is as inevitable as it is inadvisable. By and large, the projects are doomed from the start. Critics see them first and always fixate on comparing it to the original. The tone isn’t right. The cultural nuance is gone. They dial back the most intense moments, or get rid of the narrative fat that gave the film character. Even the all-powerful element of surprise is sacrificed from the get-go. It’s pretty hard for a film to climb out of that hole, especially when the same people who gave the original movie cache are the first to take it away. We critics are the worst, I know. </p>

<p>But I have some good news for you, Brad.</p>

<p>I’m ready for the remake of <em>Toni Erdmann</em>. I can’t wait, actually. Not because I loved this original German version, but because I honestly think it can be done better. You, specifically, can do better. And by the sounds of it, you‘re already <a href="http://variety.com/2017/film/news/jack-nicholson-toni-erdmann-remake-retirement-oscar-nominated-1201980617/">well on your way</a>.</p>

<p>You’ve got Adam McKay and Will Ferrell in your corner as fellow producers. Kristen Wiig has been tapped to play the female lead. And, of course, the giant who got the whole ball rolling; Jack Nicholson He called you up personally, asking you to acquire the rights for Paramount so he could star and come out of his six-year retirement. Cast-wise, it’s a match made in heaven. No writer or director has yet been attached, but with this talent onboard, safe to say you’ll have your pick of the litter. What could possibly scare them off? </p>

<p>For starters, the runtime. It seems unconscionable to make a 2 hour and 45 minute off-beat, laggard “comedy” that lives and dies by a believable character quirk. The core of the story revolves around a father-daughter dynamic that it’s in no rush to explore, slowly revealing a transformation that’s both unexpected and obvious. She’s a tightly-wound executive consultant, he’s an unkempt and unpredictable drifter who prefers prosthetic teeth over proper conversation. The languid pacing serves to repel any gravitational pull towards slapstick comedy, or laugh-out-loud comedy of any sort. Which means if people only see Ferrell’s name attached, and your history producing movies like <em>Happy Gilmore</em>, <em>The Cable Guy</em> and <em>Scary Movie</em>, they might make up their mind that you’re about to embark on the definition of a bad Hollywood remake. But, of course, you’ll quickly point them to another film on your resume - one of the most successful (critically and commercially) remakes of all-time – <em>The</em> <em>Departed.</em> A different genre, to be sure, but with Nicholson on board again, sparks could fly. But only if you make some tough decisions.</p>

<p>Let’s start with that big one. I beg you: don’t cut 30 minutes from this film. Cut 60. Don’t be scared. I’m positive you can still provide a sparse atmosphere and all the necessary character dynamics. The trick will be not to rush the moments that matter most. Especially, the most memorable one (you know which one I mean). Wiig has already proven that she’s willing to expose herself for a film, so retaining the incredibly awkward and sustained nude scene is going to be essential. It’s the shot of caffeine that turns the film on its head, and cheating the photography by cropping out the naughty parts will rob the moment of its power. The song she sings later is also an easy win to keep, as well at least a hint of her secret relationship (I can live with a less German version of that kink, though). </p>

<p>But the biggest changes will be around the titular Toni Erdmann. As it stands, Peter Simonischek plays the role almost apologetically. The restraint is admirable for its attempt to keep it the story grounded, but there’s room to grow without crossing into farce. We normally watch a remake lamenting what was – I watched Toni Erdmann only thinking what it <em>could</em> be – and this was before I knew anything about your upcoming remake. </p>

<p>I’ll be in the minority, to be sure, since this Oscar-nominated version will have no shortage of fans and defenders. But there would be no satisfying them anyway. So be brave, and make a new version of <em>Erdmann</em> – one that’s both as familiar and unrecognizable as a twilight-aged man getting into character to find simple joy in life and reconnect with lost love.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fifty Shades Darker</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/10/fifty-shades-darker.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=FiftyShadesDarker" />
    <published>2017-02-10T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-10T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/10/fifty-shades-darker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You are the last person listed in the crew credits on IMDb. I’ve been there: film production offices where I was expected to “look up to” people who ran the spectrum from mildly douchey to outright sadistic. People in positions of power who got off on lording over us lowly, proletariat scum. I’m addressing this to you because you likely had the least influence on this film. With that distance, maybe you feel the same way about it that I do. Or maybe not. Honestly, I feel like I don’t know anything anymore.</p>

<p>Have you ever walked out of a theater after seeing a film so amazing that it changes you? You proselytize about it endlessly to anyone who will listen, and think, if everyone saw this film, the world would be a different place. I have, many times. That’s why I do this. I want people to understand why I love the films I love, or explain why I think other films don’t work. </p>

<p><em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> changed me. I walked out of theater questioning everything I know, and not just about movies, but about life itself. I sat in my car afterwards and stared at people walking down the street, oblivious to the internal carnage this film had wrought. <em>They’re the lucky ones</em>, I thought, <em>they can still be saved.</em> </p>

<p>Please don’t take this as mere film snobbery on my part. I love many bad films. But this film wasn’t bad. It was awful. It was so irredeemably and intolerably awful that it didn’t make me angry the way bad films usually do. It made me sad. Bereft, even. Often I watch bad films and wonder, “who is this for?” With <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> the answer was clear from the hundreds of women (and six guys), some of whom I saw literally <em>running</em> to get in the theater before the screening began. Following the screening I thought of these people and asked myself, “who am I?” I wondered if there was something wrong with <em>m</em>e that made me hate this film so much while others seemed to love it. What discernible character flaw sets me apart from so many women that can’t get enough of this type of shit? </p>

<p>I really don’t want to take a dig at the people that do love this tripe. We love what we love, and we shouldn’t feel guilty about it or apologize for it. That said, the sheer, palpable force of women around me tittering and swooning as every horrible relationship red flag, and every tired gender stereotype weren’t just reinforced but glorified actually pained me. I get it: it’s fantasy, it’s wish fulfillment. It’s a doe-eyed young woman surrounded by pretty, expensive things who has sex with a hot guy. But that’s what <em>Vogue</em> magazine and porn are for.</p>

<p>Please know, dearest Maggie, that I tried. Having not seen the first film in this series, I knew, thanks to <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/13/fifty-shades-of-grey.html">Christopher Redmond’s review</a>, that this second installment would likely not be very good. But in the interest of professionalism I tried to force myself to be objective. Some familiar names popped up during the opening titles that gave me hope – Marcia Gay Harden, Kim Basinger, Danny Elfman – that maybe this wouldn’t be a complete wash. It didn’t matter. Nothing matters anymore. </p>

<p>Before you mistake me for some kind of prude, I’ll tell you, I grew up on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bleu_Nuit"><em>Bleu Nuit</em></a> and scrambled cable porn, both of which are infinitely sexier than <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em>. I stupidly thought that maybe Kim Basinger’s addition to this film might lend it an air of gravitas. She starred in what is arguably the granddaddy of naughty, soft-core studio films from the 80s, <em>9 _1/2</em> weeks. She and pre-motorcycle accident Mickey Rourke had genuine chemistry, their sex scenes were hawt as hell, and were gorgeously shot. The film was no <em>Citizen Kane</em>, but it was a gritty, titillating exploration of a woman’s sexual awakening. </p>

<p><em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> is positively artless. The sex scenes are robotic, abrupt, and laughably vanilla for a film purporting to glorify the BDSM lifestyle. The accompanying soundtrack is grating, and the cinematography is offensively banal. <em>Lifetime</em>movies aren’t this shamelessly boring. At least they don’t take themselves seriously, and they know exactly what they are. Unlike this drivel that can’t decide if it’s a thriller, a romance, or a third-rate Madonna video. </p>

<p>For every time Dakota Johnson’s Anastasia bit her lip, I bit my tongue twice as hard. I have been thrown out of a theater exactly once before for yelling (1996, <em>The English Patient</em> “just leave her in the goddamned cave!”). I came very close here. This film is just like Christian Grey, its lead male character – a manipulative piece of shit. Every time Christian exhibits borderline abusive behaviour – buying the company Anastasia works for, knowing all of her banking info, demanding she not go on a business trip – Anastasia has a fleeting moment of “hey wait, this is wrong”, which is quickly replaced with a reminder of how rich and hot Christian is, just in case anyone in the audience starts thinking maybe Anastasia should walk the fuck away. If I gave a sketchy ex another chance, and three days in he suggested shoving Ben Wa balls up my hoo-ha to wear to his parent’s fancy party I’d be out the door, but not before shoving them up his ass. Oh, but Christian is <em>damaged</em>, you see, and he’s trying to <em>change</em>. Instead of yelling out “BOOOO!” until I was hoarse, I sat motionless in my seat and screamed silently.</p>

<p>I’m still screaming.</p>

<p>I’d attempt to describe the plot but I’m afraid I’d fall asleep at the keyboard. This film is about one thing: money. It’s a cynical box-office cash-grab timed to coincide with a manufactured holiday. But you’re so low on the totem pole it’s not like you’re expecting any points on the back end or anything. You can walk away from this and go on with your career and eventually, when you rack up a ton of credits, you can drop this one from your resume. </p>

<p>If I could give this film less than zero stars I would. I’m actually tempted to go back and give extra stars to other films I thought were horrible because before <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em> I didn’t know what I didn’t know. It has set the bar so low that my faith in myself as a critic has been shaken to the core. </p>

<p>So why waste so much time tearing it to shreds, you might ask? Believe me, my first instinct was to just type the word “FUUUUUCK” a thousand times and submit that as my review. Then I realized that the only hollow joy I might derive from this turd rodeo would be to warn other people away from it. I don’t like to call myself a hero, but if I can save just one person from <em>Fifty Shades Darker</em>, then I’m a goddamned hero.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>War On Everyone</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/9/war-on-everyone.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=WarOnEveryone" />
    <published>2017-02-09T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-09T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/9/war-on-everyone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Oh, the Nineties. I wore some outrageous outfits, ingested copious amounts of recreational pharmaceuticals, and watched a ton of movies. There were a lot of edgy, post-Tarantino flicks that glorified drugs, nihilism, and violence and also managed to be funny and sexy. <em>The Way of the Gun</em>, <em>Out of Sight</em>, and <em>Two Days in the Valley</em> sprung immediately to mind while watching <em>War on Everyone.</em> With characters that spew quotes from philosophers as often as they curse, consume too many illicit substances, and chase bad guys in a 70s Monte Carlo while listening to Glen Campbell, I felt like I was back on my second-hand couch in my little Waverly Street apartment about to spark up a joint before settling in for a wild two-hour cinematic ride. Though like many things from the 90’s I’ve outgrown,<em>War on Everyone</em> is fun to revisit, but the nostalgia effect too often dips into self-indulgence. </p>

<p>Michael Pena and Alexander Skarsgard play crooked buddy cops Bob and Terry, and you deck them out in natty, three-piece suits. When we meet them, they are chasing down a mime. Bob asks dryly, “if you hit a mime, does it make a sound?” Terry provides the answer shortly after. This kind of pithiness sets the tone for a film that drifts back and forth from the ridiculous to the sublime, rarely managing to find the perfect balance between the two. But when it does, it is almost magical. Many of those moments aren’t delivered as drolly as the dialogue. They come courtesy of the art direction, and from your over-the-top costume choices.</p>

<p>Instead of real people, we mostly get actors in costumes, and what costumes they are. Shady informants, Reggie X and Padraic wear matching Reebok tracksuits while giving each other foot massages and ratting each other out. Evil Brit Lord Magnan, and his creepy henchman Russell are resplendent in colourful three-piece suits seemingly stolen from the <em>Starsky</em> <em>&amp; Hutch</em> wardrobe archives. When Terry hits on hooker-with-a-heart-of-gold Jackie, he is in a white –t and cowboy hat, and she is in a skimpy majorette ensemble. What makes these costumes – and the film itself – pop are sets painted in vibrant, primary hues, decorated with mid-Century modern furniture and props, set against a desolate desert landscape. A post-coital scene sees Terry looking out the window at the city skyline. It is evocative and beautiful, but it feels mismatched beside talky scenes of Bob discussing Simone de Beauvoir, or lamenting Jennifer Lopez’ almost bare tits in <em>Out of Sight</em>.</p>

<p>In his previous films, <em>The Guard</em> and <em>Calvary,</em> writer/director John Michael McDonagh gave us heroes that blur the line between good and bad. Morally flawed characters are often the most interesting to follow, but they need to have heart. Terry is supposed to be the emotional center of this film, but like the rest of the characters, his traits seem manufactured merely for tragicomic effect. </p>

<p>The scenes that really work are the ones between Terry and Jackie. They have an electric chemistry that follows them from the bedroom to Terry’s minimalist manse, where they dance to Glen Campbell’s <em>Rhinestone Cowboy</em>, a song that I heretofore never considered the least bit sexy and likely never will again. Jackie is played by Tessa Thompson, who is quickly becoming one of my favourite young actors. Cringe-worthy scenes where she reads Susan Faludi poolside and Terry asks her if feminists can still wear hotpants and call themselves feminists wouldn’t have been salvageable in lesser hands. Like the rainbow spike heels she wears to go hiking with Terry and the young boy they accidentally adopt, she can pull off charmingly wacky without bordering on Manic Pixie Dreamgirl territory.</p>

<p><em>War on Everyone</em> seems mainly to be at war with its place in time, unsure if it’s a 90’s comic-thriller throwback, or a 70s cop show, borrowing elements from both which start out fun, but eventually drain the viewer. Set in modern day, jokes about racist law enforcement, thinly veiled misogyny, and a dark subplot about child pornography clash as badly as floral and plaid. There were some genuine laugh out loud moments that, like my 90s turquoise snakeskin pants, which were so, so wrong and made me wish that they fit better with the rest of the outfit. And yet, despite these clashing elements and not because of them, I enjoyed this film far more than I like to admit. </p>

<p>Maybe it’s time to break those turquoise snakeskins out of retirement.</p>

<p>Or maybe not.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lion</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/3/lion.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Lion" />
    <published>2017-02-03T07:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-03T07:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/3/lion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The last thing I was thinking about when the credits rolled on <em>Lion</em> was the visual effects. The first was getting out of the theatre before someone saw my two-hour long transformation into a puddle of tears. As I tried to compose myself, hood over my head like a petulant child, I watched the documentary footage post-script during the credits. That sure as hell didn’t help stop the waterworks, but it did keep me in my seat long enough to notice the army of (over 50) visual effects team members under your supervision. It made me think.</p>

<p>Even if only <em>half</em> your team was dedicated to Nicole Kidman’s age denying effects (justified early in the film, but a vain movie star demand after the narrative’s 20 year jump), that still left a whole lot of movie to work on. Surprising since each frame of this film feels natural and grounded. Director Garth Davis, in his feature film debut, opts for balance over flare at every turn in his storytelling. This may be in service of the story, or as a way to counteract the many inevitable and inescapable comparisons with <em>Slumdog Millionaire</em>. Regardless, it’s the right choice, and whatever digital trickery was involved in manipulating the images, it was as seamless as Kidman’s oxygen repelling pores. </p>

<p>That’s enough picking on poor old Nicole. By lending her name and talents to the film (and any reservations about sporting God-awful 80s hair), she no doubt helped sell this story about Australian parents who adopt a homeless Indian child. She and David Wenham, however, rightly play second fiddle to a pair of performances portraying Saroo Brierly – one by seven-year-old Sunny Pawar, and the other by <em>Slumdog</em> alum Dev Patel. After the heart-wrenching first act of the film where Saroo loses his family, the story falls into Patel’s hands, who gamely pulls off the transformation into an Australian surfer bro and Handsome Leading Man. I assume his new muscles or long locks didn’t come from your team, but who knows. They sure looked real, and provided a temporarily (welcomed) distraction from the emotionally loaded narrative in this film.</p>

<p>But as embarrassing as it felt in the moment, I don’t resent <em>Lion</em>’s ability to manipulate my emotions. Every turn felt earned, and the performances never crossed into melodrama. When the story finally resolves in both satisfying and heart-breaking ways, the visual choices made to convey a sense of closure felt simple and inspired. The only places your work may have been prominent were during the Google Map searches that that inspire Saroo’s journey. But even there, technology is always simply an enabler for human connection and never foregrounded for effect. Just the way it’s supposed to be, as I’m sure you’d agree.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>20th Century Women</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/2/20th-century-women.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=20thCenturyWomen" />
    <published>2017-02-02T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-02T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/2/20th-century-women</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I don’t often write my letters to the cast part of Dear Cast &amp; Crew. I find it far more interesting to celebrate (or sometimes excoriate) people behind the camera since these fine folks rarely get their due. But you are different, dear Annette. Or maybe not. Too often you are overlooked when awards season comes around. Sure, you’ve been nominated plenty, and I thought this year you would be a shoe-in for an Oscar nod for this role in <em>20th Century Women</em>. But I think I’ve found the reason the Golden Boy remains out of your reach; you make it look easy. Like most parents of teenagers, I’m afraid we take you for granted. You’re just too damn good. </p>

<p>You are like an experienced sound engineer or lighting tech; you have become a master at your craft. Films rely on people of your calibre to run smoothly. Your work is seamless, appearing effortless. You inject your characters with a singularity so organic that once you’ve taken on a role it’s impossible to imagine anyone else owning it. If it seems like I’m gushing, please forgive me. In <em>20th Century Women</em> you play the head-strong Dorothea, a mom at a loss to understand her teenage son in 1979 Santa Barbara. You were a stand-in for writer/director Mike Mills’ mother, but within the first few minutes of watching you on screen, I felt a creeping sense of familiarity. You were standing in for my mother too.  </p>

<p>Like Dorothea, my mother had me late in life. And like Dorothea, my mother didn’t remarry after my father died. Mum raised me by herself, but she was not alone. She collected people, and our house was never empty. Like Dorothea did for her 15-year-old son Jamie, Mum allowed me a great deal of independence, probably more than I deserved. Some moments in the film seemed ripped from my own life, and you gave me the gift of reliving them through my mother’s perspective. </p>

<p>The film opens on Dorothea’s car on fire in a grocery store parking lot on her birthday. Our family car caught on fire at Loblaws on my 10th birthday, and now I understand how Mum was able to shake it off. Dorothea doesn’t understand her son’s music, but makes the effort to try. My Mum raced out to a house party I was at when I called to check in and told her the noise in the background was The Cult. She was mortally embarrassed when she realized it was a band, and not an actual cult. </p>

<p>The commonality of the struggles of raising a teenager alone have never been illustrated so artfully. <em>20th Century Women</em> gave me a deeper understanding of not just what my mother went through, but what my other single mom friends endure. When Jamie yells at Dorothea, “Mom, I’m dealing with everything right now, you are dealing with nothing!” I actually gasped from shame at having said something so similar to my Mum. Jamie apologizes for Dorothea’s eccentricities much the way I did with my Mum; Jamie, “she’s from the Great Depression” (me: “she grew up during the War”). What Mills does beautifully is provide context for each of his characters by recognizing the importance of their time and place in the world; where they are from, who they are in 1979, and who they will become.</p>

<p>Mills’ background is in advertising and music video direction, and it shows here in the best possible way. Mills incorporates multi-character narration, historical footage, and period-relevant books, music and politics to tell the story of an unconventional family that manages to be both unique and relatable.</p>

<p>Affectations that I dismissed as twee in Mills’ previous autobiographical turn, <em>Beginners</em>, are more mature in <em>20th</em> <em>Century Women</em> and far less mannered. But like <em>Beginners</em>, the cast he assembled here is exemplary. Greta Gerwig as the wounded punk Abbie, Elle Fanning as the wise-beyond-her-years Julie, and newcomer Lucas Jade Zumann as Jamie, have a natural chemistry that makes us root for this unorthodox family. But it’s your scenes with Billy Crudup’s William, Dorothea’s handyman boarder, that I wished would never end. Seeing two amazing actors play people so funny and flawed yet self-aware is a rare treat. When people lament the loss of mid-budget films celebrating real people, they should hold this film up as a champion of the type of story that is both small and universal, where nothing and <em>everything</em> happens.</p>

<p>For a long time I bemoaned the fact that my favourite actor, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/the-giver.html">Jeff Bridges</a>, was infuriatingly underrated. Then he won an Oscar for <em>Crazy Heart</em> in 2010 and now I have to share him with everyone who finally recognizes his brilliance. Like a jealous child, part of me wants to keep you all to myself. But like a proud daughter, I want the rest of the world to reward the incredible work you do making complex characters knowable. I have no doubt your time will come.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>