<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-17T15:01:22Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Revenge of the Sith</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/17/revenge-of-the-sith.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RevengeoftheSith" />
    <published>2015-12-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/17/revenge-of-the-sith</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Let me just start by saying that writing this letter was not my idea. I have always maintained a respectful (if somewhat scornful) distance from the <em>Star Wars</em> franchise. I saw the original trilogy for the first time a couple years ago, just to put an end to hearing: “YOU’VE NEVER SEEN <em>STAR WARS</em>??!!” That conversation had begun to end friendships. When I tried saying, “It’s okay, I’ve seen the first one,” someone would inevitably smugly point out, “You mean the fourth one?” And more friendships ended. I hoped all things <em>Star Wars</em> would leave me the hell alone, but then the folks here at Dear Cast and Crew were all like, “Please write about <em>Revenge of the</em> <em>Sith</em>” and I was all like, “Which one is he, again?” and my Companion was all like, “... you need to clear your schedule.”</p>

<p>And that’s how a perfectly good weekend was ruined. </p>

<p>While preparing myself mentally for the onslaught of siths and wonkies and whatever else, I found myself wishing – not for the first time – that someone had just showed me these damn movies when I was a kid. I think early exposure is key to liking <em>Star Wars</em>, nostalgia being the only thing that helps you look past its many, many weaknesses. I had to watch all three prequels so that <em>Revenge of the Sith</em> would make any sense at all, so I resolved to approach them with softer eyes, promising myself that, by the end of it, I would be able to list three things I liked about <em>Star Wars</em>. </p>

<p>This optimism lasted about ten minutes. What followed was six hours of me going, “Who wrote this shit?” My sympathies were with you, Fraser, as I sighed through scene after scene of clunky dialogue and performances that would have made the cast of my Grade 1 production of <em>The Very Hungry Caterpillar</em> raise a snide eyebrow. I pictured you watching each day’s footage, and I can’t even imagine what it was like to sift through multiple takes of Hayden Christansen muttering, “My strength has doubled since we last fought” (because that’s what apparently passes for smack talk in a galaxy far, far away) and having to pick the best one. You had to go through all the raw material to make sure it was fit to turn into a film worthy of franchise devotees’ loyalty and passion. It must have been awkward knowing they were going to get a steaming pile of wookie doo-doo instead. </p>

<p>So I decided to adjust my expectations, because I didn’t want to be one of those grumpy, stuck-up people who shits all over <em>Star Wars</em>. I was going to jump on this bandwagon if it killed me. And I managed to come up with one thing that could have been truly great if it didn’t suck so much, and another that actually <em>was</em> great. </p>

<p>If the Force was strong in me, I would, without a doubt, be Team Dark Side. I thought Darth Vader was the most compelling character in the original trilogy, so I thought I would enjoy watching his story unfold. It’s just too bad Anakin/Vader was portrayed with the intensity of a soaked badger. Vitriol aside, by the time I was ready to watch <em>Revenge of the Sith</em>, Anakin’s story did have me hooked. Even though I knew how it would end, I felt for him—but I really had to reach for it. To me, the most tragic aspect of Anakin’s story is that he was failed by people who loved him. Their inability to see past his Chosen One-ness and reach out to a boy who was clearly suffering a crisis of identity and faith is pretty heartbreaking when you think about it. And don’t even get me started on Padme. Whenever Anakin tries to express doubt or disillusionment, her stock response of, “But but the Republic!” was unhelpful, insensitive, and frankly, a bit dickish. Eventually Anakin goes full Vader, and it’s all quite sad, but I was kind of glad to see him packed off to the Death Star so that he could finally have a chance for some much-needed Vader-time. I guess I should say I liked the <em>idea</em> of Vader more than what I saw onscreen.</p>

<p>As for the one thing I ended up loving, Yoda, my little green homeboy, walks away with that distinction. I think there is a parallel to be drawn between Yoda and you, in that you both watched a massive clusterfuck unfolding and were ultimately powerless to stop it. I realize that, had Qui-Gon Jinn listened to Yoda in Episode I, there would be no Episodes II through VI, but I couldn’t help but remember Yoda, all the way back in <em>The Phantom Menace</em>, basically warning everyone, “Train that kid we must not, shady as fuck he is.” Likewise, I pictured you watching day after day of dailies with your head in your hands, going, “Turn out badly this will...” </p>

<p>(It’s also to my everlasting disappointment that, before going into exile, Yoda didn’t find Obi-Wan Kenobi, bitch slap him hard, and yell, “TOLD YOU SO I DID!” Just another missed opportunity that might have made the film truly great.)</p>

<p>Ultimately, I’m glad I’ve finally (sort of) climbed aboard the <em>Star Wars</em> bandwagon, if for no other reason than I now get all the <em>Star Wars</em> references in other movies and TV shows. I should also probably track down that guy on the subway who tried to hit on me with his best Chewbacca impression; I now understand what that was, and I’m very sorry for hitting him with my purse and pulling the emergency alarm.</p>

<p>I will probably see <em>The Force Awakens</em> at some point. Maybe in a few months, when the horde of costumed weirdos currently lined up outside the theatre has had its fill. Because it is, undeniably, a great story, and no amount of scorn I or anyone else choose to heap upon the films ultimately detracts from that. My fingers are crossed that this next iteration will be the truly great film series that all the Trekkies deserve. </p>

<p>Wait, that’s not right, is it? </p>

<p>Shit.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Attack of the Clones</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/16/attack-of-the-clones.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AttackoftheClones" />
    <published>2015-12-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/16/attack-of-the-clones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You knew this was coming.</p>

<p>With <em>Star Wars: The Force Awakens</em> being released tomorrow, fans are bound to revisit the previous six films to prepare themselves for what’s to come. Which means your inbox is going to get filled with a ton of hate mail. </p>

<p>Again.   </p>

<p>I grew up with prequels. I was a kid addicted to action, and your CGI action sequences were my bread and butter. All that boring old man stuff in the original trilogy didn&#39;t interest me. What <em>did</em> interest me was the all-out war at the end of <em>Attack of the Clones</em>—droids, clones, and Jedis, oh my! When the Jedi reinforcements rescued Padme, Anakin, and Obi-Wan from the gladiator dome and proceeded to charge into battle against the droids, I lost my shit. It was so cool. </p>

<p>But when I re-watched Episode II the other day, I had to face a harsh truth: the movie I loved as a child is actually just a clunky mess.</p>

<p>It shouldn’t’ surprise me. <em>Attack of the Clones</em> is touted as the worst of all the <em>Star Wars</em> films. This is due, in large part, to the shocking amount of green screen used throughout the two hour span. When the original trilogy came out, the visual effects blew people’s minds; a thing as relatively simply as the beam of the Death Star’s superlaser left moviegoers in awe. In <em>Attack of the Clones</em>, that awe was replaced by disgust. Fans were in an uproar about the blatantly fake landscapes, sticky character movements, and the digitized characters and sets. It kept fans from being immersed in the beautiful world of <em>Star Wars</em>. In short, they weren’t transported to a galaxy far, far away.</p>

<p>But bashing <em>Attack of the Clones</em> is beating a dead horse. Everyone at Lucasfilm and Industrial Lights and Magic—a subdivision of Lucasfilm and the studio you work for—has learned from it. It’s not like you didn’t know what you were doing. What ended up onscreen is exactly what George Lucas was aiming for: he wanted the world’s first all-digital film (a lofty goal in the yesteryear of 2002). It must have been hard work, and I have to give you and your team serious props for being able to bring things to life with the tech you had available at that time. </p>

<p>That being said, the animation work on <em>Attack of the Clones</em> – which used to be my favorite thing – is now my biggest complaint. The interactions between actor and green screen are flat and lifeless, almost as if the actors had to move slowly enough to keep pace with the rendering of the backgrounds. Whenever we have a shot of an actor walking next to a computer-generated character, there’s a sluggishness which is hard to shake. </p>

<p>The slightly-off movements of digitized characters is a blatant distraction, too. Such is the case when Obi-Wan mounts the Reek. The transition when Obi-Wan jumps and sticks the landing is just cartoonish. He practically flies. There’s no struggle—you know, the kind of struggle you’d expect when someone tries to climb on top of an angry alien rhinoceros. </p>

<p>But the best example of the shoddy animation work has to be when we get our first glimpse of the clone army marching into formation. Their walking has no weight. The small subtleties of the human body in motion are completely missing. It’s the stuff you just can’t capture without advanced mocap suits, which you didn’t have, and which make the clone army look like they’re gliding across the ground into the Republic Gunship. If you’ve seen <em>The Force Awakens</em> trailer, you’ll agree that the snippet of Stormtroopers stepping into position (real human extras in costume) already feels more authentic than what we saw with the clone army. </p>

<p>I understand you did your best. You’ve gotten a lot more slack than you deserve. <em>Attack of the Clones</em> was a digital breakthrough, and paved the way for many of the digital advancements that have been made since. But there <em>is</em> such a thing as too much of a good thing. Your effects stripped away any sense of realism, and a with a film featuring Hayden Christensen in a lead role, believability is already a concern.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Phantom Menace</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/15/the-phantom-menace.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ThePhantomMenace" />
    <published>2015-12-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/15/the-phantom-menace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I wonder how things could have turned out if you had just said no, Rick. If you had listened to your gut and challenged George Lucas. Deep down you must have known his ideas were contrary to everything that made Star Wars such a beloved cultural institution in the first place. In an ideal world, there would be a whole new generation of Star Wars fans looking back at the prequels with the same level of reverence as the original trilogy. Instead, with <em>The</em> <em>Phantom Menace</em>, we get a baffling nightmare chock-full of half-baked political ideas, characters too thin to even be considered one-dimensional, and zero consistency in the internal logic of the plot.  </p>

<p>I understand there&#39;s a certain level of redundancy in critiquing the prequels in our post-Red Letter Media world, but I&#39;ll ask you to bear with me. Rewatching <em>Phantom</em> for the first time in at least twelve years, what flew over my head as a child served only to confuse and irritate me as an adult. It even got to the point where, an hour in, I had to send a series of increasingly desperate texts to a friend in an attempt to piece together the story. I began to feel like the embattled detective in a film noir, face to face with a massive conspiracy, desperately trying to find a connection between seemingly disparate elements. But instead of having a grand &quot;Eureka!&quot; moment, I came away sad and dispirited.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s what I think I know: a conflict has been staged by future-evil-emperor Palpatine in order to gain political power. But, past that, the whole thing begin to fall apart. Why would the Trade Federation, a merchant coalition, be interested in (and even having the means of) launching a full scale planetary invasion? Furthermore, what incentive would the Trade Federation have for attacking Naboo? They don&#39;t know that they&#39;re inadvertently helping Palpatine, and don&#39;t really seem to get anything out of the deal. Why does a disguised Palpatine insist that Queen Amidala sign a treaty legalizing her planet&#39;s invasion when that very action foils his plan? (By the way, as someone who studies criminal law, I&#39;m pretty sure forcing someone to sign a consent agreement does not equate to consent—even in a galaxy far, far away). And, most importantly, why do the Jedi let Jar Jar Binks tag along instead of abandoning him the first chance they get?</p>

<p>That covers about the first 20 minutes. I could go on, but you surely get the gist. A weak story could theoretically be overlooked if <em>Phantom Menace</em>&#39;s biggest problem wasn&#39;t everything else. Consider Liam Neeson, who looks like he wants to crawl into bed every time he&#39;s onscreen,and delivers his lines with the enthusiasm of a fast food drive-thru attendant. Or Natalie Portman, who seems like she was injected with animal tranquilizers during the climactic battle.  </p>

<p>And what about the mind-numbing action sequences, where our heroes fight cannon fodder without even coming close to being in danger—over and over and <em>over</em> until I began howling gibberish and yanking out fistfuls of hair. If our protagonists look like they can&#39;t be bothered when their lives are on the line, than neither can I. Not even the two-on-one fight with Darth Maul excites, despite some occasionally impressive choreography. Since we know absolutely nothing about any of the participants, the whole thing feels like an elaborate Cirque-Du-Soleil performance rather than the life and death struggle it&#39;s supposed to be.  </p>

<p>George Lucas has seemed to surround himself with people too afraid to raise dissenting opinions. I wish I knew why you didn&#39;t make the most of your position, maybe try to salvage some of the wonderment and originality that got buried beneath all the nonsense. Maybe just tell him that having racist Asian caricatures as the villains wouldn&#39;t add to the film&#39;s lasting appeal. Or that the mess of a story is alienating to both children and adults alike. Or that the whole thing just feels lifeless and lacks the spark that made the originals endure for long as they have.  </p>

<p>Sad to say, Rick, some of the blame for how this all turned out ultimately rests in your hands.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Return of the Jedi</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/14/return-of-the-jedi.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ReturnoftheJedi" />
    <published>2015-12-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/14/return-of-the-jedi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>All you had say was: “No, George.”</p>

<p>That is one of the prerogatives of being a co-writer—you can just say no. Because those fucking Ewoks are the first step on a slippery slope that leads to—well, you know who.</p>

<p>Somewhere in the midst of writing <em>Return Of The Jedi,</em> your collaborator lost contact with what made the first two Star Wars movies more than the sum of their individual parts. As his writing partner you had an opportunity to halt this particular cancer—before it metastasized. If you had just reminded him of the works in which he found his initial inspiration—Kurosawa’s <em>Hidden Fortress</em>, John Ford westerns, the 30’s <em>Flash Gordon serials, _Metropolis</em>, the Harryhausen <em>Sinbad</em> films—he may have seen the error of his ways. Because, while all of these films share a basic earnestness and an often fantastical tone, they were never created specifically for children. </p>

<p>Certainly children could (and did) enjoy all of the various Star Wars properties, but they enjoyed them in the same way that they would have enjoyed Edgar Rice Burroughs or Greek Myths. On one level, they were simple adventure stories: populated by monsters and heroes and whatever subtext existed could be happily ignored. But trying to square the circle of films that feature planet destroying technology <em>and</em> a cloying, rabbit-eared buffoon requires a defter pen than the one your partner wielded—and that really was where you should have stepped in, Lawrence.</p>

<p>When <em>Return Of The Jedi</em> was released in 1983, I had just turned 21—yet it was still clear to me that something had gone astray. It wasn’t difficult to pin down the exact moment, either. </p>

<p>When Leia first encounters the Ewoks about halfway through ROTJ, the unsettling cuteness that had just marginally tainted the first two films—from Jawas to Yoda to R2-D2—really kicked in. Up to that point, <em>Return Of The Jedi</em> had managed to maintain a goofy weekly serial vibe with bits like the stop motion <strong>Rancor</strong> and Jabba getting hoisted on his own petard by Slave Leia™. These beats were perfectly consistent with the tenor of the first two films. But then you and your co-writer began to construct a Frankenstein’s monster—grafting a one-note tribe of children’s discarded plushies onto a relatively complex space opera. It was as if, in a coke-fuelled haze of the likes of which defined American filmmaking in the late seventies, one of your buddies (maybe Francis Ford or Mr. Schrader) dared you to find a place to insert a rag-tag band of cannibal teddy bears into this magnum opus.</p>

<p>Wait. No. That makes Ewoks sound waaaaay more interesting than they are. The truth is they are more like a nicotine stained Chihuahua. Kind of cute from a distance but annoying as hell when you spend more than half a minute in their presence.</p>

<p>The problem with the second half of <em>Return Of The Jedi</em>, which is the same problem that plagues the films that came after, is that they lost the thread; they occupied a tonal space that was completely at odds with the original concept. Neither beast nor fowl, the two different approaches never coalesced. Instead, this fundamental discordance infected what came afterwards—to the extent that, in trying to reconcile the completely irreconcilable halves, they collapsed into an orgy of mismatched pairings: Senate trade deliberations attended by Bugs Bunny with a speech impediment;  a tow-headed Ani growing up into a monster that slaughters a roomful of small children.</p>

<p>All I can really say Lawrence is that I wish you had bullied your pal a little bit and made him <em>pick a fucking lane</em>. Then maybe all the pointless vitriol and hand wringing of the last decade could have been avoided.</p>

<p>I’ve always thought that the cultural significance of the Star Wars films is more deep and meaningful than the actual films themselves. The world they hint at is fascinating but it sort of feels like a tour of Rome with a really shitty guide: you can see the coliseum off in the distance, but you never get to see it close up, to feel the age of the marble, to smell the blood baked into the ancient sand. And the Ewoks and everything they presaged feels like being herded into a junk shop filled with keychain tchotchke versions of the real buildings you’ll never get to experience.</p>

<p>Still. I’m really stoked about December 17<sup>th</sup> .</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Empire Strikes Back</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/13/the-empire-strikes-back.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheEmpireStrikesBack" />
    <published>2015-12-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/13/the-empire-strikes-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve wanted to write some version of this letter for a long time.</p>

<p>This is probably not the most original insight, but I’ve long maintained that the stature of the entire Star Wars saga is due mainly to the halo effect caused by <em>The Empire Strikes Back.</em> I’m not casting aspersions on all of the other films – <em><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/12/star-wars.html">Star Wars</a></em>, specifically, is of course its own, different kind of masterpiece – but, let’s be honest: ever since <em>Empire</em>, the <em>Star Wars</em> movies have been a study in diminishing returns. And that downward trend coincides with one obvious event: the end of your involvement as producer.</p>

<p>As you know, much of the producer’s job is to say no. Whether it’s budget, schedule, or the worst tendencies of a filmmaker, a good producer keeps a holistic view of a project and reigns in anything that threatens the original vision. If necessity is the mother of invention, then it could be argued that a producer’s duty is to sometimes force necessity—to create boundaries that force creative decisions.</p>

<p>But I’m not writing this letter to bitch about what happened after George Lucas surrounded himself with spineless yes-men. I’m writing to praise <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em>, a film I can comfortably say is nearly <em>perfect</em>.</p>

<p><em>Empire</em> is that rare occurrence that results from every decision being right. So let’s talk a few of them out.</p>

<p>First of all, this film <em>moves</em>. It benefits from the heavy (if seemingly effortless) lifting that <em>Star Wars</em> did in establishing the universe. With the world-building and character introductions out of the way, <em>Empire</em> hits the ground running at a full sprint and never lets up. As a precursor of things to come, about a minute after we catch up with Luke, he gets his face smashed in and is dragged off to a cave (of course, this was also a necessary event, to explain the scars Mark Hamill received from a car accident between films). The intended message comes through loud and clear: no one is safe. We’re in darker territory than <em>Star Wars.</em> </p>

<p>This is made even more clear by the decision to reverse the plot structure of <em>Star Wars</em>, placing the big, show-stopping battle in the first act instead of the third. This establishes the fact that <em>Empire</em> is essentially an extended chase sequence, with not a lot of time to slow down for long expository exchanges. Thank god.</p>

<p>The go-for-broke narrative works its way into the performances as well. Leigh Brackett and Lawrence Kasdan amp up the exchanges, particularly between Han Solo and Princess Leia, giving them a classic Hollywood screwball comedy zing (not surprising, considering Brackett’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0102824/">bona fides</a>). Re-watching Harrison Ford and Carrie Fisher exchange insults, I could imagine director Irvin Kershner using <em>His Girl Friday</em> as a reference point for his actors: talk as fast as you can, and force the audience to try and keep up. There’s no hand-holding here—we don’t need it anymore (strangely, this approach was jettisoned for <em>Return of the Jedi</em>, whose first 30 minutes is nothing <em>but</em> a series of character reintroductions.)</p>

<p>Speaking of Kershner, I’m not sure how involved you were in selecting him as director, Gary, but it was a very smart move. <em>Empire</em> is the most well-directed of all six <em>Star Wars</em> films—by a country mile. But it’s not his visual flair that wins the day (even though <em>Empire</em> is also the best-looking film of the series), it’s his focus on the basics: performance and character. As an outsider to this cinematic universe, Kershner was able to hone-in on what he knew how to do best, which was to push out all the superfluous crap that traditionally clogs up storytelling (c.f. <em>The Phantom Menace</em>).  </p>

<p>This kind of laser-sharp attention is what makes Yoda work as the heart and soul of the film.  <em>Empire</em> has its share of action centerpieces (the extended lightsaber duel between Luke and Vader has never been topped in emotional intensity) and mind-blowing plot twists (yes, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/10/how-to-avoid-the-star-wars-syndrome.html"><em>that</em></a> one), but Yoda is what gives the film its depth. I can only guess at your reaction when you saw that the emotional heft of your production was going to rest on the performance of a 3-foot tall muppet, but whatever reluctance (or sheer terror) you may have felt was for naught. And your faith in Kershner was rewarded, as he treated Yoda the only way he knew how: as an actual character. This might sound obvious, but Yoda’s subsequent appearances have proven that the presence of muppeteer Frank Oz is not enough to make him work onscreen. Again, it comes down to decisions – character and performance – and they were perfect.</p>

<p>I could go on – the ingenious cliffhanger with Han Solo, edited to look like a possible last-minute rescue; the way you showed just enough of Darth Vader to prove there’s a human inside the armour – but I’m going to leave you with a simple thanks. </p>

<p>Thank you for helping assemble – and then <em>trusting</em> – the production team to make their own decisions. Thank you for having the faith in the audience’s ability to keep up. But most importantly, thank you for having the backbone to keep George Lucas disciplined. Because no one has since, and that’s why <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> is the only perfect <em>Star Wars</em> film.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Star Wars</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/12/star-wars.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StarWars" />
    <published>2015-12-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/12/star-wars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Before I’d ever even seen <em>Star Wars</em> (which I begrudgingly admit was less than 48 hours ago), your character was my entry point into the story. As the only little girl in my neighbourhood, when the boys wanted to play <em>Star Wars</em>, I always had to be Princess Leia. I wasn’t a fan of dolls, or dresses, or princesses. Princesses sit around in castles looking pretty, waiting for princes. I wanted to be the <em>Bionic Woman</em>. But when the boys told me Princess Leia was smart, and she gets to shoot a gun, fight bad guys <em>and</em> tell Han Solo off, it seemed like a gig I was born for.</p>

<p>I have a feeling you know what I’m talking about.</p>

<p>Coming to the <em>Star Wars</em> universe at this very late date has had its disadvantages. Even though I’ve only seen the first film in the series, I’m all-too-aware of the plot, the characters, the relationships, and the minutiae. The franchise’s popularity is just too ubiquitous <em>not</em> to. When I sat down to watch <em>Episode IV</em> for the very first time the other night, I knew I would struggle to maintain objectivity. So I imagined myself as a kid in the Seventies (which I was), seeing <em>Star Wars</em> for the first time. What would I have laughed at? What would I have found exciting, or scary, or confusing? Would I have understood the stakes? The relationships? The very concept of The Force? Who would I consider the hero of the story? </p>

<p>Here’s how my kid-brain would have broken it down: Droids and Wookies = funny, Darth Vader = bad, Obi Wan = pretty much Santa with a light saber, Luke = kind of goofy, Han Solo = kind of a dick, Storm Troopers = useless,  Cantina Bar =  cool, The Force = …uh, I’m still not really sure what the Force is. But then there’s Princess Leia, and Princess Leia = <em>awesome!</em> Seriously. Right from the get-go she insults Darth Vader, she cleverly plans her own rescue by hiding a message in R2D2, she gets tortured but doesn’t give anything up, and when she gets out she chides her rescuers for sucking at rescuing her. Then, when they’re stuck in the trash compactor, she figures out how to brace it open, and when her planet gets destroyed she keeps calm and carries on, shoots tons of bad guys, and, yes, she tells Han Solo off. A lot. She’s in control, she’s a rebel, and she’s got attitude. </p>

<p>Obviously, she’s the hero. </p>

<p>To be honest, over the last several decades, I never really felt I was missing out by not seeing the <em>Star Wars</em> movies. I appreciate their pop-cultural significance, I respect the ingenuity that went into them, and I understand why they are so beloved by so, so many. I love great sci-fi, and action movies, too, and I now know why this one is considered to be the ultimate. It was fun, and thrilling and I really did feel like a kid watching it; I managed to experience the excitement, suspense, and camaraderie of joining this ragtag group of misfits as they tried to take down a ruthless dictator intent on world domination. </p>

<p>As far as stories go, however, these aren’t necessarily the ones that grab me by the gut. I’ve always been more intrigued by reality—in seeing the good and evil of regular people played out in all its awkward, hilarious, pathetic wretchedness.
I have a feeling you know what I’m talking about.</p>

<p>Viewing this movie for the first time as an adult means that it comes with a little bit of backstory. Through your hilariously frank autobiographies <em>Postcards</em> <em>From</em> <em>the Edge,</em> and <em>Wishful Drinking</em>, I know about your upbringing, your bipolar disorder, your drug addiction, relationships, and unease with your <em>Star Wars</em> related-fame. As much as I tried to watch <em>A New Hope</em> through a kid’s eyes, I couldn’t separate what I know about you, the person, with what I saw in your portrayal of Leia. And maybe that’s why I loved you so much in this role. </p>

<p>You were 19 years-old when you made this movie, with many of your life’s biggest obstacles and triumphs still ahead of you. And yet you were able to give Leia a sophistication, determination, and playful cynicism that was well beyond your years. It’s a role that, for better or for worse, has defined your career, and it’s impossible to imagine anyone else coming even close. </p>

<p>I do plan on watching <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> and <em>Return of the Jedi</em> (in their unadulterated, pre-’97, VHS versions, by decree of C. Redmond,  C. Tourangeau, and J. Young), mainly because I want to see what else you bring to Leia. I may even watch the rest of the series, if only so I can get to see you play Leia in <em>The Force Awakens</em> with some context. Or instead I may just continue to follow your brilliant, <a href="http://time.com/4137685/carrie-fisher-star-wars-the-force-awakens-good-morning-america-interview/">DGAF publicity</a> for the movie. </p>

<p>Either way, it’s obvious to me that you’re still the hero.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Youth</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/11/youth.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Youth" />
    <published>2015-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/11/youth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Youth</em> is a film that is difficult to assess, at least in conventional terms. It remains resolutely surreal throughout the whole of its run time. Your affinity for Fellini-esque discursion makes it difficult to discuss your intentions in concrete terms. What I can say with some certainty is that it provoked a strong emotional reaction, although it’s a little difficult to identify exactly what those emotions are. Regret perhaps. Certainly sadness, a little bit of hope, and a truckload of melancholy.</p>

<p>More than anything else <em>Youth</em> explores what happens when an artist is forced to come to terms with the inexorable passage of time—and whether that necessarily means a diminishment in their capacity to create and see the world in ways that are vital and interesting. </p>

<p>Michael Caine—whose character the film revolves around—plays an emotionally remote, recently retired symphony conductor. He shares a couple of what should be idyllic weeks at a Swiss spa with Harvey Keitel—an octogenarian director. There are several other unique personalities in residence, including Paul Dano and Rachel Weiz. The cast is, with a couple of exceptions, interesting and eclectic—especially Jane Fonda in a harrowingly accurate portrayal of what happens to aging women when shaped by the exigencies of Hollywood.</p>

<p>More a series of loosely connected vignettes than anything else, <em>Youth</em> depends upon a consistency in tone, rather than narrative cohesion, to maintain contact with its characters. The film maintains a delicate tension between hope and regret throughout—a constant push and pull between the idea of a life utterly wasted and the ephemeral rewards a creative existence sometimes allows. Michael Caine in particular seems to view his past with an ambiguity that belies his apparent success, whereas Keitel plays an eighty-year-old man who still (seemingly) remains completely passionate about his vocation. </p>

<p>The rest of the film explores some of the more absurd obsessions that creative people suffer from: relentless self regard, a kind of fetishizing of beauty that is adolescent and unpleasantly instrumental, and crippling self doubt. This all dovetails with a couple of mundane, and brutally honest, moments that pull the characters back into a less esoteric version of reality.</p>

<p>Paul Dano, in a small but vital counterpoint to the more elderly cast, manages to create an enigmatic and consistently interesting arc with a character that would have likely been cartoonish in lesser hands. He is really something special, at least partially because what he manages to achieve is so opaque and resistant to analysis. His performance is both surprising and also seemingly effortless.</p>

<p>The music in <em>Youth</em> is affecting and masterfully placed—both the incidental and the diegetic pieces. The orchestral dénouement, which would otherwise sound hopelessly sentimental, was so extraordinary it obliterated whatever resistance I may have had to its obvious manipulation.   </p>

<p>While I found some of the heightened and deliberately theatrical moments a little difficult to swallow, the entire film still managed to connect in an insightful way, in part because the visual conceits—both the surreal and, in a couple of instances, the brutally real—cohered so beautifully. And at the end I was left regretting how quickly the lights came up. As much as this may be an art house film, it is a far more enriching experience if you allow it to be one of the heart rather than the head.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Star Wars Week</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/11/star-wars-week.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StarWarsWeek" />
    <published>2015-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/11/star-wars-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Review, we will, a film each day until The Force Awakens!</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to Avoid the Star Wars Syndrome</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/10/how-to-avoid-the-star-wars-syndrome.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HowtoAvoidtheStarWarsSyndrome" />
    <published>2015-12-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/10/how-to-avoid-the-star-wars-syndrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In the Star Wars universe, it’s called manifest destiny. But on this planet, it’s just lazy storytelling.</p>

<p>Once upon a time, in a theatre far, far away (from this writer, anyway, born in small-town Alberta in 1983), a movie came out that simultaneously thrilled and shocked the world. <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> is widely considered the high point of the most beloved franchise in movie history, and remains the gold standard against which sequels are measured. So why have so many storytellers taken the exact wrong lesson from a movie filled with countless technical accomplishments and visceral pleasures?</p>

<p>When Darth Vader reveals to Luke Skywalker (shortly after slicing off his hand) that they share the same blood, it’s a barely-foreshadowed brain-buster that seems to make little-to-no sense in the galaxy-spanning story. So incredulous was the claim that, even after wrapping up the trilogy, George Lucas decided he needed another three films just to make sure that the overly convenient plot-twist didn’t go down as the most cosmic coincidence of all-time. Lucas has claimed that the pre-occupation of father and son, and the ways in which we forge our identities through family relations, has been his sole focus from the very start. No need to play in this billion dollar sandbox any longer, <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/business-20146942">thank you very much</a>. </p>

<p>But the idea of making the hero and villain related has become so ubiquitous in recent years, you’d think it’s an official step along The Hero’s Journey. And in fact, much of the blame could no doubt be traced back to Joseph Campbell and <em>The Hero with 1000 Faces</em>, which Lucas drew from in order to build his archetypes and make his space opera relatable. But archetype is just the well-spoken cousin of <em>stereo</em>type, and when a media-saturated world is keeping up with Lucas <em>and</em> the Kardashians, a shortcut to depth is too often forced through family ties.</p>

<p>Take the latest James Bond film, <em>Spectre,</em> as one of the most egregious recent examples (spoiler-waring). To one-up the emotional climax in <em>Skyfall</em>, which is accomplished through a symbolic maternal relationship, the only direction the filmmakers felt they could go was to double-down with daddy issues, shared between Bond and his nemesis. Well, phew. I don’t know about you, but I’m finally ready to enjoy the past 50 years of James Bond knowing every world-threatening event was the evil brainchild of a jilted brother.  The series would just be silly otherwise.</p>

<p>Television is just as guilty of committing these sins. Everything from <em>24</em> to <em>Alias</em> has been reduced, at some point, to a Thanksgiving-dinner squabble played out with nuclear launch codes. Not to mention all the blockbuster franchises that have relied on a family twist to either shock us, or try to squeeze out renewed sympathy—from <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em>, to <em>Indiana Jones and the Crystal Skull</em>, to <em>A Good Day to Die Hard</em>, etc. Recent North American democracies are dominated by family dynasties, from The Bushes, to The Clintons, and now The Trudeaus.  We’ve surrendered the everyman element that makes elections and action adventures relatable. It’s no fun imagining that our heroes are only heroic because of nepotism—we get enough of that in real life.</p>

<p>And in case there are any doubts that this trend links back to the original <em>Star Wars</em> trilogy, look no further than the groan (and barf) -inducing revelation that Princess Leia is actually Luke Skywalker’s twin sister. I may have been born the year <em>Return of the Jedi</em> came out, but I can guarantee that golden bikini buzz-kill plot twist wasn’t to thank. Write this down, everyone. Family stories, good; family twists, bad.</p>

<p>I can (almost) look back and laugh at such an ill-conceived plot point. But it’s not so funny when it’s inspiring so many modern stories. There’s a hell of a lot to learn from those original movies, but family dynamics aren’t one of them.Maybe if Darth Vader had been rejected from art school, the series would have been just as good. Better, actually. He doesn’t need to be Winston Churchill’s dad for me to care.</p>

<p>I hope J.J. Abrams takes note.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>I Smile Back</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/8/i-smile-back.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ISmileBack" />
    <published>2015-12-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/8/i-smile-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In <em>I Smile Back</em> you have written a direct, if unintentional, rebuke to mumblecore bullshit like Greta Gerwig and Noah Baumbach’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/9/4/mistress-america.html"><em>Mistress America</em></a>. Where the latter is coy and hides its arch and ultimately empty purpose behind layers of artifice, <em>I Smile Back</em> just spits it intentions right in your eye.</p>

<p>Sarah Silverman is not high on my list of actresses that I ever expected to admire. But in <em>I Smile Back</em>, Silverman displays the same fearlessness that Charlize Theron so readily employed in 2003’s <em>Monster</em>. There is, however, an ambiguity to Silverman’s performance that is finely tuned. Is she simply someone who suffers from a quiet but profound mental illness? Or has she succumbed to an unrepentant self-indulgence that is only made more unpalatable by her state of cartoonish privilege?</p>

<p>This is a film and a performance that has one thing on its mind—an unsentimental portrayal of just how ugly and existentially empty life can be, even in what seem to be idyllic circumstances. And if that is not necessarily an original concept, the depth and unflinching nature of this film certainly holds it apart from its lesser brethren. </p>

<p>One of the most interesting aspects of a film that is otherwise episodic and choppy—the narrative concerns itself far more with chipping away at the core of Silverman’s character than any specific plot points—is how often the tropes inherent to films about addiction and recovery are subverted. Each time the usual event occurs—reuniting with an absent father or the now clichéd epiphany about how some behaviors are destructive not only to the person engaged in them but to everyone attached to that person—the film turns away from what is expected. Instead we have a scene of a drunken Silverman masturbating on her young daughter’s bedroom floor, while holding a teddy bear. <em>I Smile Back</em> is filled with moments just like that.</p>

<p>The unsettling core of the whole project is the effort made to present Silverman’s illness as part of her character rather than the whole of it. <em>I Smile Back</em> refuses to shift the weight entirely off of the protagonist’s shoulders despite her obvious and very real illness. It is here that the film treads on some dangerous but important ground: it understands that while mental illness is tangible and real there comes a point that whatever the initial circumstance, choices we make often have irrevocable consequences. And that no one, especially when children are involved, has carte blanche—however unfair the circumstances of their existence.</p>

<p><em>I Smile Back</em> is a vaccination against a particular kind of Oprah-esque, feel-good nonsense that is often employed in portrayals of addiction and depression. It is also a tremendous performance by a woman playing an almost entirely unsympathetic character. Silverman makes a strong case for herself as a modern day female equivalent to Travis Bickle. Both are repugnant and still also caught in the throes of something they can’t really control or understand.</p>

<p>I believe Sarah Silverman would have made John Cassavetes a happy man, and I can’t think of higher praise for an actress. You gave her the raw material to make that hyperbolic praise difficult to refute, Paige, and while I won’t thank you for it, I still respect the hell of out what you both managed to create.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>