<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-04T01:13:17Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Terminator: Genysis</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/7/4/terminator-genysis.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Terminator:Genysis" />
    <published>2015-07-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/7/4/terminator-genysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It would be unfair to place the responsibility for the fiasco that is <em>Terminator: Genisys</em> entirely at your feet. It’s a film whose shortcomings are so varied, so composite, that they defy easy categorization. The special effects are degenerative—somehow less thrilling, less real, than they were twenty-three (!) years ago in <em>Terminator 2: Judgment Day.</em> The script unfolds like something the producers acquired through Fiverr—it has all the nuance and surprise of a crowdsourced piece of fan fiction. The production feels small-scale, constrained, cheap. Even the music – which occasionally pays tribute to Brad Feidel’s clamorous carillon theme – is so vacuous and forgettable that the film may as well have been scored by radio static. </p>

<p>All of this contributes to the feeling that <em>Terminator: Genisys</em> is nothing more than a great big B-movie (and not in the efficient, self-aware manner that that first <em>Terminator</em> was a B-movie). And what really solidifies the film’s lack of ambition is that you, Ronna, <em>cast</em> it like a B-movie. Amongst all its deficiencies, this is the most grievous: the lifelessness and lack of charisma that the actors bring to the screen. It’s almost impossible to comprehend. </p>

<p>Impossible, because there are Oscar-winners among the cast. And some terrific veteran character actors. Yet, together, they form a sort of tepid mass of humanity that doesn’t inspire even the smallest bit of affection (with one important exception, which, though obvious, I’ll wait to explain). </p>

<p>Yes, Emilia Clarke looks a bit like Linda Hamilton, and on <em>Game of Thrones</em> is able to conjure a matronly aura. But here she is doing a mere impression of being matronly, stuck somewhere between the Sarah Connor of the first film – a perpetually terrified damsel in distress – and the Sarah Connor of the second, all sinewy muscle and desperate authority. Clarke just doesn’t have the presence or the range to pull it off. </p>

<p>Jason Clarke, on the other hand, possesses...something. At least everyone who saw <em>Zero Dark Thirty</em> seems to think so. But when he’s given more than ten minutes of screen-time, his <em>something</em> is proven to be a finite resource. In <em>Dawn of the Planet of the Apes</em>, he was overshadowed not just by the troupe of CGI monkeys, but by virtually every other human performer as well. Here, as John Connor, the inspiring military leader who saves the human race, he inspires little more than indifference.</p>

<p>But the real centerpiece of this bromidic cast is Jai Courtenay, who now boasts a perfect two-for-two record in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/2/15/a-good-day-to-die-hard.html">ruining beloved action franchises</a>.</p>

<p>I will admit that Michael Biehn, who originated the role of Kyle Reese, is no Laurence Olivier. Still, there was something in the intense sincerity with which he delivered every line, that made him seem like he came from the future, like he really was sent back on a dangerous mission. He delivered every line like it was a matter of life and death. </p>

<p>Courtney delivers his lines like he <em>is</em> dead. To say that he has no presence is inaccurate. He is a void. Like a black hole, he swallows the charisma of every orbiting body. He simply doesn’t seem to occupy quantum space as we know it. He is a man-shaped nothingness. There might as well be a square-jawed, bro-shaped hole in the movie screen; revealing, behind him, all the pulleys that control the curtain, all the wiring for the surround-sound speakers. His reaction when Sarah Connor tells him the story of her parents’ death (“The cabin blew up!”) is the stuff that Internet memes are made from; if you’ve ever wanted to see what a man’s face looks like when he’s conscious of how his eyebrows are moving, just watch that scene.  </p>

<p>But this isn’t some sprawling Robert Altman film. What do all these peripheral folks matter
? You see <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/12/jurassic-world.html">Jurassic Park movies</a> for the dinosaurs, and you see Terminator movies for the Terminators. And, yes, there at the center of it all is Arnold Schwarzenegger, who, as he has aged, as his hair has greyed and delts have deflated, has somehow managed to become even more charismatic. </p>

<p>And that’s the miraculous thing about this fifth Terminator flick: that a franchise founded on the very inhuman blankness of it’s titular character could turn its blank, inhuman antagonist/protagonist into a complicated, evolving, sympathetic character. But it’s also the disappointing thing. Because this isn’t one of those sequels to a sequel to a sequel that has nothing new to offer the convoluted mythology. <em>Terminator: Genisys</em> introduces the very compelling idea of an aging Terminator confronting its obsolescence (“old, but not obsolete,” the T-800 keeps insisting), and Arnie brings that idea to life with a rather remarkable performance (every single ounce of charm this movie possesses is his). But the film is too busy trying to hit every action flick beat (specifically, every action flick <em>cliché</em>) to give that part of the story the attention is deserves. </p>

<p>So what are we left with? A series of inane expository conversations occasionally interrupted by some of the most unexciting, unimaginative action sequences in recent film history. Which wouldn’t be so interminable if the actors in the middle of those sequences had more charm than the cars and trucks and helicopters that were blowing up.</p>

<p>All it takes to elevate second-rate material is to put a magnetic presence in the middle of it. Arnold Schwarzenegger knows this. He’s built an entire career on it. It’s a shame you chose to surround him with such a deadly-dull gang of supporting players.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Magic Mike XXL</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/7/2/magic-mike-xxl.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MagicMikeXXL" />
    <published>2015-07-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/7/2/magic-mike-xxl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You&#39;d think a movie like <em>Magic Mike XXL</em> would be the ultimate platform for misogynistic boasting, but it was the complete opposite thanks largely to you.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve been a fan of your no-bullshit attitude since you donned the red highlights as Fish Mooney in <em>Gotham</em>. Maybe this is why you were the perfect choice to literally lead the charge, as the emcee for a group of retiring male dancers looking for one last hoorah in the spotlight at Myrtle Beach&#39;s premiere stripper convention.</p>

<p>Frankly, you saved the movie. Aside from the mesmerizing dancing that defied all laws of physics (the human body shouldn&#39;t be able to do what Channing Tatum can do), <em>Magic Mike XXL</em> chooses to spend several chunks of screen time on dialogue that goes nowhere. You can only handle so much frat boy flirting before you tune out.</p>

<p>But when you talk, you command attention, rivalling even the ass-less-iest of ass-less chaps. I can say this because all your key moments were wedged between pivotal stripping scenes.</p>

<p>When we are introduced to your strange house of male burlesque, you remind the women in attendance that they are <em>queens.</em> If they want to watch men take off their clothes, then they should go right ahead and do it. If they want to have a one night stand with a sculpted stranger, then screw society and its labels. Most importantly, you remind them that <em>women are just like men</em>: they have sexual needs and there is nothing wrong with that.</p>

<p>Your sass and bravado are enough to change the tone of the entire movie. When Matthew McConaughey was the ring leader in <em>Magic Mike</em>, he was flirtatious and coy. He knew the women were there for the men. But with you, it was evident that the men were there for the women.</p>

<p>It was a breath of fresh air to see you stand your ground. When other women buttered at the sight of a naked torso, you saw it as your job. No amount of pelvic gyrations could make you flinch.</p>

<p>It is a shame that <em>Magic Mike XXL</em> fell short. It definitely wasn&#39;t as good as the first (which was surprisingly good). Thankfully, your performance kept me intrigued when penis innuendos couldn&#39;t.</p>

<p><strong>Alright, alright, alright,</strong></p>

<p>Ankit</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ted 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/26/ted-2.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Ted2" />
    <published>2015-06-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/26/ted-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>When kids play with one of your Nerf toys, or adults sit down with your classic board game Clue, their goal is to turn off part of their brains and just enjoy themselves for an hour or two. The same is true of stupid comedies. Maybe this is why it makes sense that you’re a part of the stoner buddy-movie sequel <em>Ted 2</em>. Who would know better than you that sometimes people just want to have fun without searching for some deeper purpose? And yet, surprisingly, there are moments when <em>Ted 2</em> manages to do both.</p>

<p>The original 2012 movie, <em>Ted</em>, was about the bond between man-child John Bennett and his best friend, a stuffed bear who magically came to life when John was 8 years-old. As adults, John and Ted are lovable slackers grappling with the future of their friendship. <em>Ted 2</em> picks up three years after the end of the first film, and focuses on Ted and his brassy wife Tami-Lynn’s attempts to have a child. In order to do so, Ted must go to court to legally establish himself as a living person so that he can be recognized by the government of the United States, and not merely as property.</p>

<p>For a children’s toy company, you took a big Risk (pun wholly intended) participating in a raunchy R-rated flick. Not only do you lend your company name and products to the film, but you’re an integral part of the plot. While Ted’s civil rights trial is heating up, his creeptastic stalker, Donnie (now a janitor at Hasbro), hatches a scheme to rig Ted’s trial so he loses and will be legally considered property. Donnie convinces your CEO to go along with his plot, and to kidnap Ted after the trial. Then Hasbro can dissect him to find out how he became “real” and manufacture billions of Teds. </p>

<p>Sound ridiculous? Of course it is. It’s a movie about a dirty-talking, pot-smoking Teddy bear. But it’s no more ridiculous than your Furby dolls, and people <em>love</em> those stupid things. Writer/Producer/Director Seth MacFarlane goes back to the hilariously vulgar trough that supplied many of the laughs in the first film, including pop culture references, celebrity cameos, and defiant political incorrectness. If homages to films like <em>Jurassic Park</em> and <em>Planes, Trains and Automobile</em>s, scenes of Liam Neeson buying cereal, and Ted sarcastically comparing his struggle to that of Kunta Kinte doesn’t entertain you, it might be better for you to spend your evening playing an endless game of Monopoly (which you should know will invariably end with one of your friends screaming “fuck this!” and flipping the board over).</p>

<p>Even when the film takes a moral stand – and it <em>does</em> make some salient points about human rights and the concept of personhood – it does so with tongue planted firmly in furry cheek. Patrick Stewart’s narration reminds us right at the beginning of the film that “America doesn’t give a shit about anything.” Except, maybe, corporations making money. And you certainly took advantage of your position, Hasbro, showing off many of your products. One of the film’s major locations is the New York Comicon, where you are boldly represented by giant Transformers, Nerf guns, and Play-Doh displays. Usually this kind of brazen product placement sours my palate, but I was too busy laughing at the nerd fight involving characters like Daleks, Gollum, and Doc and Marty from <em>Back to the Future</em>. Patrick Warburton, who reprises his role as the gay dude-bro Guy, shows up dressed exactly as you would expect Patrick Warburton to dress. There’s nothing your aggressive branding could have done to undermine <em>that</em> image.</p>

<p>Even though there’s not much new in this installment, beyond the addition of Amanda Seyfried as Ted’s pot smoking lawyer (and John’s eventual love interest) Samantha, it’s still fun to go slumming in Ted and John’s world—for 115 minutes, at least. Yes, Ted is a CGI invention, but somehow he and Mark Wahlberg manage to have better chemistry than most humans in a buddy-comedy are able to generate. They have a shorthand that feels familiar. They’re the kind of like friends you’d get drunk and play Jenga with—just not very often. Sometimes giving people exactly what they expect isn’t such a bad thing (but as the co-owners of the <em>Transformers</em> movie franchise, I surely don’t have to tell you that).</p>

<p>One of the best things about playing your board games as an adult is that it reminds me of how much fun I had playing them as a kid. In a predictably inappropriate way, <em>Ted 2</em> invoked a similar response. In the 80s, R-Rated comedies –  <em>Fast Times at</em> <em>Ridgemont</em> <em>High, Blues Brothers,</em> <em>Caddyshack</em> –  had something many of today’s R-Rated comedies are missing: a bit of heart. And <em>Ted 2,</em> despite its immaturity and vulgarity, manages to slip in some warm and fuzzies. When Ted’s case makes it to the Supreme Court, his high-profile lawyer (in a cameo that should remain unnamed) reminds him that, “the public doesn’t judge by reason, it judges by emotion.” </p>

<p>So, thanks for all the toys and board games that allowed me to goof off during my childhood, and for contributing to the two hours I wasted on <em>Ted 2</em>.  </p>

<p>But that still doesn’t mean you’re off the hook for what you did to <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/movies/black-widow-gets-replaced-by-captain-america-on-118893025097.html">Black Widow</a>.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Face of An Angel</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/25/the-face-of-an-angel.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheFaceofAnAngel" />
    <published>2015-06-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/25/the-face-of-an-angel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>This will come as no surprise to you, but you don’t actually appear in this movie. I’m not going to let that stop me from wishing you did.</p>

<p>You and director Michael Winterbottom have collaborated so often that you can’t blame me for picturing you as the lead of his latest film, <em>The Face of An Angel</em>. This wannabe sexy thriller takes itself so seriously that it’s almost a comedy. <em>Almost.</em> Unfortunately, we don’t have your deadpan delivery to exaggerate the pomposity of a film about yet another white male having an existential crisis. </p>

<p><em>The Face of An Angel</em> purports to tell the story of the real-life murder of exchange-student Meredith Kercher in Perugia, Italy in 2007. Kercher’s roommate, Amanda Knox, along with Knox’s boyfriend and another man were convicted (and in Knox’ case, eventually acquitted) of the murder—but instead, we suffer alongside Daniel Bruhl (an actor far too talented and interesting to have been wasted on this wank) who, as a filmmaker named Thomas, is searching for an angle from which to tell the story as a movie. Thomas – who is wrestling with dark thoughts about his ex-wife (a starlet who cheated on him with her co-star), and feeling alienated from his young daughter – begins to unravel in his attempts to make sense of the infamous murder case.  </p>

<p>The film starts out cleverly enough, with Thomas meeting Simone, a savvy journalist who has written a book about the case. Simone advises Thomas to write his script as fiction to avoid a lawsuit, telling him there were many things she couldn’t include in her book because they were true. This bit of exposition gives Winterbottom creative license with the story.  Names and locations are substituted, but the details of the notorious case remain the same. </p>

<p>This should have been the first clue that my excitement about a director as skilled as Winterbottom taking on a story as twisted as the Amanda Knox case was perhaps misdirected. </p>

<p>The character of Thomas seems almost to be a proxy for you, Steve—at least the meta-version of you from films like <em>The Trip</em>: smug, prone to jealousy, chases women half his age, an absentee father, known to overindulge. It almost seems like your friend Michael saw this as a comedic role for you, and when you couldn’t commit, he threw his hands up and said, “bugger it all, I’ll just make it a thriller.” </p>

<p>I hope you regret turning it down. Thomas becomes obsessed with telling the story using Dante’s Inferno as a device, which would explain the unintentionally funny CGI demons that attack Thomas in dark cobblestone alleys and his laughably perverse coke-fueled visions, which look like something from an episode of <em>Criminal Minds</em>. Just think of how much fun you would have had filming <em>that!</em> </p>

<p>Thomas has a brief fling with Simone, probably because he’s attracted to how well she delivers exposition (she doesn’t do much else). He enters into a weird relationship with Melanie, a barely-legal student and subdued British version of the Manic Pixie Dream Girl. It would have been a thrill to watch you navigate between these two women with your trademark pretentious incompetence. Instead, we’re subjected to countless scenes of Bruhl brooding in cars, trattorias, and on Tuscan hotel balconies. </p>

<p>Winterbottom seems genuinely interested in reminding us that Sarah (Meredith Kercher’s proxy) was a person, and not just the victim of a sex crime (going so far as to dedicate the film to Kercher). Thomas is forever at odds with the tabloid reporters and TV execs who are intent on exploiting every detail, however salacious, about the schoolgirl’s murder. In these moments – when Thomas interacts with the world-weary, cynical journos – Winterbottom recalls some of the brilliance of his 1997 film <em>Welcome to Sarajevo.</em> Lines like, ”trials are like <em>X-Factor</em>; if they like your face, you win,” are biting and true. But the impact of these statements is immediately undercut by Thomas’ incessant whining about “telling the truth, <em>dammit!</em>” Scenes in which Thomas has to endure a studio exec’s inane feedback are played so flatly they almost disappear. In your hands, Steve, these exchanges would have been just as grating and bloviated, but way more fun to watch. Without your dry comic timing, Winterbottom’s points come across as butthurt complaints instead of cutting observations.</p>

<p>Your inimitable talents would have completely changed the tone of the film, which swings from dull to ridiculous and back again without any sense of irony. You’ve made a tidy living (and a devoted fan base) capitalizing on your innate ability to be comically unselfaware yet tragically self-absorbed. Who better to play a narcissistic filmmaker? All your best roles – Alan Partridge, Tony Wilson in <em>24 Hour Party People</em>, and yourself in <em>Tristram Shandy</em> – are unsympathetic characters who mask their deep insecurities with arrogance. I have every confidence that, with you in the lead, <em>The Face of an Angel</em> would have been a sharp and dark comic meditation on tabloid journalism and the public’s insatiable thirst for scandal. It would also have <em>taken the piss</em> (as you Brits say) out of the self-important filmmakers who fancy themselves truth-tellers. </p>

<p>Unfortunately, your friend Michael just wasn’t in on the joke this time.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Inside Out</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/22/inside-out.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=InsideOut" />
    <published>2015-06-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/22/inside-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You did a lot more than write the screenplay for <em>Inside Out</em>. Along with Ronaldo Del Carmen you also developed the original story and co-directed it. But I want to talk about how <em>Inside Out</em> is structured as a story, so “Co-screenwriter” is going to have to do for now.</p>

<p>See, there’s something about the way <em>Inside Out</em> is constructed that is just so very Pixar. There is no fat on the film – everything is there for a reason, and story ideas that are planted early come to fruition in unexpected but wholly satisfying ways. The emotional crisis of a preteen girl named Riley – told mainly from within her own head where each emotion is a character running the human brain as a day job– is certainly an unexpected concept from a studio that has been focusing lately more on sequels and prequels. You helped create the original <em>Monsters Inc.</em> and the glorious <em>Up</em>, after all. I don’t think it’s in your nature to make something completely unoriginal. </p>

<p>A lot of care and thinking has been put into every moment we see on screen, not matter how small. You can feel the guiding hand of what Ed Catmull detailed in his book about Pixar’s creative process, <em>Creativity Inc.</em>: when a film is in development at Pixar, it is subjected to relentless group discussions where every aspect of it is scrutinized and questioned until what is left is hopefully the purest story possible. Every character, every beat, every turn in <em>Inside Out</em> has been scrutinized by Pixar’s core creative team, whether any of their names appear in the credits or not. Inside and out, <em>Inside Out</em> is every inch a Pixar film – and that’s what caused a bit of a crisis for me as a viewer. </p>

<p>More on that later – let’s look at everything else first.</p>

<p>Being a Pixar production doesn&#39;t just impact story development. Everything single thing on screen is meticulously devised. The production design and working details of Riley’s emotions are both beautiful and hilarious. You’ve spoken before about how much of an influence Hayao Miyazaki’s work has had on you as an artist, and the way you combine—and fully embrace—the everyday drama of life and absurd whimsy, without a need to completely reconcile the two. This makes you perhaps the most Miyazaki-like of Pixar’s directors. The characters that run Riley’s emotions—Joy, Fear, Anger, Disgust, and Sadness—look almost fairy-like, with an oh-so-slight glowing shimmer that follows them (Anger’s head literally shoots flames, adding to the supernatural element). The world of Riley’s consciousness feels like a candy-colored version of the spirit world Miyazaki’s <em>Spirited Away</em>. It has its own social order, rules and characters that all have jobs to do and want things to work the way they’re supposed to because that’s how it’s always been. Like Miyazaki’s spirits, the last thing anyone needs is something upsetting the status quo.</p>

<p>Of all the characters running Riley’s brain, the one who most wants things to never change is Joy. Played with her unique combination of pluck, desperation and maddeningly cheerful aggression, Amy Poehler makes Joy the Leslie Knope of the id. She sees herself as the leader of the five emotions, and is set on making sure Riley’s daily life and memories have the least amount of possible stress. So of course when developing this story, Pete, you made sure that a series of accidents and good intentions gone wrong lead Joy to get tossed from her safe spot in HQ to the wilds of Riley’s subconscious with the one emotion she is least equipped to deal with: Sadness.</p>

<p>This brings me back to my point of crisis. You knew to do this from a story point of view because you’ve done it before: the two quarrelling characters that get tossed from the safety of their privileged position and need to make their way back through a series of obstacles is taken right from the <em>Toy Story</em> playbook (a playbook you also co-wrote). Joy’s constant exasperation with Sadness’s refusal to accept her place and stay out of Joy’s way has much in common with the Woody/Buzz Lightyear dynamic. Both characters here are funny and original—and Phyllis Smith’s voice work as Sadness is at least on par with Poehler’s—but we’ve seen this situation before.</p>

<p>Similarly, the “it’s just a job” take on the inner workings of the human psyche has a decidedly <em>Monsters Inc.</em> bent to it. As these familiar elements came to my mind while watching <em>Inside Out,</em> I questioned whether you and your team had taken the safe route on your journey, choosing the tried and true in place of the actually new. Worried that Pixar’s iterative, group-based story development could be so good at distilling out story impurities that what was left, while pure, was also becoming homogenized, that the personal quirks were being lost to group consensus.</p>

<p>But, put simply, that’s my problem to deal with, not <em>Inside Out</em>’s—I can’t judge a film for what I think might have been there. The only responsibility you and the entire production team have is to the film. If the film works (and it does), then whatever baggage I bring based on your or your studio’s previous works is mine and mine alone. And I think I can see why you wanted to make these familiar choices: you’ve anchored your entire story on the emotional breakdown of an 11-year old girl. That’s a bold choice for what is being sold as a fun night out with those goofy guys from Pixar. You use those familiar elements to pull off quite the balancing act: what Riley is experiencing with Joy and Sadness missing from her psyche is pretty heavy stuff, and probably not what a general audience will be expecting when they purchase their tickets. Emotional shutdown isn’t usually associated with a fun time at the movies, after all.</p>

<p>I’m not going to complain if you want to support a story this potentially upsetting (especially for those close in age to Riley, not to mention their parents) with elements that make us all feel a little more at ease, or let us know a steady hand is guiding us through the rough terrain. (I will, however, complain just a little bit about the various themed “lands”  in Riley’s brain that felt pre-designed to work in a new Disney attraction – I can already imagine lineups for the “Don’t Touch the Lava” obstacle course.)</p>

<p>When the familiar and the unexpected work in concert, they influence each other. As we invest more in Riley, we imbue every small moment, every reaction she can’t even explain to herself with a weight that most summer blockbusters can’t generate by threatening to destroy the entire planet Earth. And characters that seem introduced only to generate laughs become tragic figures when they realize the role they have to play in Riley’s mental development—a role that is as heartbreaking for their acceptance of it as it is in its inevitability. You had me so hooked on the familiar storytelling that I didn’t even realize how invested I was in Riley’s story – I had my own emotional reaction that I couldn’t explain. </p>

<p>At least not until I could sit back a bit and admire your craft from a distance.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Dope</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/19/dope.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Dope" />
    <published>2015-06-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/19/dope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Dope</em> is as much a cultural artifact as it is a story. An artifact because it often only makes sense in relationship to the films that it depends on to first inform, and prop up, its central premise—movies like <em>Juice</em>, <em>Boys N’ The Hood</em> and especially <em>Menace II Society.</em></p>

<p>These movies all dealt with the limited number of choices that inner city youth face. In the 1990’s the cinematic response to this dearth of choices usually took the shape of nihilistic acceptance, or sometimes defiance followed quickly by tragic consequences. <em>Dope</em> tries to sketch a third option. Bur that new option only makes sense, in this case, when contrasted with what came before. This is not necessarily an ineffectual strategy, but it <em>does</em> depend upon a prior knowledge of the genre, which is a risky approach.</p>

<p><em>Dope</em> certainly begins with real promise. The main characters—a 90’s throwback nerd, a lesbian and a bro-y stick figure who all live in present day Inglewood CA.—aren’t types that conventionally populate the urban youth genre. Not to mention their single unifying principle—membership in the only new wave/thrash band in their zip code. It gave me hope that this might be a different take on an otherwise well-worn premise.</p>

<p>When this trio of high school kids becomes unwittingly embroiled in a drug transaction gone wrong is the moment when you make your first appearance (in this case as a knapsack full of MDMA) and also where the film goes a little off-track. Because McGuffins like yourself (as Hitchcock once described you—the <em>thing</em> that the spy’s are all concerned with but the audience doesn’t really care about) are only useful in very small doses.</p>

<p>In this case you trigger a convoluted narrative involving competing drug gangs, bit-coins, corrupt city officials and some pretty retrograde gender politics. This unnecessary baggage muddies what had begun as a pretty interesting—and sometimes funny—meditation on what it is like to be an outsider in a very specific set of circumstances.  </p>

<p>While <em>Dope</em> seems intent on repudiating the underlining despair present in the films that it structurally mimics, it often falls into the very tropes it wants to undermine. It is, in some significant ways, a prisoner to the kind of inexorable logic that made the earlier films so powerful. They were expressing what seemed to be an unanswerable dilemma for the young men at the center of these stories, and one that also seemed to lack a win/win option. Caine in <em>Menace II Society</em>, Bishop in <em>Juice</em>, Doughboy in <em>Boyz N’ The Hood</em> all end up dead, caught up in lives that are circumscribed by mostly terrible options.  </p>

<p>So when this film starts to lean more heavily on the standards of the genre, especially in the second and third act, those conventions tend to step on the more nuanced approach of the first act. Characters become much less three-dimensional as the story mechanics flatten them out. Plot starts to drive character and the film becomes less organic, more by the numbers.</p>

<p>But there is a lot to like here. Good central performances by a young cast, more than a few sharply observed moments that establish a strong sense of place, and a script that is ambitious and often surprising. Unfortunately, that promise fades away when you, Mr. McGuffin, take centre stage. </p>

<p>Certainly you’re useful as an entry point, a reason for the characters to engage and act. But when you become the focal point of the story, you’re revealed for what you are—a mechanism and nothing more. That kind of exposure means the rest of the film becomes an exercise of moving from a to b to c. </p>

<p>McGuffins, as is true of so many other aspects of cinema (like editing, or the soundtrack, or even the performances), are best when they go unnoticed. Sadly, in <em>Dope</em>, you draw far too much attention to yourself and what could have been a pretty good film is instead reduced to a self-defeating exercise.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jurassic World</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/12/jurassic-world.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=JurassicWorld" />
    <published>2015-06-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/12/jurassic-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re the most famous palaeontologist since Ross from <em>Friends</em>. Which is kind of sad because you’re <em>actually</em> a palaeontologist with years of study under your belt. Your behind-the-scenes presence in all the <em>Jurassic Park</em> releases has helped provide a realistic-ish portrayal of what would happen if humans faced off against dinosaurs. </p>

<p>I say realistic-<em>ish</em> because you yourself admitted that you had to curb your expertise for the sake of entertainment, which is admirable. It’s one thing to be a consultant about dinosaurs, but it’s another to consciously suppress your knowledge for the betterment of the movie. Although, you have to agree, velociraptors are scarier without the feathers. </p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong; your most recent project, <em>Jurassic World</em>, was entertaining as hell. It isn’t every day you get to see an alpha standoff between a genetically altered mega-dinosaur and a T-rex. My inner child pretty much passed out from excitement. </p>

<p>But as entertaining as it was, this showdown is part of the problem. <em>Jurassic World</em> strayed too far away from being a movie about dinosaurs to being a summer blockbuster about “monsters.” </p>

<p>Your input in the original trilogy was based on fact, but <em>Jurassic World</em> had a new twist involving humans tampering with gene-modification to create a new, enhanced species of dinosaur. The film shows us what would happen if that dinosaur was raised in captivity only to escape and wreak havoc on unsuspecting tourists in a prehistoric-themed amusement park (same thing happened when I played <em>Zoo Tycoon: Dinosaur Digs</em>). </p>

<p>It’s the type of ideal scenario for a classic Hollywood monster mash. When our mega dinosaur is loose in the forest and an elite team of soldiers goes in to contain it, the bloodbath that follows closely resembles something out of <em>Alien</em>: lots of screaming and people being flung around. What’s the best way to show this creature is a force to be reckoned with? Throw some collateral damage its way. </p>

<p>That type of arc opens doors for even more clichés, blatant and excessive foreshadowing, and inappropriate moments of comedy and romance that strip away realism and predictable character growth.</p>

<p>I for one enjoyed the minor details you helped provide: the velociraptors, using their hind legs to aggressively climb their prey (similar to hungry hyenas), or the rotting teeth that can be seen when our antagonist dino sniffs out Chris Pratt. I would have liked to see more of that. </p>

<p><em>Jurassic World</em> is definitely entertaining. It’s a summer blockbuster. I get that. And as far as summer blockbusters go, it hit the mark. I had fun watching it, as did my girlfriend (who was there for Chris Pratt). I laughed, felt tense, and even jumped out of my seat a couple of times. If this is the trend that any sequel will follow, I’d be okay with it. I just hope if you are to be attached again, that you’ll have more of a say with the how the movie pans out. </p>

<p>I’m sure the success of <em>Jurassic World</em> will help finance your goal to bring <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/paleontologist-jack-horner-is-hard-at-work-trying-to-turn-a-chicken-into-a-dinosaur/2014/11/10/cb35e46e-4e59-11e4-babe-e91da079cb8a_story.html">Chickenosaurus</a> to life.</p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong><br>
Ankit</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Entourage</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/11/entourage.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Entourage" />
    <published>2015-06-11T19:43:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-11T19:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/11/entourage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Eight seasons and a movie. That’s a long run for any creative endeavour. Just keeping up the energy is a feat in and of itself—especially for something as fundamentally empty as <em>Entourage</em>. The Hollywood adventures of Vinnie Chase and his gang of charisma-free bros—brother and fellow actor Johnny Drama, his manager E, and driver Turtle (I’d name the actors, but let’s not pretend they’ll have any kind of career outside this)—felt like something that warranted three, maybe four seasons. It was always a trifle of a show, and the longer it went on it was obvious that there never was any <em>there</em> there. Nothing. At all. How could you keep returning to mine something that emptied its reserves so long ago?</p>

<p>What became clear to me while watching your movie version of <em>Entourage</em>, though, was that the eight season run is actually the key. In what I can only assume may be the first known instance of cinematic Stockholm Syndrome, at some point you stopped being any kind of observer of your subjects. Instead of viewing them objectively, you started to admire them. You wanted to be them; your own creations became your aspiration. That has to be it. It’s certainly the best way to explain why <em>Entourage</em> is as lazy—and as dumb—as its characters. It takes the easy way out of, well, everything.</p>

<p>On the plus side, I suppose, we do have a bit of a field guide for the lazy auteur.</p>

<p>For example, we finally have an answer to the age old problem of what to do when a writer needs his character to spout exposition, but can’t be bothered to make it in any way a natural part of dialogue: make them non-sequitors! It leads to awesome exchanges like this:</p>

<p>“It’s great Vinnie invited us to is yacht in Ibiza!”<br>
“Yeah. I can’t believe he split up with his wife on their honeymoon!”</p>

<p>Need to introduce a sort-of celebrity that may not be instantly recognizable with an audience whose head isn&#39;t up the ass of Hollywood? Just have Turtle and E engage in call-and-response until the relevant information has been explained in a way that would embarrass the author of an <em>I Can Read</em> book:</p>

<p>&quot;Hey, look!&quot;<br>
&quot;Who&#39;s that?&quot;<br>
&quot;It&#39;s Ronda Rousey!&quot;<br>
&quot;The MMA fighter?&quot;<br>
&quot;Yeah!&quot;</p>

<p>Okay, I get it. Writing is hard. And if anything, <em>Entourage</em> is and always was about things coming easy. I&#39;m not the first one to point this out to you, Doug, but <em>Entourage</em> may be the most conflict-free series to ever grace television and the big screen. HBO&#39;s comedy successors to your time slot, <em>Veep</em> and <em>Silicon Valley</em> both know that there&#39;s little—drama <em>or</em> comedy—in watching characters constantly win at life. </p>

<p>To be fair, Doug, you do seem to understand this on some basic level. In <em>Entourage</em>, you make the most token of gestures towards some sort of conflict: the supposed dramatic crux set up pre-credits is that Vinnie demands to direct the next movie in which he stars. I was willing to ride along; there’s something to be made from the proposal that Vinnie’s hubris will destroy his reputation and take his agent Ari down with him. But then the opening credit sequence concluded with the title “Eight months later.” You skipped over the entire production of the film to get back to … more parties, more luxury porn, and—worst of all—more bro-humour. Like the loathsome depiction of every female character in this movie, I guess I only have myself to blame for thinking things would be different this time.</p>

<p>It did let me watch <em>Entourage</em> in a different light, though. Instead of seeing it only as the not-funny, up-its-own-ass piece of misogynous dreck it most assuredly is, I could also see the self-reflecting prison you had built around yourself. When Vinnie asks Ari (Jeremy Piven, being the one reliable bright spot on the show, returning to erase any good will that remained for his character) for another 10 or so million dollars to finish the film, everyone worries that the movie is in trouble. Maybe it will reveal that, much like Adrienne Grenier, there’s absolutely nothing to Vinnie Chase. And then you go and make the biggest of bone-headed decisions: you show a scene from the actual movie.</p>

<p>That movie is some sort sci-fi reimagining of <em>Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde</em> called, naturally, <em>Hyde</em>. As Ari sits though a rough cut, terrified that he’s about to witness a megaflop, we are treated to <em>Hyde</em>’s opening credits: Vinnie dressed a hooded, kind of Jedi-Knight-cyborg-DJ overseeing what looks to be the rave scene from <em>The Matrix Reloaded</em>. For real. And the thing is, I couldn’t tell if I was supposed to read this as amazing or laughably ridiculous. Okay, I knew it was the latter, but I wasn’t sure what side everyone in <em>Entourage</em> was on.</p>

<p>Thankfully, Doug, you came to the rescue as always with your dialogue designed to explain the scene for all levels of learning impairments. “It’s a masterpiece!” “It’s the best thing he’s ever done!” “This will win at the Golden Globes!” I might have bought this just a little if you hadn’t shown me something that has all the artistic merit of a cut Uwe Boll scene. </p>

<p>When Ari steps up as the champion for <em>Hyde</em>, willing to risk everything to protect its vision, I’m fairly certain I’m not supposed to be siding with the <em>Entourage’s</em> villain, the investor’s son, who wants to reedit <em>Hyde</em> himself purely out of spite because Vinnie stole a girl from him. Anything he does can’t be worse than what we’ve already seen.</p>

<p>So I had a brief-but-actual dilemma: was I watching a movie made by people so blinded by their own reflection that they can no longer tell when they’ve crossed the line into self-parody? Or was I watching a satire <em>about</em> those very people that was so razor sharp, so pitch perfect, that maybe I was the one too dense to be in on the joke? Maybe there were some signifiers that I just didn’t get - maybe the possibility of winning a Golden Globe <em>is</em> supposed to come off as the joke we all know it is. And then I remembered, in perhaps the biggest irony of all, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/26/pain-gain.html">Michael Bay already made that movie</a>.</p>

<p>You actually believe what you’re shovelling.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Requiem for an Underdog</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RequiemforanUnderdog" />
    <published>2015-06-11T07:43:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-11T07:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>1985 was the year I escaped into movies. And it was a good year to escape from. I was eleven, and there were only two things I was scared of: nuclear war, and losing one of my parents. In 1985, one of those things happened. And since I’m not writing to you from an underground bunker filled with powdered water and assault rifles (although that <em>would</em> be pretty cool), you can probably guess which of the two I’m talking about. </p>

<p>My dad was almost fifty when I was born. He’d served in the army during World War II. He was part of that Greatest Generation of men who smoked two packs a day, drank liberally at the Legion, and never saw a doctor. On my 11th birthday he went to the hospital because he couldn’t breathe. By the fall, he was back home. He was dying. </p>

<p>I happened to be at home during that time, too, with a case of mono so bad my whole body was swollen and I was delirious with fever. Over the next six weeks, as I recovered, Dad and I propped ourselves up on couches in the den and binge-watched movies on Pay TV. </p>

<p>I was the youngest child by so many years that my family treated me like another adult. Nothing was dumbed down for me, nothing was kept from me. I had no bedtime, and no restrictions on what I could read or watch. I know that my family did this out of love, and out of respect for my intelligence and curiosity. But an unfortunate side effect of having no little-kid filter was that, while I was fully aware of what was going on in the world, I had no tools with which to process it. I had a visceral, almost debilitating fear of what would happen if the U.S. and Russia launched their nuclear missiles. Sure, I knew that if I needed clarity on something I could go to one of the many adults in my life, but, in the case of the Cold War, no one could adequately explain what was going on because so much of it was completely absurd. </p>

<p>In the mid-80s, Cold War tensions were high. Not a week went by when we didn’t hear about nuclear testing, or have a regularly-scheduled program interrupted by Peter Jennings, who would somberly describe yet another plane hijacking or hostage taking. When Reagan, Thatcher, and Gorbachev weren’t busy playing chicken with warheads, they were metaphorically whipping out their junk to see whose was biggest (unsurprisingly, it was Maggie’s). Every once in a while, Gaddafi or Khomeini would do something crazy—you know, just to keep things interesting. Then there was Apartheid. And acid rain. And the recession, and famine in Ethiopia, and random mass shootings, and the AIDS epidemic. It’s no wonder coke was the drug of choice in the 80s; we were running out of time and there was <em>soooo</em> much to talk about. </p>

<p>My Dad was a burly, barrel-chested guy. He’d been an amateur boxer and hockey player before he met my mother. But, sitting there on the couch beside me, he was sunken and grey. His favourite actors were John Wayne, Clint Eastwood, and Charles Bronson. Manly men. His favourite movie was <em>Gunga Din</em>, a 1939 war movie about three unruly British sergeants holding back a murderous horde of thugs in 1880s India. Fighting alongside them is their water boy, Gunga Din, who dreams of making a better life for himself. Dad loved watching underdog movies. It’s the only time he ever cried. </p>

<p>Before I spent that fall watching movies with my father, there were three films that had profoundly affected me: <em>Testament, The Day After,</em> and <em>The Big Chill</em>. </p>

<p>The first two are about people trying to survive the fallout of nuclear war. The third is a yuppie classic about a bunch of affluent white people who get together after a friend’s suicide to figure out what happened to their stupid hippie idealism. <em>The Big Chill</em> appealed to me because I took some weird satisfaction in seeing a group of adults struggling with their collective existential angst the same way I did. The other two were training films of sorts. <em>Testament</em> was a remarkably subtle portrait of a woman trying to keep her family and sanity intact after nuclear war upends her comfortable suburban existence. <em>The Day After</em> is an explicit play by play of a nuclear attack on a small American town. It was so terrifying that after it was shown on TV my school held an assembly to calm down all the kids who were freaked the fuck out (and it wasn’t just us fragile children; the network had 1-800 phone lines set up with counsellors to talk down hysterical viewers). After seeing those films, I didn’t feel so alone.</p>

<p>But that didn’t last long.</p>

<p>My dad died on February 11, 1985. At home, right there in the room where we’d watched all those movies together. Which movies? I couldn’t even say. There’s a lot that I don’t remember about that time. And other things I recall as clearly as if they happened yesterday. I remember Dad’s Legion buddies filing past his coffin to place poppies inside. I remember bagpipes. I didn’t cry. Not once. I remember all the adults telling me to “take care of your mother.” I was left on my own to find a way to take care of myself. </p>

<p>So I did.</p>

<p>I won’t bother familiarizing you with the <em>Rocky</em> franchise—the first five minutes of every <em>Rocky</em> film does that for you. <em>Rocky IV</em> is “the one with the Russian” (as it is colloquially known). Rocky is retired, but agrees to coach his best friend Apollo Creed in a friendly exhibition fight against Ivan Drago, a giant hunk of Caucasian granite and the pride of the Soviet athletic training system. After being stunned by the spectacle of James Brown singing <em>Living In America</em>, Drago recovers and proceeds to pummel Apollo. Rocky has an opportunity to throw in the towel, to save Apollo’s life, but he doesn’t do it, and Apollo is killed. After a requisite period of mourning and soul-searching (which involves driving his Bugatti around town to Robert Tepper’s synth-heavy song <em>No Easy Way Out</em>) Rocky decides to fight Drago himself...<em>in Russia</em>. </p>

<p>I will defend <em>Rocky IV</em>. To the death. I once came close to throwing down fisticuffs with someone who dared to say that <em>Rocky V</em> (the Voldemort of the <em>Rocky</em> franchise) was better than <em>Rocky IV</em>. I had to be physically restrained and removed from the room (please note: this was sober, and at a child’s birthday party). I don’t labor under any delusions that <em>Rocky IV</em> is a “good” movie. It’s not. I know this objectively. I knew it in the fall of ’85, when my brother took me to see it at the small movie theatre in our hometown. I knew it when I begged him to take me several more times. I knew it wasn’t good in the way I knew <em>Amadeus</em> was good, or that <em>Ghostbusters</em> was good. But I didn’t need <em>Rocky IV</em> to be good. I needed it to make me <em>feel</em> good. I needed it to give me some hope, however contrived.</p>

<p><em>Rocky IV</em> was an antidote to <em>Testament</em> and <em>The Day After</em> (and even to <em>The Big Chill</em>). I wasn’t worried about trying to survive radiation poisoning anymore, or about whether or not adults would get their heads out of their asses long enough to keep the world from imploding. The Italian Stallion gave me back my power. </p>

<p>My love for <em>Rocky IV</em> is, at its essence, very simple. It’s about wish fulfillment. Rocky didn’t just win the fight—he managed to capture the hearts and minds of our Godless communist enemies. And on <em>Christmas Day</em> no less! He didn’t just show up and win, either. He had to work hard, without his family, with the KGB on his ass. He trained in a goddamned barn! No one believed in him, no one thought he could win. But he did. Of course he did. And at the end of his triumphant victory, as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MsJnxlXepsY">his world-changing speech</a> concludes, he gives a shout out to his kid, and tells him he loves him, and his kid mouths back the words: “I love you.” </p>

<p>Waterworks. Every time.</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter that <em>Rocky IV</em> is rife with cliché, full of cartoonish stereotypes, and laced with horrible (and somehow unforgettable) dialogue. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cxs1MHw2_Ds">It features the granddaddy of all sports montages</a>, set to the jingoistic fist-pumper <em>Burning Heart</em>. It has one of the cheesiest slo-mo sequences in film history, where Duke shouts “Noooooooo!” as Apollo falls to the floor. It has a creepy love story between Adrian’s ingrate brother Paulie and a sexy robot. The acting is almost as embarrassing as the blatant product placement. It even features a fake Gorbachev! But I don’t care. I love it—not in spite of those shortcomings, but <em>because</em> of them. </p>

<p>There’s a freedom that comes from facing your biggest fear and living through it. Especially at a young age. 1985 was the year that I realized no one - kids or adults – knows <em>anything</em>, and I took a perverse comfort in that. Things that mattered before my Dad died suddenly seemed petty or insignificant. Other things became more important. The impact of it changed my emotional DNA. I became guarded. I refused to let anyone see me hurting. Movies got me through that year, though—and through subsequent years that weren’t much easier. Like my Dad, I don’t cry unless I’m watching a movie. And like my Dad I’m a sucker for underdog movies. It’s the only time I let myself indulge in unapologetic sentimentality. I’m a natural born cynic, and those movies taught me that my cynicism is borne from hope. </p>

<p>I love <em>Rocky IV</em>’s earnestness. I sincerely think Sylvester Stallone was as frustrated and frightened as the rest of us, and that he genuinely wanted to make a difference. So he tried. The only way he knew how: by making a movie about punching people while listening to <em>Survivor</em>. </p>

<p>I truly believe Stallone hoped <em>Rocky IV</em> would change the world. Maybe it did, maybe it didn’t. But it sure changed mine.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Spy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/4/spy.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Spy" />
    <published>2015-06-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/4/spy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The ‘Melissa McCarthy movie’ has almost become a sub-sub-genre in itself; Packaged as comedy but somehow more horrifying than funny. The premise of any Melissa McCarthy movie seems to be ‘How obnoxious, dirty, and pathetic can we make her look? How deeply can we degrade and humiliate her character before people stop laughing?” It has often bugged me that all we seem to get is more <em>Tammy</em>, when all I want is to see her play the President in a remake of <em>Air Force One</em> (come on, you <em>know</em> how hard that movie would bring it).</p>

<p>I’ll probably be waiting for a while for that particular wish to come true, but in the meantime I’m happy to report that <em>Spy</em> is a welcome step in the right direction.</p>

<p>The spy genre has been spoofed many times with mixed results, and I was starting to feel like it was losing steam. But McCarthy’s turn as a dowdy CIA desk jockey-turned field agent is hysterically funny. Her Susan Cooper might just be an even bigger badass than James Bond (I actually think James Bond is a lousy spy, but that’s a conversation for another day). Spy flick tropes are used as launch pads for gags that are over the top, but never overplayed (I’m looking at you, Austin Powers).There is also some heavy gender politicking at play here; Susan’s boss, her sidekick, and the villain are all women. Male characters, be they good guys or bad guys, make for excellent eye candy, but are pretty well useless beyond that. </p>

<p>Most of the conversation surrounding <em>Spy</em> will probably be about another traditionally male-oriented genre being ‘overwhelmed by estrogen’ or some such nonsense. But what appealed to me most was the Feig-McCarthy <em>cri de</em> <em>coeur</em> against the now common tropes of the Melissa McCarthy movie, the <em>Tammy</em>s and <em>Identity</em> <em>Thief</em>s of this world. Susan’s various cover identities created for her by the CIA - frumpy single mom, unemployed call centre associate, etc. - are variations on many of the sad, fat mess characters she has played in the past. Her frustrated reaction to the pathetic back stories and cringe-worthy disguises (like you) echoed my own feelings of being fed-up to the teeth with this shit. Rather than waiting for the excruciatingly embarrassing splatter onto rock bottom for the eventual makeover where everyone is supposed to go, “Oh, look! She’s actually like, really pretty!” Susan ditches the sadsack cover and takes it upon herself to glam up. Her rage has as much to do with other people’s bullshit perceptions of her as it does with the arms dealers and assassins she encounters, something to which many other unassuming, desk job-working women out there will relate (holla’!), but minus the arms dealer and assassin part (I’m assuming).</p>

<p><em>Spy</em> delivers a good, swift kick to the idea that women carrying ‘traditionally male’ films have to be demeaned and (sometimes literally) dragged through mud in appliqué cat sweaters and ugly wigs, but I doubt it will have the last word on the matter. Indeed, I expect the upcoming ‘male<em>Ghostbusters</em> remake vs. female <em>Ghostbusters</em> remake’ furor to reach near-Culloden proportions. </p>

<p>It is my sincere hope - and don’t take this the wrong way - that you and other disguises of your kind will no longer be considered necessary in the women-can-be-‘dude-funny’-too debate that I can’t even believe is still a thing. I’m sure there’s an Adam Sandler project in production that could use you, though.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>