<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-27T00:27:20Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Great Canadian Supercut</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/26/the-great-canadian-supercut.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheGreatCanadianSupercut" />
    <published>2017-06-26T18:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-26T18:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/26/the-great-canadian-supercut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You know that strange tickle you get when Canada gets mentioned in a movie? Sometimes you cringe, sometimes you giggle, but you always react. We do, anyway – and we thought Canada’s 150<sup>th</sup> birthday was the perfect time to release a supercut showing some hilarious, ridiculous and surprising times Canada and Canadian characters are mentioned in Hollywood films.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1iDnJOq_5yo?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p><strong>A little background</strong></p>

<p>Our inspiration came from the film <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/12/2/allied.html"><em>Allied</em></a> (2016), where Brad Pitt portrays a Canadian soldier in WWII.  After seeing the film, we tried to name other films that featured (better yet, starred) Canadian characters. We could only come up with a handful, but decided to dig deeper. Much deeper.  After months and months of research, what we found was wildly entertaining and enlightening.</p>

<p>Yes, it’s true that Canada is often used as a punchline or a place of refuge for feeling Americans. Also, our passports constantly protect undercover spies.  But our military is also highly regarded, we make a lovely honeymoon destination, our national anthem is sung with unlikely enthusiasm, and &quot;revealed as a Canadian&quot; is apparently a go-to movie trope.</p>

<p>In fact, we found so many times Canada is name-dropped that we could have made at least <em>three</em> supercuts each using 150 different films. But we’ve curated our favourites to tell a story of how Hollywood – and by extension, much of the world – sees us on film.</p>

<p>We also tried to limit clip selections to times &quot;Canada&quot; or &quot;Canadian&quot; is specifically referenced, with a few exceptions (like the above-mention <em>Allied</em>, where he says he’s from Ontario). Call-outs to provinces and cities will have to be saved for another day. We also stuck to English language– but you’d be surprised how many times Canada gets mentioned in Bollywood movies (like I said, we went DEEP).</p>

<p>Enjoy the video, let us know what you think, and use the handy guide below to figure out where we took each clip.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Rough Night</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/20/rough-night.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RoughNight" />
    <published>2017-06-20T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-20T04:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/20/rough-night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The expression &quot;clothes make the man&quot; used to imply that tailors like you were king-makers. Then along comes President Long-tie Von Baggypants and the rule book gets thrown out the window. Balls-out confidence now trumps decorum (and almost everything else). If you’re a man, that is.</p>

<p>Ladies still follow a completely different playbook. People in your industry, and in general, obsessively fixate on how they look, how they dress, and are judged accordingly. This doesn’t just apply to politics – it’s true in business, social settings, and even comedy. Louis C.K. can sport the same black T-shirt every night, and Eddie Murphy can go shirtless under a red leather jacket and hot pants, and everyone just nods along. Meanwhile, Amy Schumer needs to excuse a slightly unconventional wardrobe choice by labelling an entire set &quot;The Leather Special&quot; (it’s on purpose, it’s funny, relax!).</p>

<p>How you outfit the cast of <em>Rough Night</em> is no different – everyone is visually coded to fit their respective stereotype: the buttoned-down politically ambitious conservative (Scarlett Johansson), the fat-but-fun floral-wearing friend (Jillian Bell), the proud-in-plaid lesbian political activist (Ilana Glazner), the power-suited business-savvy sex-magnet (Zoe Kravitz) and the free-spirit-in-a- sun-dress foreigner (Kate McKinnon). Every character is designed for a traditional ensemble pre-wedding comedy. And that’s part of the problem.</p>

<p>To say <em>Rough Night</em> lacks imagination would be an understatement, but retreads don’t always spell doom. Funny is funny, and even if the film had started with a novel concept, it would by no means guarantee bigger laughs.  Comedy needs to evolve at a rate much closer to women’s fashion than men’s (which has doggedly stuck to small variations of a jacket and tie for over a century). Suits are like drama, where the same premise can be recycled for generations because it’s considered basic but fundamental. Comedy, on the other hand, can quickly feel dated, but also wildly fresh when the right risks are taken. <em>Rough Night</em> aims to be timeless (a conscious style decision by writing pair Lucia Aniello and Paul W. Downs), but only occasionally hits that narrow target. More often than not there seems to be a mismatch of creative intent and attempted trend-setting.</p>

<p>What does this mean exactly? Well for one, Aniella, as director, side steps the one-up-(wo)manship of recent shock comedies. Ample opportunities are established for eye-bulging nudity (like a penis-identifying gag with the stripper, or walking in on Demi Moore and Ty Burrell who are supposed to be sun tanning nude), but all we get are made-for-TV gags. The film almost brazenly repeats important beats found in <em>Very Bad Things</em>, <em>The Hangover</em> (any of the three), and <em>Bridesmaids</em>. Even the shadow of less successful films like <em>Bachelorette</em> and <em>Mike and Dave Need Wedding Dates</em> hang over the film to create all the excitement of holding a runway show a month after Paris Fashion Week. If it’s great, sure, maybe people will notice, but the high bar has been set, so you risk premiering in the discount bin if what you’re unveiling isn’t out of the park.</p>

<p>While I did enjoy the way the film pulls back from becoming a true black comedy and provides a few late payoffs for earlier set-pieces, the overall mood was still a BEmusement (to half-quote a McKinnon bit) rather than anything flat-out-funny. Based on the behind-the-scenes pedigree, I hoped for at least the same laughs-per-minute ratio as <em>Broad City¸</em> but that may have been pegging my expectations too high.</p>

<p>Pegging because… never mind, that one <em>was</em> tailor-made for <em>Broad City</em> fans.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Wonder Woman</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/16/wonder-woman.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=WonderWoman" />
    <published>2017-06-16T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-16T04:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/16/wonder-woman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>A lot of the hype surrounding <em>Wonder Woman</em> has had to do with its progressive trappings: A $240 million film directed by a woman! The first female lead in a blockbuster superhero film! Women’s-only screenings taking place around the world! And to be honest, that’s what led me to write to you. After all, your job was traditionally seen as a woman’s job - so much so that the its original, official title was Script Girl. I’m sure you’d agree that Script Supervisor is a definite (and inclusive) improvement. So here’s to progress, right?</p>

<p>Let’s not get too far ahead of ourselves.</p>

<p>For all its bold pronouncements, <em>Wonder Woman</em> is still a superhero movie, and therefore a studio tent-pole film,  which means it needs to reign back lofty ambitions with careful world (a.k.a franchise) building. More specifically, it’s a superhero film that’s part of the nascent DC Extended Universe overseen by Zack Snyder. That’s a pretty stacked deck.</p>

<p>Let’s start with the good, though, which I’m happy to report outweighs the less-than-good by a decent margin. Most importantly, Gal Gadot brings a level of charisma to said Wonder Woman that I hadn’t felt since Christopher Reeves’ Superman. Chris Pine also provides a fine sparring partner for Gadot, proving he can flirt with more than just Vulcan first officers, and helps ground their chemistry in something approaching authenticity, instead of the obligatory box-ticking these relationships often feel like.</p>

<p>In fact, you must have been leafing through the script in disbelief during the early outdoor scenes set on the mythical, Amazon-only inhabited Themyscira, an island which seems specifically designed to blow up the Bechdel Test. Talk about a breath of fresh air. Not only does it feature fully-realized female characters with individual identities and agency (Connie Nielsen and Robin Wright especially make strong impressions), it has something else new: color.</p>

<p>I don’t mean that metaphorically, even though the Amazonian cast is made up of welcome mix of skin colours and ethnicities. No, I mean there is literally colour in these scenes. Heretofore, Snyder’s testosterone-driven vision of the DC universe, in both <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/14/man-of-steel.html"><em>Man of Steel</em></a> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html"><em>Batman v. Superman: Dawn of Justice</em></a>, has been notable for desaturated colors and night scenes that render action incomprehensible. It’s a depressing but undeniable fact that a simple choice like this represents progress in today’s Hollywood.</p>

<p>In these opening scenes, it’s as if director Patty Jenkins is stating her intent to move forward through colour palette alone. If this sounds too out-there as a read on the film, Jenkins goes even further. As the film moves from Themyscira to World War I-ravaged Europe (and more conventional story tropes), the palette becomes darker, less saturated. Yet Gadot’s Wonder Woman remains a vibrant colourful presence — again, literally — colour-timed to pop out of the muddy backgrounds. This is not a coincidence.</p>

<p>As a script supervisor, I know color correction consistency is not the type of continuity for which you are responsible – your focus is ensuring scene-to-scene (and often shot-to-shot) on-screen continuity for the likes of costumes, make-up, and props. And even though ’script’ is in your title, its quality is not your purview.  which may be for the best: as a story, <em>Wonder Woman</em> is ... fine. As it moves towards its climax, <em>Wonder Woman</em> really does become more and more conventional. The motivations of the central villains, German officers Dr. Poison and Ludendorff, are as muddy as the No Man’s Land trenches Gadot and Pine’s crew find themselves dredging through. And what wants to be a late-film plot twist is telegraphed far in advance by casting alone, robbing it of any urgency.</p>

<p>For a film that wants to be seen as mold-breaking as it’s heroine is seen by stiff-lipped Edwardian society, it doesn’t have the faith of its convictions. By the time <em>Wonder Woman</em> had become two mostly-CGI characters lunging, spinning, and smashing into each other in what feels like an endless climax, I felt my enthusiasm being swallowed by the poorly-lit, undefined computer backdrop the characters fight against.* <em>Wonder Woman</em> gains access to the superhero boys club by mimicking its predecessors, not redefining them.</p>

<p>Was the ending Snyder wresting control of the project away form Jenkins, draping his ugly aesthetic overtop of someone else’s vision? It sure felt that way. I’m sure the script notes don’t hold those kinds of answers.</p>

<p>So yes, let’s hear it for baby steps of progress. The title change in your profession may seem cosmetic, but it creates inclusivity by taking gender out of the balance. <em>Wonder Woman</em> creates equality by punching and body-slamming her way into established superhero-dom. And while it’s great to see it finally happen, it’s a little sad that it had to be accomplished in the most typically male way possible.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>It Comes at Night</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/14/it-comes-at-night.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ItComesatNight" />
    <published>2017-06-14T07:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-14T07:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/14/it-comes-at-night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>It Comes at Night</em> doesn’t fit cleanly into any one genre, but it’s certainly a seat-gripper: a movie that resists simple horror tropes like jump scares and simple-minded monsters, opting instead for psychological drama created almost exclusively through tone. In other words, it’s a film where what we <em>don’t</em> see on screen is much more important than what we do see. And this is where you come in.</p>

<p>Grips are the camera department’s multitalented gophers, doing everything from rigging camera set-ups to orchestrating the lighting design. I took particular note of that latter responsibility in this film. Writer/Director Trey Edward Shults takes full advantage of the low-lighting sensors of modern cameras, using minimal light sources in any given frame in an effort to reflect the post-apocalyptic microcosm of the film’s central location, a boarded-up cabin in the woods. As the characters creep through corridors or dine by candlelight, the black space onscreen (or negative fill, as your department would call it) creates important space for anxiety to proliferate and questions to form. And it’s in these dark corners that the film draws its strength.</p>

<p>Combined with a slow (but never dull) editing pace that withholds information (but never inhibits our interest), the film keeps pulling us deeper into the mentality of a family making choices between staying safe and being moral. Some characters, like the father played by Joel Edgerton, tackle this responsibility with a predictable severity, leaving any grey areas up to his 17-year-old son to navigate. The hierarchy within their home is not all that unlike the way you, Bum, are responsible for helping shape the lighting on set, but aren’t actually allowed to touch the lights themselves (union rules!). You’re complicit in creatingand shaping the darkness, but depend on those in a higher position to let in the appropriate amount of light.</p>

<p>In the case of <em>It Comes at Night</em>, this was more effective at certain times than others. When the characters have a direct lighting source, such as a flashlight mounted to a shotgun or a kerosene lantern, the contrasts are effective and effecting. But in the film’s quieter moments, where feels like only available light is sculpting the scene, the film feels like it has less to say.  Even if the story is clearly building towards a specific message. Based on the principles of drama, we know there’s a confrontation coming, but we aren’t sure if it will be from within the house or outside of it. It’s a credit to the performances – and especially Christopher Abbott as the stranger the family meets – that I was almost rooting against the drama, as if I thought everything might just be okay in the end. But as you know, darkness is a powerful force—one that neither you nor Schults obviously shy away from.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Mummy	</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/12/the-mummy.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheMummy	" />
    <published>2017-06-12T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-12T04:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/12/the-mummy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I&#39;ll give you this: <em>The Mummy</em> has a decent opening scene.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, that scene occurs about fifteen minutes into the film, after the audience&#39;s capacity for childlike wonderment has been pulverized by a worthless, turgid, redundant expository prologue. A prologue that serves not only to ruin whatever meager suspense the screenwriters later attempt to set up, but also to demonstrate the complete intellectual contempt with which your studio, in its lust to reap the riches of an expanded universe of films, holds for the general movie-going public. So, things could have started well. But they didn&#39;t.</p>

<p>This movie is a Frank Frazetta paperback cover painted over by Thomas Kincaid; it is possible to sometimes glimpse the camp and fun and menace beneath the surface, but it&#39;s so quickly subsumed by the deafening stupidity of your contemptuous moneygrubbing – which here takes the form of bad plotting that accommodates bad action sequences that are executed with bad special effects – that the experience of sitting in a theater and watching it is only slightly less pleasant than spending 100 minutes witnessing a drowning swimmer struggle to break the surface, gasp for air, choke on the brackish water, and disappear into the murk.</p>

<p>Ask yourself this question: how bad does a movie have to be to extinguish Tom Cruise&#39;s seemingly inextinguishable charisma? His career has weathered countless queasy rumours and religious peculiarities and weird public outbursts; is it a feather in your cap, Jeff, to be able to claim that you were the one, finally, to kill his onscreen charm?</p>

<p>Why am I blaming you? I don&#39;t know. Someone has to answer for this. And you have a history of trying to perpetrate this sort of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/20/split.html">cinematic pyramid scheme</a>. It&#39;s hard for me to pin the blame on the screenwriters. There are six of them, after all, and I&#39;d bet even <em>they</em> can&#39;t remember who wrote which imbecilic lines of dialogue (though I refuse to believe that it was David Koepp or Christopher McQuarrie, the two men responsible for <em>Jurassic Park</em> and <em>The Usual Suspects,</em> and will instead cast a sideways glance at John Spaihts, the guy who wrote <em>Prometheus</em> and gifted cinema with that unforgettable line of dialogue: <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/6/12/prometheus.html">&quot;he cut me off!&quot;</a>).</p>

<p>But what makes <em>The Mummy</em> so godawful isn&#39;t some issue of filmmaking craft—it&#39;s a cultural one. As television has replaced film as the medium where dramatic risk and creative multiplicity are rewarded, Hollywood studios like yours have cynically chosen to narrow the scope of what cinema is capable of doing. The wide-release movie was once a thing of endless possibility: it could be for adults, or kids, or intellectuals, or dimwits, or scaredy-cats, or young women, or even old women; it could be self-serious, or funny, or awkward, or ebullient, or corny, or ironic—or all of those things at once. But wide-release movies today are just big, endlessly long, and have no beginning and no end, only a middle act that comes from nowhere and goes nowhere.</p>

<p>But even to call <em>The Mummy</em> &quot;middling&quot; is too big a compliment. Like each of Donald Trump&#39;s moral and criminal missteps, I always expect that the latest one will be his last. Because how can he possibly survive to make another? The camel&#39;s back is already bowed beneath the weight of a million tons of straw; <em>this</em> one will surely break it! Likewise, how can the studio system bear to make another blockbuster after a major release as catastrophically shitty as <em>The Mummy</em>? Like Trump, I&#39;m sure you&#39;ll find a way to surprise me (by which I mean, of course, disappoint me).</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Men Tell No Tales</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/7/pirates-of-the-caribbean-dead-men-tell-no-tales.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=PiratesoftheCaribbean:DeadMenTellNoTales" />
    <published>2017-06-07T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-07T06:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/7/pirates-of-the-caribbean-dead-men-tell-no-tales</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Hey, it’s me. Again. We need to talk.</p>

<p>A year ago, I wrote to you to express my disappointment in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/31/alice-through-the-looking-glass.html"><em>Alice Through the Looking Glass</em></a>. That movie upset me in a lot of ways, but I mainly took issue with your performance. I was shocked by how little you brought to the character. So I started making excuses. I chalked up your lack of passion as a byproduct of studio meddling. I dug up evidence online that you were creatively constrained. I claimed you had too much star power to be a secondary character. You used to be my favourite actor, Johnny. So I defended you. But after seeing <em>Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Men Tell No Tales</em>, I’ve come to a painful realization.</p>

<p>The problem isn’t studios or creative restraints. It’s <em>you</em>.</p>

<p>The longer the film went on, the longer I had to watch your latest portrayal of Captain Jack Sparrow, the more I found myself observing an actor who is desperately clinging to the past. I could see all the pressures of your personal life manifested in Jack Sparrow, infecting the very character who reignited the second half of your career. It’s almost as if Jack Sparrow, the fictional pirate, was carrying the weight of real-life actor Johnny Depp’s <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2017/02/01/johnny-depps-2-million-monthly-spending-including-30000-month/">financial woes</a> and <a href="http://www.mercurynews.com/2017/05/10/will-johnny-depps-personal-crises-sink-the-latest-pirates-movie/">personal demons</a>.</p>

<p>So, instead of being treated to another wild adventure with the Keith Richards of the sea, I was forced to accompany a sad man who looked like Jack Sparrow and talked like Jack Sparrow but wasn’t Jack Sparrow.</p>

<p>Sad Jack is an annoying drunk. He wanders on screen to perform the same shtick he has been performing since 2003, but without any of the charisma that inspired all these sequels. Anytime he is faced with any sort of danger, he runs. Every single time. I can’t recall him drawing a sword even once. He wasn’t swashbuckling or savvy. He was a shell of a man who spent 90-percent of the film screaming in fear.</p>

<p>That’s a big change from the Jack Sparrow who went toe-to-tentacle against Davy Jones atop a ship’s mast. Or the Jack Sparrow who jumped straight into the Kraken’s mouth with a smile on his face. It’s definitely not the Jack that got you nominated for a fucking <em>Oscar</em>.</p>

<p>The true Jack Sparrow is a wily pirate who faced danger with wit, charm, and courage. Yes, he likes his rum and often escapes conflict by the skin of his teeth—but that doesn’t mean he can’t get his hands dirty every once in a while.</p>

<p>This change from pirate to wimp parallels your own fall from grace.</p>

<p>Here’s an excerpt from my <em>Alice Through the Looking Glass</em> letter: “Whatever people say about your career, there is no doubt that you’re the master of enigmatic performances. When people see your name attached to a project, they know they’re going to get a passionate portrayal.”</p>

<p>I don’t believe that statement anymore.</p>

<p>You still want to be a rock star, but you don’t seem to want to make the effort anymore. I wouldn’t be surprised if the <a href="http://www.mirror.co.uk/3am/celebrity-news/johnny-depp-fed-film-lines-10339984">allegations</a> that you hired a sound engineer to feed you lines through an earpiece are true. It shows in your performance. When I recently saw your name pop up in the trailer for <em>Murder on the Orient Express,</em> and saw you posing with the “Dark Universe” crew, I couldn’t help but think that these movies are going to suffer because of your involvement.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Everything, Everything</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/6/5/everything-everything.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=EverythingEverything" />
    <published>2017-06-05T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-05T04:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/6/5/everything-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>A week or two ago, I came across this <a href="http://mashable.com/2017/04/19/13-reasons-why-sophomore-teens-meme/?utm_cid=mash-com-fb-main-link%23pQPkOMqOx5qN#WP94zRdBb5qo">hilarious meme</a> that highlighted how attractive male teens are in pop-culture. It got me thinking about Young Adult (YA) films and how your involvement in <em>Everything, Everything</em> served as a remedy to a casting epidemic that has plagued the genre for years.</p>

<p>YA films, if you don’t already know, are teen-based romances spliced with another genre (comedy, fantasy, action, etc.). These films feature teenagers in the leading roles and are geared towards other teens in their most hormonal of stages; anywhere between the ages of 13-17. The epidemic comes when we’re led to believe that the 6’2”, 220-pound 25-year old with a five-o’clock shadow is considered a ‘teenager’.</p>

<p>Think about it. How many instances have there been where instead of casting actors who <em>actually</em> resemble their proposed age-range, you get full-grown men playing the part of a sophomore? Off the top of my head; Cory Monteith in <em>Glee,</em> Theo James in the <em>Divergent</em> series, Trevor Donovan in the <em>90210</em> reboot. And let’s not forget Team Jacob VS. Team Edward from <em>Twilight</em>.</p>

<p>I’m only giving examples of males since they are the most evident in their miscasting. Generally, in YA epics, female actors are chosen based on their ability to look young, so the lines between high schooler and grown-ass adult with an RRSP fund are hard to differentiate. </p>

<p>That’s why <em>Everything, Everything</em>  stood out for me. The relationship between Maddy, played by Amandla Stenberg, and Olly, played by Nick Robinson, seemed so natural and authentic because they looked and acted like teenagers. They were reckless in their pursuits and driven by an emotion that is so unknown for someone of their age. In short: their love was believable. At no point did I ever snap out of my movie-going experience and wonder, “Hey, you know what? I think she’s just into him because he can bench press a small car.”</p>

<p>If I compare back to “High School” hunks like Theo James or Taylor Lautner, Nick Robinson seems frail and awkward -- which is <em>perfect</em>. His long, parted hair, his preference for black clothing (clearly a phase), and the way he slightly slouches and drags his feet; everything about Olly screams “teenager in revolt”. His lack of an Adonis-like physique gives the audience a reason to watch him as a boy trying to get the attention of girl. We laugh at his lame gestures and see the nervousness in his eyes when he professes his love.</p>

<p>Same goes for Amandla Stenberg as Maddy. In <em>Everything, Everything,</em> Maddy suffers from a rare immune disease that forces her to stay indoors 24/7. When she finally meets Olly face-to-face, her bashful yet determined confidence to take control of her own life results in an awkward and charming relationship that has to be experienced. </p>

<p>Because that’s what relationships are like in high school, right? They’re experimentations. They’re embarrassing moments, like when Olly sees Maddy in a swimsuit, only to quickly turn away because he doesn’t want to seem like a creep. They’re derived from varying self-esteems. And most importantly, they’re full of teachable moments and life lessons.</p>

<p>I understand it may sound bitter of me to chastise the legitimacy of teen love just because one partner isn’t as awkward or underdeveloped as the other. I know this is a reality for many people. My issue is with pop-culture’s constant unbelievable portrayals. It’s the casting decisions that alter mindsets of young men and women everywhere.</p>

<p>Casting attractive ‘teens’ and having them fall in love is the basis for Young Adult genre films and a major factor in their box office success, I get that. All I’m saying is every now and then, let’s take a page out of <em>Everything, Everything</em> and add some authenticity.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bon Cop Bad Cop 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/5/24/bon-cop-bad-cop-2.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BonCopBadCop2" />
    <published>2017-05-24T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/5/24/bon-cop-bad-cop-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What makes a film genuinely Canadian? People cite all sorts of common clichés, or get all bureaucratic and claim it’s the producer’s passport. But I’d like to share one that I’ve long held to be true: Canadian films don’t end in crane shots. </p>

<p>Having seen more than 500 Canadian films, it’s something I’ve often noticed. The crane shot, aside from boasting big production value, signals to the viewer that it’s okay to leave the story now—everything’s going to be fine! Crane shots are the cinematic equivalent of “they all lived happily ever after,” or, when they start a film, the equivalent of “once upon a time.” Two tropes which are so very un-Canadian, don’t you think?</p>

<p>Maybe that’s why <em>Bon Cop Bad Cop 2</em>, which aspires to be both uber-Canadian and American-esque, ends with an entire crane <em>sequence</em>. Characters, cars, and cameras all get their turn riding the big boy in the climax. It struck me as both cheeky and appropriate.</p>

<p>The last <em>Bon Cop Bad Cop</em> film was a fairy tale in itself, after all. Billed as the first truly bilingual film in the country, it went on to be the most successful homegrown movie in Canadian history. It seemed inevitable that there would be a sequel, but it has taken more than a decade for David Bouchard and David Ward to re-team. The time between has seen the men noticeably age, but also grow more comfortable in their roles. Colm Feore, in particular, has found subtle ways of infusing more comedy into his straight-laced persona. Patrick Huard (who also wrote the screenplay) unveils a more emotional centre to his Martin Riggs-inspired rogue cop. In both cases, it’s never anything short of terrific when the two of them are together. </p>

<p>The look of the sequel has also changed drastically. Whereas <em>Bon Cop Bad Cop</em>’s director Erik Canuel aimed to parallel David Fincher’s aesthetics and desaturated colour pallette, director Alain Desrocher is clearly more influenced by the Fast and the Furious films (which makes sense, after his hit film <em>Nitro</em>). The film opens at a car rally to the sound of July Talk’s “Push + Pull” – and of course that smooth, possibly crane-assisted camera movement through the rows of show cars – before turning into a (modest) chase on the Décarie. Whether by design or by necessity (hint: it’s both), character is always at the forefront, which makes the action sequences feel secondary, but never second rate. </p>

<p><em>Bon Cop Bad Cop 2</em> is a welcome change of pace from what we typically see in theatres—even if the film, a decade later, now has to compete with an extremely elevated level of television production (most notably the I-can’t-believe-I-like-this-show-so-much <em>Lethal Weapon</em> series). Sweeping crane shots, after all, are no longer just the domain of feature films. But when you know what you’re doing with them, and when people are clearly having fun on both sides of the screen, size really doesn’t matter.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Alien: Covenant</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/5/23/alien-covenant.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Alien:Covenant" />
    <published>2017-05-23T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-23T04:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/5/23/alien-covenant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I feel like I was ill-prepared for my introduction to you, and to the <em>Alien</em> franchise, and it’s my own fault. I’ve never seen any of the other <em>Alien</em> films, and after my initial cowardly hesitation (I hate monster movies) when asked to review <em>Alien: Covenant</em>, I had a decision to make; to catch up, or not to catch up. My companion informed me there were four films to watch if I wanted to roll up at the screening all clued in like a boss, and I was totally going to, but then I spent the weekend binge-watching <em>Call the Midwife</em> (again) instead. Sorry.</p>

<p>So I went in blind, and told myself it was actually better this way; I wouldn’t be weighed down by any expectations, nor would I spend the entire screening inwardly grumbling about all things missed or ruined.  I was right, to an extent. However, being part of a much-loved franchise, the film was, of course, peppered with references to the other films, and inside jokes I didn’t get. My useless companion thought, “Shush, just watch” was a helpful response to all of my very important questions, so it was like showing up to write an exam without having studied, and the nerd sitting next to you won’t let you copy off him.   </p>

<p>As it turns out, my totally objective, baggage-free opinion of <em>Alien: _Covenant</em> is a lot more positive than I thought it would be. Show me a film where large things bite people and I tend to become the octopus in that gif where it scurries away and the caption reads, “NOPE NOPE NOPE.” I didn’t get too attached to any of the characters, as I had a feeling most of them would be meat pulp by the halfway mark. Nor did I get too worked up over things such as the often atrocious dialogue, like when one of the colonial marines watches a crewmate  get torn apart by a very large, scary creature of indeterminate origin and then asks the remaining members of her team, “But are you sure it’s safe here?!” Normally, that would have bugged the hell out of me, but I just laughed and inwardly referred to her as Dead Becky Walking for the tragically brief remainder of her screen time. </p>

<p>While I may have cottoned on to references to Byron and Shelley, all the references to previous <em>Alien</em> films went straight over my head. There was the one part, David, when you showed the captain of the Covenant a bunch of weird looking pods, and assured him it was safe to take a closer look. The audience thought that was hilarious but I didn’t really get it, especially given what happened next.  </p>

<p>With all that carnage unfolding on screen, it seemed pointless to care too much about any of the characters, but I was totally into you two. Your scenes with each other draw together all of the film’s major thematic concerns; creation versus destruction, nature versus nurture, the difference between being human and being humane, and a delightfully vicious ideological opposition to colonialism are all examined during the sole opportunity you two really have to sit down and chat without the Covenant crew whining and demanding, like, help against the monstrous space bug trying to eat them or whatever.  You don’t have a lot of screen time together, but your chemistry was amazing.  Judging from the awed, “Whoa!”s in the theatre during your little music lesson, the audience agreed with me. With all the human characters getting snacked on, knocked up, and torn apart, it makes sense that you synthetics are the safest bets to anchor the narrative and provide continuity from the prequel and, I’m assuming, into a sequel. </p>

<p>My first <em>Alien</em> experience was as harrowing as I expected, but I think I will catch myself up in time for the next film. There are still so many things I need explained, like, “How can you tell the girl aliens apart from the boy aliens?” and, “...did that thing just impregnate his <em>face</em>?!” I tried asking my companion these questions at the time, but being frantically shushed to death by sci-fi nerds was not how I wanted to go out, so I will do my homework, and go all the way back to the beginning to see what happens next. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Snatched</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/5/12/snatched.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Snatched" />
    <published>2017-05-12T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-12T04:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/5/12/snatched</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There are a couple of reasons why I often address these letters to writers. The first is self-serving. It is the thing I know most about. The second is more specific to the movie you wrote. If it ain&#39;t on the page, it&#39;s unlikely to be up on the screen, especially with a comedy. And <em>Snatched</em> is so thinly drawn, you&#39;d have a hard time squashing a bug with it.</p>

<p>I won&#39;t pretend I&#39;ve liked your earlier work, <em>The Heat</em> or the rebooted <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/20/ghostbusters.html"><em>Ghostbusters</em></a>, both of which struck me as tepid and lazy examples of the lowest common denominator kind of comedy, that leans far too hard on star power and not nearly enough on good writing. Even if you have actors as sharp and well attuned to one another as Steve Coogan and Rob Brydon in <em>The Trip</em>, or someone who can carry the emotional weight of a whole film like Jenny Slate in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/4/obvious-child.html"><em>Obvious Child</em></a>, comedy still needs a strong script to be anything other than the absolutely forgettable nonsense that is <em>Snatched</em>.</p>

<p>With a film like this the plot doesn&#39;t really matter, it is simply a contrivance to create weird situations that are hopefully comedic. But here&#39;s a thumbnail sketch: Amy Schumer is a hapless thirty something whose boyfriend breaks up with her, so she drags her mother Goldie Hawn along on a South American vacation. From there an increasingly unlikely set of circumstances ensue.</p>

<p>That this is the film that Goldie Hawn chose to make her return in is frankly baffling. She is wasted as a parody of a lonely, divorced mom who hasn&#39;t had sex since her husband left. She is also so hamstrung by the way her character is written that she is nothing more than a foil to Amy Schumer&#39;s feckless and completely self-involved disaster. In fact, every character (except Schumer&#39;s) in this film barely registers as human, inasmuch as they are nothing but a collection of paper thin clichés that show up when the plot requires, and then disappear just as quickly. Joan Cusack and Wanda Sykes as a platonic couple are a particularly good (bad) example of characters that appear out of nowhere in order to help navigate a plot point, and then are literally driven off stage once their usefulness has concluded.</p>

<p>To be fair, <em>Snatched</em> is not directed at me at all. However, I went with my wife Sarah, who is a thirty something directly in the crosshairs of the marketing campaign, and other than a couple of mother/daughter moments that resonated, <em>Snatched</em> fell flat for her as well, and for the same reasons.</p>

<p>The caveat to all this is that, perhaps of all genres, comedy is the most specific to personal tastes. There may be something here that I&#39;m missing, or someone else might find more interesting. But that&#39;s probably me trying to assuage my own conscience about so thoroughly disliking what you had a hand in creating.</p>

<p>Hopefully, next time it will go better for both of us.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>