<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-19T22:44:20Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Love the Coopers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/18/love-the-coopers.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LovetheCoopers" />
    <published>2015-11-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/18/love-the-coopers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s no secret that the holiday season brings out the worst in consumer culture. The moment the clock strikes midnight on October 31st, stores quickly fill every nook and cranny with winter-themed tchotchkes in order to get a jumpstart on their competition. As Assistant Property Manager, it’s your job to bring that forced holiday cheer to the big screen.</p>

<p><em>Love The Coopers</em> is but the first of many holiday films to be released in 2015. Using the same concept as most seasonal bangers in the past (<em>Family Stone, New Years Eve, Valentine’s Day</em>,) <em>Love The Coopers </em>employs a star-studded cast in order to put asses in seats and be the first to welcome you to the holiday season. </p>

<p>And as we’ve learned from internet commenters, being first doesn’t justify anything. When the tinsel has settled, it’s glaringly apparent that <em>Love</em> <em>The</em> <em>Coopers </em>is just another PG-13 comedy about a zany family having to deal with one another during the holidays. There are contrived laughs to uphold its light-hearted conceit, and occasional bouts of emotions sprinkled on top to surprise us—until the family dog jumps on the table causing everyone to yell and be dysfunctional. It’s a stenciled formula that we’ve grown accustomed to dealing with for a month or two, just like the sad men in Santa outfits, busy malls, and rows and rows of packed shelves holding lame trinkets.</p>

<p>The type of trinkets that make one wonder, “do people actually buy these?”.</p>

<p>Apparently they do. You had the presumably unfortunate job of sourcing these trinkets to create a life-like scenario of what we experience at the end of every year. As we saw during our visit to the part-time job of Lauren Hesselberg—the awkward teenage crush for Ed Helms’ son; thousands of red, white and green streamers along with Santa dolls filling a shop aisle are an inescapable truth. No matter how lame and gaudy they are, they seem to show up every year—just like cheesy holiday movies. </p>

<p>If red Starbuck cups have taught us anything, it’s that making changes to a time-honored tradition can create backlash, despite how trivial it may be. It’s almost become mechanical: every year, a handful of holiday movies appear and every year, Assistant Property Masters like you will run out to prop warehouses, crank open the giant doors and pull out a disheveled plastic Rudolph tangled in Christmas lights and feathered white boas. But that’s the nature of the job I suppose. </p>

<p>Commercialization of the holidays has been around for many years, and it will no doubt continue for many more. And in a strange twist of fate, it means you will always have income around this time of year to spend on your family. And isn’t that what the holidays are all about?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bridge of Spies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/18/bridge-of-spies.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BridgeofSpies" />
    <published>2015-11-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/18/bridge-of-spies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>And here I thought <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/10/20/pan.html">Kurt Cobain</a> was going to be the most surprising credit of the year.</p>

<p>Seeing your name in the end credits of Steven Spielberg’s <em>Bridge of Spies</em> threw me for a loop. As you are no doubt well aware, <em>Bridge of Spies</em> is only the second Spielberg feature <em>not</em> scored by John Williams. The other was <em>The Color Purple</em>, which was scored by Quincy Jones. I know, I know, you’re a six-time Grammy winner and a 12-time Oscar nominee. You’re certainly not an unknown quantity. But Jones has won 27 Grammys and been nominated 79 times, while Williams has won 5 Oscars, been nominated 44 times, and has also won 22 Grammys himself. You’re stepping in to replace two men who are basically the most recognized artists in your field. That’s a tall step.</p>

<p>And it&#39;s not that you don’t have your own impressive film credentials: <em>American Beauty</em>, <em>Finding</em> <em>Nemo</em>, <em>Skyfall</em>, and <em>WALL•E,</em> just to name only a few. But it’s not your pedigree that that makes you an unusual choice. It’s your musical style.</p>

<p>Let’s face it: you aren’t known as being the most emotional of composers. My introduction to your music was Robert Altman’s <em>The Player</em>, where the electronic iciness and ironic detachment was a perfect accompaniment to Altman’s black comedy. And even as you’ve worked on higher-budget, higher-profile productions, you’ve maintained some of that signature aloofness, almost always to the benefit of your collaborators.</p>

<p>And here you are, working with Steven Spielberg, considered by many—unfairly, at times—as one of the most sentimental filmmakers of all time. The natural question is: how does this affect <em>Bridge of Spies</em>? Is a Spielberg movie a different experience when John Williams isn’t delivering his bombastic brass or swelling strings? </p>

<p>Yes. And no.</p>

<p>The music <em>is</em> different. This may be Spielberg’s least-scored film since <em>Saving Private Ryan</em>. It’s a welcome change, as his most recent film, <em>Lincoln</em> – <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/16/lincoln.html">which I loved</a> – leaned too heavily on mawkish cues that it didn’t need. Here, you do your best to maintain some distance from the events onscreen, which gives everything an icy sheen entirely appropriate to a story set during the Cold War. </p>

<p>Though inspired by actual events, <em>Bridge of</em> <em>Spies</em> is a deceptively simple film in terms of plot. In 1957, Rudolph Able, a Russian deep-cover operative, is arrested by the CIA after retrieving a dead drop package. American lawyer James Donovan is asked to defend him—but only <em>just</em> enough to give the appearance of due process. Not long afterwards, US Air Force pilot Francis Powers is captured in Russia while flying a covert operation to film military sites. Donovan is then asked to facilitate a prisoner swap between the two nations, Abel for Powers. </p>

<p>It’s all classic spy stuff, but Spielberg treats it all matter-of-factly and without fuss. Although it’s beautifully shot (by Janusz Kaminski, of course; Williams is the only of Spielberg’s regulars absent here), one would be hard-pressed to find what could be called “typical” Spielberg shots; there’s nary a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VS5W4RxGv4s">Spielberg Face</a> to be found.  Even Tom Hanks subdues his natural warmth and charisma, playing Donovan as a man more annoyed than honored by his nation’s call to duty. </p>

<p>And this, Thomas, is why your music fits so well.</p>

<p><em>Bridge of Spies</em> is an inward-looking film. It’s telling that the first shot of the film is one of Able peering into a mirror, studying his own face. This is a story about the way we see ourselves – as people, as nations – and how we present ourselves to the world. Able may be a spy, but he is an honest one: once caught, he readily admits who he is and what he’s done. He’s not going to give up any Soviet secrets, but he’s also not going to pretend he doesn’t have them. For Donovan, this is far more admirable than what his own government is asking. His own moral compass won’t let him do what his country demands, and must deal with the consequences of the way this action (or inaction) is perceived. </p>

<p>You music takes it’s cue from Able: quiet, introspective, but sure of its place and purpose. It doesn’t need to be showy. And Like Mark Rylance’s superb performance as the captured spy, it puts us at a remove, free of emotional manipulation. And that’s no small feat.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Man Vs</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/17/man-vs.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ManVs" />
    <published>2015-11-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/17/man-vs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re usually the first person on set, aren’t you? You have to be there before the sun is up, ready to provide coffee, juice and sad Costco Danish for the bleary-eyed cast and crew when they arrive. Sometimes, though, being alone on set must be kind of peaceful. You get to have the location to yourself before the other trucks arrive, and you can take your time setting up before the mad rush of shooting begins. Other times it must be a little bit creepy. Especially when your location is in the middle of nowhere. I mean, anything could be out there in the woods. Anything. </p>

<p>That is the premise of <em>Man Vs,</em> a horror/psychological thriller set on a remote island on the Canadian Shield. The titular man is Doug Woods, a survivalist and star of <em>Woods vs,</em> a television show in the vein of <em>Survivorman</em>, that sees Doug left in the woods with little more than a camera and his wits with which to survive for five days. When his small crew drops him off, they remind him that this new season is their chance to get a network deal – a not-so-subtle suggestion to amp up the stakes of the show. Once on the island, Doug begins to fear that he is not alone, but who, or what exactly is out there with him?</p>

<p>One of the benefits of working on a relatively small production must be that most days you serve the same people. No crowd scenes means no background to have to prepare food for, which makes your life easier. But to satisfy the same group over and over means you have to be, um <em>crafty</em>. <em>Man Vs</em>, faces the same obstacle. Fans of the horror/thriller genre are a tough bunch to please.  But at the same time, they are among some of the most forgiving. If the story is strong they are willing to overlook a boom mike in shot or a clumsy overdub. Not that they have to worry about that here. <em>Man Vs</em> is a low-budget film, but it isn’t cheap. </p>

<p>In the same way you can probably feed a hundred people when you’re only budgeted for seventy-five, <em>Man Vs</em> is creative. It uses tropes we are familiar with – survivalist reality TV, horror, action – and delivers a lean and pretty compelling story. We never doubt that Doug, played with equal amounts TV host-smarm and genuine terror by Chris Diamantopoulos, is at home in the wilderness. When strange things start to happen on the second day – dead fish in the river, a huge chunk of the tree line demolished – he rationalizes it away. But when things get seriously weird we begin to wonder – is it Duncan, the creepy scout the production team hired to bring Doug to the island? Is it the team screwing with Doug to boost the show’s ratings? Is Doug losing his mind? Or is it something else entirely?  </p>

<p>The film clips along at a steadily intensifying pace, and Diamantopoulos revs up his fear accordingly. He is the only person on screen for the majority of the film (much of which is him filming himself for the show with a Go-Pro), and manages that responsibility deftly. <em>Man Vs</em> has a few “as if” moments, like there are in most films of this ilk, but nothing serious enough to derail the premise. In the last third of the film, when we finally see what is versus man, it’s genuinely chilling. Like the organic chocolate chip cookies you hoard for the crew members that help you wash dishes, it’s important not to give too much away. </p>

<p>Feeding people is easy, but actually satisfying them is harder than it looks. Too many horror/psychological thriller films go for the “more is more” approach, leaving audiences starved for narrative. <em>Man Vs</em> has a simple premise, but that it has a smart and tight script, shot economically with a compelling lead and blessedly sparing use of visual effects and still manages to be an ultimately disturbing movie is crafty indeed.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Spotlight</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Spotlight" />
    <published>2015-11-13T06:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-13T06:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/13/spotlight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Sometimes life can correct art. In season five of <em>The Wire</em> you played an investigative reporter who spun stories out of whole cloth just to boost your signal in the newsroom of the Baltimore Sun. Now, seven years later, you co-write and direct a film about the investigative arm of the Boston Globe (dubbed Spotlight) that literally changed the world. Because of the series of stories that the Globe published in the early 2000’s—stories that detail decades of sexual abuse by priests as well as the Catholic Church’s implication in a massive cover up—millions of people would come to reassess their relationship with the church, as well as with the people who are its ostensible guardians.</p>

<p><em>Spotlight</em> is a reversion to a kind of filmmaking that has often been declared dead and buried by countless (and as it turns out, alarmist) think pieces. Thoughtful and nuanced, the story spools out effortlessly. The performances are low key and far less heightened than most films that are trumpeted as Oscar bait. This is a true ensemble piece with strong turns from Mark Ruffalo, Michael Keaton, Rachel MacAdams and Liev Schreiber—not to mention stellar work from Stanley Tucci in a small, but vital, performance. </p>

<p>The filmmaking itself is invisible—a return to the kind of aesthetic that made films like <em>All The Presidents Men</em> or even <em>The French Connection</em> feel like they were one degree away from real. In the same way that well written dialogue goes unnoted, the audience is completely unaware of the architecture of the work and is left to simply absorb the narrative. Much like last year’s <em>A Most Violent Year</em> or even <em>Timbuktu</em>, <em>Spotlight</em> is a medium budget film that puts lie to the idea that there is no such thing as adult entertainment that doesn’t end with the suffix <strong>hub</strong>.</p>

<p>It is a subtle pleasure to watch something so carefully modulated. There are very few moments of high drama. Instead we all get to see how the sausage is made—the whole movie gives itself over to the fascinating process of how a story so monumental is found in nooks and crannies, detail by detail—by professionals who are dedicated to their craft. And the resulting piece of art is completely riveting.</p>

<p><em>Spotlight</em> is a clear example of how film can parse fraught and incendiary themes with intelligence and sensitivity. You managed a balance between blunt truths and an understanding that these are real people, not just mannequins you rearrange to create narrative flourishes. Nor is <em>Spotlight</em> an instrument of advocacy other than demonstrating the value of an increasingly rare sort of journalistic enterprise. Everyone populating the landscape you helped create were characters with complicated, and often conflicted, motivations and desires.</p>

<p><em>Station Agent,</em> a film of yours I happened across years ago, is an intimate, small-scale  funny/sad story about a group of socially ill-equipped humans finding community with one another—and in so many ways is a necessarily different work than <em>Spotlight</em>. But the two films do share one commonality: a fundamental compassion about the fragility at the core of the human condition. With <em>Spotlight</em> you managed to create something that simultaneously honors that fragility and yet never launders the ugly truths at the core of the story. That kind of tightrope walk is a rare pleasure to watch.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Suffragette</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/13/suffragette.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Suffragette" />
    <published>2015-11-13T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-13T06:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/13/suffragette</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In 1913 you quite literally gave your life for the cause; the right for women to vote. You and your sisters-in-arms endured public humiliation, beatings at the hands of police, and brutal stints in prison. Not to mention, you know, the widespread, garden-variety sexism that was the norm in early 20th century Britain. Along with famed suffrage leader Emmeline Pankhurst and others, you espoused confrontational tactics in order to gain attention and support for the cause. You broke windows, blew shit up, and the government branded you terrorists. What you really were was an epic badass and a hero. </p>

<p>So why did you only show up half way through <em>Suffragette</em>?</p>

<p>You’d be pleased to know that the film about a movement you helped foster was written by a woman, and directed by a woman (who worked very hard to make sure the crew behind the camera was populated by a <a href="http://www.fastcocreate.com/3052619/suffragette-director-sarah-gavron-on-fixing-the-gender-imbalance-in-filmmaking">proportionate number of women</a>). But instead of focusing on you or the militant organization behind suffrage, the movie chooses an unlikely hero to be our entry point into the story; a poor, working class mother. </p>

<p>Carey Mulligan plays Maud Watts, a laundry employee fed up with unfair working conditions and her predatory boss. Though reluctant to join the suffrage movement, she soon becomes deeply engaged in the cause, becoming what the local constabulary refer to as an “agitator”. Her humiliated husband kicks her out and forbids her to see her young son, thus making the suffrage movement the only thing in Maud’s life worth fighting for. </p>

<p>If you don’t recognize the name Maud Watts, it’s because she, and some other characters are fictional. Writer Abi Morgan lets us watch Maud grow from an obedient wife and employee, to a radicalized suffragette. Morgan, who also wrote <em>Shame</em> and <em>Iron Lady</em>, is an actor’s writer  - just ask Michael Fassbender, and Meryl Streep (blink and you’ll miss her cameo here as Pankhurst). She leaves a lot of the character off the page and in the hands of Mulligan, who lets Maud emerge with melancholic dignity. Other characters, like Helena Bonham Carter’s rebellious nurse Edith Ellyn, and Maud’s stern husband Sonny, are not given as much dimension. </p>

<p>Real or composite, many of the characters and scenarios feel rote, with the exception of the scenes between Maud and Inspector Arthur Steed, who is tasked with taking down the Women’s Social and Political Union (WSPU). Played with grizzled righteousness by Brendon Gleeson, Steed compares the suffragettes to anarchists and Fenian agitators, and sees them as a threat against the government and the king. Mulligan and Gleeson’s interactions are reminiscent of those between Bobby Sands and Father Dominic in <em>Hunger</em>; rife with tension, steely resolve, and begrudging respect. Sadly these interactions are too few. </p>

<p>Director Sarah Gavron infuses <em>Suffragette</em> with diligent attention to period detail while subtly illustrating the progress of the new century beside the tenuous grasp of the old. Double decker buses share the road with horses and carriages, the WSPU uses telephones and printing presses, Steel’s officers use cameras to secretly to track the suffragette’s movements, all in effort to remind us that this really wasn’t such a long time ago. </p>

<p>Perhaps your character is not given as much screen time because Morgan and Gavron thought the audience would find it easier to root for a woman who has lost everything. <em>Suffragette</em>, unfortunately, isn’t really for me, but for a younger audience of women and men who maybe aren’t so familiar with the early women’s rights movement. This is why at times the film feels like a primer. <a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/feminism/2015/10/what-did-suffragette-movement-britain-really-look">The real suffrage movement</a> was far more fractious and messy – it included women of colour, lesbians, imperialism, elitism, racism, and people and events that don’t necessarily lend themselves to an easy narrative. </p>

<p>The backlash against the movie <em>Suffragette</em> for <a href="http://www.thestranger.com/film/feature/2015/11/04/23117815/why-our-reviewer-refuses-to-write-a-review-of-suffragette">white-washing history</a>, and against the cast for <a href="http://flavorwire.com/541222/meryl-streeps-suffragette-t-shirt-disaster-what-were-they-thinking">being tone-deaf</a>, is unfortunate but not unwarranted. The movie is good, but not good enough to rise above its own prejudices. Your triumphant heroics – and those of Sophia Duleep Singh, Annie Kenney and others - are worthy of their own biopic. If that happens, I’ll be sure to let you know how it turns out.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Our Brand is Crisis</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/10/our-brand-is-crisis.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=OurBrandisCrisis" />
    <published>2015-11-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/10/our-brand-is-crisis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Forgive me if I don’t know where to send this letter, but you’ve been incommunicado since Stephen Harper’s slaughter at the hands of the Liberal Party on October 19th. Can’t say I blame you. Running a federal campaign is an exhausting (and mostly thankless) task. Regardless of the result, it should conclude with a well-earned rest. Hell, just watching it was a pretty tiresome, despite the occasional laugh and a not-so-predictable ending. </p>

<p>But those aren’t the only things the Canadian election had in common with <em>Our Brand Is Crisis.</em></p>

<p>It’s no secret that your campaign unraveled and you were unceremoniously dumped by the outgoing PM the day after his crushing defeat. But in 2011, you were celebrated as the brains behind Stephen Harper’s triumphant majority win. You were known as an Alpha: a rigid, on-message task-master. You were powerful. You were feared. You were employed. Now you’re...well, where <em>are</em> you? If you were campaign specialist “Calamity” Jane Bodine, the protagonist of <em>Our Brand Is Crisis</em>, you’d be licking your wounds in a mountain cabin, far away from the addictive pull of politics. </p>

<p>Like your campaign, <em>Our Brand Is Crisis</em> had a lot of early buzz. But, like your campaign, it fizzles quickly. We learn Jane’s backstory through the lazy device of a newspaper-clipping montage during the credits; a once-shining star on the campaign trail cut down by a drinking problem, mental instability, and hubris, Jane spends her days making unremarkable pottery in the middle of nowhere. An opportunity to make a comeback of sorts by working on the campaign of a conservative former president seeking re-election in Bolivia – and a chance to face her long-time nemesis – brings her out of retirement. </p>

<p>Maybe it’s because people around the world seem to know as much about Canada as they do about Bolivia, but the similarities between their <a href="http://www.salon.com/2015/10/28/the_real_story_of_our_brand_is_crisis_is_how_we_screwed_up_bolivia_behind_the_bland_sandra_bullock_movie_lies_another_strange_but_true_tale_of_botched_american_meddling/">quasi-fictional</a> election and ours were eerie. Jane’s candidate, Castillo, is a cold, unpopular conservative who seems physically incapable of relating to his electorate. His previous presidency was rife with corruption and controversy. His first, ludicrously-staged campaign ad is comically bad. The opponent he wants to beat is Rivera, a universally loved man of the people running on the promise of “hope and change”. At one point Jane even exclaims, “his hair is amazing!” The strategy she comes up with is to run Castillo’s campaign on fear. “You can’t change the man to fit the narrative, so we’ll change the narrative to fit the man.” </p>

<p>If I were you I’d seriously consider seeking a retroactive consulting fee from the film’s producers.</p>

<p>Ever since the <em>West Wing</em>, it seems that stories about behind-the-scenes political machinations feel the need to keep up a breathless, Sorkin-esque pace that can be both false and exhausting. Refreshingly, <em>Our Brand Is Crisis</em> (loosely based on the documentary of the same name) tries to operate more at the pace of <em>Primary Colours</em> or <em>The War Room,</em> films which put the spotlight on the people behind the candidates. By now audiences understand that the inner sanctum of any government is full of huge personalities, massive egos, and more than a little bit of insanity. But after the wacky hijinks and cutthroat back-room dealings are done, we aren’t left with characters who have much depth—<em>or</em> a story with anything fresh to say. </p>

<p>Jane’s rival, Candy, is a slimy D-bag played by Billy Bob Thornton in a role he seems to have been born to play…over and over again. Their rivalry began years ago when Jane, working for a mayoral candidate, still had morals. Morals that were dashed by a tragedy for which she may or may not have been responsible. Now Candy is working for Rivera, and his passive-aggressive, back-and-forth practical jokes with Jane fuel much of the anemic narrative. The Bolivians are the great unwashed, their struggles only important inasmuch as they provide Jane the opportunity to spout bromides like a random quote generator. Politics is a dirty game, not for the meek or idealistic. Yeah, we know.</p>

<p>But hey, maybe those pedestrian tactics work. <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/meet-the-woman-driving-harpers-re-election-campaign/article24699535/">You were known</a> to pull out a picture of yourself as a little girl, standing proudly beside your father with a freshly killed deer at your feet, to remind Conservatives that they were fighting for people outside of the Ottawa bubble. <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/canada-election-2015-jenni-byrne-tossed-1.3280702">But some insiders now think</a> that, beyond your bullish personality, the fact that you are a woman may have lead to your ultimate demise. Early scuttlebutt surrounding <em>Our Brand Is Crisis</em> focused on the fact that the role of Jane was originally written for a man, then <a href="http://www.ew.com/article/2015/08/12/sandra-bullock-our-brand-crisis-first-look">Bullock lobbied</a> to star in the lead. But producers Grant Heslov and George Clooney and writer Peter Straughan (working from Rachel Boynton’s doc) seem content to merely swap out the genders instead of adding any unique layers to Jane. They missed an opportunity to explore the challenges inherent when a difficult woman is in charge of getting an unworthy man elected. </p>

<p>Politics and the film business have some distinct parallels: it takes a whole team of dedicated people to get a project done, and when it fails, it’s far too easy to blame one person. In the case of Harper and <em>Our Brand Is Crisis</em>, neither team seemed interested in delivering something new, and in the end, the message just didn’t sell.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Peanuts Movie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/9/the-peanuts-movie.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ThePeanutsMovie" />
    <published>2015-11-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/9/the-peanuts-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Adaptations or remakes are generally tough to pull off. They require a careful balance between preserving the essence of the original, and making it new enough for there to be any point to the exercise. I’ve been a fan of Peanuts since I was a kid, but I honestly didn’t see Charles Schulz’s characters lending themselves too well to the high octane, pithy style of animated features we’re used to. A big part of the charm of Peanuts is its quiet simplicity. I was curious as to how (or even if) you would give the beloved cartoon enough verve and punch for the younger crowd while preserving the old-fashioned sweetness for those of us who crack up at the sound of Miss Othmar’s voice, and say ‘Oh, good grief’ like it’s still a thing. </p>

<p>A school year serves as a very basic narrative frame for <em>The Peanuts Movie</em>. There is no plot to speak of, just a series of events on the school calendar (first day, standardized test, school dance, etc.) loosely tied together by Charlie Brown’s quest to win the affections of the Little Readheaded Girl. There is some sort of parallel Flying Ace/Red Baron fantasy plot featuring Snoopy and Woodstock, and it’s cute enough, but given that they have more-than-ample screen time in the main plot, I’m not sure why this was necessary. There are a couple of points at which the two plotlines intersect quite cleverly, but they could have easily been stand-alone gags.</p>

<p>The biggest departure from the original comics and cartoons is the film’s visual aesthetic, which trades Schulz’s shaky pencilled lines for more a more solid, vivid look. It’s new, but maintains the softness and charm I’m used to. I also appreciated that the more outdated elements of the Peanuts world are left alone. Thank you for not swapping out the rotary phones with smart phones, and for making Charlie Brown fly an actual kite rather than struggle with some sort of Kite Krusher app. </p>

<p>The film is basically 90 minutes worth of Peanuts strips strung together and brought to life, and I was curious as to whether this would be a good or bad thing. Sure, Charlie Brown’s sad-sack meanderings are great in small doses, but I wasn’t sure sustained, feature-length sad-sackery would be all that appealing. However, this is where the rest of the Peanuts gang really shines. Seeing Charlie Brown through the eyes of characters like Linus and Sally lets us appreciate his loyalty and tenacity in between laughing at one botched undertaking after another.</p>

<p>Because there are so many quintessentially Peanuts elements that have to be included, the film feels like it’s checking things off a list of trademark gags and one-liners without much thought to how or where they actually fit into the narrative, or even if they need to be in there at all. There had to have been a better spot for the Charlie Brown/Lucy/football gag than being shoehorned into a few seconds during the end credits. </p>

<p>While <em>The Peanuts Movie</em> retains much of the charm of Schulz’s work, and has enough to entertain long-time fans as well as newer, younger audiences, it just didn’t appeal to me on the same level as the comic strips, or previous animated adaptations. For me, the beauty of Peanuts is how it invites you to linger over a single vignette, and <em>The Peanuts Movie</em> flips through its various antics and misadventures a little too quickly. Just my five cents’ worth – for the doctor’s cookie jar, of course.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Spectre</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/6/spectre.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Spectre" />
    <published>2015-11-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/6/spectre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Warning: Spoilers Throughout</em></p>

<p>You and I are the same age James (at least your movie incarnation) both being born in the black and white world of 1962. That you—or at least a very specific iteration of you—died so early seems inevitable. That I lived to see it is just disappointing</p>

<p><em>Spectre</em> is an unintentionally apt title for this film James, since you are now a ghost of what you once were—and a pitiful, declawed ghost at that. The brutish, unmannered pig we were introduced to in <em>Casino Royale</em> has evolved into a character that is close to indistinguishable from some overwrought Roger Moore/Pierce Brosnan hybrid. Sans the invisible car, thankfully. Although we do get the front half of a plane skiing down a hill.</p>

<p>Jesus.</p>

<p>There were hints of this in <em>Skyfall—</em>intimations of a return to the smarmy, ludicrously heightened Bond. The old Aston Martin, the return of a male M, Moneypenny back in the office. I had hoped those moments were just a bit of fan service, a bump in the road before we got back to what makes your character so compelling: the fact that you are a blunt instrument of realpolitik; the ugly, twisted tip of the spear.</p>

<p>Instead, in this new installment, over the course of one hundred and forty eight minutes, you are utterly de-balled. The film begins well enough, with an effectively tense and well-choreographed opening sequence. Superb really. But at the very end of that sequence something occurred that made me cringe—and that small moment made it clear that Bond was back. But it was the small b-Bond, with the dad jokes and the annoying visual gags, not the Bond that you actually believed might be worthy of a double O designation.</p>

<p>And here’s the thing: the world has moved on. The character you were initially modeled on was repugnant. Ian Fleming’s Bond was a racist homophobe who couldn’t comprehend the term cultural sensitivity, let alone practice it. He was the epitome of a kind of colonialism that was, and is, completely toxic. The fact that the filmmakers choose to move you along with the world may have been expedient, but it destroyed the very thing that made you such a durable and interesting character. </p>

<p>That Bond was also someone who would much rather die than evolve. He smoked seventy cigarettes a day and drank like a fish. Jittery and bleak-minded he epitomized a life that absolutely precluded dying old and in bed. He was a spy with a license to kill, and he enjoyed the shit out of that prerogative.  </p>

<p>That Bond was a nasty dinosaur, a man literally out of time, and by far the most interesting incarnation by any standard. The man who, bare-handed, beat another man to death in <em>Casino Royale</em>—in black and white no less—has now given way to a man who throws his weapon of choice aside in order to ride off into the sunset with his girlfriend.</p>

<p>For you to exist in any meaningful way James, you have to contrast with your environment—you have to be the antithesis of a chameleon. For you, to <em>adapt</em> is to <em>die</em>. And if you continue down this road, it will be a slow, undignified expiration.</p>

<p>A <em>Spectre</em> of your former self indeed.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Crimson Peak</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/5/crimson-peak.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CrimsonPeak" />
    <published>2015-11-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/5/crimson-peak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If the lyric “every artist is a cannibal” holds any truth at all, it just might explain why you are more than a little rotund. You voraciously consume every sort of genre and then spew out a glorious mess that is neither beast nor fowl. If that seems indelicate and lyrical at the same time it is because that it what your work always seems to reduce to—a kind of lurid poetry that is impossible to ignore.</p>

<p>There is no point in trying to assess <em>Crimson Peak</em> by the usual metrics because its value is located somewhere far to the south of the standard criteria. Plot, consistency in tone, genre fidelity aren’t your primary concerns. Instead your work reads like something the Quay Bros. would produce—after being force fed ether by David Lynch. </p>

<p><em>Crimson Peak</em> is a film full of heightened performances, fifty two layers of metaphor in each frame, art direction inspired by a mix of Hieronymus Bosch and Durer with a touch of Mary Shelley and the Bronte’s, as well an innocence that sees this all as wondrous rather than grotesque. An elaborate children’s tea party that ends with all the dolls beheaded.</p>

<p>There are a lot of people this film will not impress. On its surface it’s an ornate melodrama punctuated by moments of horrific violence. It’s most overt metaphor is the awakening of the artist—in this case personified by Mia Wasikowska with her usual brilliance—which will irritate the hell out of the less esoterically inclined. It is neither as viscerally affecting as <em>Pan’s Labyrinth</em> nor as filled with childhood melancholy as <em>Devil’s Backbone</em>. What it does have though is a kind of sub rosa power that really doesn’t hit until long after the film is over.</p>

<p><em>Crimson Peak</em> is what Charlie Kaufman’s <em>Adaptation</em> would look like if it were re-interpreted as a historical romance sprinkled in gore. The narrative evolves as Wasikowska’s character—Edith Cushing—becomes more and more engaged with her own vocation as a writer. Each character that comes into (or in one case tragically and violently leaves) her life changes the tone of the story: the film begins as a stilted, turn-of-the-century period piece set in Buffalo NY and ends as Gothic horror. The finale occurs at a moor-locked, dilapidated manor house surrounded by newly fallen snow—snow that is stained blood red by seeping clay pits. </p>

<p>Subtlety thy name is <em>not</em> Del Toro.</p>

<p><em>Crimson Peak</em> is, more than anything else, a visually preposterous film. There is so much beauty and excess that it often threatens to overwhelm, but you have an innate capacity to fill the frame exactly up to the line,but never over. Jessica Chastain and Tom Hiddleston manage to make a sibling relationship seem both wrong and undeniably charged. Charlie Hunnam suits his character as well his period costume fit him (which is just fine) and Jim Beaver is starting to rival Sean Bean as the character least likely to make it to the third act. There are whole passages cribbed from Jane Eyre, I half expected Gary Oldman to appear stage left in his Dracula drag and there is an actual elevator to hell that plays a fairly prominent role in the latter half of the film.</p>

<p>And yet somehow, through some bizarre alchemy it seems impossible to pin down, this is a serious film made by an artist at the height of his powers. <em>Crimson Peak</em> has an ambiguous character that is both unsettling and riveting: a cherub disguised as a monster. Either way, it is a film worth the grapple.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Truth</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/4/truth.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Truth" />
    <published>2015-11-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/4/truth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I trust you were extra careful with every paper you handled on the set of <em>Truth</em>. Like, anal retentive, triple-check, hyper-cautiously-aware of your responsibilities. Sure, you were only hired as a production assistant, but first-time director James Vanderbilt obviously knows the importance of a solid paper trail after adapting Mary Mapes’ novel, so he must have hired you specifically to make sure everything was by-the-book. Otherwise, you know—the whole project/company/profession could have come crashing down.</p>

<p>No pressure.</p>

<p>It’s this kind of high-stakes attention to detail that sits at the heart of Vanderbilt’s film adaptation of <em>Truth and Duty: The Press, the President, and the Privilege of Power</em>, a first-hand account of the infamous CBS 60 Minutes news segment that questioned President George W. Bush’s military service record. What began as an earnest fact-finding mission about whether or not Bush was given a cushy job with the National Guard to avoid combat in Vietnam turned into a shadowy chess match between obscure sources with even more obscure motivations—one that famously cost host Dan Rather and producer Mary Mapes their careers.</p>

<p>The 60 Minutes segment aired during the 2004 presidential election, and was journalistically justified, in part, by Republican attacks against the service record of Democratic Presidential candidate John Kerry. But, with the help of a sleuth internet community, major questions arose about the authenticity of a key document being featured. The typeface, critics argued, matched those of a 2004 Word processor perfectly, and wasn’t the same as the ones found in most typewriters from 1971. More specifically, a superscript font appeared to be anachronistic. Within days, the story quickly shifted from Bush’s record to that of the news team that broke the story.</p>

<p>Much in the same way that the true scope of this story snuck up on the reporters, so too does the drama in Vanderbilt’s telling. The gravitas of what is happening isn’t apparent early on, nor was it for me as a university journalist student when this incident was first unfolding. After all, the media is famous for aggrandizing their own importance. And in the digital age, it has become fashionable to cheer the demise of the old establishment, even if it’s just to watch it burn. But seeing their credibility go up in smoke is a much more somber experience from the inside.  </p>

<p>What really makes this film work, however, are the more progressive elements of the story—namely, prioritizing Mapes’ story over Rather’s (who, in the public, was the much more prominent player). Experiencing the pile-on from a female perspective adds an intangible strength to the story in which the opposition came directly from the old boys club. Cate Blanchett navigates her role with the dignity you’d expect, and even gets backing from her (non-)trope “supportive husband”. Sure, Mapes’ psychology is a bit reductive (daddy-issues, with some on-the-nose dialogue to hammer the point home), but her professional motivations and methods are less easy to pick apart. </p>

<p>The film is also, thankfully, workmanlike in its approach, devoid of the hyperbolic visual flare that plagued <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/22/the-fifth-estate.html"><em>The Fifth Estate</em></a>, focusing instead on the details. A lot of care went into translating what was on the page onto the screen, which is exactly what a good journalism is all about. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>