<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-27T00:15:31Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lights Out</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/26/lights-out.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LightsOut" />
    <published>2016-07-26T19:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T19:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/26/lights-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Lights Out</em> is adapted from a well-regarded short film of the same name. </p>

<p>…and in that statement lies the central difficulty that plagues this inconsistent, only occasionally interesting film: how do you manage to expand a perfect little three minute short into a feature length film.</p>

<p>In some ways you succeeded. There is some real depth of character here, with a couple of performances that hint at a rich backstory. However, what you didn’t manage to develop—and this is crucial to a film that mixes the supernatural with the mundane—is a compelling mythology.</p>

<p>Effective horror depends upon creating a world that allows and encourages the suspension of disbelief. For a film to really crawl into your head, it must convince the you that the monster, whether it’s a relentless xenomorph, a young child inhabited by a devil, a pagan harridan preying upon an isolated New England family, or even a robotic assassin, is grounded in a reality that is credible in the context of the central concept. </p>

<p>To achieve this without bogging the film down in endless, dry exposition is difficult. In <em>Lights Out</em> you manage, for the most part, to avoid the dreary exposition. But you didn’t manage to create a mythology that felt like anything other than a cut and paste horror franchise origin story. Your monster had no depth, and because of that everything else felt kind of weightless. </p>

<p>Often the most tragic element (and therefore most compelling) of horror films is how the creature came into being, but if you fail to convey that in a plausible way, it undermines what gives these kinds of film their visceral power. One of the better examples of this is <em>Ringu</em>, a Japanese horror film from 1998 (a film which <em>Lights Out</em> shares more than a little DNA with, especially visually). In <em>Ringu</em> we’re given evocative hints about how the demonic apparition came to be, and moreover we are led to feel more than a little compassion for the creature. This doesn’t happen with the fumbling and perfunctory attempts that <em>Lights Out</em> makes at creating a similar mythos.</p>

<p>There are some effective visual conceits throughout <em>Lights Out</em> that involve light and the absence of it, but too often the story seems pushed into corners to accommodate these sequences. And while the performances range from solid to exceptional (Maria Bello’s interpretation of a mentally disturbed mother is unsettling in its authenticity) the contrast between them and the cobbled together feeling of the creature’s backstory only serves to highlight the film’s central weakness.</p>

<p>Where <em>Lights Out</em> works best is in set pieces common to this genre. There are a couple of scenes involving Maria Bello and her young son, as well as one other unseen participant that are masterfully blocked to maximize tension. In these moments <em>Lights Out</em> creates a sense of dread that is not just about the shock of the reveal, but also about how something in the dark can be whispering your death into the ear of someone who you expect to protect and nurture you.</p>

<p>If the whole film had lived more fully in these moments, if you had managed to ground something fantastic in something that felt convincing, <em>Lights Out</em> would have been something more than an occasionally watchable genre film. </p>

<p>Horseshoes and hand grenades.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My De Palma is Better Than Your De Palma</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MyDePalmaisBetterThanYourDePalma" />
    <published>2016-07-26T12:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T12:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>This is a thing I’ve long wondered about criticism in general and film criticism in particular: how can one disassociate the experience of art with the object of art itself? </p>

<p>No one reads a book or listens to music or watches a film in a total vacuum of objective critical focus. These are entertainments, and the whole notion of entertainment is to distract or edify or otherwise conjure good feelings inside one’s brain and/or heart. A book that you read on a beach in Mexico during a much-needed vacation from the crushing responsibilities of your professional life is experienced in a very different way than the book you read in fifteen-minute iterations over the course of a month on the bus that carries you each day to and from the crushing responsibilities of that professional life. A song that you first hear faintly playing in the background at a friend’s barbecue certainly affects you in a different way than the song that was playing at your junior high mixer when you looked across the gymnasium and saw Jessica Harbicht slow-dancing with Eric Forbes and <em>his hands</em> were <em>in her back pockets</em>! </p>

<p>And films. Films are the worst. Particularly when you see them in theaters. Because orbiting around the theater experience are numerous considerations: arrangements to be made (with friends, Tinder dates, babysitters); snacks (salty, sweet, unhealthy, <em>extremely</em> unhealthy); and, worst/best of all, other people sitting around you, each having their own unique moviegoing experience. </p>

<p>We like to think, as aficionados, that our arcane knowledge trumps our subjectivity—that somehow our understanding of, say, Auteur Theory or Apparatus Theory, or our devotion to Pauline Kael or Andrew Sarris, colours our ability to rationally judge an experience more than, say, whether you were able to time your arrival at the front of the concession to coincide with a freshly-popped batch of popcorn, or whether you got stuck with one of those limp three-quarters-full bags that has been sitting under a heat lamp for twenty minutes and turns out to be, once you dig to deeper strata, mostly composed of broken, burnt bits scraped from the bottom of the machine hours earlier. I can’t understand how a person can <em>honestly</em> say that the middle act of <em>Interstellar</em> is too self-serious and meandering when there’s a chance they might have been eating a bag of popcorn like that.</p>

<p>So what can I tell you, Tim, of my experience watching Noah Baumbach and Jake Paltrow’s documentary, <em>De Palma</em>, that isn’t deeply influenced by the physical conditions of my immediate environment and precise circumstances of my life in that particular moment of time? </p>

<p>I arrived at the VanCity Theater in Vancouver in a state of existential unease. The kind that is unique to business travel, wherein one is simultaneously relieved to be away from the routine of the 9-to-5 workday – the small talk with colleagues, the big talk with bosses – and also perturbed by the uncertainties of the foreign workday that awaits: the new people to make small talk with, the big talk one must inevitably engage in to justify the cost of cross-continent plane fare and deluxe accommodation. Not to mention the part where one misses one’s family and resents being taken away from them, yet simultaneously feels guiltily glad to be away from them and have a bit of freedom to, say, eat an entire pizza for dinner and then go to a movie alone.</p>

<p>The VanCity Theater is an exceptional little place. It’s not one of those old repertory cinemas with an ornate marquee, columns and lintels, velvet curtains and vintage, musty odors. They <em>do</em> have a little exterior ticket window, and the interior is laid out like the lobby of a hip hotel, all plain white walls, tall windows, café tables and couches. I arrived early enough to buy a beer and a package of licorice and lounge around for a while. The others waiting in the lobby with me were so typical of the demographic you might imagine to be loitering in the lobby of a nifty modern theater in Vancouver that it seems somehow cruel to describe them in further detail other than to say they were wealthy and middle-aged and predominantly white.  </p>

<p>When the doors eventually opened, we poured in and selected our seats a respectful distance from one another, passing the last few minutes before showtime watching the screen upon which an upcoming retrospective on mid-century Cuban cinema was being promoted. The place smelled like a classroom. The seats were soft and deep and ergonomically supportive. My cold beer sat sweating in the cupholder, waiting. This, the beginning of things. </p>

<p>I was overcome with such a sense of peace and excitement in that moment of prologue that I felt it physically; like there was a nozzle in my chest and someone had attached a hose and released into my body a hissing blast of ice-cold helium. The iris closed and blacked out the whole complicated fractal spread of my life – the myriad responsibilities both professional and personal and the myriad fears and anxieties attached to each of them – and I was <em>there</em>, in the theater, <em>present in the cosmic moment</em> in that Zen Buddhist way that self-help books about mindfulness try (and fail) to teach you how to conjure at will. </p>

<p>So, Tim, here’s the essential question I want to ask you:</p>

<p>Was <em>De Palma</em> a sublime moviegoing experience because it was a terrifically constructed and materially fascinating film which in its deceptive simplicity – basically just a single-take of a charismatic guy sitting in a chair in what appears to be his dining room, chatting unreservedly about his long and controversial career – is able to convey an artistic complexity and ambition of vision that on the surface of Brian De Palma’s <em>actual</em> films is difficult to identify (and maybe, in some cases, completely invisible)? </p>

<p>Or was the sublimity I experienced an effect of my mood, and of my physiological reaction to the hoppy IPA and perfectly supple licorice whips and the library-like quiet of the lobby and my desperate need, that particular evening, to remove myself from the world?</p>

<p>What we often pretend at, in criticism, is that we are not people, but rather these free-floating consciousnesses—bodiless intellectual machines that can process the pure data of a Thing and output an absolute empirical answer about whether or not that Thing sucks or is awesome or is just kinda okay. But movies – even analytical documentaries like this – are not expressions of pure intellectual substance. And people – even knowledgeable, tasteful people like me (self-proclaimed) – have memories and desires and are subject to unknowable subconscious prejudices. </p>

<p>The answer to the question I’ve asked above (which I’ll admit I don’t know) probably goes a long way to explaining my <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/3/iron-man-3.html">own</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/8/thor-the-dark-world.html">curious</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/30/x-men-days-of-future-past.html">reaction</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/7/27/the-dark-knight-rises.html">to</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/18/captain-america-civil-war.html">superhero</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html">movies</a>, as well as the dissonance many critics feel between their immediate instinctive response to a film and the broadening (or shrinking) of perspective they experience after the passing of a few days or weeks or even years (after that time has passed, they must reconcile their memories of that film with their experience of seeing it, which has been amplified or shrunken by their autobiographical memory). </p>

<p>When the end of the year arrives and we start compiling our lists of the best films of the year, <em>De Palma</em> will be at the top of mine. Perhaps by then I may have a sense that it wasn’t <em>objectively</em> the best motion picture released in the last 12 months. But our favorite things are never objective. They <em>belong</em> to us. We possess them, and we do so because they are meaningful beyond the simple diegetic expression of what we have seen onscreen and heard on the soundtrack. Our favorite movies mean something—not just because they are good, but because, in some way, they made our lives good, too.</p>

<p>For those two hours in Vancouver, at a time when I desperately needed it, <em>De Palma</em> made my life better. Which, on its own, is no criteria by which anyone should decide to rush out and see it. But is reason enough for me to judge it, empirically, unfairly, but totally accurately, a five-star film. </p>

<p>For whatever that’s worth. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/21/absolutely-fabulous-the-movie.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AbsolutelyFabulous:TheMovie" />
    <published>2016-07-21T10:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-21T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/21/absolutely-fabulous-the-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There was a time, in the early aughts, when <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/writers/dig/">Di</a> and I worked together at a video store almost every day. And we watched a <em>lot</em> of Ab Fab. It would remind us both of your heady days: when terrorists were Germans played by Alan Rickman, tall buildings exploding were considered cool (not PTSD triggers) and broad caricatures of gay men, minorities and the elderly and infirm were just fine, if done with one’s tongue sufficiently embedded in one’s cheek.</p>

<p>But man, that was then. <em>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</em> feels like a remake of Gilligan’s Island made 20 years after the fact—and without the irony. There is nothing about this film that manages to successfully remodel what made Ab Fab so delightful: two utterly unrepentantly selfish women, with almost no redeeming features, ingesting every legal and illegal substance known to man or woman. There really was no message, it was just this rolling train wreck populated by Jennifer Saunders and Joanna Lumley, and the whole joy was watching that very train wreck end exactly where it was aimed from the giddyup.</p>

<p>But for more reasons than I can fit in this space the film can’t reproduce that particular point in time and these characters, Patsy and Edina, can’t evolve without distorting them out of all recognition. The things that made them funny: their casual and unrepentant racism, the class snobbishness, their happy immersion in the worst sort of consumerism and their complete lack of interest in the welfare of Edina’s child (and in this film Edina’s grandchild—a character that is a perfect example of the kind of egregious tone deafness this film too often indulges) just aren’t funny anymore. This isn’t because either women is any less sharp or capable but what their characters are, at their core, is now so unpalatable that it has moved from being outrageous to simply unacceptable.</p>

<p>Structurally <em>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</em> also suffers from what any number of television show/feature film conversions suffer from—it feels like a single half hour episode stretched out over 90 minutes. Every scene is more or less a couple of jokes attached to whatever the particular premise for that sequence is, without any real through line, so instead of a feature length film it feels like a clip show of the more mediocre episodes. The material and pacing are stretched so thin that the thing that made Ab Fab so special—this inevitable, meteoric rush to disaster—is diluted to the point where it feels plodding. </p>

<p>I tend to think the only way this film could have worked is if they had played it utterly straight and gone super dark. Because for better or worse, the subjective distance between your blinkered innocence and the world today is far more than just a couple of decades. So these people whom we could once laugh at from a comfortable distance have become our modern day boogey(wo)men—not laughable, but simply targets of derision and contempt.</p>

<p>Some things are of their time and <em>Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie</em> is definitely an artifact that only really makes sense when wrapped in your warm, slightly ignorant, embrace.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ghostbusters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/20/ghostbusters.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Ghostbusters" />
    <published>2016-07-20T09:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-20T09:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/20/ghostbusters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>First year Film Studies taught me that you are a metaphor for the things that trouble our collective psyche. Obsession with female purity, threatened masculinity, you’re stand-ins for all of it. Often, the protagonists’ quest to rid themselves and the world of your presence represents a desire to exorcise the more unsavoury aspects of ourselves and our societies. Then Internet trolls remind us of all the shit we foolishly think we’ve resolved and buried, and it’s obvious you aren’t finished haunting us. </p>

<p>I knew I was going to enjoy Paul Feig’s <em>Ghostbusters</em> reboot long before I saw it. I’m not overly familiar with the original, but I’d give a 90-minute static shot of an oscillating fan two thumbs way, way up if it made sad men-children on the Internet as apoplectically furious as <em>LadyGhostbusters</em> has. Watching the film was actually a weird experience; it was formulaic, but also not. I guess I’m just not used to seeing this many women in a movie that doesn’t have any wet clothing or period jokes. Our heroines may get drenched in ectoplasm, but they don’t even smear it over their chests coquettishly - it was all very new for me. </p>

<p>I’m just kidding, <em>Ghostbusters</em> is a very clever and funny film. With four of the funniest women on the planet at the helm, all the one-liners, punchlines, and slapstick gags land with near-impeccable precision. I also admire the more activist aspect of the narrative, especially given the shitstorm of sexist temper tantrums that seem to have dogged the film at every turn. </p>

<p>When your corps of spooky spectres include men who chained their daughters up in cellars, and a large, white, puffed up, angry male, full of hot air, that literally tries to suffocate women, it isn’t hard to tell what Feig is getting at. By aiming their proton packs at all of you, our heroines aren’t merely busting ghosts, they’re out to exorcise The Patriarchy itself. Rather than ignoring the haters or bothering with all that ‘rising above’ crap, Feig and his cast harness all that vitriol, throw it right out in front of them, and then take aim. And they do not miss. The film further broadens its scope in order to call out institutionalized sexism in science and academia, and pokes fun at the way in which we gloss over the depravity and misogyny of history’s Great Men. Is it a tad ham-fisted and on the nose? Sure, but also pretty damn satisfying.</p>

<p>Still, <em>Ghostbusters</em> falls short in one glaring way. I was expecting the team to be comprised of four scientists, not three white scientists and a black woman who has to constantly defend her presence among them. And this has nothing to do with the fact that Leslie Jones is my very best friend (she just doesn’t know it yet). I was sorely disappointed by the way in which her character, Patty, is set apart from the other three. Their credentials and expertise are evident from the get-go; Patty, on the other hand, struggles to make space for herself and her awesomely encyclopedic brain. She has to constantly remind her teammates, “Hey, I’m smart, too!” while they stare back at her uncomprehendingly. For all the ghosts blasted away, one spectre unfortunately lives to see another day. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Free State of Jones</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/11/free-state-of-jones.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=FreeStateofJones" />
    <published>2016-07-11T06:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-11T06:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/11/free-state-of-jones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What <em>Free State of Jones</em> gets right is the details. For instance, Matthew McConaughey’s prosthetic teeth are truly repugnant, as was the style of the time. Grey-yellow and rotting, they certainly mirrored the society that spawned McConaughey’s Confederate deserter, Newton Knight—as well as establishing a clear sense of time and place</p>

<p>These little touches, from the flintlocks to the spiked necklaces that runaway slaves were forced to endure, all speak to a commitment to detail necessary these days to sell any period piece, particularly one so well documented as the American Civil War. </p>

<p>Where <em>Free State of Jones</em> falls short is in the more ephemeral aspects of a story that tries to present a revisionist history of the Southern experience. Knight (and tell me that isn’t a surname that has some specific weight for a white Southerner) led an internal revolt in the Confederate South during the Civil War. After deserting his unit and returning to his Mississippi home, Knight is confronted by the deprivations inflicted by the local Confederate detachment. Soon he is leading a ragtag militia of escaped slaves, local farmers and fellow deserters.</p>

<p>Hollywood is facing some difficult choices these days—most of which are of their own making. Audiences less and less interested in watching films where white males are doing the Moses thing—leading the poor and disenfranchised to a new world. So casting McConaughey as an enlightened sharecropper might have made sense ten, maybe even five, years ago, but now it feels tone deaf and out of step (especially when compared to something like the-soon-to-be-released Sundance darling <em>Birth of a Nation</em>).</p>

<p>It’s not that the story isn’t intrinsically interesting, but <em>Free State of Jones</em> is never agile enough to thread the sort of needles necessary to avoid feeling mawkish and retrograde. The spotlight that follows Knight throughout the film means that too much of the story revolves around his redemption and not nearly enough on those for whom the whole exercise is much more than an abstract moral choice. </p>

<p>There were any number of characters that would have been equally compelling and also would have presented a fresh perspective. Newton’s complicated domestic circumstance—his estranged wife returning years after he had been living common law with a former slave—presented an excellent jumping off point for an entirely different version of this story. Either one of their POV’s would have presented some fascinating narrative opportunities. </p>

<p>Instead what we got was a kind of paint by numbers script, which includes a needlessly complicated framing device involving a 20th century trial. The whole thing felt threadbare and tacked on. </p>

<p><em>Free State of Jones</em> finally devolves into a series of tableaux that attempt to describe the Reconstructionist Southern experience for people of color—all the while staying firmly affixed to Knight and his more mundane domestic tribulations.</p>

<p>If there had been more of a commitment to the ugly, difficult truths that your work represented, <em>Free State of Jones</em> may have managed to break from the mold it otherwise so thoroughly inhabited. Instead its entirely cosmetic approach to complex issues failed to rise to your exacting, if unattractive, standards.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>M. Night Shyamalan: The Final Blockbuster Auteur</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/8/m-night-shyamalan-the-final-blockbuster-auteur.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=M.NightShyamalan:TheFinalBlockbusterAuteur" />
    <published>2016-07-08T07:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-08T07:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/8/m-night-shyamalan-the-final-blockbuster-auteur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve got some bad news for you. If you grew up hoping to be the next Hitchcock, Spielberg, Scorsese, or Tarantino – a director so bankable that your name alone could sell a film – those dreams died 1999. Simply put: if you didn’t make a name for yourself by the end of the Millennium, you officially outlived the era of Blockbuster Auteurs. Membership is officially closed. Sorry.</p>

<p>The end came unexpectedly. In fact, in 1999, anything seemed possible. Two parallel phenomena were sweeping Hollywood, both in the ever-maligned horror genre. First, <em>The Sixth Sense</em> burst into theatres as a crowd-pleasing critical darling. Through sophisticated tension, careful visual construction, and a delicious twist ending, writer-director M. Night Shyamalan was instantly heralded as a master architect of suspense. His barely-seen previous films (a family comedy starring Rosie O’Donnell, and a comedic coming-of-age story starring himself) were somehow irrelevant; <em>The Sixth Sense</em> proved that he was a director to watch out for. His unusual name became a talking point—not just among cinephiles, but by average movie goers who couldn’t wait to see what he’d do next. </p>

<p>On the other end of the spectrum came <em>The Blair Witch Project</em>, a gimmicky premise that was somehow turned into a bona fide blockbuster (and still the most profitable independent film of all-time). The found-footage film arrived at a perfect moment: the Internet was accessible enough to spread the word, but not sophisticated enough to de-bunk the hoax. The film’s success was predicated almost entirely on the chance that it might, maybe, who knows, <em>actually be real</em>. But for aspiring filmmakers, what it really meant was that anyone with a camcorder could potentially make a name for themselves. </p>

<p>It was a glorious time. </p>

<p>And then something happened. <em>X-Men</em> was released in 2000 and introduced a new, more socially-relevant, more earnest approach to blockbuster filmmaking. That success bred <em>Spider-Man</em>, and eventually a re-booted Batman series. Each of these films were directed by lauded filmmakers: Brian Singer, Sam Raimi, and Christopher Nolan, respectively. And in this unholy marriage of unique voices and familiar properties, a new formula for Hollywood success was born. </p>

<p>On the other end of the spectrum, it was a race to the bottom for low-budget break-out success. The wild rates of return experienced by the <em>Saw</em> and <em>Paranormal Activity</em> franchises made skittish studio executives gitty over mainstream genre exercises. And slowly but surely, the mid-range budgets that visionary directors normally found to grow the scale of their films and audience started to disappear. The gamble on talent became too rich for Tinsletown. </p>

<p>So by the end of the decade, the name of the director quickly took a backseat to the property being developed. Like Disney animation or MGM musicals, the brand of the studio replaced the brand of the director; the producers, and their long-term corporate expansion plans, became the visionaries who drove the storytelling. And now, in all the years that have passed since 1999, not a single new blockbuster director has emerged as a marketable talent for the average movie-going public to recognize and galvanize behind. </p>

<p>It sounds hard to believe, I know. But Peter Jackson brought us <em>The Lord of The Rings</em> in 2001, only after directing five other films. And though his LOTR trilogy was a massive success, his follow-up in 2005, <em>King Kong</em> (another established property), failed to pave the way for any bold or original future works. Even Michael Bay – a polarizing figure in cinema but undeniable audience magnet – shifted into franchise filmmaking with <em>Transformers</em>. Of course, other legacy name-brand directors like James Cameron, Tim Burton, and David Fincher continued their output, but no new names have been added beneath them on the list. Not a single Millennial director has captured the world’s attention the way M. Night Shyamalan last did.</p>

<p>Should we blame Shyamalan for this? Did he really burn his studios so badly with his subsequent string of mega-flops that they will never again try to build their brands on the back of a director? True, by the time he released <em>Lady in the Water</em> in 2006, his name was more of a liability than selling feature. But does that really explain why someone hasn’t taken up the mantle?</p>

<p>You might argue a case for a few names in comedy: Judd Apatow, Tyler Perry. But both come with big caveats. Apatow works more as a producer than director, and good luck getting your mom to name a film that Apatow has directed (my personal barometer for cross-over success). Perry is more of a niche success, like Wes Anderson, P.T. Anderson, The Cohen Brothers, or Woody Allen, even though starring in many of his films gives him better name recognition. After that, we get to names like J.J. Abrams, who works almost exclusively with other people’s franchises (<em>Mission: Impossible</em>, <em>Star Trek</em>, <em>Star Wars</em>). And those other unique voices we might have held out hope for? Ryan Johnson, Ryan Coogler, even Zack Snyder? They, too, find themselves at the mercy of the mega-franchise. </p>

<p>It’s sad. Devastating, really. We hear anecdotal stories all the time about directors like Steven Soderberg wanting to quit the business. But the theatres still fill up, and the studios are making more money than ever. So why do so many famous filmmakers paint a doom and gloom picture of a life making movies? It’s simple, really. And in a sense, it all comes back to M. Night Shyamalan. The man who re-invigorated Hollywood’s appetite for big budget auteurs may have also brought about their demise. How’s that for a Shyamalanian twist ending? </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Independence Day: Resurgence</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/6/independence-day-resurgence.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=IndependenceDay:Resurgence" />
    <published>2016-07-06T05:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-06T05:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/6/independence-day-resurgence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The way Hollywood spends money is a growing matter of contention. I don’t just mean which states and countries get productions based on tax credits and exchange rates, but what <em>types</em> of films get greenlit in the first place. Much has been said about how the middle has fallen out of cinema – you’re either making an independent film for less than $5M and hoping for a modest return, or you’re pumping up a $150M tent-pole production with a P&amp;A budget (prints and advertising)that <a href="http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/200-million-rising-hollywood-struggles-721818">doubles down on that investment</a>. In other words, for every <em>Independence Day: Resurgence</em>, the world is getting anywhere from five to 50 <em>less</em> mid- and low-budget films. </p>

<p>How’s that for an apocalyptic scenario?</p>

<p>The business appeal of doing something like <em>Resurgence</em> is pretty straight-forward. In theory, all these reboots, remakes, sequels, and adaptations already have built-in brand recognition that will ease entry to the market place. But familiarity can quickly turn into fatigue, and when a recycled business model becomes transparent, audiences usually wise-up. And boy, were eyes wide open for this planet-sized cash grab.</p>

<p>Still, I entered the cinema on my own terms and in good faith. I naively hoped that this new film could recapture some of the thrill I felt as a 13-year-old seeing <em>Independence Day</em> in 1996. Plus, <em>Jurassic World</em> proved that following up a mid-90s mega hit could nail the sweet spot of nostalgia and new appeal. But while Chris Pratt brought that extra element of rising star appeal to the dino-sequel, <em>Resurgence</em> had a Will Smith-sized void in that department (apologies to non-Thor Hemsworth). I couldn’t help but wonder – was it a budget thing?  </p>

<p>You’re not the right person to ask, I know. People like you are tasked with controlling dollars on the ground during production, which may also be problematic. You were no doubt given a blue print for not only what’s been spent in the past, but what is a reasonable rate of return for investments in the future. Blowing up a scaled-down exact model of the White House, for example, proved to be an extremely wise bang-for-your-buck investment back in 1996. When <em>Independence Day</em> hit theatres, that trailer image electrified audiences and made the film a must-see. There was still a novelty to end-of-the-world films, which hadn’t yet saturated the market (<em>Armageddon</em> and <em>Deep Impact</em> took care of that a couple years later). So what’s the big money shot this go around? The gag of just barely bending the flag atop the White House is pretty much the only unique image that comes to mind – and that was barely worthy of a smirk. </p>

<p>In a world where “we’ll fix it in post” has gone from being a punchline to standard operating procedure, there was a lack of tangible investment in this film – both physical and emotional. We’ve seen so many cities crumble on screen with so little consequence, studios forget it’s not a one-for-one exchange: ticket prices aren’t based on the number of buildings that crumble.</p>

<p>I don’t know what it would have cost to make a film where we give a shit what happens, but it’s a whole less than this.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Legend of Tarzan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/5/the-legend-of-tarzan.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheLegendofTarzan" />
    <published>2016-07-05T05:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-05T05:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/5/the-legend-of-tarzan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I see what you were going for here; a high volume of tightly framed shots to urge the audience to tap into our dormant, primal selves, employing a womb-like closeness, hoping to showcase the animalistic savagery that hides deep inside all humans. The concept invited intimacy and could have been really impactful if used sparingly, instead it only highlighted <em>The</em> <em>Legend of Tarzan</em>’s shoddy editing and its humdrum lead, Alexander Skarsgård.</p>

<p>Contrary to what many attendees of <em>Legend of Tarzan</em> believed (judging by the amount of kids in the audience), the movie is <em>not</em> a sequel to the 1999 Disney animated classic. <em>The _Legend of Tarzan</em> is actually an original story of sorts, grabbing inspiration from the ‘Tarzan of the Apes’ series by Edgar Rice Burroughs. </p>

<p>It follows Tarzan – now known as John Clayton or Lord Greystoke – as he hesitantly agrees to head back to the jungles of the Congo after years of living in London as a civilized gentleman. He believes he is there to act as an ambassador for Britain when he is actually walking into a trap set by the villainous Leon Rom, who wants to establish slavery in order to mine precious diamonds. Once he arrives at the Congo, Tarzan is ambushed by Rom and forced to watch his wife, Jane, be taken captive. In order to get her back, he must ditch his pressed pantaloons and become, once again, the King of the Apes. </p>

<p>It makes total sense why you chose to favour the extreme close-up. After spending so many years being civilized, Tarzan struggles to go back to the man he once was. Your too-close-for-comfort cinematography was meant to capture his feral nature clawing to get out. </p>

<p>Unfortunately, Alexander Skarsgård’s monotonous energy drained any level of excitement from the experience, even when he was parading as some strange jungle Batman, attacking people from the shadows and fighting off hordes of colonial military men in close quarters. Given that he was cast to literally play the King of the Apes, it&#39;s a shame that Skarsgård couldn&#39;t emote any sort of fervour other than tight-lipped smouldering. It seems he was more concerned with flexing his abs than he was with being Tarzan. He was less man raised by apes and more Abercrombie model with mud smeared on his face. </p>

<p>But he looks good without a shirt on, which is probably the only reason he got the job in the first place. He was a highly mismatched beauty to your beastly filming concept. </p>

<p>But we can’t blame Skarsgård for everything. Your up close and personal approach took its biggest hit during the editing process. The extreme close-ups were interspersed between panning shots, action sequences, and flashbacks without any outward reasoning. There didn&#39;t seem to be any method behind the madness. </p>

<p>Your techniques should&#39;ve been used sparingly to show the true nature of, well, <em>nature</em>. Instead your tight frames were implemented over and over until all that was left was a movie with a lack of identity, which is ironic because <em>The</em> <em>Legend of Tarzan</em> is all about identity. </p>

<p><em>The</em> <em>Legend of Tarzan</em> had all the elements to be a great movie; a classic character returning to glory to stop an evil tyrant bent on using slavery to get his way, a strong message of staying true to one&#39;s self and never forgetting where you came from, and excellent performances by Samuel L. Jackson and Christoph Waltz. It even had your tight frame concept that would have done wonders if used properly.</p>

<p>Sadly, the concept was tied to a stone-faced lead and an editing process that had its own aspirations which left <em>The</em> <em>Legend of Tarzan</em> incapable of seeing the forest for the trees.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Shallows</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/6/30/the-shallows.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheShallows" />
    <published>2016-06-30T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-06-30T04:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/6/30/the-shallows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My colleague Di and I disagree a fair bit. What we most certainly do <em>not</em> disagree on is that locations are not characters. </p>

<p>But addressing you directly is unavoidable. <em>The Shallows</em> leans all over your preternatural beauty, especially your pristine water—a shade of aching blue green that I have heretofore never experienced. In fact, the first half of the film is so overwhelmingly pretty, so well composed, so unearthly that I kind of resented the fact that it slowly morphed into a fairly tense one hander, starring an affable and quietly believable Blake Lively.</p>

<p>There were problems to be sure. Lively is a surfer who has managed to find an isolated beach that, surprise, surprise also has a personal significance. Too much of <em>The Shallows</em> was obvious in its construction and that kind of transparency—seeing the metaphorical framework—always undercuts the audience’s ability to suspend disbelief. The performances, mostly Lively, as well as a few smaller roles (mostly sharkbait) were uniformly good. Naturalistic and unassuming they were a useful counterpoint to the obvious plot mechanics. The CG was abominable, as both the shark, and the earlier surfing scenes where Lively’s face was badly grafted onto someone else’s body, conspired to undermine what was otherwise a visually compelling film.</p>

<p>There <em>were</em> moments of genuine humor, tension, occasional pathos and a couple of really clever set pieces—not to mention a setting that was constantly beautiful, whether it was noon or midnight. It would be supremely difficult to find a bad shot given how perfect you look.</p>

<p>This was a frustrating experience in some ways because <em>The Shallows</em> was so close to being an excellent genre film. Jaume Collet-Serra, who’s directing credits include <em>Non-Stop</em> and <em>The Orphan,</em> compensates for his lack of subtly with a technical competence, and there is real power in some of his visual flourishes. But it is the writing that really drags <em>The Shallows</em> down, mostly by telegraphing every narrative beat. </p>

<p>And for every good moment there was something that managed to break the mood almost immediately. The best example of this is a recurring non-human character that was used very effectively until the film makers (and I have barely managed to avoid this till now) jumped the shark. Then the whole audience investment in what was a surprisingly engaging subplot was completely squandered. Too often <em>The Shallows</em> zigged when it should have zagged, and more than anything else it was these poor choices that dragged the film down in the morass of countless other B grade thrillers.</p>

<p>But I will never forget your compelling presence and eye watering beauty, Lord Howe Island, and while you aren’t in the cast list, I tend to think if I remember anything about <em>The Shallows</em> six weeks from now, it will be you and only you.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Swiss Army Man</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/6/27/swiss-army-man.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SwissArmyMan" />
    <published>2016-06-27T05:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-06-27T05:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/6/27/swiss-army-man</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Don’t be creeped out, but I was watching you while you were watching <em>Swiss Army Man</em>. And I’m not sure which was more entertaining—which is saying something.</p>

<p>The mixture of disgust, amusement, genuine sadness, goofy joy and confusion that flitted across your features spoke volumes. Clearly what you were experiencing was having a profound effect upon you. Not surprising, I suppose, given how the themes that inform <em>Swiss Army Man</em>—alienation, self-loathing, self-imposed isolation, parental disregard and suicidal ideation—are all things you have, or continue to, struggle with.</p>

<p>Weird eh? But I’ve been watching you for a really, really long time.</p>

<p>That these themes played out in a visual style that is best described as Michael Gondry suffering through a mescaline overdose also had something to do with how overwhelming <em>Swiss Army Man</em> was to experience. Add to this a couple of truly inspired performances from Daniel Radcliffe and Paul Dano, who managed to take material that is utterly absurd and transform it into something happily coherent, and I can understand why this film seemed to hold you in its sway for its entire run time.</p>

<p><em>Swiss Army Man</em> is that rare piece of art that is both joyful in execution, while speaking in brutally honest terms to the kinds of existential truths that seem to plague most members of our species—those of love and death, and the impossibility of ever really being comfortable in your own skin. That it so happily dissects these in such a surreal but concise way is a wonder of storytelling alchemy.</p>

<p>The visual grammar of this film supports a constantly engaging narrative, despite a very loose relationship with chronology or anything close to objective reality. The dream logic that informs most of the film deals in the sort of emotional truths that are difficult to convey with conventional narrative schemes. That <em>Swiss Army Man</em> succeeds in that difficult task was made obvious by your unblinking attention. You were completely immersed in what was happening up on the screen. </p>

<p>And while this film is anything but meandering, what it evokes is both complicated and difficult to express, because it bypasses the frontal cortex and shoots straight into the midbrain. In the best possible way <em>Swiss Army Man</em> is an arthouse film that doesn’t require you to think so much as it demands you experience it on its own terms. That I got to watch you struggle with that frankly made my day.</p>

<p>By the way, you sure do cry a lot. If I had to guess I would say you were probably in tears for a good third of this film, not to mention the entire walk home from Bloor to Shaw—which is like, what, a good hour or so?</p>

<p>Oh yes, I know where you live. Don’t worry though, you won’t ever see me.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>