<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-27T22:45:29Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Top 5 Reviews: Personal Favourites</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/24/top-five-reviews-personal-favourites.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Top5Reviews:PersonalFavourites" />
    <published>2017-03-24T06:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-24T06:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/24/top-five-reviews-personal-favourites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>We do this site out of pure love – a love of watching movies, writing about movies, and reading about movies. As a collective of film nerds, we get off on finding different ways to look at a film’s production or think about its meaning. And after five years, there are times we feel we’ve done that better than others.</p>

<p>So here they are, each critic’s <strong>favourite reviews they’ve written</strong> during the DC&amp;C Era (past five years) – which rarely correspond with our favourite <em>films</em> from the past five years (that Top 5 coming soon!).</p>

<p>Please note: not ranked – but with a small description for each.</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Christopher Redmond’s  Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/10/prisoners.html"><em>Prisoners</em></a><br>
Jared once said he liked this review, which automatically makes it one of my favourites. Plus, when I <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve.html">interviewed Denis Villeneuve</a> a few months later, I asked him to shout-out a below-the-line crew member that he thought wouldn’t otherwise be recognized. He praised Bruce Hamme. Blew my mind.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/11/enemy.html"><em>Enemy</em></a><br>
Another review for a Villeneuve film, but writing this one somehow made me understand (or at least enjoy) the film more.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/8/16/dream-house.html"><em>Dream House</em></a><br>
When you have a chance to take your anger against the sub-prime mortgage crisis out on an appallingly bad movie called <em>Dream House</em> – you hit that shit hard.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/12/american-reunion.html"><em>American Reunion</em></a><br>
It’s so simple, but it works. At 149 words, it’s one of our shortest reviews too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/10/28/the-16-sexiest-roles-on-a-film-set.html"><em>The 16 Sexiest Roles on a Film Set</em></a><br>
I’ve written a few dozen essays over the years, so I wanted some representation of that. They aren’t usually this silly, but the real goal was to give every on-set department some praise, peppered with a bit of insight. That’s the whole goal of the site, after all.</p>

<p><em>Honourable mention:</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/2/the-artist.html"><em>The Artist</em></a><br>
Not only my first review, but the first DC&amp;C review, period. It was intended as a proof-point that we could make the site’s concept work writ-large and a template I personally tried to follow for not including a standard plot synopsis, taking a slightly ironic approach (writing to a sound tech on a silent film), and referencing the recipient’s previous work. Not my favourite review by any means, but a meaningful one.</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Jared Young’s  Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/22/olympus-has-fallen.html"><em>Olympus Has Fallen</em></a><br>
I still can’t decide how sarcastic I was being with this five-star review, but I nonetheless enjoyed writing a little paean to the awesome action soundtracks of my youth.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/7/27/the-dark-knight-rises.html"><em>The Dark Knight Rises</em></a><br>
Me at my most self-righteous.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/7/shame.html"><em>Shame</em></a><br>
The anatomical review that started a Dear Cast and Crew craze.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/24/straight-outta-comptopn.html"><em>Straight Outta Compton</em></a><br>
I still struggle with some of the questions I posed in this review: how do you reconcile with the work of an artist who commits terrible acts in their private life?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/5/mr-turner.html"><em>Mr. Turner</em></a><br>
I’m not sure I can clearly explain why I’m so fond of this particular review; it was a tough one to write, but it turned out to feel (to me, at least) very genuine. Also, it’s written to a guy named Dick Pope.</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Casey Tourangeau’s Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/26/the-lucky-one.html"><em>The Lucky One</em></a><br>
My first full-length review for the site. Sometimes the first time is the best.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/9/sorry-the-lego-movie-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html"><em>Sorry, The Lego Movie is the Best Film of 2014</em></a><br>
I had a lot of trepidation naming a movie best of the year for such personal reasons, but the resulting piece justified its selection.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/7/wolf-of-wall-street.html"><em>The Wolf of Wall Street</em></a><br>
This review was as much a reaction to some criticism I thought was invalid (attacking it for the actions of its real-life subject, instead of how it’s treated on screen) as it was review of the movie itself. Either way, it forced me into a deep dive I rarely get the chance to take.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/2/15/a-good-day-to-die-hard.html"><em>A Good Day to Die Hard</em></a><br>
As much fun as I had systematically taking this apart, I wish my review could have simply been what the person sitting next to me yelled during a scene in which the sound drops out in an effort to inspire awe: “BOOOOOOOO!!!”</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/1/cloudy-with-a-chance-of-meatballs-2.html"><em>Cloudy with a Chance of Meatballs 2</em></a><br>
This must be the most aggressive I’ve ever felt writing a review. The fact that it was aimed at a cynical children’s film made it feel all the better.</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Di Golding’s Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/12/19/grudge-match.html"><em>Grudge Match</em></a><br>
My first review for DC&amp;C. I showed my first draft to Tim McEown (my friend of 16 years who lovingly refers to me as Her Vagesty, Queen of Ascerbia), and he recommended I maybe scale back my hostility until I’d established a rapport with the rest of the team. So I sent a toned down revised draft to Christopher Redmond who asked if I could maybe amp up my vitriol. I knew then that I’d found my people.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/15/still-not-over-the-canyon-thelma-and-louise-at-25.html"><em>Still Not Over the Canyon: Thelma and Louise at 25</em></a><br>
What I love most about writing for DC&amp;C is the freedom I have to write what I want, how I want. This essay is about one of my favourite films, and what has (and hasn’t) changed for women in front of and behind the camera in 25+ years.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/8/1/amy.html"><em>Amy</em></a><br>
I do my best to go into a film with minimal expectations. That said, I thought I knew what this film was going to be, and I was glad to be wrong. If I could go back and give it another star, I would.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/27/creed.html"><em>Creed</em></a><br>
My DC&amp;C compatriots revere a film from the mid-70s that went on to spawn a franchise that has endured for the last four decades and is poised to continue to do so for the foreseeable future. So do I. Theirs features a Wookie. Mine features an Italian Stallion. Apologies to Jared Young who somehow always gets the unenviable task of editing one of my Rocky pieces (three and counting).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam.html"><em>We Need to Talk About Adam</em></a><br>
As long as his movies keep getting greenlit, we will never not need to talk about Adam.</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Tim McEown’s Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/8/22/kubo-and-the-two-strings.html"><em>Kubo and The Two Strings</em></a><br>
Most fun review because I got to talk about Noh theatre, Ray Harryhausen, Samurai and Monkeys. Hard to beat that.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/8/22/kubo-and-the-two-strings.html"><em>Mistress America</em></a><br>
Sometimes it’s childishly fulfilling to be able to sincerely dump on people’s sacred cows.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/12/9/jackie.html"><em>Jackie</em></a><br>
This was, for me, the most difficult review I’ve had to write because the film was so technically complex. I worked harder on this than any other review I’ve written.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html"><em>Nightcrawler</em></a><br>
This was the first review where I began to understand what exactly I wanted to do when writing about films.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar.html"><em>Hail, Caesar!</em></a><br>
Best time at the movies I’ve had in a very long time. So easy to write.</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Nat Master’s Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/19/elle-is-the-best-and-angriest-film-of-2016.html"><em>Elle is the Best (and Angriest) Film of 2016</em></a><br>
I got to rage against The Patriarchy, which is always fun (and essential).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/23/the-night-before.html"><em>The Night Before</em></a><br>
I enjoyed writing this so much I briefly considered formatting all my reviews as poems going forward, but then I changed my mind, so you were all spared my haiku on the undercurrent of misogyny in <em>The Peanuts Movie</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/4/leviathan.html"><em>Leviathan</em></a><br>
I feel like this one makes me sound really insightful and smart, which is a marked departure from my usual stream of cursing and complaining.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/1/4/love.html"><em>Love</em></a><br>
You guys don’t even know how many truly awful 3D dick puns there were in my original draft.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/3/a-hologram-for-the-king.html"><em>A Hologram for the King</em></a><br>
The guy I addressed the review to actually sent us a lovely, gracious email expressing thanks for my comments, which was so nice because I am constantly paranoid that addressees will be super-offended by my reviews and @ me all like, “Hey, fuck you!”</p>

<hr>

<p><u><strong>Ankit Verma’s Top 5 Fav Reviews</strong></u></p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/29/gods-of-egypt.html"><em>Gods of Egypt</em></a><br>
I love going on a good rant. I find it therapeutic. Chicken soup for the soul. <em>Gods of Egypt</em> gave me so much ammo to unleash, I found myself in a zen-like state of pure bliss by the end.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/7/2/magic-mike-xxl.html"><em>Magic Mike XXL</em></a><br>
<em>Magic Mike XXL</em> was the first review where I was so sure about my pick for letter recipient, that I hammered out a draft in under 20 minutes. Plus, I got to use the phrase, ’ass-less-iest of ass-less chaps’ which is historic in its own right.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/8/2/nerve.html"><em>Nerve</em></a><br>
Sometimes it’s good to go into a movie with low expectations so you can be blown away by how utterly real it is.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/10/27/jack-reacher-never-go-back.html"><em>Jack Reacher: Never Go Back</em></a><br>
Call it nostalgia or call it bad taste; I have a strange soft-spot for lame 90’s action movies. <em>Jack Reacher: Never Go Back</em> was the ultimate throwback.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/23/captain-america-civil-war-is-the-best-and-worthiest-film-of-2016.html"><em>Captain America: Civil War is the Best (and Worthiest) Film of 2016</em></a><br>
2016 was a fantastic year for critically-acclaimed movies. So, when it came down to choosing the best of the best, I stuck with my gut and chose a superhero movie that transcended its genre and exceeded all of my expectations. I still get death threats to this day. Good times.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello Destroyer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/22/hello-destroyer.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HelloDestroyer" />
    <published>2017-03-22T12:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-22T12:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/22/hello-destroyer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Hockey is easy to glorify on film. From crowd pleasing chest-thumpers like <em>Miracle</em> and <em>The Rocket</em> to quotable fist-pumpers like <em>Slap Shot</em> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/2/goon.html"><em>Goon</em></a> (and this month’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/3/21/goon-last-of-the-enforcers.html"><em>Goon: Last of the Enforcers</em></a>), there’s something about watching modern-day ice gladiators that appeals to my sense of patriotism and my blood-lust. I’m a sucker for the bone crushing sounds of hard hits and fast fists. But <em>Hello Destroyer</em> is not a typical hockey film. It’s only about hockey inasmuch as that sport, for many young men in this country, is a means to escape rural desolation, and pursue some modicum of greatness. </p>

<p>Canadians spend a lot of time deifying hockey heroes. <em>Hello Destroyer</em>, chips away at the myth of the hockey god to show us the mere mortal inside.</p>

<p>There is a moment early on in the film when the protagonist, Tyson, speaks of his childhood phobia – silence. He tells a teammate how he would physically react to silence, with nausea and headaches so bad his parents would have to soothe him with music to drown it out. He tells this anecdote matter-of-factly, and it is the longest monologue he has in the film. Your thoughtful sound design fills in the rest of the blanks of this hulking man-child’s experience on and off the ice. He may be a destroyer on the rink, but he is prisoner in his own head.</p>

<p>Tyson is an enforcer for the junior hockey league in British Columbia, and though he is part of a team, you make his isolation obvious. From the raucous locker room hazing rituals, to the drowned out, ambient noise of the post-game shower, it becomes clear that Tyson is not like the others, though he very much longs to be. In one effective shot, we see a close-up of an uneasy Tyson on the rink, his helmet and visor awash in the strobing neon of the pre-game chaos, as ear-splitting techno music throbs around him. Writer/director Kevan Funk shows us Tyson’s separateness, but you make us hear it. Tyson struggles to belong – to the team, to the family that hosts him, to the paternalistic coaches who encourage his latent aggression – but he never quite figures out how. When he is summarily dismissed for being too effective as an enforcer, he retreats like a scolded animal, never quite understanding what it is he did wrong.</p>

<p>Jared Abrahamson anchors this film with a subtle intensity. His Tyson is wholly believable as both a brutal force on the ice and a tortured child in the real world. Your sound design echoes this dichotomy perfectly, with abruptly loud noises like the saw Tyson uses to cut slabs of beef in the slaughterhouse, followed by stark silences as he walks the grey, wintery streets of suburban B.C. and rural Alberta, his hoodie zipped overhead to protect him. Perhaps the most deafening silence of all comes from within the walls of Tyson’s family home, where his parents barely acknowledge him. His painfully awkward attempts to express himself, and his inability to form any meaningful human connections are agonizing to watch, and while Funk’s prolonged shots of Tyson’s isolation from the world eventually grow tiresome, Abrahamson’s portrayal never does. </p>

<p>You punctuate this film with noises we are all familiar with – sticks hitting ice, pads hitting boards, coaches and players hurling insults – as well as the white-noise monotony and silences that punctuate Tyson’s discomfort in his own skin. Hockey fans, and fans of hockey films, are used to watching underdog athletes rise to victory, but rarely do we see the inner life of the young men (boys, really) who fail to succeed. Even more rare that we get to hear it. <em>Hello Destroyer</em> reminds us of a sad truth; for some players, there are no glory days.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Goon: Last of the Enforcers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/21/goon-last-of-the-enforcers.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Goon:LastoftheEnforcers" />
    <published>2017-03-21T09:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-21T09:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/21/goon-last-of-the-enforcers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There’s an old saying in hockey (all sports, probably), that it’s not the name on the back of the jersey that matters; it’s the name on the front. The team comes first. Especially for the fans that pride themselves on supporting the same club for decades, through all their ups and downs. But there comes a point when blind devotion means you’re simply cheering for laundry(like every Superman, Batman and Spider-man iteration being bullet-proof at the box-office). The Halifax Highlanders jersey from <em>Goon</em>, of course, is hardly enough to sell tickets, so luckily you were able to get those uniforms back on everyone from the original film. Well, almost everyone. And the missing piece(s) might be why this film just couldn’t make the proverbial playoffs. </p>

<p>Let’s start with the stars on the roster. Seann William Scott was obviously game for a sequel. <em>Goon</em> played to all of his strengths and unearthed an emotional center that was sorely lacking in any of his previous performances. Liev Schreiber also returns and reprises his position as the perfect anti-antagonist. The rest of the team (Marc-Andre Grondin as the hot-shot winger, Kim Coates as the baffled coach, etc) are also present and accounted for. Even the fans in the stands came back – most notably Jay Baruchel as the foul-mouthed best friend, and his real-life ex-fiancée Alison Pill. Overcoming that bit of personal drama for the good of the team proves just how dedicated both actors were to making <em>Goon: Last of the Enforcers</em>. </p>

<p>In fact, the same way Scott’s Doug Glatt is given the “C” in the opening scene of the film, Baruchel was promoted to captain of team <em>Goon when Michael Dowse was no longer available to direct. Baruchel’s dedication to the fictional Highlanders is unquestionable –having co-written both scripts – and he was able to draft some new top talent for _Last of the Enforcers,</em> including Callum Keith Rennie, Elisha Cuthbert, and the film’s real key acquisition – Wyatt Russell. But like Doug, who is all heart and no brains, Baruchel’s passion may have blinded him from making some hard cuts that would have made this a more effective team on screen.</p>

<p>T.J. Miller, for example, as a TSN-esque sports commentator, was clearly hired for his ability to improvise strange and (usually) funny comments. But because his segments are supposed to be aired on a mainstream network (as opposed to a YouTube channel, like the original <em>Goon</em>), it takes us out of the film rather than being comedic connective tissue. There are also small details, like the fact Miller only looks into his close-up camera, when Baruchel sticks mainly to the wide two-shot 2nd camera. By not looking directly into the lens, it feels like Miller is reading <em>Saturday Night Live</em> cue cards – which takes all the energy away from his improvisation. It’s a rookie director mistake, and one example of how small choices can add up and cost you the game.</p>

<p>It’s hard to know how much the other major missing player, co-writer Evan Goldberg, could have helped. <em>Last of the Enforcers</em> has plenty of heart, but misses a few too many shots. It’s often bloody and sometimes funny, but missing the element of surprise that made <em>Goon</em> a real knock-out. Still, as a die-hard fan of Baruchel and Canadian cinema, I won’t be hanging up my sweater any time soon.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Top 5 Reviews: By the Numbers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/16/top-five-reviews-by-the-numbers.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Top5Reviews:BytheNumbers" />
    <published>2017-03-16T05:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-16T05:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/16/top-five-reviews-by-the-numbers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You have some explaining to do.</p>

<p>The following reviews, essays, lists and interviews have received the most traffic since we launched Dear Cast and Crew five years ago. For the next five weeks, we&#39;ll be taking the excuse to highlight some of our best and most-read pieces. We have over 800 reviews, dozens of special features, and more than few replies from the actual people we&#39;ve written. Lots of great stuff to catch up on if you haven&#39;t read it before.</p>

<p>So let&#39;s start as objectively as possible before we start play favourites. These are the pieces that you, the readers, have been most attracted to so far:</p>

<p><strong>TOP 5 OVERALL</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/7/12/grown-ups-2.html">Grown Ups 2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/14/man-of-steel.html">Man of Steel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/20/titanic-3d.html">Titanic 3D</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/4/top-10-uncredited-heroes-of-jurassic-park.html">Top 10 Uncredited Heroes of Jurassic Park</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/7/19/the-dark-knight-rises.html">The Dark Knight Rises</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top Essays</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/1/american-snipers-magic-bullet-theory.html">American Sniper&#39;s Magic Bullet Theory</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/15/the-case-against-andy-serkis.html">The Case Against Andy Serkis</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/ghosts-of-ghostbusters.html">Ghosts of Ghostbusters</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html">Why Gone Girl Makes me Sad for the State of Cinema</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/16/canadas-hottest-filmmaker-is-making-a-hollywood-movie-and-a-classic-mistake.html">Canada&#39;s Hottest Filmmaker is Making a Hollywood Movie — and a Classic Mistake</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top Lists / Interviews</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/4/top-10-uncredited-heroes-of-jurassic-park.html">Top 10 Uncredited Heroes of Jurassic Park</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/20/10-questions-with-randall-william-cook.html">10 Questions with Randall William Cook, Animation Supervisor</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/23/9-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-the-little-mermaid.html">9 Things You Probably Didn&#39;t Know About the Little Mermaid</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/23/holy-fck-boys-we-interview-the-trailer-park-boys.html">Holy F#ck, Boys! We Interview the Trailer Park Boys</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/1/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2013.html">Redmond&#39;s Top Films of 2013</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top 5 – 2012</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/20/titanic-3d.html">Titanic 3D</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/7/19/the-dark-knight-rises.html">The Dark Knight Rises</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html">The Hunger Games</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/12/28/django-unchained.html">Django Unchained</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/26/life-of-pi.html">Life of Pi</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top 5 – 2013</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/7/12/grown-ups-2.html">Grown Ups 2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/14/man-of-steel.html">Man of Steel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/19/world-war-z.html">World War Z</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/27/stoker.html">Stoker</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/16/star-trek-into-darkness.html">Star Trek Into Darkness</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top 5 – 2014</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/7/wolf-of-wall-street.html">The Wolf of Wall Street</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/12/robocop.html">Robocop</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/28/nymphomanic-vol-1-and-2.html">Nymphomaniac Vol. 1 &amp; 2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/9/a-million-ways-to-die-in-the-west.html">A Million Ways to Die in the West</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/1/guardians-of-the-galaxy.html">Guardians of the Galaxy</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top 5 – 2015</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/13/fifty-shades-of-grey.html">Fifty Shades of Grey</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/27/sisters.html">Sisters</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html">Wild</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/2/it-follows.html">It Follows</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/17/kingsmen-the-secret-service.html">Kingsmen: The Secret Service</a></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Top 5 – 2016</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/16/a-bigger-splash.html">A Bigger Splash</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html">Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/3/a-hologram-for-the-king.html">A Hologram for the King</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/27/x-men-apocalypse.html">X-Men: Apocalypse</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/the-witch.html">The Witch</a></li>
</ol>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kong: Skull Island</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/13/kong-skull-island.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Kong:SkullIsland" />
    <published>2017-03-13T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-13T04:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/13/kong-skull-island</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I walked into this film assuming I would address my letter to the sound editor, or the motion capture specialist, or perhaps a member of the CGI team. They all certainly deserve praise for their work here. After all, films featuring giant mammals and the brawny men sent to take them down really depend on special effects wizards and post-production artists to deliver the goods audiences crave. This is usually why I’m cool on these types of films. Too often the emphasis is on making the monster realistic while the human element suffers. Not so in <em>Kong: Skull Island</em> . Kong is as authentic as we’ve ever seen him, but you, John, bring the movie to life.</p>

<p><em>Kong: Skull Island</em> is set in 1973, an era when big name stars like Paul Newman and Gene Hackman found themselves headlining over-the-top disaster/action movies like <em>Poseidon Adventure</em>, <em>Towering Inferno</em> and <em>Airport.</em> These films required that their expensive cast do little more than react to their high-concept plot points with incredulity, fear, and ultimately, relief. <em>Kong: Skull Island</em> expects much of the same from its cast. John Goodman is Randa, a scientist convinced Skull Island holds a mysterious secret and leads its exploration. Tom Hiddleston is Conrad, an unflappable, debonair mercenary hired as a tracker. Brie Larson is Mason, a Vietnam war-hardened photojournalist looking to score a Pulitzer. Samuel L. Jackson is world-weary Lieutenant Colonel Packard, in command of the helicopter squadron flying the expedition to the island. All are stock characters elevated by the calibre of their performances.</p>

<p>Then you appear.</p>

<p>At this point, we’ve already seen Kong. And he is a magnificent beast, swatting helicopters out of the sky, squashing pilots underfoot as they race to get away, and wrestling with a giant octopus. If this sounds ridiculous, it’s because it’s supposed to. Director Jordan Vogt-Roberts sets a tone that balances between visual awe, and dry humour, sometimes combining both – a scene of a pilot falling into Kong’s open maw cuts to a shot of a scientist taking a healthy chomp out of his sandwich – all while having fun with tropes and a none-too-subtle homage to <em>Apocalypse Now.</em> Your character, Marlow, is a bit of a combo of Dennis Hopper’s manic photojournalist, and Brando’s “gone native” Kurtz. But you make this character your own, and in doing so, save the film from being just another CGI cash-grab.</p>

<p>Marlow, a WWII pilot, has been living on Skull Island since his plane went down there in 1944. He is the resident expert on its inner workings. He co-exists peacefully with a tribe of natives (making a spectacular entrance) who regard Kong as a god, one who protects them from the gruesome Skullcrawlers, the true monsters in this film. Marlow’s job is more than just expository. He gives the film heart, and a true character to root for. Your sweet, loopy, and earnest portrayal even gives gravitas to the old, “I left a pregnant wife back home” cliché. If anyone deserves to get off of this island, it’s him. </p>

<p>Vogt-Roberts knows Kong is the real star of this film, and he quite smartly doesn’t over-expose him. Skull Island has many surprises in store for its guests beyond Kong. The interlopers must navigate around giant spiders, giant water buffalo, and wrestle with whether or not to kill Kong, who is the only thing that can keep the Skullcrawlers at bay. Sam Jackson’s Packard is looking for redemption for his pilots eliminated by Kong, and the two share an intense, flame-filled, Tarantino-esque staring-contest vibe. I could almost hear Jackson’s inner monologue, “the path of the righteous man is beset on all sides by the tyranny of evil primates.” Conrad and Mason take Marlow’s side in arguing that Kong is their only hope of getting off the island. This “man interfering with natural selection” sentiment doesn’t get too heavy-handed as it thrusts the characters to an epic, inter-species bar-brawl conclusion. </p>

<p>Your job here, John, was to keep things light, and provide some much-needed comic-relief following scenes of intense carnage. But you did so much more. You grounded this film. When awards season comes around, <em>Kong: Skull Island</em> will likely see some noms for the fantastic work done by the SFX and sound departments, but I hope you don’t get overlooked. Your Marlow deserves to get some recognition the same way Melissa McCarthy (<em>Bridesmaids</em>), and Robert Downey Jr (<em>Tropic Thunder</em>) saw their comic turns rewarded with Best Supporting Acting nods. Maybe, like your friends <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o5JAPkvnyso">Jack Black and Will Farrell mused with you at the 79th Academy Awards</a>, you will finally go home with an Oscar, and maybe even Helen Mirren.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Table 19</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/8/table-19.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Table19" />
    <published>2017-03-08T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-08T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/8/table-19</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I always say there are only three things you really need at a wedding: good food, good music, and a few nice photos for posterity. Mind you, I don’t actually like weddings all that much, and have used every excuse to avoid having one of my own (sorry, Mum).  I’m hardly an authority on staging the perfect nuptials, but I’ve been to enough shitty weddings to weigh in on Jeffery Blitz’s <em>Table 19</em>, which made me resent being invited to the screening to the point where I sat there inwardly screaming, “Why didn’t I just say no and send a gift?!”</p>

<p>The film is like a 90-minute speech by some asshole drunk relative, replete with poorly-timed, out of place anecdotes, delivered before a room full of awkwardly silent guests who take the opportunity to add doggy ear stickers to selfies, or hack away diligently at leathery chateaubriand. In the same way that every couple tries to buck trends or make their wedding somehow unique (they all fail; bah, humbug, etc.), <em>Table 19</em> tries to subvert the conventions of the wedding comedy but it just isn’t happening. Sure, the wedding comedy is a by-rote series of calamities and resolutions, but the fact that I can set my watch by each of them is what makes them work. The pacing of <em>Table 19</em> is off to begin with, so without the usual markers (derailed ceremony, inappropriate revelation during toast, etc.), and with plot points that frequently pull the characters away from the wedding, I often had no idea where in the story’s progression we actually were. </p>

<p>Your music was the only tolerable part of the film, your awesome pop covers the only thing diverting my attention from the numbing sensation of my butt falling asleep in my seat. Child of the 80s that I am, I don’t consider a wedding a success unless I hear at least one Cyndi Lauper song*, and you nailed it. As any good wedding band or DJ knows, wedding music can’t just be a random playlist or string of requests – there is a certain progression required when curating the perfect program that will keep the guests entertained and on their feet  - repetitive, but somehow never stale. <em>Table 19</em> tries to mess with the wedding comedy formula, and much like playing <em>I’ve had the Time of My Life</em> at the beginning of the reception or cueing up <em>Gin and Juice</em> in the background during the father of the bride’s toast, it makes no goddamn sense. </p>

<p>As much as I may not like going to weddings (which I probably won’t have to worry about after any of my altar-bound friends or family read this), I was sorely disappointed here, because I do enjoy a good wedding comedy. I actually like that they are formulaic as hell, so <em>Table 19</em> ultimately suffers from trying to fix something that ain’t broke.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Logan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/3/3/logan.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Logan" />
    <published>2017-03-03T02:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T02:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/3/3/logan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Intellectual property (IP) refers to creations of the mind, such as inventions; literary and artistic works; designs; and symbols, names and images used in commerce.</em></p>

<p>IP has taken the place of actual movie stars. Instead of the subtle charisma of a Paul Newman, we have the cheap frisson of yet another rebooted <em>Spiderman</em>. We’ve replaced the creative innovation and the brilliant range of Gene Hackman (Popeye Doyle to Little Bill Daggett and then, finally, Royal Tenenbaum) with clumsy marriages between comic book IP’s and other genres: The Space Opera (<em>Guardians of The Galaxy</em>), Retrograde Orientalism disguised as New Age enlightenment (<em>Dr. Strange</em>), Old School Westerns (<em>Logan</em>), Greek And Norse Myths (<em>The Avengers</em>). </p>

<p>At the core of all of these unwieldy mashups is something that almost always mitigates against growth and evolution—characters that are carved in stone. They are so freighted down by their own backstories—curated and guarded by fervent gatekeepers that balk at anything even mildly transgressive regarding their hallowed IP’s—that the best anyone can hope for is dressed up reiterations of the same kind of stories. And as long as these gatekeepers hold any kind of sway, all we will get is their specific versions of these iconic characters reflected back at us. That is a recipe for creative stagnation.</p>

<p>Make no mistake though, <em>Logan</em> is a fine example of a thoughtful rebranding. It is a meticulously executed, often thrilling example of an innovative marketing scheme overlaid onto an already existing property. Within those parameters, it is entirely successful.</p>

<p>Unfortunately it is, at its heart, an empty exercise.</p>

<p>So much of what hamstrings <em>Logan</em> is the entirely wrong headed idea that fan service is something that should carry any weight at all in the creative process. Instead of adding richness and depth, these character’s slavishly adhered to histories that box them in. Any time they even begin to break into new territory they are immediately pulled back to the safe and familiar.</p>

<p>In <em>Logan</em>’s case, a veneer of R-rated violence and some foul mouthed dialogue from Professor X is a promising departure from the watered down, and often absurdly bloodless, incarnations of the IP. After all, Wolverine is a nigh indestructible mutant, with razor sharp, retractable claws and a skeleton made of unbreakable metal. One love tap would collapse a normal humans orbital bone. And in <em>Logan</em>, the logic of that plays out in some startling visuals. But there is never a moment that the characters break from previous depictions in any real way. And the story itself, once stripped of its blood-spattered window dressing, is utterly same-y. In fact it is very much an extended cut of a scene in X2 where Logan (Wolverine) tries desperately to save some mutant schoolkids from the deprivations of nameless government drones.</p>

<p><em>Logan</em>, despite some hyperbole drenched reviews I’ve read touting it as a best picture contender, is nothing more or less than what Mark Cousins refers to as a bauble. Although a particularly finely wrought bauble. It’s great entertainment, and well worth the money you pay. The performances are uniformly committed and often surprisingly nuanced, especially Stephen Merchant as Caliban—and it’s also a pretty film, and tightly plotted, with few of the usual drop offs in tension that these films often suffer from.</p>

<p>What <em>Logan</em> isn’t, in any real way, is fundamentally different that what’s come before. It’s simply a well constructed example of branding as product. And that means that it will always play out in ways that are utterly transparent and obvious. Even when central characters die there is no real permanence to their ending, because you know that as long as the IP remains fiscally viable another incarnation or reboot is right around the corner. That strips any real emotional depth from the situations these characters face, and dooms them to a kind of mediocrity that seems inescapable.</p>

<p>I like Wolverine as a character, partly because he is one of the few in this milieu that even hints at what the real world consequences would be if a human being was gifted with these kinds of deadly advantages. But unless films like <em>Logan</em> can break free of the requirements that being linked to a marketing scheme and maintenance of the IP as a brand entail, rather than developing an evolving, complex character, they will always be a mile wide and an inch deep, no matter how good they look.</p>

<p>And to me, at least, that is a missed opportunity.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>I Am Not Your Negro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/28/i-am-not-your-negro.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=IAmNotYourNegro" />
    <published>2017-02-28T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-28T04:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/28/i-am-not-your-negro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I could listen to James Baldwin’s words, whether spoken by himself or a perfectly calibrated Samuel L. Jackson, for hours against an empty, black screen. Add to that the masterfully selected archival footage you provided director Raoul Peck, and what you get is a documentary that is near to perfect. But it is a profoundly disturbing and unsettling perfection, because it lays bare the chasm between the aspirations of a nation and its often ugly reality. </p>

<p><em>I Am Not Your Negro</em> is a documentary that consists entirely of words written and spoken by James Baldwin, an African American academic and author who lived and wrote during the most tumultuous period of the American civil rights movement in 1950’s and 1960’s. He was a contemporary of Angela Davis, Huey Newton, Muhammed Ali, Malcolm X., Martin Luther King and Medgar Evers. The framing of the documentary revolves around a thirty page proposal for a book, to be titled <em>Remember This House</em>, that remained unfinished at the time of his death in 1987. The book was an attempt to chronicle the lives and deaths of Evers, Malcolm X. And MLK. The rest of the documentary uses that conceit to tell Baldwin’s own narrative, intertwined with archival footage of the three men in question.</p>

<p>Six years in the making, <em>I Am Not Your Negro</em> is a precise and often devastating deconstruction of the parallel worlds that white and black America have occupied for the entirety of the US’s history. The archival footage of the ugliness inflicted upon civil rights activists, as well as the assassinations of MLK, Malcolm X. and Evers, punctuate Baldwin’s observations about how America created and maintained a two-tiered society that pretended to one set of ideals, but often played out in much more sinister ways.</p>

<p>Born and raised in Harlem, before becoming an expat in Paris, and then finally returning to New York, Baldwin was a man built of contradictions. He was, for all intents and purposes, without religion, yet was both the son of a preacher and a former preacher himself. He was a gay, African American academic and author in a time where even saying that sentence in some parts of the country would court a beating or worse. He debated William F. Buckley to a standstill, and was the inspiration for literary figures like Toni Morrison and Ta-Nehisi Coates. Yet he is, for some, a complete cipher and largely unremarked.</p>

<p>Actively dismayed at the arbitrary and often damaging class distinctions that existed not only within the African American community, but the nation as a whole, Baldwin was, it seems, a cosmopolitan humanist with little of the usual loyalties to the church or established hierarchies. He saw himself as a witness, which meant he never really belonged to any one group but sought to see the larger picture—even while acknowledging that his experience was thoroughly grounded in the particulars of an African American man born near the middle of the 20th century. How could it not be? Baldwin also precisely articulated that it is incumbent upon the people who hold and exercise power as to how this will all shake out—while expressing his belief that the black-white divide is entirely a constructed thing, based on economic and class expediency: “White is just a metaphor for those that hold power”.</p>

<p>Watching this film was an often painful experience, especially when the sneering faces that were actively engaged in the beatings and murder of African American men and women could’ve belonged to an aunt or an uncle or a sister or brother of mine; people that look very much like me doing things that were utterly unconscionable. And overtop all of that was Baldwin’s often prescient observations about how these divides would never be healed without a kind of self-reflection that seems beyond most white Americans. But the brutal poetry of images and words, so completely in tune with one another, is what elevates <em>I Am Not Your Negro</em> above similarly constructed works. Especially since so much of the imagery jumped back and forth between historical and contemporary events-- and underscored how little real difference there was between Selma and Ferguson, the lynchings of young African Americans in the Fifties and Sixties, and their current treatment at the hands of the criminal justice system.</p>

<p>James Baldwin was a man of profound depth and a piercing intellect. He was possessed of a melancholic rage at what he saw every day in his country, but rejected the “white devil” rhetoric adopted by early Malcolm X. Instead he charged the American majority with a simple but difficult task: You say you’re decent, god fearing people, who believe in justice and liberty for all. </p>

<p>Now prove it.</p>

<p>The jury is still very much out.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Cure for Wellness</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/21/a-cure-for-wellness.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ACureforWellness" />
    <published>2017-02-21T04:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-21T04:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/21/a-cure-for-wellness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I know I was supposed to be scared witless by Gore Verbinski’s <em>A Cure for Wellness</em>, and normally I would have been. As someone who is deathly afraid of pigeons, because what the actual fuck are they staring at me like that for, I’m an easy mark for horror movies. But this hot mess of cheap scares and tortured allegory annoyed me more than it scared me. Aside from the fact that the film ends about eight times before it <em>actually</em> ends, the underlying themes and narrative subtext are exasperatingly jumbled. </p>

<p>Your script gleefully plays upon our most common phobias - drowning, darkness, the dentist, geriatric nudity - to tell us a cautionary tale about the dangers of working too hard and being too obsessed with wellness. Or something. After a bunch of eels started slithering around in toilets I had no idea what the hell was going on anymore. </p>

<p>But then another narrative starts to emerge, shaped upon themes of purity and tropes of imprisonment, and things got a little uncomfortable for me. The underlying tale of a set of diseased, deadly beliefs, lurking until regaining their former strength and power, is the real horror here, but it falls flat when you consider the real-life resurgence of the same. </p>

<p>I think your basic underlying premise was this: The film is about Nazism. The evil, dastardly, purity-obsessed Nazis we thought were long gone have been hiding and recouping their strength this whole time, rounding up innocent people and conducting terrible experiments on them before exterminating them and just being generally Aryan and horrid. Normally, there would be much satisfaction and narrative catharsis when the evil Nazis/Nazi stand-ins get their comeuppance, but I just wasn’t feeling it. Were you pointing frantically from the Nazi-esques in your script to the real-life alt-right horror show currently unfolding in our own back yards while screaming, “It’s the same damn thing!”?  Because that is more frightening than your water tank scene, your eel scene, and your aggressive dentist scene. </p>

<p>In the decades since WWII, while we’ve solemnly intoned, “Never again, never again,” we have enjoyed a variety of cultural product where Nazis or Nazi-ish bad guys are dealt with violently and mercilessly. We cheer on the avenging heroes and fervently wish they had been around ‘back then’. Well, Nazi-ish appears to be back in vogue, and today, a film like <em>Inglourious Basterds</em> would probably end with a lecture about the importance of dialogue and respect for the Nazis’ freedom of speech. And perhaps you see the horror in that too. When the protagonist Lockhart confronts Nazi-ish bad guy Dr. Volmer over his Nazi-reminiscent misdeeds against his unsuspecting clientele, the latter purrs, “It was easier this time, with such willing pawns.” </p>

<p>Your Nazi allegory is the truly terrifying heart of the film, and it could have been pretty compelling if you had just focused the narrative around it from the get-go. I guess I just didn’t see the point of all that other crap about the evils of greed, or corporatism, or whatever you seemed to be taking aim at initially. Your story tried to be about too many things at once, or was initially about one thing, then changed its mind and decided to be about something else. </p>

<p>If the horror film is a vehicle through which our deepest underlying fears and anxieties over the state of the world play out, the next four to eight years will likely produce a steady stream of fright-fests featuring vaguely (or blatantly) Germanic villains and monsters, with brave protagonists sending them back to Hell, all like, “Not today, Franz!” But the horror on screen is no longer quite as hair-raising as the real world spectres that return for unwanted and unwelcome sequels (that was not a suggestion to write a sequel to this film. Please don’t).</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The LEGO Batman Movie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/2/14/the-lego-batman-movie.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheLEGOBatmanMovie" />
    <published>2017-02-14T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-14T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/2/14/the-lego-batman-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>One of the standouts of 2014’s <em>The LEGO Movie</em> was the uber-catchy original song by Tegan and Sara ft. The Lonely Island, <em>Everything is Awesome</em>. Not to be outdone by a bunch of moody twins and a trio of losers, you tapped into your inner Batman and grumbled out a hit of your own: Who’s the (Bat)Man.</p>

<p>Of course, I don’t really think Tegan and Sara are moody twins nor Lonely Island, losers, I was just inspired by the rock ‘n’ roll personality of <em>Who’s the (Bat)Man</em>. Your song is essentially <em>Everything is Awesome</em>, but the everything is replaced with Batman and that’s perfectly acceptable because Batman <em>is</em> awesome and so is <em>The LEGO Batman Movie.</em></p>

<p><em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> is the widely anticipated spin-off for <em>The LEGO Movie</em>’s standout character, Batman; a self-absorbed narcissist who is the product of every fan’s obsession with him. He’s essentially Christopher Nolan’s husky voiced Dark Knight and <em>How It Should Have Ended</em>’s post-credit Batman. If you’re not familiar with the latter, look it up and see the similarities for yourself. </p>

<p>LEGO Batman is well aware that he’s the moneymaker for DC Comics and he revels in the fact. He’s a celebrity, both as Bruce Wayne and Batman. He’s prone to talking about his chiseled abs and his ability to take down villains without breaking a sweat. He’s the plastic manifestation of pop-culture’s obsession with superheroes which is why he might be the most compelling caped crusader to ever grace the big screen.</p>

<p><em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> could have been whatever it wanted to be and it chose to be an homage to the character’s history across film, TV, and comics. This film is a quirky and hilarious treat for moviegoers of all ages. The children who go to see it will absolutely love the potty-mouthed humour while some of the older crowd will appreciate all the nods to Batman’s past. Although, I would be lying if I didn’t admit that The Joker rubbing his butt on the Batmobile and calling it the ‘buttmobile’ cracked me the hell up.</p>

<p>One instance in which <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> absolutely nails what it is to be a lifelong Batman fan comes in the opener where The Joker is introducing his team of supervillains. He names off the usual subjects like Catwoman, The Riddler, and Bane, but continues to go down the list to even the most obscure and laughable villains such as Eraser, Crazy Quilt, and Condiment King. The scene works on many levels but the kicker was the moment my girlfriend leaned over and asked, “are those all real names?” to which my answer was a gleeful “<em>yes”</em>.</p>

<p>Despite all the meta moments and references to butts, there is a genuinely heartfelt story in <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> that takes Batman through a journey of self-discovery. He actually grows as a character which is the biggest critique against the live-action DC films. It makes me wonder how a movie about plastic toys can draw out more emotion than their live-action counterparts. LEGO Batman is actively saving DC’s ass, which only helps add to his over-the-top persona. </p>

<p>Now more than ever I realize just how important <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> really is. Eight decades is a long time to be The Man, yet Batman continues to evolve and stay at the top of his league. Batman has already secured his spot as the <em>It</em> superhero for the foreseeable future. Sure, people would love to fly around Metropolis like Superman, but it wouldn’t compare to the gravitas that comes with being The Dark Knight. </p>

<p>Even though <em>The LEGO Batman Movie</em> pokes fun at the character, it does him an even greater service by reminding us about all the times Batman has been awesome.</p>

<p>So, if I may quote some of your lyrics:</p>

<p>Who has the coolest gadgets? </p>

<p>Who has the tricked out ride? </p>

<p>Who does the sickest backflips? </p>

<p>Who&#39;s the manliest man?</p>

<p>You better believe it’s the Batman.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>