<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-08T16:30:27Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Midnight Special</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/4/8/midnight-special.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MidnightSpecial" />
    <published>2016-04-08T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-08T03:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/4/8/midnight-special</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>For a science fiction film <em>Midnight Special</em> is notable for its general lack of CGI fireworks. But when they’re necessary, the film delivers. A large part of that is down to your efforts and how completely they manage to create an otherworldly aesthetic—while constrained by budget concerns that would have stymied a lesser artist. </p>

<p>Your ability to create effective visuals in the face significant limitations (either self-imposed or otherwise) is one of the aspects that elevate <em>Midnight Special</em> to something more than the usually overwrought <em>Stranger In A Strange Land</em> motif. This kind of minimalist approach is also indicative of a film that allows the story to unfold organically, without an excess of the obvious signposts that sometimes bog down narratives that deal with complex ideas. </p>

<p><em>Midnight Special</em> is like an early Spielberg film—a stripped down version of the awestruck stories that littered the ground in the seventies and eighties: films like <em>E.T</em>., <em>Close Encounters of the Third Kind</em>, <em>The Explorers,</em> even John Carpenter’s <em>Starman</em>. <em>Midnight Special</em> certainly shares DNA with all of these works but it also is possessed of two fundamental differences. The first is that director Jeff Nichols is much less coy about his theme—family and the sacrifice required to raise a child. Secondly, he is far less concerned with narrative hand-holding than most mass-marketed film. There aren’t any expository breaks when one character or another recaps the story for the benefit of the audience. </p>

<p>If you weren’t paying attention it would be easy to lose the thread while watching <em>Midnight Special</em>. This is a small, intimate film (despite the over sized concepts) that never really stops moving. There is a propulsive and often tense undercurrent present as the story unfolds—driven by remarkable performances across the board. Nichols allows the audience just enough information to piece together the necessary narrative skeleton. The rest is up to the actors and the visuals, as well as an engaged audience.</p>

<p>When it comes time for your work to be revealed its impact is profound, partly because of the visual discipline exercised throughout the first two acts of <em>Midnight Special</em>. Nichols is careful about when and where he tips his hand, so when it does happen it is not lost in the wash of the dozens of moment that came before it. This is a perfect example of how effective not showing the shark can be in the hands of someone who is confident enough to wait for the proper moment.</p>

<p>For an audience that wants to do a little bit of work while being absorbed in a high concept, high stakes, low budget science fiction film <em>Midnight Special</em> is close to the perfect fit. Your work, which manages to be both subtle and affecting, is just one of the many reasons why this film is so successful as a very particular coming of age narrative. You perfectly matched both the tone and the intention of this masterful piece of work.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Across the Line</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/4/8/across-the-line.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AcrosstheLine" />
    <published>2016-04-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/4/8/across-the-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>A director’s first feature film is always a draw for me. If they make it big, I can be one of those smug assholes who say, “Oh, are you <em>just</em>hearing about them now? How interesting.” Granted, Director X has already made a name for himself – most recently as the guy who brought us the Hotline Bling video.So, to be honest, part of me thought a film by a hot shot music video director might be too enamoured with jump cuts, and all soundtrack, no substance. But <em>Across the Line</em> resists being written off as any one thing, and left me equal parts disappointed and impressed.</p>

<p>Even more than Director X, you’re both to blame and to thank for that.</p>

<p>In your story, high school hockey star Mattie is gunning for the NHL - if he keeps practicing, gets good grades, and stays out of trouble. But Mattie also attends a high school where racial tensions between black and white students lead to regular brawls in the hallways and parking lot, echoing the real-life racially incited violence that has flared up every few years at Nova Scotia’s Cole Harbour High School, most notably in 1989. Making matters worse is Mattie’s increasingly strained relationship with his older brother, the family fuck-up who does terrible things like pimping out girls from school. At first, I had a hard time with the way Mattie often hovers on the periphery of the action, but when you consider the fact that he is always one fight or bogus traffic stop away from losing his shot at pursuing his hockey dreams, it makes sense. The constant run-ins with white kids hurling racial epithets verge on repetitive, but they effectively underscore the notion that for Mattie, every day is essentially a series of booby-traps to be avoided, because the gatekeepers of his opportunities and his ticket out of small-town Nova Scotia are far less accommodating or forgiving of a young black man who excels at a predominantly white sport.</p>

<p>There were a few plot holes and minor irritants that often pulled me out of the story. We are constantly reminded that Mattie is a spectacular hockey player, but we never actually see him do more than leisurely drills on an otherwise empty rink. In a film about a hockey player, there is no actual hockey played at any point, and that bugged me. Given that the narrative alludes to racial inequality in the NHL, and in Canadian hockey in general, could we not have been spared one or two throw-downs before English class in favour of at least one scene that would actually show us the pressures and prejudices Mattie faces as a black hockey player?</p>

<p>I realize that, being an independent Canadian film, there must have been budgetary constraints at play, and maybe it just wasn’t possible to stage any hockey on screen. But when such gaps occur out of necessity, like the lack of hockey, or that Mattie’s English teacher appears to be the only adult present at the high school, the script needs to be strong enough to make them easy to overlook - and in this case, it doesn’t quite get there. </p>

<p>Worst of all Floyd, the dialogue in the film made me cringe. A lot. The narrative raises some heavy issues centered on racial inequality, but the dialogue frequently collapses into cliché, stunted, after school special-like histrionics. There were moments that reminded me of a few mortifyingly awkward anti-racism role playing workshops from my own school days, with hackneyed references to “<em>those</em> people…!” and the inevitable “Can’t we all just get along?!” outburst that I was pretty much able to preemptively recite word for word. </p>

<p>While the script is weak at telling, its strength is in the showing. There are instances of silent interaction between the characters that are masterfully constructed and staged. In a scene where Mattie’s brother drags him along to collect a couple of girls in his employ, Mattie recognizes one of them from school. They make eye contact for an instant before she gets into his car. They sit there in complete silence, but that moment pulls together every narrative thread in the film - Mattie’s family troubles, the appalling racism that poisons the characters’ interactions, and the various risks posed to Mattie’s future. That moment is when Mattie’s desperation to escape to something better is most palpable, and drives home just how high the stakes are for him. </p>

<p>Your script has its weaknesses, but I ultimately liked its ambition. It raises uncomfortable issues of race relations in Canada, reaches back towards an important aspect of Canadian history that is not often spoken about, and tries to illustrate how racism pervades our communities as well as our most well-loved institutions. I won’t be enthusiastically quoting lines from the film any time soon, but I am interested in the conversations it might start - that it <em>should</em> start.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Knight of Cups</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/4/1/knight-of-cups.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=KnightofCups" />
    <published>2016-04-01T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-01T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/4/1/knight-of-cups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>“Persistence of vision refers to the optical illusion whereby multiple discrete images blend into a single image in the human mind, and was once believed to be the explanation for motion perception in cinema and animated films.”</em></p>

<p>To try and write about this film in the usual way would be to miss the point entirely, I think. </p>

<p>We all tell ourselves stories in order to make sense of the world: <em>this is the third time today I‘ve seen the word placenta, so my wife must be pregnant</em>; <em>that dog crossing the road on its own must have negligent owners</em>; <em>I found twenty dollars—going to be my lucky day</em>. All these brief, self-created narratives seek to make sense of the endless parade of random events that suddenly appear before us, to give context to something that is without intrinsic meaning. Finding linkages between these events, creating an order from them, is one of the reasons humans have pumpkins for heads—an evolutionary compromise necessitated by the wetware required. </p>

<p>That is where you come in. To interact in any meaningful way with this film requires a more metaphorical approach. And while you have fallen out of favor as a scientific explanation, you still provide a useful framework. After all, the project of wrestling discrete, separate moments into a contiguous and meaningful narrative is the central project of every human being—which makes it fair game for Malik’s particular sensibilities.</p>

<p><em>Knight of Cups</em> effectiveness hinges on Malik’s interpretation of someone’s un-arbitrated memories: the raw sensory data of a person’s life (in this case Christian Bale as a Hollywood screenwriter) before it has been run through the filtering software in his head. So the film unspools without the kind of interstitial mending that conventional narratives lean so heavily upon. The connective pieces are missing, one image simply crowds the previous image out of frame, so that watching <em>Knight of Cups</em> is a disconcerting and often unsettling experience. This seems both a creative choice about how to visually portray this particular sort of existential crisis, as well as having the audience experience, in a visceral way, the unsettling bewilderment that accompanies this sort of profound disconnection.</p>

<p>The central thesis of <em>Knight of Cups</em> is how fractured existence can be for someone who lacks an organizing principle (in Malik’s case what he would describe as a spiritual center). That the connective tissue we create to make sense of the world is most effective when filtered through a particular lens, and lacking that filter, we are condemned to a series of disconnected, hazy moments piling one atop of another—and Malik’s uncompromising portrayal of the fractured and often incoherent nature of that struggle is why this film is often so difficult to parse.</p>

<p><em>Knight of Cups</em> portrays what life is like for a person who lacks the will to maintain persistence of vision in their moment-to-moment existence. It is not that Bale’s character lacks the basic tools to create meaning; so much as he seems disinclined to make the effort required—and that is why the Hollywood setting is essential, as it so succinctly underscores that emptiness and lack of connection. The only time the film feels at peace with itself are the moments where Bale has removed himself from that environment, and Malik’s camera finds him wandering through some pastoral setting: a beach, a field, a mountain range.</p>

<p>I can certainly understand how this film would simply not register with some. Those who feel at peace in their lives, who have a sense of purpose and direction, probably won’t feel a need to engage with what is at work here, For me it was a powerful (and often unsettling) encounter, heightened by cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki’s tendency to ride Bale’ shoulder with his camera. Images are alternately gauzy and ephemeral, and then all of sudden <em>right up close</em>: sharp, crisp, and often unkind in their honesty.</p>

<p>Many people struggle to describe the experience of watching a Terrence Malik film, so I’m certainly not alone in that. His work seems to defy a particular sort of analysis, even if just by avoiding convention and categorization. But given how stubbornly we humans try to give order and meaning to what is essentially ineffable, I will say this: whatever happened to me while watching this film was profound. And maybe it’s okay that I can’t describe that experience fully, since my interpretation of the film’s value is specific to me and my attempt to create meaning out of something I‘m not sure I will ever completely understand.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BatmanvSuperman:DawnofJustice" />
    <published>2016-03-29T12:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-29T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Much is being made of your <a href="https://youtu.be/cwXfv25xJUw">glum response</a> to <em>Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice</em>’s critical beating at the hands of professional film reviewers. As of this writing, it’s <a href="http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/batman_v_superman_dawn_of_justice/">running at 28-percent on Rotten Tomatoes</a>.</p>

<p>I get the impression that you’ve invested a lot in this franchise; you brought your Oscar-winning screenwriter pal Chris Terrio onboard; you’ve signed on to appear as Batman in “multiple” films (some rumours claim that number as high as <em>six</em>). So I get why you’re so bummed by this bad start. You must be surprised how eagerly critics and comic shop philosophers alike are hating on this flick. </p>

<p>But, believe me, you’re nowhere near as surprised as I am that <em>I’m</em> going to be the one to try and cheer you up.</p>

<p><em>Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice</em> is flawed, for sure. And the flaws are pretty big. But what works well in the film works <em>really</em> well. And most of the stuff that works well is the stuff that you’re involved in. A simpler way to say it might be: <em>Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice</em> is an atrocious Superman movie, a half-decent (if brief) Wonder Woman movie, and an <em>excellent</em> Batman movie.  </p>

<p>I can’t blame audiences for being frustrated by the experience of sitting through this thing; anyone who pays twenty bucks for a 3D ticket shouldn’t be expected to do the work of the editing department and parse through the glut of footage to find something that resembles an intelligible visual narrative. But I can say that I benefited greatly from my lowered expectations; <em>Man of Steel</em>, the predecessor to this film, set the bar so stupendously low that it was difficult to go into this movie believing it <em>wasn’t</em> going to be a mess. </p>

<p>The main plot (for the first 90 minutes, at least) is pretty linear, and drives the two heroes together in a pretty rational, believable way: Superman is offended by Batman’s brutal tactics, Batman is offended by the lack of checks and balances on Superman’s absolute power—and of course, in the end, it turns out that all these offenses are (spoiler alert) being secretly manipulated by the bad guy. </p>

<p><em>Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice</em> works best when it indulges in this kind of simplicity. It <em>should</em> be simple. This is a story we teach ourselves when we’re still just children: two good guys meet, misunderstand one another, battle to a draw, then come under threat by some third party, at which point they reconcile their differences and fight together. Evil is thwarted, happy ending. Any kid who grew up playing with action figures knows this narrative structure. It’s how you learn to collaborate with your pals (because no one wants to be the bad guy). In this manner, <em>Batman V Superman: Dawn of Justice</em> is the cinematic equivalent of banging toys together while spitting susurrus sound effects. And there’s something weirdly satisfying about it. </p>

<p>Until, yeah, things fall apart. </p>

<p>It’s all the same third act problems that we’ve come to expect from superhero movies (and modern blockbusters in general), so I won’t get too deep into it, except to say that there should be an injunction on crackling domes of energy and a restriction on how many city blocks can be annihilated for every minute of screen time (the film pays lip service to the wanton destruction that occurred at the end of <em>Man of Steel</em>, then goes and does it all again). </p>

<p>But before all that, we’re treated to some fun stuff. Jesse Eisenberg’s Lex Luthor gets twitchier and more grating as the film wears on, but in earlier scenes he manages to do something fresh with the character: Mark Zuckerberg as megalomaniacal supervillain. Gal Gadot doesn’t get to do much as Wonder Woman except slink around a cocktail party in a diaphanous dress, but she slinks well, and has a few good lines (all of which are spoiled in the trailer). And your tired, grey-templed Bruce Wayne might actually be truer to the fundaments of the source material than Christian Bale’s sociopathic socialite. (Please note: I am saying all this as an obsessive superfan of Christopher Nolan’s Dark Knight Trilogy.)</p>

<p>If you need to be further cheered, I’ll go on the record and say this: the best Batman fight scene ever committed to film occurs in the last half hour of this movie. And whether or not that was actually you underneath the cowl (or some burly stunt-double), I <em>believed</em> it was you, and in that moment – if <em>only</em> that moment – was thrilled by what this movie was doing.</p>

<p>Even Zack Snyder seems to have matured. He has built his career on an instinct for creating beautiful images (he just can’t seem to string them together coherently, which, unfortunately for him, is the fundamental difference between visual art and filmmaking), and even though we’ve seen Bruce Wayne’s parents get murdered over and over and over, there are a few images from Snyder’s interpretation of that scene that really stuck with me; specifically, a pearl necklace caught on the barrel of a gun.  </p>

<p>All I want to tell you, Ben, is that <em>Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice is nothing for you to be ashamed of. The opposite, in fact. Of everyone involved in this film, you’re the one (maybe the _only</em> one) who has earned the right to hold your head up high. You’ve made a solid Batman movie. It’s just a shame it was folded up in the middle of this sloppy franchise prologue.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Clan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/24/the-clan.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheClan" />
    <published>2016-03-24T12:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-24T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/24/the-clan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>The Clan</em> is an object lesson in how to make a true crime drama. And your performance as the patriarch (aptly named Arquímedes Puccio) of a truly bizarre family is an object lesson in how to portray a fully rounded human monster.</p>

<p>An Argentinean film from 2015, <em>The Clan</em> is a scathing rebuttal to the over wrought superficiality of recent english language films of the same species—<a href=""><em>Gangster Squad</em></a> and <a href=""><em>Black Mass</em></a> are two of the most obvious culprits that use surface sheen and heightened performances (as well as prosthetics) to obscure their lack of real depth. <em>The Clan,</em> by contrast<em>,</em> is a superior piece of filmmaking. Central to the films success is your pitch perfect depiction of the corrupt head of a crumbling family—whose business happens to be kidnapping. </p>

<p>Each moment you are screen you transmit a kind of barely restrained rage that is an echo of Ben Kingsley’s Don Logan in <em>Sexy Beast</em>—both of your characters are creatures of almost entirely unrestrained id, the difference being yours is a quiet, calculating rage. Your Arquímedes is a despicable creature, prepared to use even his own children as co-conspirators. He’s so callous that he keeps and tortures his victims in a room in his own home—while his two young daughters are kept awake by their keening wails.</p>

<p>This is the true story of the Puccio family, three sons, two daughters and a wife. Each of whom seems to be the usual working class family member: the father a shopkeeper, the mother a teacher, the middle son a rugby star. Yet each of them were also either complicit in—or at least aware of—the family’s real business. Taking advantage of the political chaos in Argentina during the early eighties the Puccios kidnapped and murdered several young men and women from well to do families—all the while being shielded from prosecution by their ties to the military.</p>

<p><em>The Clan</em> is a remarkably deft example of a particular sort of neo realism. Directed with restraint and subtlety, it maintains close contact with the central characters while the larger political concerns play at the margins. This is a film firmly embedded in the struggles of the Argentinean working class during a period of post war political upheaval. Concentrating on this specific family is what makes this narrative so compelling, but, in many moments, it also feels like an uncomplicated kitchen sink drama about a traditional family coming apart at the seams.</p>

<p>The real horror of <em>The Clan</em> doesn’t come from Arquímedes’ casual disposal of his victims once they have served their purpose, but from how relentlessly he bullies and cajoles his family into compliance. And while his wife is equally guilty—her cold blooded emotional manipulation is as chilling as his rage—Arquímedes is the catalyst for his family’s inevitable downfall.</p>

<p>There was never a moment when I was taken out of this film, either by the direction or a false step in the performances. <em>The Clan</em> is a rare film: both fascinating and grounded, a close cousin to cinema vérité, yet still a full-throated drama. </p>

<p>And finally, the last two minutes of this film are perhaps the most affecting I have experienced while watching a film in a long time—the irony so tragically rich that it still sticks in my throat.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Miracles from Heaven</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/24/miracles-from-heaven.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MiraclesfromHeaven" />
    <published>2016-03-24T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-24T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/24/miracles-from-heaven</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In a very short period of time you have become my nemesis. In the last month, almost four hours of my dwindling existence has been eaten by your nonsense.</p>

<p>Like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/27/risen.html"><em>Risen</em></a> before it, <em>Miracles from Heaven</em> is a Christian-themed film that meets one criteria, and one criteria only—it’s a Christian-themed film. Which is to say the story, characters, tone, narrative intentions, performances are all secondary considerations. The only thing that the film is concerned with communicating is a fundamentally dull narrative conceit—God exists.</p>

<p>Films that have compelling questions at the center of them, films like <em>Apocalypse Now</em> (what does war really look like) or even <em>Blade Runner</em> (what is it, exactly, that defines what it is to be human) are intrinsically interesting. On the other hand, films that have answers baked into the subtext like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/22/tomorrowland.html"><em>Tomorrowland</em></a>, or in this particular case, <em>Miracles from Heaven</em>, are intrinsically boring as fuck. If the question is already answered at the beginning of the film and the whole runtime is nothing but an exercise in propping up that conclusion, how is it anything but propaganda?</p>

<p>To spend a lot of time tracing out the plot would be a waste of everyone’s time. Suffice it to say, a little girl has to suffer the agony of some horrible, and rare, intestinal affliction in order to reignite her mother’s undying devotion to a cruel and capricious deity. There is one scene, though, that really kind of exemplifies why I find this kind of film so utterly wrongheaded.</p>

<p>The aforementioned little girl manages to climb 30 feet up a tree (despite being debilitated by pain) and falls headfirst into the tree’s hollow heart. As family and neighbors pray at the foot of this tree—in a scene so contrived and overlit it made me angry—firefighters rappel headfirst into the hollow and retrieve the unconscious child. As she is placed on a stretcher, the whole impromptu congregation raises their eyes to heaven and thank God for the child’s deliverance—as the people who actually risked their own well-being are utterly ignored.</p>

<p>The problem here isn’t really the underlying themes. It is the fact that <em>Miracles from Heaven</em> is so incurious about its own premises. Any character that might exhibit the slightest doubts about the existence of God is either portrayed as a buffoon or converted by the end of the film. And so much of what makes narrative film great depends upon the tension inherent in ambiguities. If you know who the murderer is from the first frame, it is incredibly difficult to care much about the rest of the story. This kind of just-so filmmaking really doesn’t create much in the way of entertainment, and even as a kind of comfort food it is so banal that it is nothing but thin gruel.</p>

<p>And nobody but Oliver likes that shit.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Allegiant</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/23/allegiant.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Allegiant" />
    <published>2016-03-23T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-23T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/23/allegiant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As you know, Tris’ character transformation from <em>Divergent</em> to <em>Insurgent</em> was epitomized by her dramatic shift in hairstyle. As we’ve written about <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/21/insurgent.html">previously</a>, a woman’s choice to chop off her hair in cinema usually symbolizes victimization or strength. In <em>Insurgent</em>’s case, it was the latter. </p>

<p>Tris wholeheartedly accepted her new-found revolutionary role by sporting a new pixie cut. Viewers and fashion outlets definitely took notice. The ‘<em>Insurgent</em> haircut’ was a hit on Pinterest and women across the globe were pining for it. In <em>Allegiant</em>, Tris still rocks a short cut, but it’s tamed. The way you perfectly coiffed and added volume to Shailene Woodly’s hair presented her in a doting manner. It’s the exact opposite of what positioned her as a badass in <em>Insurgent</em>. It’s what Hollywood would prefer in a leading lady and a perfect example of the boresome decline of the <em>Divergent</em> franchise.  </p>

<p>I quite enjoyed the first <em>Divergent</em> film. In what seemed to be the boom of dystopian melodramas (<em>Elysium</em>, <em>The Hunger Games</em>, <em>The Giver</em>, <em>Maze Runner</em>, etc.), <em>Divergent</em> stood out. The whole idea of factions struck a chord and I looked forward to the sequels. But as more and more anti-utopian features came out, the lines between them started to blur. It was in that mess of suppressed civilians under a totalitarian regime that <em>Insurgent</em> came out and I couldn&#39;t have cared less. I remember seeing the previews but didn&#39;t think anything past that point (I wasn’t interested in getting the haircut). I eventually forgot that it ever existed, which is what led me to believe that <em>Allegiant</em> was the direct sequel to <em>Divergent</em>. While this came as a shock to me, it also helped solidify that the franchise is forgettable. </p>

<p>The fact that I skipped an entire connecting movie didn’t make a difference. It’s been two years since I last saw a <em>Divergent</em> film and I picked up right where I left off with <em>Allegiant</em>. I was stunned to see that the story didn&#39;t change and none of the characters developed. Four is a copy and paste from the first movie and Peter is still an irritating prick (largely due to Miles Teller). Tris actually regressed by being fooled by corruption, again; only this time, instead of Kate Winslet, it&#39;s Jeff Daniels, who’s been cursed with playing &#39;white man in power suit&#39; for the rest of his acting days.</p>

<p>Tris’ uninspired hair is not just a metaphor for the decline of the <em>Divergent franchise, but also an ode to the state of blockbuster sagas. Once franchises garner a strong fan base, they become lazy. They accept that they don’t have to try as hard to make the same amount of money and decide to coast on mediocrity. It’s buzzcuts, all around. I can’t describe to you the complete neutrality of my feelings with _Allegiant</em>. It was so conventional—so familiar. It didn’t raise a single hair on my body. </p>

<p>In an expected attempt to rake in more dough and stay relevant for a little while longer, <em>Allegiant</em>—the final chapter of the saga—has been split into two separate films, much like what has been done with <em>The Hunger Games</em>, <em>Twilight</em>, and <em>Harry Potter</em>. If it’s anything like <em>Allegiant</em>, part two isn’t going to be exciting. Unless you change that. You are the Key Hair Stylist and the trend-setter. Give Tris a purple Mohawk and let her go out guns blazing, closing the franchise in the same way that made it popular to being with.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Born to be Blue</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/21/born-to-be-blue.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BorntobeBlue" />
    <published>2016-03-21T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-21T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/21/born-to-be-blue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You never lose, do you? As the most insidious daughter of the poppy, you seem to trump every other consideration: wife, career, teeth, (more on that later). And you do seem to have a particular affinity for Jazz.</p>

<p>Ethan Hawke is the best choice imaginable to play Chet Baker: a trumpet player in the same league as iconic musicians Miles Davis and Charlie Parker. Baker reached the height of his fame in the early to mid fifties and then plummeted to earth, largely because you rode him all the way down—down to the point where some unpaid dealers knocked his front teeth out in 1968. Just to be clear, playing the trumpet definitely requires your two front teeth (see: <em>embouchure</em>.)</p>

<p><em>Born To Be Blue</em> is a shaggy, undisciplined mess of a film, yet it still works remarkably well. Ethan Hawke inhabits this role in a way I’ve not seen in decades. The supporting cast—including Canadian stalwarts Callum Keith Rennie and Stephen McHattie—are great, their performances uniformly understated and complex. The film begins with Baker being plucked from a European jailhouse in order to star in his own biopic. After this there are a series of complicated digressions melding the fictional film Baker is in with the actual film Hawke is making about Baker being in a film. Once <em>Born To Be Blue</em> steps out of that muddled first act, though, and adheres to the usual biopic convention, it really allows the story to take hold.</p>

<p>And make no mistake, this is a fascinating story in its detail, even if it is an amalgam of fact and invention, playing fast and loose with chronology as well as real and imagined characters. This is the story of Baker’s fall and rise and then eventual heroin-soaked apotheosis in and around the period from about 1961 to the early seventies.</p>

<p>What <em>Born To Be Blue</em> really sinks its teeth into is exploring the relationship between substance dependency and a particular kind of artist. Hawke, for a variety of reasons, is utterly convincing as a drug-addled cad that just wants to score, fuck, and play his trumpet. The actual musical performances in the film (and there are a few) of Baker’s works are unusually affecting, capturing a little of what made Baker special. And always there is the pull of the needle, and Baker’s constant, if sub rosa, struggle with unpacking the relationship between that ever present need and his life’s work. </p>

<p>The second act, with its ups and downs—from the non-consensual tooth removal to his eventual return to playing, as well as a flourishing love relationship—is utterly conventional in its beats, but still manages to be captivating. Part of that is the perverse certainty that somehow or another you will rear your seductive head in the third act and bring it all crashing down. There is no more painful, yet fascinating, slow motion train wreck than the ebbs and flows of a junkies’ life—and make no mistake, more than anything else, you and that needle define Baker’s existence. </p>

<p>What ever else the audience can take from this film, in one thing it is completely honest. There is nothing more important to a junkie than a fix. Love, career, health, ego, integrity all come a poor second to their first love—and that is why you always win, even if you end up killing those that love you most.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>10 Cloverfield Lane</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/17/10-cloverfield-lane.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=10CloverfieldLane" />
    <published>2016-03-17T10:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-17T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/17/10-cloverfield-lane</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You seem to have found your niche in this business. But it’s not (surprisingly) as a director. Rather, you’re someone who seems to excel at matching talent with content and shepherding the whole herd of cats to a (mostly) satisfying conclusion. </p>

<p>Made for a budget of 5 million, <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> is an unique amalgam of low budget indie and slick studio product. It is helmed by first time director Dan Trachtenberg, yet looks and feels nothing like a first effort. With technical and creative support from you and your production studio, Bad Robot, <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> never suffers from the kind of ragged edges low budget films often display. It is well shot, crisply edited, and boasts three strong performances. </p>

<p><em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> spends most its time in an underground survival shelter built and occupied by a twitchy former satellite engineer Howard (John Goodman). The shelter has two other occupants Michelle (Mary Elizabeth Winstead) and Emmett (John Gallagher Jr.). Emmett fought his way in while Michelle woke after a car crash to find herself shackled to a water pipe. The rest of the film takes it time exploring exactly what lead to these peculiar circumstances—and how each of the three copes with what they discover about one another, and the truth of their predicament.</p>

<p>This film is one example of how to marry the resources of a studio to a low-budget script, and, in so doing, how to create a workaround for the roadblocks that these kind of films often have to negotiate. It has become a truism that it’s impossibly difficult for original content to find a home anywhere in the studio system, so unless a property has some kind of name recognition it’s unlikely to get green lit. What you managed to do with <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> was produce an original script by marrying the content to an already existing property—in this case the 2008 film, <em>Cloverfield</em>. I have my reservations about this particular model—specifically how much you have to compromise the initial vision in order to include the franchise elements—but it’s certainly a path that seems viable.  </p>

<p>There are a few visible seams between what is a self-contained three hander about the particular kind of crazy that leads someone to construct an elaborate bomb shelter—which is then melded with a very different kind of story involving much more expansive themes. The odd mix of humor, tension, and creeping dread is consistently effective. There comes a point in the film where it is not clear at all whether Michelle, Emmitt and Howard are safer inside the shelter, or facing the very real, but not entirely distinct, danger that lurks just outside the door.</p>

<p>There is one caveat, at least for me, in all of this: this film occasionally resembles fusion cuisine that is less than the sum of its parts. Neither beast nor fowl, it has a few moments that feel heavy-handed—especially a kind of overt Chekov’s gun reveal early in the first act. This is how you tried to foreshadow a big turn, but it felt awkward and interrupted the otherwise clockwork rhythm of the film, making the <em>Cloverfield</em> connection sometimes feel like it was grafted onto an original script with more low-key ambitions.</p>

<p>I like Kraft Dinner. And I like Salmon. I’m just not sure I love them mashed together. And while <em>10 Cloverfield Lane</em> was well crafted throughout, I could never quite shake the feeling that it was as much marketing experiment as clever genre exercise. </p>

<p>It was, all in all, a pretty enjoyable thriller though. And a lot of that success comes from you being smart enough to know exactly where your strengths lie. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kilo Two Bravo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/3/11/kilo-two-bravo.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=KiloTwoBravo" />
    <published>2016-03-11T09:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-03-11T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/3/11/kilo-two-bravo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Legacy minefields. Now there’s some Newspeak for you. </p>

<p>This is the term used to describe the millions of unexploded mines that litter the landscape of Afghanistan—most of which are left over from the Soviet incursion in the eighties. </p>

<p>It was your job to faithfully reproduce the injuries that these anti-personnel mines inflict. And you were uncomfortably successful. Perhaps the most important fact about these mines is that they are designed to maim, rather than to kill, in order to drain resources away from engagement with the central conflict. But with the advances in battlefield medicine, unprecedented numbers of soldiers are surviving the kind of injuries that just a few decades ago would have almost certainly killed them. This is both a blessing and sometimes a curse.</p>

<p><em>Kilo Two Bravo</em> is the story of 3 Para, a small company of British soldiers tasked with overseeing a desolate piece of the Afghani landscape in 2006. A three-member patrol is moving through a dry riverbed—or wadi—when one of them steps on one of the aforementioned legacy mines. The rest of the story becomes an almost unbearably tense clusterfuck of failed rescue attempts, which make up the most uncomfortable two hours of film I have ever experienced. Once the first mine explodes (and there had been a number of foreshadowing events, including a camp dog missing a back leg) every footfall and stray rock is potentially fatal—or at least disabling.</p>

<p>Interestingly, for a war film, there is nary a shot fired in anger. In fact, the only close contact the company has with indigenous Afghanis comes very early in the film—in a moment that is almost absurdly benign. This is a film about the kind of damage that war does to the human body and it is relentless in that depiction. The work you did in mimicking the debilitating injuries these mines inflict was on constant display—and was made all the more effective by the level of authenticity the whole production exhibited. I have personally spent some time in and around the military and these were exactly the sort of conversations and personalities I’ve experienced—especially around the lower ranks. Right down to the slightly melodramatic tattoos and hyper-masculine displays. </p>

<p>Time and energy is spent fleshing out these real-life characters—the film meticulously reenacts an actual incident—and the film possesses an understated naturalism that made the whole experience impossible to distance oneself from. There is no engagement with larger geopolitical issues, nor does it feel like there is a particular agenda at work, other than to document, as lucidly as possible, a very specific set of horrifying circumstances.</p>

<p>But that doesn’t mean <em>Kilo Two Bravo</em> doesn’t raise the spectre of just how appalling these legacy minefields are. These men, as badly as they are injured, have a vast infrastructure to support them, however imperfect those institutions may be. From the medical treatment they receive onsite to the hospital and rehabilitation facilities they have access to when they return home (one of the soldiers, after losing a leg, returns to active duty with a sophisticated prosthetic) there is, at least, some hope to live close to a normal life.</p>

<p>Unfortunately mines don’t discriminate between an Afghan child and a combatant. Which couldn’t help but raise the question of how often this occurs when the people subjected to this kind of violent trauma don’t have access to modern military field medicine, or helicopter evac, or physical therapy, or advanced prosthetics. What kind of physical and emotional damage that will that inflict over the course of generations, and how can that do anything other than foster hostility and distrust?</p>

<p>So while I certainly respected the horror that these men endured and the heroism they displayed, I was left with a nagging question at the end of this film. What does it really mean when we use the term “legacy” minefield? </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>