<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-29T13:48:43Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Gods of Egypt</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/29/gods%20of%20egypt.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=GodsofEgypt" />
    <published>2016-02-29T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-29T08:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/29/gods of egypt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As <em>Gods of Egypt</em> gets torn by critics of all kinds, I hope you’re sitting in a room, preferably a dark room with a glass of scotch and lit cigarette resting next to you. And in this room, I hope you’re contemplating the events in your life that brought you to pitch, fund, cast, and direct what I can only describe as the worst movie of 2016. The fact it’s only February, be damned.</p>

<p>Where shall I begin? </p>

<p>How about the obvious? 95% of your cast is Caucasian in a film based off Egyptian mythology. I know you’re fed up of hearing this and you’ve already<a href="http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/envelope/cotown/la-et-mn-gods-of-egypt-racial-miscasting-20151128-story.html"> apologized</a> for the oblivious casting decisions, but you need to hear it again. Your movie starts off with Bek, played by Brenton Thwaites, who has the acting ability of a stale piece of cheese. The moment he opens his mouth; you can’t help but notice a distinct British (even though he’s Australian) accent. This is followed by Dutch actor, Nikolaj Coster-Waldau having disagreements with Scottish actor, Gerard Butler. You went around the world to cast these men except the only place that actually mattered: Africa. The casting is not just misguided, it’s part of a proven recipe of failure. </p>

<p><em>Exodus: Gods and Kings</em>, another Egyptian epic plagued by white actors was a box-office bomb. No one for one second believed that Christian Bale was Moses, the Hebrew prophet. Just like they didn’t believe Emma Stone was Asian-American in <em>Aloha</em> and Rooney Mara was Native-American in <em>Pan</em>. Racial miscasts aren’t just insulting to deserving actors who are right for the role, they’re prime examples of why many high budget and high profile movies flat-out fail at the box office. </p>

<p>Racial blunders aside, <em>Gods of Egypt</em> is a plot-hole ridden nightmare. I couldn’t count how many times I leaned over to my girlfriend with a confused look on my face. There are so many egregious attempts at mysticism, I couldn’t tell up from down. The only way I could make sense of anything featured in <em>Gods of Egypt</em> was to start laughing and convince myself that I’m watching a comedy. I was very tempted to walk out but my occupation as a critic sometimes means I have to witness shit. So I stuck through it. </p>

<p>I witnessed you turn a mythical adventure about gods turn into a space odyssey, complete with flying robots, space vessels and strange, extra-terrestrial beasts—at which point I threw up my hands and said ‘fuck it’. </p>

<p>How could you let this happen? What compelled you to believe this was a good idea? Were you driven by creativity? Did you want to create something that turned the ‘sword and sandal’ saga on its head? Well, if that was your attempt, you failed. You ended up creating a film infested with banality. I sound surprised, but I shouldn’t be. You only hired Matt Sazama and Burk Sharpless, two of the three writers behind<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/3/the-last-witch-hunter.html"> <em>The Last Witch</em> <em>Hunter</em></a><em>—</em>a gothic cliché of epic proportions. </p>

<p>At least I feel like I’m a part of cinematic history. I got to see a movie that is the embodiment of everything that is wrong in Hollywood today: greed, intense CGI, nonsensical plot lines, cringe-worthy dialogue, and whitewashing. It’s a testament to how studio execs will turn a blind-eye to almost anything just so they can rake in money – which, by the way, won’t be much based on its opening weekend. </p>

<p>It’s safe to say I didn’t enjoy <em>Gods of Egypt</em>. I think it’s also safe to say you didn’t enjoy it. How could you? Any straight-minded director knows that <em>Gods of Egypt</em> is destined to fail. The script itself should have screamed failure. <em>Gods of Egypt</em> is a cash grab and nothing else; there is no substance, no enjoyment, and no excuses. You have created  a failure of biblical proportions. </p>

<p>2016 has been a year of firsts for me. I gave out my first<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/17/racing-extinction.html"> 5-star</a> review, and today, I give my first zero stars.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Risen</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/27/risen.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Risen" />
    <published>2016-02-27T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-27T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/27/risen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You are, bluntly put, a tool of Satan. Or the production arm of Sony studios dedicated to producing Christian evangelical films like <em>Faith Like Potatoes</em>, <em>Heaven is Real</em>, Kirk Cameron’s magnum opus <em>Fireproof</em>—and now the Kevin Reynold’s helmed <em>Risen</em>.</p>

<p>So, a tool of Satan. And Sony. But let’s face it, these days they are pretty much indistinguishable.</p>

<p>The problem with these films is not that they are Christian themed, it is that they are terrible. And they are terrible for a fundamental (heh) reason. It is almost impossible to square the circle of revealed truth and interesting filmmaking. You have to be remarkably adept as a filmmaker to produce a film whose ending everyone already knows (see: <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html"><em>Spotlight</em></a>). And Kevin Reynolds—he of <em>Waterworld</em> and <em>Robin Hood: Prince of Thieves</em>—is not that adept.</p>

<p>That this particular film echoes the ersatz biblical epic at the centre of the Coens’ latest <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar.html"><em>Hail Caesar!</em> </a>(there is almost a shot for shot sequence involving the first reveal of Christ as something more than a simple carpenter) doesn’t help either. The real problem is that the film is—from the very first frame—inexorably pointed in one direction. And the only way to make that uni-directional narrative structure engaging for an audience is to create some tension around the why of it. <em>Why</em> is this inevitable, <em>why</em> can this be no other way? And that can’t happen, since to answer that question requires the filmmakers to literally know the mind of God. </p>

<p>Which, you have to admit, is a pretty big ask of any piece of art. </p>

<p>What <em>Risen</em> does instead—rather than trying to come to grips with these big questions—is to introduce Joseph Fiennes as the Roman Centurion Clavius. A simple soldier charged with keeping order in Jerusalem in and around the year 33AD, Clavius returns from a hard day fighting the Peoples’ Front of Judea (or was it The Judean’s Peoples Front? I can never get those straight) to find Peter Firth’s Pontius Pilate all atwitter because he had to crucify some pesky messiah. This leads to a watered down CSI-like plot contrivance where Clavius tries to make sure that this Christ fellow isn’t more trouble dead than alive.</p>

<p>But, too late, he realizes that he is dealing with forces beyond his control—in this case the creator of the entirety of space-time. So the film pivots and becomes a journey to spiritual awakening for this bereft Centurion as he follows Jesus and his disciples to Galilee—with the fishing, and the ascension and whatnot.</p>

<p>Look, Affirm Films (even that title is vaguely cloying in its ostensible cleverness) I don’t give  a rat’s ass what you think is commercially viable or even what drives you to produce films in the first place. As an atheist I have very little interest in your particular worldview. But if you give me a movie that actually tries to come to grips with the animating reasons for faith, or how, in the face of all the evidence to the contrary, smart people still find a way to believe in the ineffable, I will watch the shit out of that. But no one is interested in your just-so stories that reveal nothing but the tautological nature of your specific beliefs, other than adherents of your particular interpretation of the Godhead.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>What Happened, Miss Simone?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/27/what-happened-miss-simone.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=WhatHappenedMissSimone?" />
    <published>2016-02-27T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-27T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/27/what-happened-miss-simone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>When trying to tell the story of someone who was a musical genius, a ground-breaking artist, and an African-American icon, where does one even begin? Nina Simone’s career and personal life had so many ups and downs that it must have been near impossible to choose an appropriate jumping off point for the documentary, <em>What Happened, Miss Simone?</em>. I’m sure it was especially difficult for you, not just as a producer and an interview subject, but as Nina Simone’s only child. </p>

<p>Like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html"><em>Kurt Cobain: Montage of Heck</em></a>, this is an unflinching documentary produced by the daughter of its subject. But Kurt’s daughter, Francis Bean Cobain, was almost two when she lost her father, and has had to construct a one-sided relationship with her famous musician parent. You, Lisa, have a lifetime of less than happy memories to inform your relationship with the legend you knew as mom. Kurt Cobain is worshiped as a grunge deity. But your mother’s musical legacy is even more significant. With this film, Nina SImone – the woman and the artist – finally gets the veneration she so richly deserves.</p>

<p><em>What Happened, Miss Simone?</em> begins with footage from the 1968 Montreux Jazz Festival in Switzerland. Your mother walks out to cheers and applause, but seems ill at ease, possibly under the influence of medication, and definitely unsure of herself. She looks offstage, as though she’s waiting to be told what to do. She speaks awkwardly, and stares blankly. It is both utterly compelling and deeply unsettling. But it is a fascinating way to begin to tell the story of a powerful woman who was constantly searching for, but was unable to find, true freedom.</p>

<p>You were born into better circumstances than your mother was in 1933. She displayed a talent for classical piano at a very young age in segregated North Carolina, and with the help of wealthy white benefactors, she eventually made her way to the Julliard School of Music in New York City. Only when she was denied acceptance to the Curtis School of Music in Philadelphia did she change her name and pursue a career as a nightclub entertainer in order to support her family. She only began to sing when prompted by a club owner. She rocketed to stardom when she met your father, who became her manager. In fact, the more we learn about your mother, the more it seems her life was shaped largely by the choices made for her by others.</p>

<p>As a producer, your day revolves around making choices, both big and small. Sifting through the refreshingly candid footage of your mother must have given you a deeper perspective of her as an artist. And the more personal footage and photographs likely gave you some insight to the type of woman she was trying to be. I’m sure telling her story so frankly was painful, but you chose the right balance. Like the decision to include audio of your mother saying that the most peaceful and free she ever felt was when she held you for three hours after you were born, contrasted with you later describing how she beat you so often as a teenager that you contemplated suicide. Then there was the inclusion of her journal entries, which detail her depression, her beatings and rape at the hands of your father, and her overwhelming feelings of hopelessness. Somehow, you manage not to let us feel too sorry for any of the players, yourself included. </p>

<p>The one thing Nina <em>did</em> choose was her fierce engagement with the Civil Rights Movement, which may have been her greatest personal achievement, though it hampered her ability to become a traditionally successful artist. It seems like the more oppressed she felt under your father’s iron-fisted rule, the stronger her commitment to becoming the patron saint of the rebellion. She stopped performing jazz and blues standards and wrote protest songs like “To Be Young, Gifted and Black”, “4 Women”, and “Mississippi Goddamn”. Her live shows became racially charged, and her new style of music, which she called Civil Rights Music, excluded white audiences and greatly diminished her mainstream bankability. By the time she left your father and moved to Liberia, she was nearly destitute. </p>

<p>Through it all, you claim, she was always Nina Simone.</p>

<p>Her onstage and offstage persona were one and the same. When her mental illness is revealed, it’s hardly a secret, and you don’t treat is as a plot point, but as just another facet that composed the personality of a brilliant but complicated artist. And the film is all the better for this precarious neutrality that neither allows the film to delve into smug hagiography, nor <em>Mommie Dearest</em> tell-all. Despite her shortcomings, it’s obvious that you are fiercely proud of your mother’s achievements. I believe she would be just as proud of yours.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Eddie the Eagle</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/26/eddie-the-eagle.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=EddietheEagle" />
    <published>2016-02-26T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-26T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/26/eddie-the-eagle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I knew you were a big deal the moment I saw your name. I just didn’t know why. </p>

<p>See, I fully expected the feel-good sports film <em>Eddie the Eagle</em> to end on an upbeat note. After all, it’s based on the heartwarming real-life story that charmed the world back at the 1988 Olympics. What threw me off-kilter was seeing your credit at the end—it’s the first one onscreen, alone, and directly tied to all the warm feelings spilling over from the soaring story. </p>

<p>A seemingly low-ranking participant stealing the glory usually reserved for the more accomplished players. Sound familiar? </p>

<p>I knew it couldn’t be an accident. You must have earned this moment in the spotlight. So I looked you up. Indian Jones. Superman. James Bond. You didn’t just work on these films, you<em>were</em> these characters. When the action star couldn’t cut it, you were the one they called. You won the 2005 Lifetime Achievement Award at the World Stunt Awards. You were awarded an Academy Award for Technical Achievement after helping to create a safety rig for stunt performers. You’re the most prolific stunt double in the word, according to the Guinness Book of World Records. And now you’re responsible for helping us soar with Michael “Eddie the Eagle” Edwards. It all started to make sense.</p>

<p>Unlike Eddie, you didn’t get to jump the cue because of outdated rules or lack of competition. You no doubt earned the respect of your fellow filmmakers, including director Dexter Fletcher, through years of perseverance in a craft that is poorly understood even (<em>within</em> the profession—still <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/16/5-radical-ways-to-rejuvenate-the-oscars.html">no Oscar for Best Stunts</a>) and mostly reserved for daredevils with a death wish. </p>

<p>Actually, this is where you and Eddie start to have a lot in common. </p>

<p>Ski jumping is a head-scratching and head-smashing sport that few have the gall to try, and even fewer are able to survive Olympic competition. But this was exactly the opportunity that allowed an oddball like Michael “Eddie” Edwards to live his dream. He was cut from the British Men’s alpine team, but found a back door perched 70m above the hill. Without anyone else in Britain competing for the position of ski Jumper on the 1988 Olympic team, he mustered up the guts to go for it, and the rest is a hell of a fun little film. </p>

<p>So where do you come in? I find it hard to imagine this film tested your abilities as a stunt coordinator or director, with the bulk of the action always being confined to a straight track that shoots skiers into the sky. But the simplicity of the action (and narrative) is exactly what makes <em>Eddie the Eagle</em>so fun to watch. The stakes are raised directly in relation to the height of each jump, and peaks at just the right moment. After all, ski jumping is a perfect spectator’s sport. It’s a lot harder on the athletes, which is how the film finds joy in small moments of perseverance, and a loveable performance by Taron Egerton. We’re also treated to some immersive and clear visuals that help us feel the heights and crashes, which you no doubt had a hand in crafting.</p>

<p>When it comes to dramatic tension, there are a few bureaucratic and logistical hurdles, but we know where this is story going (even if, personally, I didn’t know how it would end). Would it be a <em>Mighty Ducks</em> victory or a <em>Cool Runnings</em>heartbreak? I was prepared for either (Hollywood embellishments and all), and rather pleased with how it all ended. Including, I can now say, seeing your name so prominent in the final credits.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Straight Outta Compton</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/24/straight-outta-comptopn.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StraightOuttaCompton" />
    <published>2016-02-24T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-24T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/24/straight-outta-comptopn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>“You are now about to witness the strength of street knowledge.”</p>

<p>That’s the first line of the first track of N.W.A.’s debut album, from which your screenplay takes its name, and it is undeniably a call to arms. Whatever opinions you might have about the album – that it’s a true-to-life document of the sociocultural climate of inner-city Los Angeles in the 1980s, an artistic feat that revolutionized modern pop music, or a glorification of misogyny and violence – one thing is for certain: it’s fuelled by the complicated, brutal, erosive real-life experiences of its creators. It’s fuelled by <em>street knowledge</em>.  </p>

<p>So, now that I’ve had a bit of time to think deeply about the movie <em>Straight Outta Compton</em>, I am left wondering how a story that was inspired by such righteous anger and revealed such unpleasant truths could be so shallow, banal, and untruthful.</p>

<p>It’s a film fuelled by the <em>opposite</em> of street knowledge. What’s missing, ultimately, from your screenplay, is a sense of danger, of fearlessness, of purpose—the same desire to incite thought and feeling that every track on the album smolders with. Instead, <em>Straight Outta Compton</em> is the kind of middle-of-the-road, play-it-safe, milquetoast pop-culture product that N.W.A. built their reputation by undermining. Which is more than just ironic. It’s <em>tragic</em>. Your film, in attempting to build a monument to the legacy of N.W.A., has compromised it instead. </p>

<p>I’ll be honest. I left the theater after seeing <em>Straight Outta Compton</em> feeling rather upbeat. The people I’d gone with seemed to have enjoyed it, too. How could we not? It’s a feel-good music biopic that luxuriates in all the satisfying tropes of the genre: artist(s) come from disadvantageous circumstances, overcome adversity, prove naysayers wrong, overindulge in fame and success, learn lessons, overcome adversity once again, cement legacy, The End.</p>

<p>Like eating fast food, there is a certain base-level caloric satisfaction one receives from such stuff. The film is competently made. The performances are decent. It’s well-shot. But the story of one of the most important, contentious music groups of recent history deserves more than mere competence. Having had time to contemplate, I feel this strange sense of anger towards this film. I’m angry that it tricked me into thinking it had fulfilled its <em>raison d’etre</em> – to tell the true story of how N.W.A. changed the world by bringing street knowledge to the mainstream – when in fact it tells the story of how the mainstream has learned nothing from it. </p>

<p>N.W.A.’s success was about more than just talent, or the luck of being in the right place at the right time. It was about hard work. It was about trying and failing and trying again; doing the <em>hard</em> thing instead of the easy thing. But in telling their story, you did the easy thing. You wrote a by-the-numbers screenplay that is, as both historical document and artistic expression, a compromise. It’s built upon a blueprint that offers ample opportunity for great risks to be taken (and great rewards to be reaped), but at each and every one of these opportunities your screenplay plays it safe. No, it’s more than just playing it safe. It obscures the truth in order to hide the story’s sharpest edges. It uncomplicates racial and cultural dynamics with a simplistic (almost propagandic) thematic focus. </p>

<p>But how can any of this be your fault? Sure, you wrote the screenplay. But you clearly weren’t writing for the audience. You were writing for the producers of the film, and there is no room to misinterpret your intentions: to deify them. </p>

<p>Those producers? Dr. Dre, Ice Cube, and Eazy-E’s widow, Tomica Woods-Wright. They have become the powerbrokers that they once rebelled against. Willing to protect their reputations (aka. their business interests) at any cost...</p>

<p>But. </p>

<p>Wait. </p>

<p>I feel like I need to think this through a little further. </p>

<p>Why am I so angry? Why does this offend me so much? Aren’t glossy, hollow, aggrandizing biopics as much a Hollywood tradition as bible epics and romantic comedies and superhero franchises? Why shouldn’t African American cultural icons receive the same varnished, agitprop treatment that white figures like Johnny Cash, Jerry Lee Lewis, and Steve Jobs have? In a year when the #OscarSoWhite movement has garnered more attention than any of the nominees, what does it mean that I’m all twisted up about the exaltation (however cloying) of this generation’s black leaders and the institutions they’ve created? Why did the inaccuracies and generalities of <em>Straight Outta Compton</em> provoke more ire in me than films like <em>The Social Network</em> or <em>Walk The Line</em>? Because it wasn’t dark enough, wasn’t gritty enough? And why on earth, of all the people to whom I could have written this outraged letter, did I choose the white lady who wrote one of the earliest drafts of the screenplay? </p>

<p>Maybe I’m taking the easy road, too? </p>

<p>Maybe my reaction to this movie is proof of the very <em>need</em> for movies like this. Perhaps, to be meaningful, to have real social impact, African Americans films don’t have to categorically be dark, gritty, brutal, ruthless, or fuelled by my white-guy’s detached academic notions of what street knowledge is. Maybe <em>Straight Outta Compton</em> is actually the story of how street knowledge made its way into the corridors of power. Making this kind of generic, revisionist-history biopic is, itself, an act of revolution akin to the album that inspired it.  </p>

<p>Yeah. Maybe.</p>

<p>Clearly you weren’t writing this film for the audience. Or even for posterity. You were writing it for the producers of the film, Dr. Dre, Ice Cube, and Eazy-E’s widow, Tomica Woods-Wright. And there is no room to misinterpret your intentions: to deify them. </p>

<p>Dre and Cube certainly aren’t in Compton anymore. They have become the powerbrokers that they once rebelled against. They’re part of the establishment, they’ve joined the system. They have the political and financial influence to produce films about themselves. </p>

<p>That’s not a bad thing—even if it produces bad movies like this.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Race</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/23/race.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Race" />
    <published>2016-02-23T04:05:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-23T04:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/23/race</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The timing of Stephen Hopkins&#39; <em>Race</em> is perfect. The Jesse Owens biopic comes out during Black History Month, just in time to commemorate the 80th anniversary of the 1936 Olympic Games in Berlin, where Owens won four gold medals and, so the story goes, took a stand against the racial politics of the Nazis and showed Adolf Hitler exactly where to stow it. Constructing a myth is a lot like editing a film; you have a particular narrative in mind, and you comb through piece after piece of material, keeping everything that best supports your vision, and discarding everything that is extraneous or irrelevant to it. So it’s no surprise that <em>Race</em> also conveniently alters or discards what is inconvenient and unflattering. But it is disappointing. </p>

<p>Covering the beginnings of Owens’ career is a tedious journey to follow. Owens is shown making a name for himself in college athletics through a series of track meets that quickly become repetitive. Much of Owens’ struggle is depicted through the lens of his relationship with his coach, Larry Snyder. The most compelling part of Owens’ road to the Berlin Olympics are the conflicting pressures placed on him as an athlete representing the United States of America, as a black American, and as an individual whose own ambitions are overshadowed by what his country and community demand of him. But we get maybe two or three scenes that really delve into that aspect of Owens’ life. Mostly, it isn’t so much the Jesse Owens story as the story of how Jesse Owens helped his white coach get his groove back. For a film professing to pay homage to a prominent individual in the annals of Black history, I probably don’t need to spell out why this is problematic. </p>

<p>While the film’s pacing was way too slow off the blocks, you saved it in the final act. The plot finally hits its stride when we arrive in Berlin. There is little suspense, as we know how Owens fared at the games, but there is enough drama and intrigue there for three feature films. There is something for everyone at the Berlin Olympiad; history buffs can boo and hiss at Joseph Goebbels, film geeks can boo and hiss (or not) at Leni Riefenstahl, and sports movie enthusiasts are treated to highly engaging, kinetic race sequences. You establish a good rhythm going back and forth between the athletic sequences and the quieter scenes that establish the personal and political challenges faced by the athletes and Olympic officials, creating a compelling snapshot of a world on the brink of war. </p>

<p>While your editing ultimately shines, it’s the other more insidious narrative ‘editing’ I just couldn’t stomach. The plot makes a big deal out of the widely mythologized snubbing of Owens by Hitler. There have been numerous eyewitness accounts since 1936 disputing the claim that Hitler deliberately snubbed Owens at the Berlin Olympics – most importantly, Owens’ own account. According to him, the head of state who actually snubbed him was President Roosevelt, but I suppose that would be one of those uncomfortable, inconvenient snippets best left on a proverbial cutting room floor. When paying cinematic tribute to an individual, why stop at altering (if not flat-out disregarding) said individual’s own stated truth? </p>

<p>In <em>Race</em>, the audience is sold quite the bill of goods. The film is touted as celebrating Jesse Owens’ achievements within the greater context of Black history. However, narrative focus is split among four characters, and only one of them is Jesse Owens. Or black. Far too much time and attention is spent privileging the perspectives of white supporting characters. What makes things even worse is that their actions and motivations are themselves based on highly contentious accounts (I wanted to use the term ‘whitewashing’ but figured it might be too on the nose). If it was uncomfortable to sit through the glowingly flattering portrayal of Leni Riefenstahl, it was downright galling to watch the depiction of American Olympic Committee head, Avery Brundage, as an upstanding, idealistic champion of human rights when he was actually a vocal anti-Semite who made nice with Nazis to further his own ambitions. </p>

<p>Ironically, <em>Race</em> is a painfully accurate Jesse Owens biopic. Not as the story of an exceptional Black American athlete, but as the story of an exceptionally talented individual used by a mythmaking apparatus as a stand-in for an ideal. His actual life story proves less important than the narrative shaped to propagate a particular set of nationalist myths, in 1936 and once again in 2016.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Witch</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/19/the-witch.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheWitch" />
    <published>2016-02-19T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-19T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/19/the-witch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You and your director (Robert Eggers—a name which everyone should pay attention to) have crafted a film worthy of early Kubrick. <em>The Witch</em> is a superior piece of filmmaking. The whole experience was a pleasure, both aesthetically and intellectually.</p>

<p>And it’s also scary as shit.</p>

<p><em>The Witch</em> is a self-assured, mature piece of film craft. Your use of natural light gives the story the kind of pastoral naturalism that contrasts perfectly with the film’s supernatural underpinnings. Despite the rigor of your cinematography (echoing not just Kubrick, but the compositional perfection of Bergman’s <em>Seventh Seal</em>) it is a quiet, understated formalism. Your work is always at the service of the atmosphere of subtle dread that builds over the course of the whole film. The muted tones of autumn and early winter also evoke a patient, inevitable corruption; and the living avatar of that corruption lurks somewhere in the deep woods. Your camera intimates a mood of isolation—these people do not belong in this world. </p>

<p>And who are these people? A family living in self-imposed isolation in 17th Puritan New England, who left the safety of colonial life, largely because it didn’t meet their exacting religious standards. This gives the audience a sense of how utterly committed they are to a particular worldview, and it’s that myopically constricted commitment that serves them up as fodder for the entity that preys upon them. They are as lambs to slaughter just as much because of their blind adherence to their creed as the malevolence of their tormentor.</p>

<p>The performances are all remarkable, each member of the cast in lock step with the other. The dialogue, enriched by having been pulled from primary sources of the period, is both evocative and filled with a kind of nuanced foreboding. It would be almost unfair to single out one player over another since this film, small as it is, had no room for a mediocre performance. But Anya Taylor-Joy as Thomasin, the daughter teetering on the edge of womanhood, was particularly compelling. If any single character carried the weight of the narrative it was she, particularly as the film slid towards it’s foreordained conclusion. This film is utterly Calvinist in its inevitability, yet it never succumbs to the kind of narrative inertia a lot of films like this suffer in their final act. This is largely because the tension has less to do with what will happen and more to do with a more nuanced struggle about where your loyalties lie: to your family, or to your deity.</p>

<p>At its core <em>The Witch</em>  is a superior example of gothic horror in the same rarified category as Del Toro’s <em>Devil’s Backbone</em> or <em>The Orphanage</em>. It creates and sustains a level of dread that remains long after the film ends. If you have ever felt an atavistic shiver trying to look into the depths of a tangled wood in the early evening, just imagine that moment stretched out over almost two hours—that’s what you have created for your audience.</p>

<p><em>The Witch</em> reminded me how small-budget, low-tech filmmaking can produce superior work when it’s informed by exceptional performances, a strong script, a disciplined and clear-eyed director and captured images that build a fully rendered, fully inhabited world. This is one of the best films I have seen in a year filled with some exceptional work.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hail Caesar!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HailCaesar!" />
    <published>2016-02-19T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-19T04:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If there’s a crewmember of <em>Hail Caesar!</em> who exemplifies this film’s beating heart, it’s you. In the same way that certain Coen Brother’s films are like a Rube Goldberg device designed by MC Escher—exhausting to even think about—the hairstyles you designed for the film are equally byzantine and endlessly complex. They are elaborate, terraced constructions that capture a paradoxical authenticity; they foster the illusion that you are copying an original that <em>never actually existed</em>. </p>

<p>To watch <em>Hail Caesar!</em> is to fall through a wormhole to an alternate 1950’s Hollywood. Which, to be clear, is a charming place to be. The Coens have created an elaborate confection that is both a parody of itself and still deeply in love with the very thing it is poking fun at.</p>

<p>There are singing cowboys, Roman Centurions, Communist, Dames, a square jawed hero racked by uncertainty and, of course, Seamen everywhere. Nothing is sacred to the Coens—which is demonstrated in a sharply rendered set piece involving a priest, a rabbi, a pastor, and a patriarch walking into a room. </p>

<p>But the hair. My god, the hair in this movie. George Clooney with his Roman bowl cut, Josh Brolin with his magnificently brylcreemed pompadour, Tilda Swinton’s behatted magnificence as well as Alden Ehrenreich’s monumental spit curl, Scarlett Johansson’s hair that never gets wet (despite her turn as a faux Ester Williams) and Channing Tatum’s godlike swoop. All of this in aid of creating a place and time that feels absolutely genuine in its artifice.</p>

<p>Josh Brolin’s Eddie Mannix is the centerpiece of this film. He is a fixer for Capitol studios, spending his days and nights at the center of an endless storm of fuck-uppery: actresses having children out of wedlock; stars being kidnapped by disaffected communist screenwriters; gossip columnists attempting to leverage scandals; and then he also makes sure that the machinery of the moviemaking process remains well oiled, both metaphorically and literally.</p>

<p>There’s even an overt Christ metaphor that shadows Eddie like his ace secretary Natalie (a great performance by Heather Goldenhersh) but I suspect what the Coen’s are actually getting at is something a little more complicated.</p>

<p>If this film is attempting to do anything more than entertain, it seems to be an expression of the inherent ambivalence of the Coens’ relationship with the studios, and Hollywood in general, both past and present. They love what it could have been, or what it might still be, but they are clear-eyed about what it actually is. In the same way that <em>Birdman or (The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance)</em> is about how small-minded egomaniacs are nonetheless capable of producing great art, almost by accident, <em>Hail Caesar!</em> is a complicated love letter to the unpleasant but captivating characters who often populate the movie making industry.</p>

<p>While religion is often a screen for some of the most unpleasant of human behavior, the idea behind it still remains appealing, even if it is perverted at every turn—much like Hollywood. And it is in this small valley between the aspirational and the real that <em>Hail Caesar!</em>  plants its gaudy flag. And you and your magnificent creations helped to make sure that it is a valley populated by men and women with hair that we can all only dream of, Donna. And for that, I salute you.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Racing Extinction</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/17/racing-extinction.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RacingExtinction" />
    <published>2016-02-17T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-17T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/17/racing-extinction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re almost as famous as the dinosaurs you so righteously wiped out. The extinction you caused was severe – roughly 80% of the species living on Earth at the time didn’t make it. But nobody blames you.. We accept that  you were nature playing its course. You were an abnormality of probable odds. If you had crashed into some space debris before entering our gravitational pull, you could have been thrown off course and everything would have been different. The chances of an asteroid your size hitting Earth again are almost impossible, but that won’t stop us from entering the planet’s next extinction level event. In fact, we’re in it now. We are that event. We humans have become you, the asteroid.</p>

<p>That’s a pretty bold claim, but after watching <em>Racing Extinction</em>, it’s a harsh reality I had to face. <em>Racing Extinction</em> is an Oscar-nominated documentary (Best Original Song) that highlights the immense global destruction humans are selfishly causing—from selling endangered animals on the black market, to wiping out species by destroying natural habitats, to acidifying our oceans via carbon dioxide. If we scale Earth’s existence down to a 24-hour clock, as seen in <em>Racing</em> Extinction, humanity only appears a few seconds before midnight, and in the few seconds, we’ve promptly fucked things up. </p>

<p>We’re often quick to dust environmental impact off our shoulders; we see it as a small price to pay for modern luxuries. This is alarming considering not only are we the ones causing another extinction—we’re also the only ones who can stop it. So, unless dolphins finally get tired of our shit and revolt out of the oceans and fix the world, it’s up to us to become aware of our footprint. Which is why I believe everyone should take an hour and twenty minutes of their week to watch <em>Racing Extinction</em>. </p>

<p>We’re not a sudden force of nature. We’re not an improbable cause like you. We’re unconsciously, yet consciously bringing about our end in increments. In the back of our minds, we know all the wrong we’re doing, but we choose to suppress it. For those who do know what we’re doing and choose to accept it, only a handful of them are actually willing to put the first foot forward and make a change. I’m writing this letter but I certainly haven’t done anything of value to save the planet after watching <em>Racing Extinction—which is awful because _Racing Extinction</em> is an excellently crafted documentary. Director Louie Psihoyos does a great job of threading the audience along, informing and shocking along the way. </p>

<p>I was forced to take a hard look at myself and society around me, just like <em>Happy</em> and <em>Zeitgeist: The Movie</em> did; two of my favourite documentaries. And in that hard look, I found the lethargic human in me—the one who’s too used to public transportation and pre-cut chicken breast to want to change. </p>

<p>I, like most humans, am part of the systematic problem. I am gravity pulling you into Earth’s line of sight. I am the college student who knows my paper is due the next morning yet I can’t be bothered to stop watching Netflix. I’d rather face the consequence and justify my actions at a later time than give up what makes me feel comfortable. Humans are a very flawed species; we’re brilliant yet stupid, aware yet oblivious and driven yet lazy.</p>

<p>In other words: do you have a cousin that’s looking to make a rest stop? We might just need another wake up call.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Deadpool</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/2/12/deadpool.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Deadpool" />
    <published>2016-02-12T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-12T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/2/12/deadpool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My plan was to address this letter to <em>Deadpool’s</em> title sequence designer<em>—</em>after which I would make some clever comments about how, if nothing else, the film had a kind of internal integrity worth recommending. Then I was going to compare <em>Deadpool</em>’s opening credits—which were absolutely true to the tone of the film throughout—to other, more opaque, and nonrepresentational (to the point of distraction) opening sequences, like David Fincher’s <em>Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em>.</p>

<p>All this was going make the larger point that <em>Deadpool</em>, while essentially being the lucid dream of some really clever, but utterly perverse, 13 year old boy’s id, was at least fundamentally honest about its intentions from the start.</p>

<p>Anyway, that whole conceit kind of swallowed its own tail when I found out that you were a first time director who had largely made his bones as the creative force behind Blur Studios—which, among other things, had fashioned the opening titles for David Fincher’s version of <em>Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em>.</p>

<p>So instead of that I will go with plan B—where I point out that along with the writing team from <em>Zombieland</em> (Rhett Reese and Paul Wernick), you have managed to create a film that is flat out fun to watch. The opening titles skewer the film’s own narrative premises (the usual superhero origin story tinged by dark and gritty regret) without actively sneering at the larger framework (superhero movies in general)—and, in doing so, they announce that the movie we are about to see is as happy to laugh at itself as anything else, while still managing to follow a narrative compelling enough to carry us through the various inevitable discursions. </p>

<p>Oddly enough, the structure of this review has ended up mirroring what <em>Deadpool</em> does so well, which is comment upon its own story as it is occurring. This kind of narrative balancing act is really delicate to maintain—and probably only viable when the story is so boilerplate that it requires very little effort to follow. So while <em>Deadpool</em> the movie is a uniformly fun ride, it really doesn’t hold together under scrutiny. The only way to get anything at all out of this film is simply let it wash over you without spending too much time examining all the moving parts.</p>

<p>This is the kind of movie that probably was going to happen sooner or later—a late period superhero film that lives and dies on the expectation that the various tropes being skewered are so thoroughly inculcated that they don’t need much explanation. <em>Deadpool</em> is built upon the probability that the people watching it are at least moderately familiar with what it’s lampooning, so in some significant ways it is kind of a niche market. Like <em>Zombieland</em> before it, <em>Deadpool</em> is a fine confection—like a really good cheesecake. So if you like cheesecake, you’re good. If you think cheesecake is a pointless, empty collection of fat and calories, I wouldn’t bother.</p>

<p><em>Deadpool</em> has very little to add to a larger cultural conversation and even as a story it is pretty small stakes, but, in this case, these are both definitely points in its favor. Because I think you and your team seem to have remembered something a lot of other people have lost track of—comics and the movies they spawn can be fun just for the sake of it. So thanks for a night of just that, Mr. Miller. And I look forward to whatever you next put your hand to.</p>

<p>As long as it isn’t yourself. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>