<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-20T22:46:30Z</updated>
  <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Still Not Over the Canyon - Thelma and Louise at 25</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/15/still-not-over-the-canyon-thelma-and-louise-at-25.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StillNotOvertheCanyon-ThelmaandLouiseat25" />
    <published>2016-06-15T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-06-15T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/15/still-not-over-the-canyon-thelma-and-louise-at-25</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In the summer of 1991, something changed. Women who weren’t comfortable with the cookie-cutter roles society was offering them were introduced to a pair of badasses who were just as flawed and undefinable as themselves: Thelma Dickinson and Louise Sawyer. And we embraced you whole-heartedly. </p>

<p>My BFF Donna and I were no exception. We drove a convertible, wore our mom jeans unironically, and drank strong, dark liquor right out of the bottle. We were opinionated, unapologetic, and sometimes accidentally naked. We once stopped a domestic dispute in the street and ferried the young woman to safety. We were roommates, constant companions, sisters. Men were an afterthought. We invited them over over to kill spiders, open pickle jars, and enjoy conjugal visits. In that order. </p>

<p>We were you guys (if the car had somehow made it to the other side of the canyon). </p>

<p>One of the reasons <em>Thelma and Louise</em> resonates with so many women is that it is terrifyingly easy to imagine ourselves in your situation. Two best friends on their way out of town for a girl’s weekend who stop at a bar for a quick drink or two, and, <em>bam</em>, the course of their lives is forever changed. Even all these years later it’s impossible for me to watch the film without wondering what Donna and I would have done in the same scenario. Sadder still is the realization that, all these years later, not so much has changed. A drunk woman being sexually assaulted in a parking lot in 2016 would find her options for recourse just as limited as they were in 1991. As we learned in the last few days, you can be found half-naked and unconscious behind a dumpster with a man thrusting against you, have the two eye-witnesses who stopped the assault corroborate your story, have ample physical evidence against the assailant, deliver a gutting 12-page impact statement, and be further victimized when the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jun/02/stanford-swimmer-sexual-assault-brock-allen-turner-palo-alto?utm_content=buffer7d092&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=facebook.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer">convicted rapist receives a slap on the wrist</a>. </p>

<p>When <em>Thelma and Louise</em> was released twenty-five years ago, gratuitous film violence was at its apex. <em>Lethal Weapon</em>, <em>Rambo</em>, <em>Die Hard</em>, <em>Terminator</em>, <em>Under Siege</em>, <em>Total</em> <em>Recall</em>—these films and their ilk were in a constant competition to beat each other’s ridiculously high body counts. Off-kilter, unpredictable male protagonists like <em>Die Hard</em>’s John McClane and <em>Lethal Weapon</em>’s Riggs were the norm, and audiences couldn’t get enough of them. And then came you: the imperfect leads in a genre-busting film. Within weeks of its release, you’d made the cover of TIME Magazine under the heading, “Why Thelma &amp; Louise Strikes a Nerve.”. Inside, a clearly shaken Robert Shickel accuses you of having<a href="http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,973234,00.html">, “tapped into a wild-rushing subterranean stream of inchoate rage and deranged violence.”</a> Even though you killed exactly one person. A would-be rapist. </p>

<p><em>Thelma and Louise</em> was a love letter to female friendship that became a cultural phenomenon. Your very names have become synonymous with the kind of wild, out-of-control women that society didn’t quite know what to do with. Your moral ambiguity confused people. Some saw you as victims, others as villains. Many saw you as heroes, when in fact you are none of the above. First-time screenwriter <a href="http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1991-07-07/features/9103170610_1_thelma-and-louise-thelma-dickinson-louise-sawyer">Callie Khouri</a> wrote you as fully fleshed-out characters who were human and true, and who were simply reacting in the extreme to circumstances that far too many women regularly experience. You were never intended to be symbols of a revolution, or a promise to women everywhere that things – in front of the camera and in real life – were going to change. </p>

<p>Flash-forward twenty-five years: the Canadian cabinet has achieved gender parity and Hillary Clinton is the front-runner to be the next President of the United States. And that’s <em>great</em>. But women are still fighting for equal pay, conservatives are determined to control women’s health choices by limiting access to birth control and abortions, and the number of women working in behind-the-scenes roles on film sets (we’re talking producers, directors, cinematographers, editors, etc) has actually <em>dropped</em> in the past year to a <a href="http://womenintvfilm.sdsu.edu/files/2016%20Independent_Women_Report.pdf">still paltry 23%.</a> </p>

<p>And then there’s the realm of <a href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/">violence against women</a>, where the epidemic of assaults (both <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PuNIwYsz7PI">online</a> and IRL), victim-blaming, and <a href="http://www.dailylife.com.au/news-and-views/dl-opinion/male-sexual-entitlement-is-killing-women-20150211-13bmef.html">male entitlement</a> seems worse than ever. </p>

<p>It’s really not all that surprising that your story became <a href="http://www.ew.com/article/1997/05/23/debut-thelma-and-louise">such a sensation</a>. For decades, films glorifying brutality and violence against women had never been subject to more than just shallow scrutiny. Then you two come along and are quickly accused of male-bashing and bullying, of forwarding some twisted hyper-feminist manifesto. </p>

<p>But you were never written to be role models. Though it’s all too easy to revel in the wish-fulfillment of seeing a selfish partner told off, a chauvinist pig get his fiery comeuppance, and a smug would-be rapist get shot, it was even more satisfying to watch both of you evolve: one of you by embracing intimacy, and the other by letting it go. </p>

<p>But the double standard as it applied to you two (versus every other male protagonist in the entire history of pop culture) was comically harsh. All of your motives were questioned. Why didn’t Louise walk away from Harlan? Why did Thelma seek out a sexual dalliance so soon after her assault? Why didn’t they just go to the police? Why won’t Louise talk about what happened to her in Texas? Why didn’t they just turn themselves in? If you are to be held up as role models, it should for how adeptly you bust <a href="http://ryersonjournalism.ca/2016/02/26/rape-culture-and-the-perfect-victim-using-the-rights-words-in-sexual-assault-coverage/">the myth of the perfect rape victims</a>.</p>

<p>Under the weight of such cultural significance, It’s easy to forget that <em>Thelma and Louise</em> is an exceptional film. The <em>Badlands</em>-inspired art direction, Hans Zimmer’s slow-burn, slide-guitar score, the self-assured pacing. The sly sense of humour, the perfect storm of casting, Callie Khouri’s Oscar-winning screenplay with its so-real-it-chills dialogue. Ridley Scott’s understated confidence in the story and the team he assembled to tell it. And of course the much-debated final scene. It all still feels revelatory. </p>

<p>Had any of these moving parts been swapped out (<a href="http://mentalfloss.com/article/64289/15-things-you-might-not-know-about-thelma-louise">Goldie Hawn and Meryl Streep in the title roles, George Clooney in Brad Pitt’s star-making role, a happier ending, Khouri directing the film herself) </a>the film certainly wouldn’t purr the way it does. It was a gender-bending <em>Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid</em>, nihilistic ending et al. And it was a financial and critical success, which you’d think would have opened the door for more films by and for women. </p>

<p>But you’d be wrong. </p>

<p>Fair representation of women both in front of and behind the camera sailed over that cliff beside Louise’s ’66 Thunderbird. <a href="http://polygraph.cool/films/">Stats</a> and <a href="http://womenintvfilm.sdsu.edu/research.html">studies</a>, some of which have been commissioned by the <a href="http://seejane.org/research-informs-empowers/">Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media</a> (yes, <em>that</em> Geena Davis) show very little progress over the last couple of decades in the advancement of <a href="http://qz.com/475528/hollywood-isnt-even-trying-to-include-more-women-new-data-make-it-clear/">proportionality between women and men in the film industry</a>. It pains me to tell you that if Callie pitched her script today – unless it involved a lavish wedding, or an ass-kicking heroine with D-cups in latex – it probably wouldn’t get past an intern. Even though women make up half of the viewing audience, there’s a toxic myth in Hollywood that women will watch stories about men but men won’t watch stories about women, a bias that ultimately hurts both genders. This perception is slowly starting to change, albeit with the requisite amount of growing pains. Just ask the <a href="https://blog.womenandhollywood.com/sexism-and-misogyny-plague-ghostbusters-trailer-proving-even-male-directors-arent-immune-1cdabe3f16cb#.f984cfui7">all-female cast of the <em>Ghostbusters</em> remake</a>. </p>

<p>Geena Davis understands that perception matters. The motto of her organization is “if she can see it she can be it.” If kids see women portrayed on screen in leadership roles like in the STEM fields or in politics, it’s more likely that young girls will aspire to those same leadership roles, and young boys will be normalized to accept women in those positions. Only when female characters are given the same amount of screen-time as male characters, or are given roles that don’t require them to just be sexy, or to be accessories to the male characters, can we more accurately reflect what we see in real life. When we see women’s stories told with equal weight, we understand that their lives are just as important as the lives of boys and men. The real-life implications of this should be obvious – if you think of a woman as an equal, it makes it impossible to justify objectifying her. At that point, the notion of dragging her out to a parking lot becomes unthinkable. </p>

<p>My BFF Donna now has a daughter, and I have five nieces. Statistics tell us that at least one of them will likely <a href="http://www.sexassault.ca/statistics.htm">be the victim of sexual assault in her lifetime</a>. <em>At least</em> one. If those were the odds for getting attacked by sharks or contracting Ebola, Wolf Blitzer would be shitting himself by the pantload. Instead, we file these statistics away in the back of our minds, only to have them bubble to the surface when we wait for a bus after dark, or have too many drinks at a bar. </p>

<p>Last week I showed <em>Thelma and Louise</em> to Em, my 19 year old niece. Mere minutes after the credits rolled we were online and came across <a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/katiejmbaker/heres-the-powerful-letter-the-stanford-victim-read-to-her-ra?utm_term=.dhpyMgEr5X#.ucPXaWPqe0">the victim impact statement</a> from the now-infamous Stanford Rape case. I read it aloud to Em, who is a sorority sister and scholarship student, an ambitious, hard-working, wild and fun-loving young woman who has been to many a frat party. As I read the statement, I thought about Em’s odds, my own odds, and the odds of every woman. </p>

<p>Years from now, when Em and I and her niece or nephew or daughter or son sit down to watch <em>Thelma and Louise</em> together, I look forward to explaining the <a href="http://bechdeltest.com/">Bechdel Test</a> in the past tense. I look forward to explaining that in the olden days, men could abuse women and get away with it. I hope that young men and women twenty-five years from now will be able to enjoy <em>Thelma and Louise</em> for the cinema classic that it is, all while marvelling at the antiquated plot and saying to themselves: “well that would <em>never</em> happen today.”</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Conjuring 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/13/the-conjuring-2.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheConjuring2" />
    <published>2016-06-13T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-06-13T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/13/the-conjuring-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s only fair that you know I’m a skeptic. Not to say that I don’t believe you, or that I think you’ve perpetrated some elaborate hoax. The truth is, my skepticism has less to do with spirits and possession than it does with films that proclaim that they’re “based on actual events”; they so often distort the truth to such a degree that I wonder why they bother to make any claims to veracity in the first place. Your story and the story told in the film <a href="">share little resemblance</a>; both require a willing suspension of disbelief, an ability that just doesn’t come naturally to me. Add to that my general disinterest in the horror genre itself, and, well, let’s just say <em>The Conjuring 2</em> wasn’t my first choice for how to spend a pleasant Thursday evening. </p>

<p>So you can imagine how shocked I was to find that I kinda, sorta liked it.  </p>

<p>Since this story is only barely recognizable to what actually 
(supposedly) happened to you, I’ll give you the broad strokes. It’s 1977, in Enfield, England, and a single mother and her young family (based on <em>your</em> family) are terrorized by the unexplained phenomena occurring in their council home. The second oldest child, Janet, seems to be the most severely affected by something that I guess can best be described as a poltergeist. In order to assess these strange occurrences, the Church sends paranormal experts – husband and wife team Ed and Lorraine Warren – to investigate. Lorraine, however, is reluctant to continue working in the field as she’s seen premonitions of Ed’s death.</p>

<p>In 1977, when your home started giving you trouble, public consciousness about poltergeists, demonic possession, and the occult had already been heightened by a trifecta of horror films; <em>Rosemary’s Baby</em>, <em>The Omen</em>, and, most similar to your case, <em>The Exorcist</em>. <em>The Conjuring 2</em> director James Wan clearly understands the basics of the formula used by those films: put respected actors in lead roles, don’t rush the character’s backstories, and don’t show too much. This formula only works when you have a solid story and characters (like you) that audiences want to root for. When we care about the family, as we do here, even the slightest scares have a huge effect.</p>

<p>After your experiences, I’m sure you have your own reasons for not watching horror films. I didn’t see <em>The Conjuring</em> (though I might now), nor do I watch horror films regularly, and not because they scare me, but because (and I know I’ll probably take flack for this) I find that most of them have unlikeable characters and derivative plots that deliver only cheap visceral thrills (and I prefer to get my cheap visceral thrills elsewhere). <em>The Conjuring 2</em> offers up horror movie clichés like an all-you-can-eat buffet, and the audience I screened the movie with ate them up with gusto. But the creaky floors, Dutch angles, furniture that moves, TV switching channels on its own, creepy children’s toy that comes to life, and countless other tropes don’t feel worn out in Wan’s hands. His constant camera movement, inventive blocking, and deliberate-yet-assured pacing add freshness to a film that would otherwise come across as self-indulgent nostalgia porn.  </p>

<p>Your memories might not be so fond, but I loved the 70s. And clearly James Wan does, too. His art, hair, costume, and makeup Departments were possessed by the spirit of an editor of <em>McCalls</em> magazine, because the movie was not just period accurate, it was period <em>perfect.</em> Too often, films set in the 70s celebrate the colourful, roller-disco kitsch of the era, forgetting that most of it was swathed in dull earthtones, rococo patterns repeated into oblivion, oppressive wood furniture, bushy hairstyles, chunky knit separates, and bulky corduroy suits. When the film moves to Maggie Thatcher’s England, the tone becomes decidedly grimmer. The faux BBC TV footage of a paranormal investigation show was a particularly delightful touch. </p>

<p>I’m still not sure if the campiness of <em>The Conjuring 2</em> is intentional, or just another 70s affectation. Vera Farmiga and Patrick Wilson, who play Lorraine and Ed Warren, seem barely able to suppress the urge to wink at the camera. Though their relationship is supposed to be the glue that holds the plot together, it’s your character, Janet, that is the real heart of the film. Played with maturity and remarkable depth by Madison Wolfe, Janet is sympathetic, yes, but we never feel that she is a victim. The hardest thing for her to endure is not demonic possession, but being separated from her family and friends. You’ll be happy to know that, despite the monumental amount of dramatic license taken by the screenwriters, Janet is not a one-dimensional horror movie child. </p>

<p>Near the end of the film, the scares become more obvious and the madcap pursuit of the plot’s climax, which, when it comes, has all the loose threads drawn together in a ludicrous a-ha moment, had me rolling my eyes so much I probably looked possessed. But by that point I was so invested in the outcome that, even though I couldn’t suspend my disbelief, I <em>was</em> able to suspend my cynicism. </p>

<p>As the credits roll, Wan introduces us to the real players involved in your case: you, your family, the Warrens, and other friends and professionals. I was thinking about you and your family for hours after the credits rolled, and that thrilled me more than anything I’d expected from a horror film.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Love &amp; Friendship</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/8/love-and-friendship.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Love&amp;Friendship" />
    <published>2016-06-08T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-06-08T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/8/love-and-friendship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Love and Friendship</em>, Whit Stillman’s fourth film and his first Jane Austen adaptation (of an early unfinished novella, <em>Lady Susan</em>) is really about neither love, nor for the most part friendship. What it is about is a conniving, vapid, unrepentantly devious woman. And it’s funny—deeply, deeply funny. </p>

<p>But more about Lady Susan Vernon (an incandescent Kate Beckinsale) later. I want to talk about you, you great oaf. I’m not sure I have ever seen a more convincing portrayal of utter cluelessness since Steve Martin’s <em>The Jerk.</em> Your character, Sir James Martin, is the apex of inbreeding that only the English aristocracy is capable of.</p>

<p>Every moment you’re onscreen is lifted out of the pre-show for the Darwin Awards. How you managed to reach adulthood without succumbing to some terrible fork related fatality is a question that, while never answered, constantly hangs in the air with every breath you take.</p>

<p>Feckless. If there is a better word to describe your character, I’m certainly not aware of it. </p>

<p>Despite your florid and twitter pated perfection <em>Love and Friendship</em> is not a one trick pony. Every performance (with one exception) is in aid of a clever and pointed script that revels in the poking at the class conscious stupidities that bracket both Austen and Stillman’s sensibilities. Effortlessly cutting and still somehow affectionate, the film is trifling and yet thoroughly engaging. The tone is very much in the spirit of lighter Shakespeare (<em>As You Like It</em>): pastoral and verging on the farcical. But there is a restraint and a commitment to character by all involved that never lets it run off the rails.</p>

<p><em>Love and Friendship</em> is the epitome of what I think of when someone mentions Jane Austen. Set largely on remote country estates and filled with a tired ornateness that echoes the failing aristocracy it embodies, it is the perfect foil for Stillman’s wry, side-eye perspective. He is both charmed and slightly repelled by the kind of rigid hierarchies that live bone deep in Austen’s work. But he’s more anthropologist that polemicist, preferring to observe rather than chastise—and it works particularly well here.</p>

<p>Kate Beckinsdale’s Lady Vernon is one of those performances that remind you why there are so many UK actors populating US films. She manages to be both venal and charming, manipulative and still oddly sympathetic. It is her best work in a long time. The only real fly in the ointment is Chloe Sevigny, who just doesn’t have the chops to keep up. Her performance is flat, uninspired, and transparently amateurish in contrast to the rest of the cast. </p>

<p>You, on the other hand, elevate every scene you bumble into, which is saying something in a cast that also features Stephen Fry and Justin Edwards (the desk sergeant in the exceptional <em>Paddington)</em>. There is something about you that definitely bears watching, and while I’m happy to recommend this film as a whole, it is your contribution that puts it over the top.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Out of the Shadows</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/6/teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles-out-of-the-shadows.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TeenageMutantNinjaTurtles:OutoftheShadows" />
    <published>2016-06-06T05:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-06-06T05:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/6/teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles-out-of-the-shadows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As the end credits rolled for <em>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Out of the Shadows</em>, a familiar tune crept into my ears. It was the one and only Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles theme song from the classic 1987 cartoon. I don’t know if using that song meant anything to you, but for me, hearing it with your title sequence was the final push I needed to get over my cynical predisposition towards the Michael Bay-era Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtle franchise. </p>

<p>To my utter surprise, <em>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Out of the Shadows</em> wasn’t the incomprehensible mess I was expecting it to be. I was left scarred by its predecessor and I expected any follow up to be just as bad, or worse. But as the movie went on, I found my defensive walls slowly began to crumble. </p>

<p>I was charmed by what seemed like genuine brotherly quarrels. Raphael and Leonardo have always had a tumultuous relationship and I found that was exhibited perfectly here. . </p>

<p>I was captivated by the action sequences – which drastically toned down the use of slow-motion. Thank God. I don’t know if I would’ve been able to handle another TMNT movie where everyone sounded like the grown-ups from Charlie Brown.</p>

<p>But most of all, I was left satisfied after seeing Commander Krang, Bebop, and Rocksteady stay true to their source material. It’s been years since I’ve seen the original cartoon, yet I felt a strong connection with the trio of villains. The nostalgia factor is also why your title sequence obviously made such a difference for me. </p>

<p>Once I started picking up on the cartoon call backs, I was slightly disappointed that the theme song was nowhere to be found. It’s an integral part of any TMNT fan’s music library. When the theme song finally did play during the end credits with an exciting animation style, I perked right up from my reclined theatre seat. To add to the moment, several members of the audience sang along with the theme’s most iconic lines, “Heroes in a half shell – turtle power!”</p>

<p>At the end of the day, that’s what anyone wants from an adaption. We just want to make sure you give credit where credit is due and don’t tarnish the memories we have. That’s one area where <em>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Out of the Shadows</em>’ <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/8/teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles.html">predecessor</a> messed up. It was more concerned with bringing another adaption to life than it was with paying homage. The end title sequence that time featured Wiz Khalifa and Juicy J rapping to ‘Shell Shock’, an original song created for the movie. There wasn’t anything fans could grasp onto. It was mainstream music on top of mainstream moviemaking and nothing classic.</p>

<p>There were some aspects of <em>Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Out of the Shadows</em> that I wasn’t too thrilled about, like the cheesy dialogue and the ever emotion-less Megan Fox, but that’s not something you can control. I’m just happy you had the wherewithal to inject that last bit of turtle power and give TMNT the tribute it deserved.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Alice Through the Looking Glass</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/31/alice-through-the-looking-glass.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AliceThroughtheLookingGlass" />
    <published>2016-05-31T12:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-31T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/31/alice-through-the-looking-glass</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I think it’s safe to say you’ve had a rough go lately. In the past few weeks alone, there was the tragic death of your mother, the split and abuse allegations from your wife, Amber Heard, and the whole dog smuggling incident in Australia. Not to mention the steady string of box-office bombs year-after-year in <em>The Lone Ranger</em>, <em>Mortdecai</em>, and now, <em>Alice Through the Looking Glass</em>.</p>

<p>This adventure in Wonderland is a psychedelic trip that results in a lethal overdose of time-travelling buffoonery. It’s a product designed to capitalize on modern moviegoers’ fixation with fantasy. It hopes beautiful imagery will have enough chutzpah to make up for a lack of everything. But perhaps the biggest issue with <em>Alice Through the Looking Glass</em> is the Mad Hatter’s origin story.</p>

<p>The entire premise of is the film centred around The Mad Hatter’s past; a completely original concept that stretches far beyond the source material found in Lewis Carrol’s story.</p>

<p>In your preparation for the role of Mad Hatter in <em>Alice in Wonderland</em>, you had a strong rationale as to why your version of Mad Hatter acted the way he did. He was moulded after 18th century felt manufacturers. Back then, mercury was a key element in the production of hats, and anyone wearing those hats would eventually succumb to mercury poisoning and go mad. It was a dark and twisted origin that could only be allowed in a Tim Burton rendition of <em>Alice in Wonderland</em>.</p>

<p>If this was the beginnings of your character in <em>Alice Through the Looking Glass</em>, the entire film would’ve been different. It might have actually been good. Unfortunately, your creative preparation was thrown down the drain in exchange for a heart-warming story about a mischievous young boy who just wanted the admiration of his father when designing hats. </p>

<p>With your creativity stripped, your performance suffered. Your portrayal this time around didn’t possess your usual calibre of eccentricity. Your performance was muted. I could see the lack of passion in your eyes. You didn’t command the screen. You weren’t the Johnny Depp you usually are when you’re in character. You weren’t the vibrant Mad Hatter from <em>Alice in Wonderland</em>, you were Hatter Tarrant Hightopp, the god awful birth name given to your character in <em>Through the Looking Glass</em>. It’s even the official name of your character on the <em>Alice Through the Looking Glass</em> IMDB page. </p>

<p>And herein lies the issue with <em>Alice Through the Looking Glass;</em> you’re too important. </p>

<p>This might seem harsh but I’m not writing this letter as an attack. On the contrary, I’m writing it as a tribute. With all the bad news hitting you at once, I’m here to tell you that I still respect you. You’re Johnny Depp! You used to be my all-time favourite actor when I was younger. I was entranced by your performances in <em>Pirates of the Caribbean</em> and <em>Charlie and the Chocolate Factory</em>. So much so that I still hold a grudge against Freddie Highmore, the young lad who got to be featured in not one, but two high profile movies with you.</p>

<p>Despite how horrible the plot and execution is in <em>Alice Through The Looking Glass,</em> the film’s very existence is a testament to your star power. No other actor playing the role of the Mad Hatter would be able to justify an entire story revolving around a secondary character. </p>

<p>Whatever people say about your career, there is no doubt that you’re the master of enigmatic performances. When people see your name attached to a project, they know they’re going to get a passionate portrayal.</p>

<p>Call me biased, but I do not blame the sleep-inducing events of <em>Alice Through The Looking Glass</em> on you. I blame the writers for having you be the revolving point when you should’ve never been one, and for not letting you steer your rendition the way you would’ve wanted. </p>

<p>Even though you’re not at the top of your game anymore, you’re still high in my books. If the allegations between you and Amber Heard are true, that would change things for me, but until then, keep doing you and stick to your creative guns.   </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>X-Men: Apocalypse</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/27/x-men-apocalypse.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=X-Men:Apocalypse" />
    <published>2016-05-27T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-27T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/27/x-men-apocalypse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I mean spoiler in the conventional, non-filmic way. You ruined <em>X-Men: Apocalypse</em>—if for no other reason than the quality of your performance underlined how dismal almost every other aspect of this film was.</p>

<p>It’s sophomorically easy to make fun of superhero films, given how garish they are. From the costumes to the operatic themes, they can easily go astray. The best ones though (<em>Iron Man</em>, <em>Captain America: Civil War</em>) manage to navigate these tropes in ways that allow most of us to gloss over things that would feel ridiculous in any other context. </p>

<p>Sadly <em>X-Men: Apocalypse</em> seems determined to forego even a cosmetic attempt at this kind of useful deception. It is nothing but bombast and bad choices—except for two short sequences that involve you portraying a (seemingly) normal, if somewhat troubled and enigmatic, factory worker/family man in the hinterlands of 1980’s Poland. </p>

<p>Contrast those small moments in time with a cast that features some pretty good actors (Oscar Isaac, Jennifer Lawrence, and Nicholas Hoult) so thoroughly disengaged with the material in front of them that they hardly register. When you can make Oscar Isaac disappear with dialogue so terrible even he can’t save it, you have managed something—even if that something is a weird affront to story logic and the English language.</p>

<p>The most overt crime <em>X-Men:</em> <em>Apocalypse</em> commits is that it’s boring: visually, narratively—in any way it is possible to measure. The script and direction all feel pro forma and haphazard, as if the whole project was nothing but a slot to be filled in a particular calendar. Too often a needlessly busy camera and lazy direction undermine what could have been operatic, powerful moments. The kind of scenes that, if managed properly, would have at least made this film far more viscerally engaging.</p>

<p>Usually I resist this kind of Monday morning quarterbacking—inasmuch as it’s often the height of arrogance to assume you might know better how to make a competent entertainment than people with far more experience and skill. But in this case I feel fairly confident in saying <em>X-Men: _Apocalypse</em> is bad because the people most responsible for it’s content were lazy and disrespectful of the source material. When the plot feels like nothing more than an expedient framework to move from one poorly conceived set piece to another, it’s clear that the whole project is just a paint by numbers exercise designed to empty money from people’s pockets.</p>

<p>And then there is you, Mr. Fassbender. There are a couple of scenes early in the film where you give a nuanced, restrained performance. The setting is mundane (factory life and some domestic moments) yet you still invest them with a sincerity that makes them memorable. These scenes so painfully contrasted with the rest of the film that it felt like someone had spliced a quiet but fascinating indie into this otherwise uninspired waste of time, energy and money. </p>

<p>Part of this contrast comes from your innate talent, the ability to make a silk purse out of a sow’s ear. But I also think it speaks to a kind of professional integrity, the willingness to take the work you do seriously even if those most responsible for the finished product do not. It is your finest quality I think, even if in this case it did nothing but make the whole experience even more regrettable.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Neighbors 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/25/neighbors-2.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Neighbors2" />
    <published>2016-05-25T12:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-25T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/25/neighbors-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’m so confused. When I saw your name listed as a “set educator” for <em>Neighbors 2</em>, I first assumed you tutored some of the younger actors. But I had no idea who, since there’s no one between the ages of 2 and 18 in the cast. Then I remembered Seth Rogan never actually graduated from high school, and thought maybe he was getting a real-life GED during production as an attempt to parallel the growth of his character. But that seemed unlikely.  And then I thought, because of your last name – Bible (ha ha) – maybe you were just a Sunday school teacher, brought in to show these lost souls the light. </p>

<p>After all, there’s a familiar theme to the films and TV series you’ve worked on as a “set educator”: <em>The Apostle</em>, <em>The Leftovers</em>, <em>Thunder Broke the Heavens</em>, <em>Last Days in the Desert</em>. The list makes your inclusion in <em>Neighbors 2</em> all the more baffling. In fact, it’s about the <em>only</em> interesting thing I’ve taken away from the film. So I hope you at least found something redeemable here. </p>

<p>Because God help me, I wanted to like this film. I <em>should</em> have liked this film. I actually watched the first <a href=""><em>Neighbors</em></a> film twice, mainly because I wanted to experience it with my wife after we, too, moved into the heart of a university neighborhood with a newborn. And now, just a few years later, we’re trying to move out of said neighborhood, and away from the all-female neighbors that I actually had to testify against in court over a raucous party. In other words, I could have written the premise for this new film myself. </p>

<p>Instead, I kept waiting for the jokes to get funny, for the characters to get interesting, and for the story to go somewhere. The film’s biggest virtue, I suppose, is the overt and constant reference it pays to gender politics. But it’s so ham and bloody-tampon fisted that it rarely manages to do more than inspire a smile. Right from the first sex scene, where Rose Byrne vomiting on Seth Rogan is anticipated from the first couple of frames, the film felt like it was coasting on auto-pilot. There are no moments that come close to paralleling the first film’s milking of an inflamed breast, which worked both as gross-out humour and a genuinely tense and (emotionally) relatable how-did-we-get-into-this-mess parenting moment. </p>

<p>And then there’s the new characters. There was a lot of room to improve on the frat house actors in the first film, but really, the sorority sisters in <em>Neighbors 2</em> are a sad sack of comedy. Based on the archetypes being played here, it’s clear the filmmakers watched <em>Pitch Perfect 2,</em> but they obviously didn’t learn how to make the group dynamics work. Even the casting of Abbi Jacobson from <em>Broad City</em> is treated more like a red herring for humour, where she isn’t given a single line or moment to indulge her comedic sensibilities. And in a time where pretty much every comedy show I watch on TV is centered on women (<em>Veep, Girls, Inside Amy Schumer, Broad City</em>) I found the lack of humour almost insulting. </p>

<p>So fine, <em>Neighbors 2</em> is far from the second coming I had hoped for. But please, next time you’re brought in to teach a group of comedy actors the Good Word, make sure they don’t forget how to use the bad ones.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Nice Guys</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/24/the-nice-guys.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheNiceGuys" />
    <published>2016-05-24T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-24T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/24/the-nice-guys</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Maybe I’m prejudiced, or possibly (definitely) just old, but 1970s cop/detective shows had the best music. I always imagined a studio’s orchestra full of hirsute, polyester-clad musicians with nicotine-stained fingers, plucking strings, pressing brass valves, and slapping congas while assistants flipped pages titled, “Bad Guys Break Into The Warehouse”, “Driving Down Sunset Blvd. at Night While Smoking”, and of course, “Chase Scene!”. Though your orchestra pit was likely much different from the ones found on Hollywood lots in the 70s, you recreated a sound that was funky, sleazy, suspenseful, goofy and yet satisfyingly predictable. It’s an aural backdrop for a world where <em>The Nice Guys</em> feel perfectly at home.</p>

<p>I’m not sure how many of you are familiar with the tropes of 70s cop/detective shows considering that Slovakia was under control of the former Soviet Union at that time, but <em>The Nice Guys</em> could be considered an excellent primer. Here are a few to get you started; there’s a begrudging buddy element , the plot is a few octaves past ridiculous, there’s a wise-beyond-her years kid, tuxedoed bartenders with information, scantily clad women disco dancing, an elaborate chase scene, fantastical car crashes, gratuitous gunfire, a wacky conspiracy, a villain too narcissistic to admit wrongdoing, and  Velveeta-smooth  <em>wocka-chicka-wah</em> score punctuating every beat. </p>

<p>Of course, you don’t need to be a fan of 70s TV shows like <em>Rockford Files</em>, <em>Kojack</em>, or <em>Starsky</em> <em>&amp; Hutch</em> to enjoy <em>The Nice Guys,</em> but it helps. You see, <em>The Nice Guys</em> is an anomaly – it’s a summertime actioner starring two hugely popular actors that seems specifically designed for the sensibilities of the over-35 demographic. Writer/Director Shane Black fashioned this as an homage, as he did with 2005’s love letter to film noir, <em>Kiss Kiss Bang Bang,</em> and while both films are of the hard-boiled detective genre, <em>The Nice Guys is decidedly a period piece. Starting with the old-school balloon letter Warner Brothers logo, to gas station line-ups, and a villain based on a _Waltons</em> character, this film is full of enough value-added references (the names Tim Allen, Richard Lewis and Elaine Boosler on The Comedy Store marquis, for example) for even the most cynical Gen Xer to feel loved. </p>

<p>Our guides through this gritty, labyrinthine L.A. of 1977 are Russell Crowe’s Healy, a badass heavy with a heart of gold, and the World’s Worst Detective, Holland March, played by Ryan Gosling. The bickering-married-couple-chemistry between Crowe and Gosling is as classic as Archie and Edith’s, and they know it. The plot here – involving the missing daughter of a member of the Department of Justice, a porno that has left a trail of dead bodies, and a Detroit automaker scandal – is secondary to how much fun it is watching two incredibly talented and well-matched actors having such obvious fun themselves. Crowe is the consummate straight man to Gosling’s bumbling, mugging, scenery-chewing clown. Their timing is perfect 4/4 all the way. </p>

<p>Your xylophones, marimbas, and chimes accentuate an already ludicrous tableau. <em>The Nice Guys</em> isn’t subtle, it’s slapstick. Its comic sensibility is more in tune with the buffoonery of 70’s spoof <em>Anchorman</em> than the drollness of neo-noir favourite <em>The Big Lebowski.</em> Black doesn’t worry too much about nuance, veracity, or character development and neither should we. Your thumping funk beats, hi-hats, tempo changes, and literal score – <a href="https://vimeo.com/36459216">perfect fifths for the heroes, augmented fourths for the baddies</a> – encourage the audience to just let go and enjoy the ride.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Money Monster</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/20/money-monster.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MoneyMonster" />
    <published>2016-05-20T09:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-20T09:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/20/money-monster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You know that little crane you operate for a living?  It might look like a crutch, but it’s not. Almost every TV studio has a jib, allowing operators to swing the camera 10 feet in any direction.  Used with intelligence and discretion, it helps make a small space feel more dynamicand reduces set-up time between takes. When it’s misused, the overtswoops and swipes cheaply imitate momentum that’s obviously absent from the content. And unfortunately, there’s no jib big enough to have helped <em>Money Monster</em>. </p>

<p>You probably assumed that your job would just be to spoof those fast-paced financial talk shows like <em>Mad Money with Jim Cramer</em>. And to that extent, you are successful. The film takes place almost entirely on the set of a show called Money Monster, where host Lee Gates rope-a-dopes viewers with stock tips and market “insight”. Aside from strange miscasting of George Clooney as Gates, it’s easy to convince us that this type of show could grasp the fleeting attention of ADHD stock market investors watching CNBC or BNN. It’s when director Jodie Foster tries copying the format of a thriller that everything starts to fall apart.</p>

<p>Being held hostage for hours on live TV is a premise that’s hard to swallow at the best of times. But well beyond that, the audience is clearly supposed to feel that Jack O’Connell’s gun-wielding, bomb-strapped hostage-taker is more sympathetic than pathetic. By watering down any psychoses or eccentricities in an attempt to keep the character relatable, the film opens up a logic vacuum that no end goal can fill. He just wants… answers? To why he lost money in the stock market? And then he can die happy? As Jim Kramer would say; BULL!</p>

<p>Motivation issues of the antagonist aside, <em>Money Monster</em> the film suffers from the classic television trappings of being over-lit and overwrought. Even though the movie should be expressing itself in the censorship-free market of the cinema, Foster frames the action too cleanly and forecasts a bloodless battle. She doesn’t allow for the confident pauses that would signal the potential for disaster, nor does she sew enough seeds of doubt or duplicity to make us think anything could happen other than what has been telegraphed in the first 10 minutes. That type of crystal clear semiotic storytelling doesn’t even exist on television anymore, except for maybe the most watered down network procedurals.  But something tells me Foster’s goal for the film was the same as her hostage holder – to simply end up playing looped on TV. After all, even Hollywood is losing money these days.</p>

<p>Start looking for a new job, jib.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Captain America: Civil War</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/18/captain-america-civil-war.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=CaptainAmerica:CivilWar" />
    <published>2016-05-18T12:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-18T12:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/18/captain-america-civil-war</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks to you, there’s a bit of distance between how much I appreciate that film critics are rallying behind <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> and how much I appreciated the movie itself. </p>

<p>I suppose this distance has something to do with validation; I appreciate the positive outside critical attention because it means the wider world is finally coming to understand why it meant so much for me, as a relatively powerless kid in a small town, to pore through the spinner racks at the local convenience store in search of the latest issues of <em>Iron Man</em> or <em>West Coast Avengers</em> or <em>Guardians of the Galaxy</em> so that I could find out what my super-powered pals were up to in exotic places like New York or California or, say, the volcanic planet of Haven..  </p>

<p>In other words, I’m one of those middle-class white male comic book readers who are responsible for the current glut of superhero flicks.</p>

<p>I grew up reading <em>Spider-Man</em>, <em>Avengers</em>, <em>Batman</em>, <em>Justice League</em>, <em>X-Men</em>, and about a decade ago, when Hollywood studios discovered how much money I was willing to spend on indulging my deep nostalgia for those characters, they saw an opportunity. But they pursued that opportunity in a unique way: they didn’t build those films for mainstream audiences. They didn’t water them down, didn’t strip away the deep mythology, didn’t do away with the elaborate costumes, didn’t divorce them, visually or tonally, from the four-color format from which they originated. Instead, they embraced all those things. And, in doing so, embraced the fans that had supported those characters for decades previous. They indulged in the deep mythology. They planted obscure details that only the nerdiest comic fans would pick up. They serialized the stories, had each film give context to the next; missing an after-credits stinger meant you were missing out on an important piece of plot information for the next big blockbuster that was coming along. In short, they found a way to translate comic books onto the big screen so that casual moviegoers and deeply-invested fanboys alike could find sublimity in the cinematic versions of these patently absurd costume-wearing super-folks. </p>

<p>The studios posited that those deeply-invested fanboys (a group of which I am a fringe member) would show up for them all. And they were right. We do. Even the shitty ones. Because, like most “men” of my generation, I haven’t yet found a way to disassociate my adult self from the twelve year-old version of me who lives inside my brain, in stasis, still drinking Coke slushes on the basement floor, flipping through the pages of Wizard magazine, tracing cool Whilce Portacio poses, making lists of cool names for the superheroes I’ll one day make comics about: Nightblood, Nighthunter, Bloodhunter, Killhunter, Deathblood, etc. I am not, as Darwin might expect, an evolved version of that kid. I am a separate entity. And, as his caretaker and protector and father-figure, I will do anything to please him. Like, for example, bring him to a movie in which two teams of superheroes run towards each other across an empty airfield,  <em>Braveheart</em>-style, and collide in a flurry of fisticuffs and repulsor-blasts. It’s one of the goofiest things you’ll see onscreen this year. Maybe ever. But it’s also thrilling. It’s a George Perez splash page come to life. </p>

<p>I suppose I feel a certain amount of self-consciousness when watching these films. Like a parent at a school play. What stands out to me aren’t all the things that go well (and in the case of this film, there are a lot of them), but rather all those imperceptible miscues and minor moments of disharmony. And, by the end, the feeling most prominent in my brain and body is one of relief. I’m so worried about what other people are going to think of these movies – serious people, <em>critics</em> – that I can’t fully indulge in what should be a deeply indulgent, personally satisfying experience.  </p>

<p>Have I grown up too much to enjoy these objectively enjoyable movies? Are my expectations out of line with those of the perpetual twelve year-old trapped within me?</p>

<p>Whatever the case, my adult self thinks it’s more interesting than most people realize that this summer’s two big superhero spectacles are concerned (in different ways, both philosophically and in net effectiveness) with the very complaints that audiences have levied against such films here in the real world. It seemed a few years ago that we’d reached some pinnacle of CGI-destruction. Like some clever programmer had developed a cost-effective way to render collapsing buildings, and suddenly every film had, as its centerpiece, a scene of large-scale metropolitan destruction. I recall being particularly offended by the climax of <em>Star Trek</em> <em>Into</em> <em>Darkness</em>, in which the annihilation of San Francisco by a crashing starship is barely acknowledged by the screenwriters, or, likewise, the characters onscreen. It was a minor plot point that served only to get us from one scene to the next. But what point is there in stopping the villain after he has killed hundreds of thousands of people? Hasn’t he already won? </p>

<p>The tipping point – in the public consciousness, at least – may have been the ending of <em>Man of Steel</em>, which also features the careless ruination of an entire city, and even less empathy from those, both behind the scenes and onscreen, who were responsible for it (Superman and Lois Lane exchange a tender first kiss atop the smoking rubble). Even the good-hearted new Star Wars movie pays tribute to its ancestor by featuring the destruction of an entire planet by way of super-huge space-laser—but this time we get to see the terrified faces of its population right before they’re incinerated. If you need proof that George Lucas is a better pop filmmakers than he gets credit for, look no further than the fact that he knew better than to show us something like that. </p>

<p>Times have changed since the heyday of Lucas and Spielberg and Zemeckis and all those other summer blockbuster auteurs. There are fifteen year-olds coming to see these Marvel flicks that have never known a world in which images of mass death <em>aren’t</em> a significant part of the culture’s visual vocabulary. Sure, in the 1990s we saw asteroids destroy New York in <em>Armageddon</em>, rivers of lava rolling down the streets of Los Angeles in <em>Volcano</em>, a scale-model of the White House exploded in <em>Independence Day</em>. But the events of 9/11 fundamentally changed the way destruction is depicted onscreen. Even <em>The Avengers</em>, which seems the jauntiest foray into urban catastrophe, gave us enough thrusting clouds and snow-like debris and dust-covered citizens running for cover that it would be impossible for the filmmakers to argue they <em>weren’t</em> purposely invoking the spirit of September 11th. </p>

<p>What I liked most (in retrospect) about <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> is that the plot isn’t precipitated on some grand act of violence. Yeah, there are some bombings along the way, but the fate of the entire world <em>doesn’t</em> hang in the balance. Rather a friendship. And not a deep personal relationship. A <em>professional</em> friendship. It’s essentially the story of two coworkers who come to blows over how best to do their jobs. The villain’s maniacal plan isn’t world domination or mass death, rather to sow distrust. It’s an abstract sort of depravity, but the magic of the film is that it manages to make those stakes feel graver and more immediate than if a super-huge space-laser was pointed at the planet. There are no world engines reversing earth’s gravity, no giant energy domes crackling with electricity. Just a love triangle. Three dudes who want to trust each other, but who can’t.</p>

<p>In the context of contemporary Hollywood’s fetish for exploding buildings, something about that feels extraordinary.</p>

<p>But for all its virtues, the movie doesn’t unfold like a movie. It’s stilted, too fast, too slow, somehow simultaneously compressed and drawn out. Abandoned is the traditional Syd Field plot structure. There are inciting incidents, sure. And rising action, and denouements. But the pace at which they occur is arrhythmic. Everyone is talking about Spider-Man, and about the terrific scene in which he’s introduced (and, yes, it <em>is</em> pretty terrific). But it brings the whole film to a jarring halt, and feels like the opening or closing scene to an episode of a television series. The masterminds who have built the Marvel Cinematic Universe have done an amazing job of serializing these stories, but here, for the first time, the world feels cluttered.  </p>

<p>The bombastic action sequence I referenced earlier would, in a film of reasonable length, have been the Big Final Fight, but, in this new age of epics, actually occurs at the midpoint. Everything that follows feels like an addendum, like the hasty replacing of the chess pieces so that the next game can be played. </p>

<p>But I like chess. There are strict rules, yes, but within those rules lies the capacity to produce divine movements. Perhaps <em>Captain America: Civil War</em> is one of those movements. When I was twelve, the threshold for what constituted divinity was much lower, and I hesitate to let that twelve year old still living inside me to alter my expectations. But for a movie like this, maybe I should let him. Maybe I shouldn’t worry so much about the fractured narrative and the moral message and the critical response and just let him enjoy how well the filmmakers have managed to translate the physics and mood and fun of comic books onto the big screen. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>