<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-06T15:23:37Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Spectre</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/6/spectre.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Spectre" />
    <published>2015-11-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/6/spectre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Spoilers Throughout</em></p>

<p>You and I are the same age James (at least your movie incarnation) both being born in the black and white world of 1962. That you—or at least a very specific iteration of you—died so early seems inevitable. That I lived to see it is just disappointing</p>

<p><em>Spectre</em> is an unintentionally apt title for this film James, since you are now a ghost of what you once were—and a pitiful, declawed ghost at that. The brutish, unmannered pig we were introduced to in <em>Casino Royale</em> has evolved into a character that is close to indistinguishable from some overwrought Roger Moore/Pierce Brosnan hybrid. Sans the invisible car, thankfully. Although we do get the front half of a plane skiing down a hill.</p>

<p>Jesus.</p>

<p>There were hints of this in <em>Skyfall—</em>intimations of a return to the smarmy, ludicrously heightened Bond. The old Aston Martin, the return of a male M, Moneypenny back in the office. I had hoped those moments were just a bit of fan service, a bump in the road before we got back to what makes your character so compelling: the fact that you are a blunt instrument of realpolitik; the ugly, twisted tip of the spear.</p>

<p>Instead, in this new installment, over the course of one hundred and forty eight minutes, you are utterly de-balled. The film begins well enough, with an effectively tense and well-choreographed opening sequence. Superb really. But at the very end of that sequence something occurred that made me cringe—and that small moment made it clear that Bond was back. But it was the small b-Bond, with the dad jokes and the annoying visual gags, not the Bond that you actually believed might be worthy of a double O designation.</p>

<p>And here’s the thing: the world has moved on. The character you were initially modeled on was repugnant. Ian Fleming’s Bond was a racist homophobe who couldn’t comprehend the term cultural sensitivity, let alone practice it. He was the epitome of a kind of colonialism that was, and is, completely toxic. The fact that the filmmakers choose to move you along with the world may have been expedient, but it destroyed the very thing that made you such a durable and interesting character. </p>

<p>That Bond was also someone who would much rather die than evolve. He smoked seventy cigarettes a day and drank like a fish. Jittery and bleak-minded he epitomized a life that absolutely precluded dying old and in bed. He was a spy with a license to kill, and he enjoyed the shit out of that prerogative.  </p>

<p>That Bond was a nasty dinosaur, a man literally out of time, and by far the most interesting incarnation by any standard. The man who, bare-handed, beat another man to death in <em>Casino Royale</em>—in black and white no less—has now given way to a man who throws his weapon of choice aside in order to ride off into the sunset with his girlfriend.</p>

<p>For you to exist in any meaningful way James, you have to contrast with your environment—you have to be the antithesis of a chameleon. For you, to <em>adapt</em> is to <em>die</em>. And if you continue down this road, it will be a slow, undignified expiration.</p>

<p>A <em>Spectre</em> of your former self indeed.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The 16 Sexiest Roles on a Film Set</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/28/the-16-sexiest-roles-on-a-film-set.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=The16SexiestRolesonaFilmSet" />
    <published>2015-10-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/28/the-16-sexiest-roles-on-a-film-set</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I know why you really got into the business. It wasn’t because you’re a masochist for long hours or a sucker for uncertain income. You think film is sexy. Actually, you <em>know</em> film is sexy. And you’re right.</p>

<p>If you’re attracted to a career in filmmaking, it’s only natural that the people in the industry will turn your crank. But beware – there’s a hierarchy of hotness on set.</p>

<p>Here’s a wildly subjective ranking of roles, and what gives them different degrees of bedability. Actors have been disqualified for obvious reasons (they’re all bat-shit crazy).</p>

<p><strong>16. Data Wrangler</strong></p>

<p>Look, somebody had to be last. And let’s face it – most Data Wranglers have their heads buried in a laptop all day and rarely register on set. When you do, it’s usually disastrous. Being the bearer of bad news that a file is corrupt or a card won’t read is the ultimate buzz kill – even if it’s not your fault (and it usually isn’t). Sure, you can sometimes score points with actors by giving them a sneak peak at the digital dailies, but even then you’re just being used. It’s sad to say that the one job on set with zero room for error is not exactly a head turner, but at least you made the list (sorry, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/9/cloudburst.html">Craft Services</a>). </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Arnaud Hemery Data Manager for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/25/lucy.html"><em>LUCY</em></a></p>

<p><strong>15. Production Assistant</strong></p>

<p>You’re not last! It wouldn’t be fair to pick on this job, especially since so many of us have been PA’s at one time or another. Yes, it’s unglamorous and often attracts unskilled go-getters, but stick around because itgetsbetter. People usually have an eye on you (to see if you fuck up), but at least competence will get you noticed. It’s an entry level-job with big-time make-over potential. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Natalie Wood Production Assistant for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/14/downhill-racer.html"><em>DOWNHILL RACER</em></a></p>

<p><strong>14. Dolly Grip</strong></p>

<p>Here’s a job that many people enjoy doing, but few people enjoy watching. Dolly Grip’s win “Most Likely to Flash Plumber Crack”, but are not nearly as likely to get any ass themselves. The process of laying track and guiding the camera is one that requires a lot of focus and steady work, so luckily most Dolly Grips are too busy to care what anyone else thinks. That’s worth something. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Bruce Hamme, Dolly Grip for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/10/prisoners.html"><em>PRISONERS</em></a></p>

<p><strong>13. Props Master</strong></p>

<p>Being a Prop Master is only as sexy as you make it. Depending on the film, you’ll have various chances to show off your good taste and handy skills. The only problem is that once props are loaned out, most of you turn into neurotic headcases trying to keep track of everything; making sure that vintage book pages aren’t torn or that the vase in the background gets back to your grandma safely. Lack of control inevitably loses you points.</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Michael S. Martin, Property Master for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/13/12-years-a-slave.html"><em>12 YEARS A SLAVE</em></a></p>

<p><strong>12. Continuity / Scrip Supervisor</strong></p>

<p>Good continuity is a total turn on, but more in a reliable relationship way. You got here by proving you have a great attention to detail, and as such, are often seated at the right hand of the director to keep an eye on loose strings. Like many relationships, pointing out inconsistencies or faults might be encouraged early on, but you also have to be okay with being regularly dismissed or overruled. It’s a tricky dynamic to have work in your favour.</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Ronit Ravich-Boss, Script Supervisor for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/6/21/thats-my-boy.html"><em>THAT’S MY BOY</em></a></p>

<p><strong>11. Best Boy</strong></p>

<p>Like the Best Man at a wedding Best Boy is a true misnomer (shouldn’t the “best man” be the one getting married?). Second-in-command of either the Grip or Gaffer department, the term dates back to when managers would yell “bring me your best boy!” to come help with lighting or electrical. This official wingman status is often a thankless job, but at the same time, being shown favour on a big set gets you noticed. Plus, some people would probably hook up with a Best Boy just to say they did. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Greg Fusak, Best Boy for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/29/behind-the-candelabra.html"><em>BEHIND THE CANDLEABRA</em></a></p>

<p><strong>10. Line Producer</strong></p>

<p>Though being the money manager isn’t as sexy as it sounds, there’s some true power here, and that’s the basis for most of the appeal. Many of the department heads are likely to cozy up to a Line Producer just to try and squeeze a little extra money their way. Enjoy it. It’s the best play you have. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Sarah Craig, Line Producer for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/7/time-lapse.html"><em>TIME LAPSE</em></a></p>

<p><strong>9. Unit Production Manager</strong></p>

<p>What’s hotter than hiring and firing people? Well, a lot, but this is still a position that demands respect on set. Points are mainly lost by being so removed from the action when the camera’s rolling, usually holed up in a trailer somewhere crunching numbers and fixing schedules. But with the power to make or break many below-the-line careers, it’s no wonder there’s a little strut in your step. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Brian Bell, Unit Production Manager on</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/9/neighbors.html"><em>NEIGHBORS</em></a></p>

<p><strong>8. Assistant Director</strong></p>

<p>There have to be some cheats here, so I’m grouping all you A.D.’s together, even if the difference between a First, Second and Third is rather huge. It goes without saying that your appeal is directly related to your ranking – no one’s getting hot and bothered by a Third A.D. bossing extras around (well, bothered maybe), and Seconds are usually tucked away in the office somewhere (which at least provides an air of mystique). An effective First A.D., however, really has presence on set – even if all the yelling has more in common with a drill sergeant than a rock singer. In fact, using the band analogy, First A.D.’s are more like the drummer – making a lot of noise and keeping the rhythm of the production going. And we all know drummers get plenty of action. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Lauren Wells-Jones, Casual Assistant Director for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html"><em>THE BABADOOK</em></a></p>

<p><strong>7. Make-up Artist/Costume Designer</strong></p>

<p>If there’s a cool kids club on set, Make-up and Costumes are the gatekeepers. You get a lot of face time with the stars and are the hub of production gossip. But the real appeal comes from being so hands on; cozying up with measurements and touch-ups, striking a quick level of intimacy and familiarity the actors. By extension, Make-Up Artists and Costumer Designers are usually approachable and friendly by nature. Both disciplines (combined here for simplicity) are true art forms in and of themselves, where excellence can be rewarded with an Oscar or a spot on SyFy’s FaceOff. That’s hot. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Robin Matthews, Makeup Department Head for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html"><em>WILD</em></a></p>

<p><strong>6. Boom Operator</strong></p>

<p>If you don’t have a sense of humour, you can’t be a boom operator. The big rod you brandish makes you the butt end of easy jokes, but owning that absurdity goes a long way. It’s a low level position, but also the most visible one in the sound department – and the most fit. Keeping your mic out of the frame isn’t easy. Arm strength is one thing, but there’s also an agility required to keep up with hand-held moving action. For that reason, you’re hotter than you think. Plus, who doesn’t love somehow who knows how to work a pole?</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Valeria Ghiran, Boom Operator for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/2/the-artist.html"><em>THE ARTIST</em></a></p>

<p><strong>5. Grip/Gaffer</strong></p>

<p>Another big cheat to combine these two professions, but the same principles of attraction apply to setting up lights and laying cables. These are technical jobs that require both brain and brawn. Both land on a respectable rung of the professional ladder, and watching someone who really knows what they’re doing is always appealing. But really, this ranking is all about the belts. A lot of people wear them, but no one on set owns them like a Grip and Gaffer. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Andy Mountain, Lighting Console Operator for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html"><em>UNDER THE SKIN</em></a></p>

<p><strong>4. Director</strong> </p>

<p>An ego monster by necessity, a director’s magnetism is a real crapshoot. Everyone on set is judging you, and expecting an answer to their question. If you make mistakes, people talk behind your back. If you act like a big shot without delivering world-class goods, word travels fast that you’re an insecure phony. But no matter what people say, you’re endowed with creative control – and that’s impossible to ignore. If you do all your homework, treat people well, and , your sex appeal is second-to-none. But more often than not, seeing the sausage being made is a pretty heavy turn-off.  </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Marc Foster, Director of</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/19/world-war-z.html"><em>WORLD WAR Z</em></a></p>

<p><strong>3. Production Designer</strong> </p>

<p>You could be working anywhere – drafting buildings, designing big brands, creating personal installations – but you’ve chosen to give your talents to film. The wild variety of skill sets most Production Designers and Art Directors possess make you the most interesting people on set. Most of you care as much about Neo-classical architecture as you do contemporary tech interfaces. You might not sweat as much as the Grips and Gaffer, but you don’t need to. Plus, even in jeans and T-shirt, you still seem to dress better than most people on set.  </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Bobby Vanonen, Production Design/Art Direction for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/6/the-valley-below.html"><em>THE VALLEY BELOW</em></a></p>

<p><strong>2. Stunt Coordinator</strong></p>

<p>Not many sets have the luxury of a true Stunt Coodinator (or even stunt performers), but the ones that do – look out. Everyone’s eyes are on your action. It’s a rough and tumble profession, and one that, at its best, risks life and limb for our entertainment (will somebody give you and Oscar category already?). The reason it’s so high isn’t just because of the Ryan Gosling <em>Drive</em> factor, but the stunt makers who have really broken out, from Bruce Lee to Zoë Bell. Even when you’re doubling for a star, you’re the real show on set.</p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Brian Smyj, Stunt Coordinator for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/12/the-place-beyond-the-pines.html"><em>THE PLACE BEYOND THE PINES</em></a></p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Cinematographer</strong></li>
</ol>

<p>Was there ever any doubt? If the Director is the singer of a rock band, the Cinematographer is the lead guitar. It’s where the real music comes from, and where fans know to focus their attention. As the architect of light and movement, the Cinematographer (or Director of Photography) has enough help to side step most of the drama that plagues other department heads. And even so, you’re often the hardest working person on set. Most Directors are disproportionately indebted to their Cinematographer, so they can’t begrudge the praise you get. But don’t think they aren’t jealous when an A-list movie star<a href="http://variety.com/2015/film/news/emmanuel-lubezki-wins-oscar-for-cinematography-1201439231/">lovingly uses your nick-name</a> to announce your Oscar win to the world. </p>

<p><em>Letter: Dear Chris Cassidy, Cinematographer for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/26/side-by-side.html"><em>SIDE BY SIDE</em></a></p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Value of a Veteran Filmmaker</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/7/22/the-value-of-a-veteran-filmmaker.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheValueofaVeteranFilmmaker" />
    <published>2015-07-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/7/22/the-value-of-a-veteran-filmmaker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It is interesting, and a little alarming, that so many sophomore directors are being handed projects with potentially studio-destroying budgets. Marc Webb with the Andrew Garfield <em>Spider-Man</em>, Colin Trevorrow with <em>Jurassic World</em>, Josh Trank with <em>Fantastic Four</em>  (and, until recently, an iteration of the <em>Star Wars</em> franchise). Last year it was Gareth Edwards with <em>Godzilla</em>, this year it is Jon Watts and the Spider-Man reboot—Watts is, incidentally, a director whose first feature <em>hasn’t</em> <em>actually been</em> <em>in wide release</em> _yet. </p>

<p>While directing seems to be one of those professions that is only perfected through doing, what doesn’t seem to make a lot of sense is the immediate jump from zero funded indie to budgets that are the GNP’s of some countries. When even someone as savvy and experienced as Joss Whedon (although <em>The Avengers</em> really was just his second feature film) can be turned out because of the kind of terrible shearing pressure that these films can generate, it seems a awful lot to expect first-or-second timers to negotiate. Josh Trank, whose indie <em>Chronicle</em> (12 million dollar budget) led directly to <em>The</em> <em>Fantastic</em> <em>Four</em> (budget 122 million) just recently lost the <em>Star Wars</em> gig, at least partially, because of erratic behavior on the set of <em>FF.</em> </p>

<p>If it were only a question of money, or even logistics, perhaps a lack of practical experience would be less of an issue, but the pressures involved in these sorts of enterprises come from every angle imaginable. Anyone without a fair amount of experience, both as a director and just as a human, is likely to be pulled apart. (For an example of how badly this can go I would point everyone to the documentary <em>Overnight.</em> Troy Duffy was the writer/director of <em>Boondock Saints</em> and is the poster boy for the worst-case scenario in this instance.)</p>

<p>These budgets not only represent a huge investment on the part of the studio but they also come with any number of peripheral expectations: to serve the fan base, to meet unrealistic first weekend goals, to manage the inevitable, and often contradictory, demands that come with promotional budgets that often are as large as the production budgets. Sometimes these films even represent investments significant enough to topple whole studio—forget what a flop might do to the individuals involved. There are probably very few twenty-six year olds equipped to manage any one of these concerns, much less all of them.</p>

<p>Less important whether any particular film works, though, is what this approach may be doing to a whole generation of up and coming filmmakers. Not so long ago it was possible to build a body of work that allowed for a gradual maturing of the creative process. Directors like Scorsese, Cuarón, The Coen Bros., Kathryn Bigelow or even Guillermo Del Toro were initially involved in low budget, low stakes (at least in a fiscal sense) filmmaking. Films like <em>Mean Streets, , Near Dark, Sólo Con Tu Pareja, El Espinazo del Diablo, Blood Simple,</em> were, most importantly, all steps along a longer creative path and not just an audition for a place at the summer tentpole trough.</p>

<p>What that meant was the filmmakers in question could afford a mistake or two and it wouldn’t cost the studio millions of dollars, people their careers or even risk ending up being the punch line in a terrible joke. Q: What cost 200 million dollars and has four arms. A: <em>John Carter.</em> And let’s face it, you don’t hear Andrew Stanton being bandied about as the next big thing—but this was a guy, just three years ago, who was being touted as another Brad Bird.</p>

<p>Probably the best example I can give of the potential cost of all of this is not the most obvious one. If you compare <em>Jurassic World</em> to <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> (at least in the most reductive way possible) you might say one was a moderate success while the other was an unprecedented accomplishment. But if you watch all the interviews and other media that led up to both releases, only one of the two directors looked like they had just finished crossing the ocean in an open boat,while fighting off sharks the whole way. And it wasn’t the seventy year-old who had spent six months in the desert with a pissed off Tom Hardy.</p>

<p>Colin Trevorrow looks and sounds like he has a bad case of PTSD, and implicit in almost all his interviews is a kind of weariness that seems almost tragic. This is person whose first film, <em>Safety Not Guaranteed,</em> was a charming, low budget indie. His next film was <em>Jurassic World</em>, now one of the highest grossing films ever made. Trevorrow himself lamented his fate, in an article from Indiewire on July 7th  2015 <strong>“[Spielberg] had the privilege of being able to make a long series of original films—‘Sugarland Express,’ ‘Duel,’ and then ‘Jaws’—and from there, built up to something the size of [the ‘Jurassic Park’ franchise]. And in a certain way, I felt like I was being robbed of that right of a filmmaker to make a bunch of mistakes and learn from those mistakes.”</strong></p>

<p>Of course most directors will jump at the chance to helm one of these films. People who choose that profession often personify the term hubris (although notably, Ava DuVernay has turned down <em>Black Panther</em>, specifically citing her desire to continue developing her own voice—so it is not always the case). Certainly it is ridiculous to expect the studios not to continue along this path as long as the success rate is over a certain percentage.</p>

<p>Perhaps the question is this: what is the cost of our collective, and seemingly never ending, desire for more and bigger and faster? There is a huge amount of social media pressure being exerted on the studios to produce whole slews of the kind of shared world films that the Marvel and DC universes represent. Perhaps in our desire to see these films created we have lost sight of some of the costs involved. </p>

<p>It is worth wondering, at least, what these individuals might have done were they not so quickly subsumed into the machine, if they had to eke out their own path in the wilderness for a little while longer. </p>

<p>After all, can you really have a <em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> without first having taken the long trip Beyond Thunderdome?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Conversation with &lt;em&gt;Big Game&lt;/em&gt; Director Jalmari Helander</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/7/8/a-conversation-with-director-jalmari-helander.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AConversationwith&lt;em&gt;BigGame&lt;/em&gt;DirectorJalmariHelander" />
    <published>2015-07-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-07-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/7/8/a-conversation-with-director-jalmari-helander</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Finnish director Jalmari Helander is breaking into the Hollywood game with a new actioner starring Samuel Jackson – <em>Big Game</em>. We talk about his breakout success film <em>Rare Exports</em>, what’s wrong with most action movies today, and who he wants to make the next big action star. </p>

<p><strong>Let’s start by talking about <em>Rare Exports: A Christmas Tale (2010)</em>. The movie quickly became a cult classic, at least here in Canada. What was your goal in creating that film?</strong></p>

<p>I didn’t have any kinds of goals. I tried to survive the whole thing and get the movie done. That was my goal. I also had a goal to make a different kind of Finnish movie, because in Finland all the movies are really boring, and I wanted to do something else and I’m really glad it worked out.</p>

<p><strong>What were some of the things you learned when you were making that movie?</strong> </p>

<p>Well of course I learned quite a lot. It was my first feature film. I have to say that the biggest lesson I learned was that if something doesn’t work in the script it will not work when we’re shooting it, and it will give you nightmares. You have to solve that problem when you are writing, it’s not going to solve itself later on. That’s my biggest lesson ever.</p>

<p><strong>Were there things about that film that you felt didn’t work? Or that you wish you could go back and change?</strong></p>

<p>Of course, but I actually watched <em>Rare Exports</em> two weeks ago, and I hadn’t seen it for many years, and now those problems didn’t bother me anymore. It’s weird. It somehow has evolved into a better film.</p>

<p><strong>Would you ever think of doing a remake where Santa Claus is really Canadian? Because we’re closer to the North Pole and our national colours are red and white…</strong></p>

<p>Well I’ve been asked to do a remake from Hollywood, but I think that would be a really big mistake. And try to imagine if you were to do that, and you get all the resources you ever wanted, and have the same story but in a bigger way, and in the end you realize something is missing, like, where is the original magic that was in the original film? That would be so terrible that I could never do that. Because it might happen, and you can never tell where it comes from. Whether it works or not.</p>

<p><strong>Your new film, <em>Big Game</em>, is about a boy who needs to prove that he’s a man by killing a big animal. Did you feel like there was a parallel there for you as a writer to prove yourself to Hollywood by shooting this big American-style action movie?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, there is this idea of...it’s almost like when I was a kid and I always said I was going to make a big action film and everyone always said to me that it’s a stupid dream and it’s never going to happen, and trying to get me to realize how unlikely that is to happen. But I somehow managed to get my dreams to reality and it makes me feel good. And I like that kind of underdog stories where no one believes you are going to do something really amazing. It’s always nice in a movie, and in real life.</p>

<p><strong>What about the fantasy you sort of created in the film about saving an American president. Is this a typical fantasy for a young Finnish boy?</strong></p>

<p>(Laughs) I don’t think so. It just happened. We had a crazy idea with the producer and we just went with it.</p>

<p><strong>I’m sure you’re a fan of Hollywood films, but what would you say is the worst habit of Hollywood action films today?</strong></p>

<p>I think there are a lot of action films nowadays that are missing some kind of heart, or warmness. I think in the 80s or early 90s, when I was a really big action film fan, and would always go many times to see the same movie, there’s something different from what Hollywood is making now. I don’t know how to explain but something is missing.</p>

<p><strong>If you were to make a truly Hollywood film, who is one movie star you would both love to work with?</strong></p>

<p>I’m a big fan of Chris Pratt at the moment, which I think quite a lot of people are. If you look at something like <em>Guardians of the Galaxy</em>, I think a lot of what made it a good movie was Chris Pratt, if you ask me. I think he’s pretty cool.</p>

<p><strong>So <em>Big Game</em> sort of brings the American president to Finland, and I’m just wondering; is there a Finnish story that you would like to bring to America?</strong> </p>

<p>A lot of Finnish folklore are so dark, I don’t think it would be a big success. I already did Santa Claus which I think is a Finnish thing, although you think it’s a Canadian thing, so that’s one folklore I already did. I’m writing the next one so let’s see what happens.</p>

<p><strong>Finally – is there somebody on set, like a crew member, who really just does an incredible job and you would want to bring with you on any film you ever made?</strong></p>

<p>Somebody who was super great was Kiante Elan who was the stunt guy for Samuel Jackson. He also does the stunts for Will Smith, and he was one of the nicest people I have ever met. Always in a really, really good mood, and he doesn’t have a problem with anything and he’s super talented at what he does. He’s super great</p>

<p><strong>Do you kind of see yourself doing what Quentin Tarantino did or Keanu Reeves did where they turn a stunt person into a star of one of their films? Could you ever see him being a star in one of your films?</strong></p>

<p>I definitely could see. And I think he’s done some acting also, not anything really big but definitely, yes.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Requiem for an Underdog</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RequiemforanUnderdog" />
    <published>2015-06-11T07:43:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-11T07:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>1985 was the year I escaped into movies. And it was a good year to escape from. I was eleven, and there were only two things I was scared of: nuclear war, and losing one of my parents. In 1985, one of those things happened. And since I’m not writing to you from an underground bunker filled with powdered water and assault rifles (although that <em>would</em> be pretty cool), you can probably guess which of the two I’m talking about. </p>

<p>My dad was almost fifty when I was born. He’d served in the army during World War II. He was part of that Greatest Generation of men who smoked two packs a day, drank liberally at the Legion, and never saw a doctor. On my 11th birthday he went to the hospital because he couldn’t breathe. By the fall, he was back home. He was dying. </p>

<p>I happened to be at home during that time, too, with a case of mono so bad my whole body was swollen and I was delirious with fever. Over the next six weeks, as I recovered, Dad and I propped ourselves up on couches in the den and binge-watched movies on Pay TV. </p>

<p>I was the youngest child by so many years that my family treated me like another adult. Nothing was dumbed down for me, nothing was kept from me. I had no bedtime, and no restrictions on what I could read or watch. I know that my family did this out of love, and out of respect for my intelligence and curiosity. But an unfortunate side effect of having no little-kid filter was that, while I was fully aware of what was going on in the world, I had no tools with which to process it. I had a visceral, almost debilitating fear of what would happen if the U.S. and Russia launched their nuclear missiles. Sure, I knew that if I needed clarity on something I could go to one of the many adults in my life, but, in the case of the Cold War, no one could adequately explain what was going on because so much of it was completely absurd. </p>

<p>In the mid-80s, Cold War tensions were high. Not a week went by when we didn’t hear about nuclear testing, or have a regularly-scheduled program interrupted by Peter Jennings, who would somberly describe yet another plane hijacking or hostage taking. When Reagan, Thatcher, and Gorbachev weren’t busy playing chicken with warheads, they were metaphorically whipping out their junk to see whose was biggest (unsurprisingly, it was Maggie’s). Every once in a while, Gaddafi or Khomeini would do something crazy—you know, just to keep things interesting. Then there was Apartheid. And acid rain. And the recession, and famine in Ethiopia, and random mass shootings, and the AIDS epidemic. It’s no wonder coke was the drug of choice in the 80s; we were running out of time and there was <em>soooo</em> much to talk about. </p>

<p>My Dad was a burly, barrel-chested guy. He’d been an amateur boxer and hockey player before he met my mother. But, sitting there on the couch beside me, he was sunken and grey. His favourite actors were John Wayne, Clint Eastwood, and Charles Bronson. Manly men. His favourite movie was <em>Gunga Din</em>, a 1939 war movie about three unruly British sergeants holding back a murderous horde of thugs in 1880s India. Fighting alongside them is their water boy, Gunga Din, who dreams of making a better life for himself. Dad loved watching underdog movies. It’s the only time he ever cried. </p>

<p>Before I spent that fall watching movies with my father, there were three films that had profoundly affected me: <em>Testament, The Day After,</em> and <em>The Big Chill</em>. </p>

<p>The first two are about people trying to survive the fallout of nuclear war. The third is a yuppie classic about a bunch of affluent white people who get together after a friend’s suicide to figure out what happened to their stupid hippie idealism. <em>The Big Chill</em> appealed to me because I took some weird satisfaction in seeing a group of adults struggling with their collective existential angst the same way I did. The other two were training films of sorts. <em>Testament</em> was a remarkably subtle portrait of a woman trying to keep her family and sanity intact after nuclear war upends her comfortable suburban existence. <em>The Day After</em> is an explicit play by play of a nuclear attack on a small American town. It was so terrifying that after it was shown on TV my school held an assembly to calm down all the kids who were freaked the fuck out (and it wasn’t just us fragile children; the network had 1-800 phone lines set up with counsellors to talk down hysterical viewers). After seeing those films, I didn’t feel so alone.</p>

<p>But that didn’t last long.</p>

<p>My dad died on February 11, 1985. At home, right there in the room where we’d watched all those movies together. Which movies? I couldn’t even say. There’s a lot that I don’t remember about that time. And other things I recall as clearly as if they happened yesterday. I remember Dad’s Legion buddies filing past his coffin to place poppies inside. I remember bagpipes. I didn’t cry. Not once. I remember all the adults telling me to “take care of your mother.” I was left on my own to find a way to take care of myself. </p>

<p>So I did.</p>

<p>I won’t bother familiarizing you with the <em>Rocky</em> franchise—the first five minutes of every <em>Rocky</em> film does that for you. <em>Rocky IV</em> is “the one with the Russian” (as it is colloquially known). Rocky is retired, but agrees to coach his best friend Apollo Creed in a friendly exhibition fight against Ivan Drago, a giant hunk of Caucasian granite and the pride of the Soviet athletic training system. After being stunned by the spectacle of James Brown singing <em>Living In America</em>, Drago recovers and proceeds to pummel Apollo. Rocky has an opportunity to throw in the towel, to save Apollo’s life, but he doesn’t do it, and Apollo is killed. After a requisite period of mourning and soul-searching (which involves driving his Bugatti around town to Robert Tepper’s synth-heavy song <em>No Easy Way Out</em>) Rocky decides to fight Drago himself...<em>in Russia</em>. </p>

<p>I will defend <em>Rocky IV</em>. To the death. I once came close to throwing down fisticuffs with someone who dared to say that <em>Rocky V</em> (the Voldemort of the <em>Rocky</em> franchise) was better than <em>Rocky IV</em>. I had to be physically restrained and removed from the room (please note: this was sober, and at a child’s birthday party). I don’t labor under any delusions that <em>Rocky IV</em> is a “good” movie. It’s not. I know this objectively. I knew it in the fall of ’85, when my brother took me to see it at the small movie theatre in our hometown. I knew it when I begged him to take me several more times. I knew it wasn’t good in the way I knew <em>Amadeus</em> was good, or that <em>Ghostbusters</em> was good. But I didn’t need <em>Rocky IV</em> to be good. I needed it to make me <em>feel</em> good. I needed it to give me some hope, however contrived.</p>

<p><em>Rocky IV</em> was an antidote to <em>Testament</em> and <em>The Day After</em> (and even to <em>The Big Chill</em>). I wasn’t worried about trying to survive radiation poisoning anymore, or about whether or not adults would get their heads out of their asses long enough to keep the world from imploding. The Italian Stallion gave me back my power. </p>

<p>My love for <em>Rocky IV</em> is, at its essence, very simple. It’s about wish fulfillment. Rocky didn’t just win the fight—he managed to capture the hearts and minds of our Godless communist enemies. And on <em>Christmas Day</em> no less! He didn’t just show up and win, either. He had to work hard, without his family, with the KGB on his ass. He trained in a goddamned barn! No one believed in him, no one thought he could win. But he did. Of course he did. And at the end of his triumphant victory, as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MsJnxlXepsY">his world-changing speech</a> concludes, he gives a shout out to his kid, and tells him he loves him, and his kid mouths back the words: “I love you.” </p>

<p>Waterworks. Every time.</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter that <em>Rocky IV</em> is rife with cliché, full of cartoonish stereotypes, and laced with horrible (and somehow unforgettable) dialogue. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cxs1MHw2_Ds">It features the granddaddy of all sports montages</a>, set to the jingoistic fist-pumper <em>Burning Heart</em>. It has one of the cheesiest slo-mo sequences in film history, where Duke shouts “Noooooooo!” as Apollo falls to the floor. It has a creepy love story between Adrian’s ingrate brother Paulie and a sexy robot. The acting is almost as embarrassing as the blatant product placement. It even features a fake Gorbachev! But I don’t care. I love it—not in spite of those shortcomings, but <em>because</em> of them. </p>

<p>There’s a freedom that comes from facing your biggest fear and living through it. Especially at a young age. 1985 was the year that I realized no one - kids or adults – knows <em>anything</em>, and I took a perverse comfort in that. Things that mattered before my Dad died suddenly seemed petty or insignificant. Other things became more important. The impact of it changed my emotional DNA. I became guarded. I refused to let anyone see me hurting. Movies got me through that year, though—and through subsequent years that weren’t much easier. Like my Dad, I don’t cry unless I’m watching a movie. And like my Dad I’m a sucker for underdog movies. It’s the only time I let myself indulge in unapologetic sentimentality. I’m a natural born cynic, and those movies taught me that my cynicism is borne from hope. </p>

<p>I love <em>Rocky IV</em>’s earnestness. I sincerely think Sylvester Stallone was as frustrated and frightened as the rest of us, and that he genuinely wanted to make a difference. So he tried. The only way he knew how: by making a movie about punching people while listening to <em>Survivor</em>. </p>

<p>I truly believe Stallone hoped <em>Rocky IV</em> would change the world. Maybe it did, maybe it didn’t. But it sure changed mine.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Superhero Craze Isn&#39;t Superficial</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/5/7/the-superhero-craze-isnt-superficial.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheSuperheroCrazeIsn&#39;tSuperficial" />
    <published>2015-05-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/5/7/the-superhero-craze-isnt-superficial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>One of the most prevalent (and lazy) criticisms of the current spate of superhero themed movies is that they aren’t really about anything. At least anything other than filling sacks of cash for Disney or Warner or Sony or whoever else wants to throw a couple of hundred million dollars at Joss Whedon and his ilk.</p>

<p>The problem with this particular criticism is that it is demonstrably wrong. It is so clearly incorrect that I am often baffled at how people who seem perceptive and well intentioned become so vexed that they lose the use of their critical faculties <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/04/are-the-avengers-really-saving-the-world-if-the-sequels-are-inevitable">(like this guy)</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-avengers-age-of-ultron.html"><em>Avengers: Age of Ultron</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/4/captain-america-the-winter-soldier.html"><em>Captain America: The Winter Soldier</em></a> or any of the other colon-ridden movies are not (a.) great art or (b.) without strong profit motive. But then again you could say that about almost all of culture since we first decided to tell stories around a campfire. You can, however, make distinctions about good and bad, and those distinctions have nothing to do with the box office returns a particular movie, or set of movies, generates (if they did then Michael Bay would be considered an auteur, and no one wants to live in that universe).</p>

<p>When you’re talking about the MCU (Marvel Comics Universe) one of the reasons that some miss the forest for the trees has to do with the cross-pollination of sequential comics with traditional filmmaking. Most movies, even when you’re dealing with trilogies and sequels, are hermetically sealed. It is one of the defining features of mainstream cinema—a complete story is told in ninety or one hundred and twenty minutes. Comics work in a slightly different way. And that difference is crucial.</p>

<p>What the comic book movies do differently, on a structural level, is that the main plot carries through several different films. Think of them as chapters rather than whole novels. Each chapter carries the narrative forward toward an eventual endpoint. </p>

<p>There is an obvious caveat to be made here: some people do not want to spend the time, money, and energy necessary to engage with this kind of storytelling. For instance, I have never watched the entirety of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin_Alexanderplatz_(miniseries)"><em>Berlin Alexanderplatz</em></a>, despite its universal acclaim. But my lack of interest says absolutely nothing about its intrinsic value.</p>

<p>People who read, or have read, comics understand this kind of story telling intuitively because it is in the DNA of the form; broad, sprawling mythologies that often span several different titles and can take years to play out. Sometimes it is well done (see: Neil Gaiman’s <em>Sandman</em> or Marvel’s <em>Civil War</em> series). Other times, not so well (Marvel’s <em>The Ultimates</em>). But when executed properly, they manage to tell a big, rambunctious story with some pretty interesting themes and a depth of character that can surprise you.</p>

<p>Those responsible for the Marvel films, like Joss Whedon and Kevin Feige, understand this kind of structure intuitively. Whedon in particular wields enormous creative influence and has managed to do something I would have considered impossible even five years ago—he invested these movies with a pretty interesting through-line. </p>

<p>What these movies are really exploring—from the beginning with the first <em>Iron Man</em> through to the current <em>Avengers: Age of Ultron</em> and beyond—is the inherent tension between the desire for security and personal liberty. Oddly enough, the strongest advocate for this chaotic and often-dangerous kind of freedom is the character that could have been the most banal and jingoistic: Chris Evan’s Captain America. This split becomes explicit in <em>Avengers: Age of Ultron</em> and will play out in the coming Civil War storyline. And if the Russo Bros. do it justice, as I suspect they will, it will be a fascinating ride.</p>

<p>The Shield versus The Sword. The difference between preemptive paranoia and the idea that life is inherently dangerous and a certain amount of risk has to be accepted. In short, everyone eventually dies and the thing that matters is the quality of your life, not its length (even if death is an elastic concept in the MCU). This is the central conflict of these films and you don’t have to look very hard at any of them to see these two viewpoints banging up against one another. The idea that saving the world over and over again is the singular theme of these films is missing the obvious.</p>

<p>Now if this all sounds a little hyperbolic, that’s because it is. There isn’t much nuance here. However, the best of these movies carry an earnest power that subverts a certain tendency, in some quarters, to see the uncomplicated as something that lacks value. But like most entertainments worth that label, these films have an undercurrent that touches on things we all care about.</p>

<p>There are also drawbacks to this kind of narrative strategy. It risks sprawl. It risks commerce subverting the creative aspect so that some movies become nothing but placeholders (<em>Iron Man 2</em>, I’m pointing in your direction). There is also an unevenness that is inevitable because no matter strong the central planning is, some directors and screenwriters are just more adept than others. </p>

<p>As well—and this is perhaps where the rubber hits the road—some of this critical contempt is less about the films themselves and more about how their fans engage with them. The idea of sweaty nerdlings losing their minds about men and women in costume puts some people off. An attitude which, while perhaps understandable, really has nothing to do with the films as creative enterprises.</p>

<p>On balance, the people at the helm of this particular Juggernaut have managed to smooth out most of the rough edges and create a body of work that holds up over time. These are thoroughly enjoyable films. They don’t speak to everyone, but what does (other than the truly banal).  </p>

<p>The best of them—<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html"><em>Avengers</em></a>, <em>Iron Man,</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/3/iron-man-3.html"><em>Iron Man 3</em></a>, and <em>Captain America: Winter Soldier</em>—are quality works of genre fiction. They are well-written, well-executed, beautiful to look at, and emotionally compelling. More importantly, they move the whole story towards something that might be truly special. Fingers crossed.</p>

<p>What I am sure of is that the pointless hand-wringing over these films and their supposed lack of depth is misplaced. They are primarily entertainments, in the same way that most Broadway musicals are—or any kind of music, or most books, or any piece of cultural ephemera we consume. They are worth exactly as much time, energy, and attention as you want to give them. And if you prefer other things one of the very great features of middlebrow culture (at this point in history) is that you can never see a Marvel film as long as you live and still not lose a minute of sleep or lack any number of quality alternatives.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>We Need to Talk About Adam</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=WeNeedtoTalkAboutAdam" />
    <published>2015-04-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If you are a 13-year-old-boy, ignore this letter. Carry on with your Xboxing and your YouTubing or whatever it is you kids are into these days. But if you have pubes, and a fully developed prefrontal cortex, you also have some explaining to do.</p>

<p>Who the hell are you, exactly?</p>

<p>I’ve been trying to figure you out for years. When I picture you in my head it’s not pretty. I see monobrows, Cheeto-dusted sweatpants, and Crocs. I imagine too many digits and not enough teeth. I realize this sounds horribly condescending, especially because I was once one of you. But that was a long time ago. Clinton was president. Napster was a thing. Adam Sandler was funny. I was high. Pretty much all the time. But even now, when the most mind-altering substance I imbibe is Tazo Calm tea, I still think <em>The Wedding Singer</em> is funny. Everything he’s done since then would require me to ingest Chris Farley-levels of recreational pharmaceuticals to find even mildly amusing. </p>

<p>So really, who are you? I’ve asked around and no one will readily admit to being an Adam Sandler fan. But you must be out there. It’s kind of like how everyone likes to hate on U2, yet their massive stadium shows sell out in minutes. Someone’s going, but nobody wants to cop to it. Like that barbed wire tattoo you thought was cool for twelve minutes in ‘99, if you can hide it now why wouldn’t you? And I can’t say I blame you. Admitting you like Adam Sandler’s films means admitting to yourself what you know deep inside must be true: Adam Sandler thinks you’re stupid. He thinks you’re sexist, and racist and borderline sociopathic.</p>

<p>Or at least it seems that way. </p>

<p>Why else would he continue to make sophomoric drivel set in a Hooters, or in an <a href="http://www.citypress.co.za/entertainment/movie-review-tired-offensive/">Africa rendered so insulting and full of stereotypes</a> that he might as well have just shot it at The Rainforest Cafe? Why would he keep playing the same sad-sack Everyman with a bullying streak and an uncontrollable temper? It’s because he thinks you’re a bunch of mouth-breathing rubes who will happily pay to see whatever insipid dreck he deigns to shart out.</p>

<p>On the topic of sharting, Adam Sandler movies can best be compared to the McRib; they both come around about once a year surrounded by inflated hype, they’re molded into a pre-formed shape with the cheapest material, are completely devoid of nutritional value, and they cover you in shame sweat immediately following consumption. </p>

<p>They also make an inexplicably obscene amount of money. </p>

<p>Fast food chains don’t make food as much as they sell <em>product</em>. <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/the-three-types-of-adam-sandler-movies/">Sandler operates in much the same way.</a> To him, comedy isn’t art, it’s commerce. Like McD’s, he succeeds because he keeps operating costs low thus ensuring a high return on investment. His movies aren’t movies, they are units sold. Quantity versus quality. His goal isn’t to make millions of people laugh, it’s to make a few people rich. </p>

<p>Adam Sandler stopped trying years ago. He admits as much himself. <a href="http://www.avclub.com/article/adam-sandler-confirms-his-movies-are-just-paid-vac-204952">His films are an excuse for him and his friends to get a paid vacation</a>. Which wouldn’t be so sad if his movies were even marginally funny. Instead they take aim at the marginalized. His style of comedy isn’t just lazy, it’s mean. And it’s mean <em>because</em> it’s lazy. The easiest, cheapest laughs are the ones you get from punching down, from harvesting the lowest hanging fruit. They aren’t effortless, they are effort-free. There is no subtext, no hidden metaphors, no subtlety whatsoever. Chicago Tribune’s <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2015/04/adam-sandler-has-finally-hit-the-limit-of-satire/391550/">Michael Phillips nailed it</a> when he said, &quot;People of color, to say nothing of women, who have been marginalized, patronized or humiliated by a stupid joke in an Adam Sandler movie over the last few years constitute the biggest club in modern Hollywood.”</p>

<p>But for some reason, you’re all still laughing. </p>

<p>Last week, a group of Native American actors walked off the set of Sandler’s latest cinematic abortion, <em>Ridiculous 6</em>. <a href="http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/2015/04/23/native-actors-walk-set-adam-sandler-movie-after-insults-women-elders-160110">They had been told the movie wasn’t racist, and that the production had hired a Native consultant.</a> They went ahead in good faith that their culture would be represented respectfully. But once on set, they raised several concerns (inappropriate character names and costumes to name a few) which were summarily dismissed. It would have been bad enough if they <em>only</em> had to endure a bunch of people “whitesplaining” what should and shouldn’t offend them. They were then told by producers, “If you’re overly sensitive, you should leave.” Netflix, the company behind the film, released an overly defensive statement:</p>

<p><strong>&quot;The movie has ridiculous in the title for a reason: because it is ridiculous. It is a broad satire of Western movies and the stereotypes they popularized, featuring a diverse cast that is not only part of — but in on — the joke.”</strong></p>

<p>Let’s make one thing crystal clear: Adam Sandler wouldn’t recognize satire if it shat in his mouth. But it’s no surprise Netflix is going to stand firm. Last fall they inked a four (!) picture deal with Sandler (who approved of the union, saying <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/netflix-signs-adam-sandler-to-a-4-year-movie-deal-2014-10">Netflix rhymes with “wet chicks”</a>), and they aren’t necessarily in the same financial position that bigger studios like Disney and Sony are to weather the kind of box-office stinker that <em>Ridiculous 6</em> is destined to be, let alone endure three more.</p>

<p>So far, Sandler himself has remained mum on the incident. But his co-star <a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/movies/news/vanilla-ice-on-ridiculous-6-this-movie-isnt-dances-with-wolves-20150427">Vanilla Ice has leaped to the film’s defense</a> stating, “I’m part Chocktaw Indian” which is the Native equivalent of saying “I can’t be racist, I have a black friend.” If this was Sandler’s idea, maybe he does have a sense of humour after all.</p>

<p>The way I see it, you have a few options, you can admit you’re a horrible person who has helped to line the pockets of a self-loathing, man-child because you also think poking fun at the disenfranchised is the height of comedy. You can admit you’re a stupid person, because you think jokes like, <a href="http://defamer.gawker.com/these-are-the-jokes-that-caused-actors-to-walk-off-adam-1699990455">“Say honey, how about after this, we go some place and I put my pee-pee in your tee-pee?”</a> are funny and you just can’t be bothered to try harder because thinking hurts. </p>

<p>Or you can admit that admiring an entitled 48 year-old millionaire doofus who wears cargo shorts and ballcaps is embarrassing, grow the fuck up, and finally make an appointment to get that barbed wire tattoo lasered off. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Superman v Star Wars: The Blockbuster Awakens</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/4/22/superman-v-star-wars-the-blockbuster-awakens.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SupermanvStarWars:TheBlockbusterAwakens" />
    <published>2015-04-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-04-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/4/22/superman-v-star-wars-the-blockbuster-awakens</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Two movie trailers set the internet ablaze last week. At the annual Star Wars Celebration festival in Anaheim, director J.J. Abrams debuted the second <em>The Force Awakens</em> trailer to an auditorium full of eager fans. Earlier that same afternoon, in what you might call a teaser for the teaser of the trailer, Zack Snyder offered a few quick (and rather feckless) clips from <em>Batman</em> <em>v Superman: Dawn of Justice</em>. </p>

<p>All this pageantry and playing coy is considered best practice for film marketers; trailer releases have become almost as important as the actual release of the film—and probably <em>more</em> important to those opening weekend numbers than the actual quality of the film. But these two particular trailers –in the aesthetics they purport to represent and the manner in which they were debuted – are indicative of two very different attitudes towards the contemporary Hollywood blockbuster. One approach  has exhausted critics, seems to be on the brink of exhausting fans, and may soon exhaust its momentum at the box office. The other approach, rooted in the not-so-distant past, might revive the diminishing artistic returns of the major studios’ tent-pole popcorn flicks. </p>

<p>But first, the two trailers:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ngElkyQ6Rhs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p><em>The Force Awakens</em> bets heavily on nostalgia: we begin with a panoramic view of a familiar desert planetscape (<em>not</em> Tattooine, but a <em>new</em> arid, windswept world); we get X-Wings and tie fighters; and, most notably, a Luke Skywalker voice-over and our first glimpse of retirement-age Han Solo. If you’re not a <em>Star Wars</em> devotee (and no mystical energy field controls <em>your</em> destiny), much of this won’t matter to you. But if you <em>are</em> a fan, the swell of John Williams’ melodic strings and winds likely dried your throat, and the glimpses of your old pals Artoo and Chewie may have brought tears to your eyes. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IwfUnkBfdZ4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p><em>Batman</em> <em>v Superman</em> is a much different trailer. After Snyder’s flirtatious tweets, it <a href="http://www.ew.com/article/2015/04/17/batman-v-superman-trailer-leak">“leaked” a week early</a> (who can say whether the marketing team at Warner Bros. is just incompetent, or so incompetent that they’re brilliant). It begins with the standard throb of ominous ambient noise, then gives us a little Charlie Rose voice-over (which isn’t quite as affecting as hearing Mark Hamill); then a slow tracking shot towards a shadowed statue that is revealed to be, yes, a monument to Superman with, yes, graffiti scrawled across the chest that reads: False God. </p>

<p>Zack Snyder has never been one for subtlety. Whatever hope there had been that the influence of Christopher Nolan (who produced <em>Man Of Steel</em>, as well as this quasi-sequel) might quell his instinct for misanthropic self-seriousness was crushed by the arrival of his misanthropic, self-serious Superman film. The <em>Dawn of Justice</em> trailer suggests that his follow-up is exactly what you might expect from the much-maligned pop-artist: beautiful, hyper-real CGI shots that seem like moving Rubens paintings, and laughable, hyper-dramatic dialogue (“this is how it starts...the fear, the rage...the feeling of powerlessness...”). This sneak peek at this latest superhero crossover – with which DC Comics and Warner Bros. is hoping to establish an <em>Avengers</em>-style cinematic continuity – is more of the same: lots of shadows, sneering, heavy weaponry and political metaphors so broad that not even the Last Son of Krypton could leap them in a single bound. But let’s be frank: more of the same isn’t a bad thing for the bottom line. Despite being a critical disappointment, Superman’s big screen comeback grossed $668 Million worldwide. </p>

<p>Zack Snyder may not be seeking redemption (he’s admirably unapologetic), and neither is J.J. Abrams (though some people think he should be). But Abrams faces a different challenge with his new flick—perhaps no filmmakers in the history of filmmaking has ever faced higher expectations than Abrams does as the heir to the Holy Trilogy. Online reaction to the very first <em>SW:FA</em> teaser is proof. A pitch perfect capsule of images and sounds that elicited every good feeling about the original trilogy that the prequels supposedly forgot, and <em>still</em> the naysayers found something to complain about. </p>

<p>So what does this new <em>SW:FA</em> trailer suggest about Abrams’ approach? And how does it differ, in its foundational approach to big-budget cinema, from the <em>BvS</em> trailer? </p>

<p>First, it’s important to understand why it makes sense to compare these two pictures. What makes them relative variables is the simple fact that they <em>exist</em>. As recently as a decade ago, the notion of a big-budget superhero film featuring both of DC Comics’ two most iconic characters (along with Wonder Woman <em>and</em> Aquaman, who are featured in a series of promotional posters, and therefore, one supposes, appear in the film—once again WB’s genius/incompetent marketing at work) would have been preposterous. Likewise, the possibility of new <em>Star Wars</em> films – featuring the original cast, no less! – seemed utterly implausible even just a few short years ago. George Lucas’s prequels had seemed to annihilate the franchise’s big screen ambitions (animated properties like <em>Clone Wars</em> and <em>Rebels</em> have thrived on television and in toy aisles). That these two films are being released within a few months of each other suggests that we are reaching the crest of the sea change that began when Marvel began intermingling its characters and bundling them into blockbuster franchises. The narrative continuity that is so important to sci-fi and comic book superfans now exists in theaters. What seemed impossible is now possible. More than possible, actually. <em>Profitable</em>.  </p>

<p>So what about Abrams? He’s already rebooted one beloved sci-fi franchise, and, while he didn’t always get the ratio of fan service to storytelling right (says one of the fans he serviced), he resurrected the Enterprise and its crew fairly well. <em>Star Wars</em> will require a defter touch, though, and if this latest trailer is any indication, Abrams may have gotten it right. And he gets it right in direct opposition to the approach Snyder takes. Optimism, positivity, clarity and, most significantly–– a palpable sense of <em>fun</em> something that Hollywood seems to have completely forgotten when it comes to these types of films. What made Abrams’ second <em>Star Trek</em> flick such a disappointment was how much it felt like every other recent mega-action film: incomprehensible action, overwhelming effects, the sound and fury signifying nothing, and, worst of all, an obscenely high body count paired with imagery suggestive (almost offensively) of 9/11. </p>

<p>(You might say he Zack Snyder-ed it.)</p>

<p>But all of this is speculation (and no small amount of barely-suppressed fanboy hope), which is precisely what trailers of this kind are meant to provoke. Maybe <em>The Force Awakens</em> will be dark and gloomy and replete with the kind of slick CGI that contradicts the gritty Old-West aesthetic of the very first film. Maybe  <em>Batman</em> v Superman will embrace the absurdity of a superpowered alien fighting a rich old white guy with an underground armory and a taste for cosplay. </p>

<p>But the trailers don’t suggest so. And while these little two-minute commercials the marketing department cuts together are rarely indicative of the <em>quality</em> of the film, they tend to pretty accurately predict a film’s mood and tenor.  </p>

<p>There’s little doubt that <em>The Force Awakens</em> will top the list of 2015’s biggest films (and with a Christmas release, might just end up being 2016’s box office champion, too). And there’s also little doubt that Abrams has made it a priority to recapture a bit of the innocence and wonder that made Lucas’ space adventures more than just films. The question is, will this return to a simpler, lighter, more positive approach to the blockbuster reverse the trend that started a decade ago with the Nolan’s first Batman film? Has the gritty reboot run its course? And is that necessarily a good thing?</p>

<p>Good or not, it will be, in the meantime, a relief.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Conversation With Director Denis Villeneuve</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AConversationWithDirectorDenisVilleneuve" />
    <published>2015-04-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>On the day <em>Sicario</em> was announced as part of the 2015 Festival de Cannes’ official competition, C. Redmond speaks with the incredible French-Canadian director about his chances of winning, maintaining his signature in Hollywood, and the upcoming <em>Blade Runner</em> sequel. </p>

<p><strong>What does it mean to you to be accepted into Cannes?</strong></p>

<p>It’s the biggest honour – it’s a massive honour for me to be part of the competition this year. Cannes is the Mecca of cinema. To see the lineup, I go there with humility because just to be part of that lineup I’m already very proud, and grateful for the invitation.</p>

<p><strong>You kind of got your start at Cannes. You worked your way from the Director’s Fortnight, and then Un Certain Regard. Did you feel it was almost inevitable that you would someday have a film in competition, or are you surprised?</strong></p>

<p>It was my dream but sometimes you feel like dreams are fading because more and more I was making movies in America. So I thought I was going away from that world of film festivals, and right now this movie that was produced in Los Angeles is a nice compliment because it’s very important for me to keep my identity as a filmmaker when I’m shooting abroad. Just to be able to keep my point of view, to stay myself. And the fact that they are inviting me, they recognize the fact that I was able to protect my identity as a filmmaker in another system of production. That for me is a big compliment.</p>

<p><strong>The Coen Brothers are going to be leading the jury. Do you think that will help your odds?</strong></p>

<p>Honestly, strangely, I’m feeling that because we share Roger Deakins as a cinematographer, I think it makes things tougher (laughs).</p>

<p><strong>Can you talk to me about working with Roger</strong> <strong>Deakins? Tell me what the difference was between working with him the first time and working with him a second time.</strong></p>

<p>The second time I was much, much more comfortable with Roger. The first time I was always a bit impressed. I was feeling like a student and he’s the teacher. The second time it was more collaborative, the communication was much better. Stylistically we get along pretty well. The first experience was beautiful, but the second was better. Working with Roger, honestly, it’s rare in your lifetime that you will have a chance to work with a master. And he’s someone, even if I’m on set with him and I have to direct him, or nourish him so he’s able to create, I always feel like I’m in a learning process, because I’m learning all the time with Roger. Every shot, I’m learning something. It’s a massive privilege for me to get to work two times with him.</p>

<p><strong>Is there someone you worked with on your most recent film <em>Sicario</em>  that stood out to you as great, but might never get any media attention?</strong></p>

<p>Oh boy. Yeah, I’ll give you one right now: the dolly pusher, his name is Bruce Hamme.</p>

<p><strong>You’ve got to be kidding! I did a <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/10/prisoners.html">review of <em>Prisoners</em> and I wrote to Bruce Hamme </a>. That’s too funny. I noticed his work.</strong> </p>

<p>That’s the man. That guy is an artist. He’s the dolly grip and he’s the extension of Roger, the one who will create the dance of the camera, the one who will find the right rhythm. He’s the most precise, the way he pushes the camera is just an art form. I feel he is also the most lovely human being. Roger is using a specific crane in almost every shot, which means in almost every shot we have to build that crane, a little crane that is so precise and so delicate and Bruce is dancing with that crane all day long, and working and he never complains. And he’s the nicest human being. Bruce is definitely the one I will make an homage to, a tribute to Bruce. I could talk about him for hours.</p>

<p><strong>That’s perfect. I met you at the Genie Awards four years ago, and you told me your friends were making fun of you saying, “Denis, when are you going to stop making these pretentious art films and make a sci-fi film, because you know that’s what you really love”</strong></p>

<p>(laughs) Exactly!</p>

<p><strong>And now you’ve got two sci-fi films coming. Tell me how that finally happened.</strong> </p>

<p>When I arrived in LA with <em>Incendies</em>, all the studios were asking me, “What will you do? What would be your dream?”  And my only answer was always sci-fi, because I knew that if there was something that I could do in Hollywood that I couldn’t do at home it was sci-fi. With sci-fi you need a certain amount of resources. So I kept on saying this and at one point two young producers came with a fantastic little short story called <em>Story of Your Life</em>. It was one of the best things that I’d read and I was like “Whoa!” this is poetic, beautiful and strong and exactly the kind of project that I would dream to do. </p>

<p>I keep saying I want to do sci-fi for adults, so like <em>2001</em>, or <em>Blade Runner</em>. That was always the two examples I would give that I would want to do. Or <em>Close Encounters</em>. So with 21 Laps, a company set in LA, I developed this little sci-fi project called <em>Story of Your Life</em>. I’m going to shoot in next June.</p>

<p><strong>And now you’re going to work with Bradford Young as a cinematographer.</strong></p>

<p>Yes, I’m going to work with Bradford Young because Roger Deakins wasn’t available this summer. He wanted to do the project but there was a scheduling conflict. So I made a long research and came into contact with that cinematographer. He’s young but he already has a strong signature. I was very impressed. I fell in love with his work quite quickly, and to my great pleasure he agreed to get on board.</p>

<p><strong>Would you consider working with (cinematographer) Nicolas Bolduc again?</strong></p>

<p>I’d love to because I love Nico. Yeah, of course! But when you cast a DP, you cast a specific sensibility, and for <em>Story of Your Life</em> I needed someone like Bradford.</p>

<p><strong>What about</strong> <strong><em>Blade Runner</em>? That doesn’t seem like it would be in Roger Deakins’ normal palate of what he does. Would you consider him for that?</strong></p>

<p>I cannot answer that, but I can tell you you have the wrong instincts (laughs). It would be a dream for me to do that with Roger.</p>

<p><strong>(laughs) Good to know!</strong> <strong>Are you able to talk about at all what you want to do, how you want to put your stamp on revisiting that story?</strong></p>

<p>From a creative point of view unfortunately I can say nothing, other than that the script is pretty powerful and that it was a long decision for me to make. It was too much of a dream for me to participate on such a project and I’m aware of the massive pressure. The original <em>Blade Runner</em> is one of my favourite movies of all time. I saw that movie maybe fifty times in my life. I will do my homework and I am uber excited. I wake up every morning pinching myself.</p>

<p><strong>Do you think there are any lessons to be taken from</strong> <strong><em>Prometheus</em>?</strong> </p>

<p>You will be very disappointed because unfortunately I can say nothing.  All I can say is that the script was written by Hampton Fancher, Ridley Scott and Michael Green and the three of them did very impressive work.</p>

<p><strong>Are there any scripts that you’re writing that you want to do in the future?</strong></p>

<p>To be honest I cannot make a lineup of projects. For now I’m just concentrating on <em>Story of Your Life</em> and the possibility of <em>Blade Runner</em> right after is enough for me (laughs). After that, I will sleep for three weeks, or three months maybe. I feel that I lined up a lot of projects one after the other and after that I will probably take a break. Just for a few months and go back on to screenwriting.</p>

<p><strong>Just promise it’s not going to be as long as the break you had between  <em>Maelstrom</em> (2000) and <em>Polytechnique</em> (2009). We need you too much.</strong></p>

<p>(laughs) Don’t worry, that’s not going to happen.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Conversation With &lt;em&gt;Pretend We&#39;re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; Writer/Director Matt Sadowski</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/4/8/a-conversation-with-matt-sadowski.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AConversationWith&lt;em&gt;PretendWe&#39;reKissing&lt;/em&gt;Writer/DirectorMattSadowski" />
    <published>2015-04-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-04-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/4/8/a-conversation-with-matt-sadowski</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><strong>Di Golding talks to <em>Pretend We’re Kissing</em> writer/director Matt Sadowski  about the challenges of making a “non-rom-com” and how to film a perfectly awkward sex scene.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Is there something specific about the rom-com genre that turns you off, or made you want to make a non-rom-com?</strong></p>

<p>Listen, I like movies like <em>Win A Date With Tad Hamilton</em> as much as the next lad, but what I felt was missing was romantic comedies that accurately show that not everything <em>does</em> work out. I felt that I could connect to a lot of romantic comedies until the final act. Because for me – and maybe other people too – I never really got a second chance when I screwed things up. The main movie that really lit the fire for this was, back in 2004 there was only <em>Before Sunrise</em>, it wasn’t a trilogy yet, and I really felt like once she (Celine) gets on the train and leaves at the end, I always felt like, if they hadn’t split up, if they’d spent one more day together, would they really have had that kind of connection? I totally buy that ten years later that fire is fuelled again. But after talking to a lot of people, everyone has had those flings where, whether it’s for a minute or an hour or a day or a week, you feel like “wow, we have everything going on,” and one thing can turn it completely off. I really wanted to show that.</p>

<p><strong>Marketing a “non-rom com” film must be tricky. Who do you think the audience is for</strong> <strong><em>Pretend We’re Kissing</em>?</strong></p>

<p>It’s a little bit of marketing speak, but I really believe it’s a romantic comedy for people who don’t think they like romantic comedies. And maybe they don’t know <em>why</em> they don’t like romantic comedies. Maybe it is because they (rom-coms) have a kind of plastic coating to them, whether because of who they cast or a clichéd script or just a formulaic way of shooting it. I think some people, they know, and they can call it out. This is why I don’t make these kind of movies. But I think for some people it’s just a feeling that they have. And I really just wanted to make something that could make people feel just a little bit different and hope that they relate to it because it feels a little bit more real. And the problem with being real is that sometime you lose hope, and I wanted to make a film that kind of questions ideas about falling in love and destiny—but without being cynical about it, either. I think that’s sometimes hard to do.</p>

<p><strong>You did something interesting that was not rom-commy: instead of doing a lot of close ups and soft focus, you did a lot of long takes and medium shots, and you just kind of let things happen. You let the actors act. Did you always know that you were going to film it this way?</strong></p>

<p>There’s a certain style that people know, oh, that’s an indie film, and it’s this kind of handheld, finding the focus, documentary kind of look that really does work for a lot of films. But I felt like it wasn’t the right look for this one. The films that I was inspired by were films from the 70s and 80s, and if you look at those films, their frames linger and they last a long time and it makes you listen in a different way and it makes you expect things in a completely different way. I kind of felt like when you’re in a relationship and it’s going well, you don’t blink. That’s the essence of the vibe I wanted the film to have. I wanted it to be long, gazing looks to make the whole thing a little bit dreamier, because that’s how you feel. And I also feel like relationships aren’t very funny, they’re all kind of awkward, and holding on the frame brings the awkwardness. Not just from the characters – because Benny is pretty awkward – but finding your way on a new date or a new relationship is kind of awkward in itself, and I feel like a long take really helps that especially when you as an audience are now trained to know I’m not going to cut, or you’re not going to see an insert, or you’re not going get a close up, and we get to the sex scene, you kind of know what’s going to happen so you get on the edge of your seat in embarrassment before something actually does happen.</p>

<p><strong>I’ve often heard about actors in sex scenes saying that they’re not as easy as they look, that they need to be very precise in how they’re filmed. Did you storyboard this and did the actors rehearse a lot?</strong></p>

<p>I would say that was one of the scenes we rehearsed the most. I was also lucky that out of all the scenes in the script, Dov and Tommie really responded to that scene, more so than any other scene. Because other scenes were “Benny and Jordan walk down the sidewalk”, and that scene is very specific. “He gets on top of her, he moves his knee, he puts his hand on her hair,” so it was all inherent in the stage direction of the script. And I think that gave them a lot of confidence to just follow the script, because it read really awkward as well. So that will come across. And a little behind the scenes story as well is that you can’t shoot a sex scene without having a union rep there, and a union rep makes everyone more nervous. And that was Dov’s first romantic scene ever and I think he was already nervous, and then to have a union rep come in and be like, “Don’t do anything you’re uncomfortable with, these are your rights,” just put so much in his head, which halted production for quite a while, to be honest—but his character is so anxiety-ridden and in his head anyway that it kind of worked out for me.</p>

<p><strong>Your last feature was a documentary (<em>Don’t You Forget About Me</em>). Did that make it easier or harder for you to direct your first scripted feature?</strong></p>

<p>I think the doc was harder to make because I would say the only thing original about the doc was the idea that I had. But then you’re relying on so many other things to make the film happen. Everyone literally has a voice. Every producer has a voice, every interviewee has a voice. Sometimes you’re not able to shoot where you want so you have to shoot it in a certain style. And that film took so long to make. For that kind of specific doc, it’s an amalgamation of a lot of people’s visions whereas for this film I kind of was able to drive the ship a little more and was very lucky to have a crew that believed in the same sort of thing.</p>

<p><strong>I read that (executive producer) Pete Harvey made the entire crew read the script before signing on to make the film.</strong></p>

<p>I thought that was really cool. We shot in 14 days and we had almost 30 locations, which is unheard of. People thought we were crazy. Most indie films shoot in a 15 or 20-day window and there’s 8 locations. Or there’s <em>one</em> location. So right from the beginning he said the only way we’re gonna get a crew to work hard for us – and because of the shots that I did – its easier to shoot in a kind of verité handheld style, because you don’t need the same amount of equipment trucks and gaffing and all that kind of stuff. To make all these long shots work required a lot of production elements to kind of come together. So Pete was amazing. And I never understood it. I was like, “why does the PA have to read the script? Why does the 3rd grip have to read the scrip?” And he said: “because I want every single person to want to make the film because they think the film can be really cool.” And he was right.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>