<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-16T10:21:04Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Suburbicon</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/11/14/suburbicon.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Suburbicon" />
    <published>2017-11-14T01:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-14T01:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/11/14/suburbicon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Sometimes title credits are nothing but a literal statement about the participants in the particular film we’re about to watch. Occasionally they are used structurally to separate a small prologue sequence from the main event. Every once in a while they are a statement of intent—a way for a director to establish a tone for the rest of the film, often a series of images that evoke what will come, without being directly related to the main narrative (see: David Fincher’s catalogue).</p>

<p>The title credits for director George Clooney’s <em>Surburbicon</em> are a poorly executed pastiche of 50’s advertising that feels both overly elaborate and too clever by half.  They are definitely a statement of intent, one which left me with a sinking feeling in the pit of my stomach as the sequence unspooled. It was a ham fisted parody of suburban real estate propaganda and was still somehow completely unaffecting. It was so bland and shallow that it undercut its intended effect and set the tone for the sordid mess that would follow.</p>

<p>This film fails on almost all levels. Writing, performances, direction, editing, and even the score feel like a copy of a copy of a copy. Ostensibly a satirical take on the hypocrisies inherent in the thin veneer of decency that 1950’s America hid behind, <em>Suburbicon</em> is a hot mess of cross cutting plot lines and themes that never cohere into anything but a messy dog’s breakfast. Like the title credits, the underlying reality that the film is supposed to be satirizing doesn’t feel like anything but a third generation mimeograph of the thing it’s attempting to represent. Add to that a puzzling and criminally shorthanded parallel plot evoking the overt racism of the era (something that should have resonated, but didn’t) and you have a film that seems to be parodying something that only exists in someone’s vague and cartoonish reconstruction of the period.</p>

<p>Adapted from a discarded Coen Brothers script, this film had all the components for something special. The cast is stellar (usually) but, except for Oscar Isaac, is either wasted or truly underperforms. Matt Damon disappears into his everyman role so thoroughly that he kind of...well, disappears. Julianne Moore has less to work with than most and you can see it in her performance. She strains in a way that I don’t think I’ve seen from her before. Nothing in this film feels fully fleshed, but it is most particularly clear in how the characters feel so uninhabited, like noh masks with nothing behind them.</p>

<p>Technically the film is fine. The production design and the cinematography are well executed, if a little stiff and intentional, but in aid of what? At the end of the film we are left with a curious sense that we just watched two incomplete and only vaguely related films, neither of which we would be likely to pursue to completion. Given the principals involved it was a disappointing experience across the board.</p>

<p>The same could be said of your work. Even if it were better executed and felt grounded in something that evoked what it purports to represent, I’m not sure it would be worth the effort involved to see it through.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Thor: Ragnarok</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/11/13/thor-ragnarok.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Thor:Ragnarok" />
    <published>2017-11-13T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-13T05:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/11/13/thor-ragnarok</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>What a strange thing it must be to look upon your legacy in the year 2017. The characters you imagined out of thin air – into whom you poured so much of yourself during those 14-hour days at the drafting table – are gods to us now, as much a part of our contemporary mythology as any real historical figure. In the past decade, your work has come vibrantly to life in the form of a shared cinematic universe that has generated billions of dollars and spread the gospel of the superhero across the world (and, hey, your heirs are <a href="https://nerdist.com/marvel-ends-its-bitter-feud-with-jack-kirbys-heirs/">finally getting their cut of the profits</a>).</p>

<p>Which brings us to the latest manifestation of the Jack Kirby aesthetic in the global popular culture. What can be said about <em>Thor: Ragnarok</em> that hasn’t already been said? It’s being touted as a turning point in superhero movies; the super-comedy writ large. Director Taika Waititi is being hailed as the savior of blockbuster filmmaking, the man who brought the cold imperiousness of the “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2015/6/15/8784353/batman-begins-anniversary-gritty-reboot-hollywood-criticism">gritty reboot</a>” back down to earth.</p>

<p>But the movie, which is part buddy-comedy, part Christopher Guest-style repertory act, only works because it <em>isn’t</em> actually a sharp left turn for the franchise—it works because it’s amplifying elements that have been there all along.</p>

<p>From the very beginning – yes, even the stately Shakespearian debut directed by Kenneth Branagh – the Thor series has essentially been a fish-out-water comedy. Some of the best moments in Marvel’s introductory phase came from the first <em>Thor</em> movie, when he was walking around naked and smashing coffee mugs on diner floors, and likewise from <em>The Avengers</em>, where Chris Hemsworth proved himself to be Robert Downey Jr.’s equal when it comes to comedic timing.</p>

<p>You were always able to tread that line well, Jack. As hyperkinetic and stylized (and revolutionary) as your artwork was, it was always <em>fun</em>. There was something inherently enthusiastic and optimistic about it, even when you were drawing the hellscapes of Apokolips. The costume and set design in <em>Thor: Ragnarok</em> isn’t just inspired by your work—it <em>is</em> your work. Dan Hennah and Mayes C. Rubeo took your drawings and built them in three-dimensions. From the armor worn by The Grandmaster’s palace guards to the slums of Sakaar, it is unmistakably your style. In fact, I can think of no other 20th century artist whose aesthetic is so distinct, whose design is so singular, that their work is so instantly recognizable.</p>

<p>The plot of <em>Thor: Ragnarok</em> is distinctly Kirby-esque, too. Weird, intergalactic, action-packed. There are trans-dimensional portals and gladiatorial spectacles and weird sickle-shaped spaceships and mile-high monolithic statues and strange aliens and psychedelic light shows.</p>

<p>You always understood how to handle the balance between preposterousness and authenticity. Even back in the four-colour days, when you and Lee and Ditko and the others were re-writing the rules of comic books, you knew that there is a necessary interplay between the darkness and the light; one cannot fully exist without the other. Which works particularly well for Thor. Because the premise of the character, by his nature, is completely absurd: a humanoid space alien mistaken for an earthly deity. And, despite our cultural appetites for grey skies and brutal violence, Marvel Studios has been smart enough to keep it more Jack Kirby than Game of Thrones. This film simply doubles down on that investment.</p>

<p>People can celebrate that fact that Taikia Waititi brought a comedy-first sensibility to this film (and, indeed, it’s funny—maybe the funniest movie of the year) but the grand notion of silver age comics that this film indulges in and celebrates – the anything-goes beauty of weird worlds made tangible – is your legacy. After all, the bible from which these myths spring forth was written by you.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Killing Of A Sacred Deer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/11/10/the-killing-of-a-sacred-deer.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheKillingOfASacredDeer" />
    <published>2017-11-10T09:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-10T09:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/11/10/the-killing-of-a-sacred-deer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It makes sense that a film so finely calibrated could pivot on whether a watch strap is made of leather or steel. But it really does—although in ways that are both convoluted and often unsettling.</p>

<p>Every set, every piece of furniture, and yes, every watch strap in <em>The Killing Of A Sacred Deer</em> signifies something essential. The colour palette—crisp whites and pastels for the well-to-do, dull and washed out for the have-nots—is only one of the layers of the production design that underscores the themes director Yorgos Lanthimos is playing with here.</p>

<p>I’m not exactly sure how to describe <em>The Killing Of A Sacred Deer</em>.  Is it a black comedy/satire/harangue that is so fiercely wrought it can make you wince in the middle of a laugh? Or is it simply a mirror reflecting back exactly what it sees in the bougie decline of late stage American capitalism?</p>

<p>Colin Farrell is a cardiologist with a family so surface perfect that initially it feels like a parody. Soon though, that facade is stained by an enigmatic young man who insinuates himself into Farrell’s picture perfect tableaux. After that things take a bit of a turn.</p>

<p>This is a film that requires close watching. So much of the story revolves around Farrell’s relationship to his possessions, and the obsessive attention to the details of his life that signal where exactly he rests on the hierarchical ladder. His car, clothing, office, home, accessories, furniture, the paint on his walls, the colour of his couch, the clothes his wife and children wear, feel as if they were co-ordinated with a singular purpose. All of these talismans of status are important because of what they project to the rest of the world, far more than the material purpose they serve.</p>

<p>That these details are fundamentally more important to Farrell than his actual family may <em>seem</em> like a banal assertion, but only to someone who hasn’t seen the last third of the film. This inversion of priorities and how prevalent that mindset is within a small, but incredibly influential, segment of American society is something Lanthimos dissects with a finely honed scalpel. And it isn’t so much that these are uniformly terrible people—even the children—but that their motivations and calculations are so solipsistic and empty. Not a one of them seems even close to happy but they plod along like automatons, as if they long ago had lost the capacity to make different choices.</p>

<p>It was an interesting choice to lavish so much attention to minutiae in the production design, not just for the visual effect, but because it was important in a much deeper sense. Just watching someone walk into a new room is a surreal experience; you can anticipate its decor because of the unanimity of the film’s overall aesthetic. Which is an echo of Farrell’s own compulsive self-regard when it comes to the front his character conspicuously presents.</p>

<p>What makes this film important, and worth grinding through—and it is a grind, no question—is you and your production team never lose sight of what really matters: that those details have to add up to something other than a brittle, pointless exhibition.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Battle of the Sexes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/11/5/battle-of-the-sexes.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BattleoftheSexes" />
    <published>2017-11-05T01:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-05T01:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/11/5/battle-of-the-sexes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You have to admire someone who knows exactly what they are. Today, most people resist labels and resent being categorized in any way. So when a man just flat out calls himself a racist, a homophobe or a chauvinist (like your character who cheers on fellow chauvinist, tennis champion Bobby Riggs), it’s almost refreshing. We can stop dancing around language and start dealing with the issues head on. Or in this case, head-to-head in front of 90 million people.</p>

<p>It is this public spectacle at the centre of <em>Battle of the Sexes</em> that makes the story so special. Two tennis world champions faced off in a match that was both completely meaningless and symbolically life changing. Women’s lib was peaking in the early 70s, with women burning their bras and demanding equal footing in the world. Billie Jean King suddenly found herself in the middle of it all, begrudgingly accepting a challenge from retired tennis star Riggs to play in a money match that would exploit the zeitgeist and turn the winner a pretty profit. It was a story made for Hollywood from Day 1, so it’s pretty shocking it took 40 years to get it to the big screen.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the film’s politics still resonate decades later. The struggle doesn’t feel quaint in retrospect - but actually wildly progressive and inspiring. Sure, King would probably cower from the mighty swings of today’s female tennis professionals, but the evolution of athletes hasn’t necessarily kept pace with equal rights in general. And in fact, the A-story of <em>Battle of the Sexes</em> is even less about men vs. women as it is straight vs. gay. The closeted relationship King has with her hairdresser is the perfect emotional primer for the story that elevates the stakes in the climactic tennis match to otherwise unreachable heights. Few American athletes have ever had more to gain and/or lose by winning an out-of-competition match.</p>

<p>I was particularly struck by the reactions of people like you in the crowd. It’s easy to side with the women who are cheering on King and hinging unspeakable levels of hope on the result. But it’s the men in the crowd who take advantage of Rigg’s own “playful” use of the term chauvinist (“I’m here to put the show back in chauvinist!”), as well as all the keep-em-in-the-kitchen stereotypes that are Trump-like troubling. Steve Carell may have a much smaller role than Emma Stone in the film, but he brings the perfect amount of charisma and charm to help us see why the press lapped up his media-savvy antics as tongue-in cheek. The problem is, it was less a dog whistle than call-to-arms for otherwise sexist men to flaunt their bigotry, feeling shielded by larger public examples. It is still all too familiar.</p>

<p>If Hillary Clinton had won, the film might have felt like a powerful parallel. Instead, it comes across as a utopian fantasy where guys like you go home with your tail between your legs, instead of resting them on Oval Office furniture. But as escapist fantasy, it’s a hell of a film.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Blade Runner 2049</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/10/17/blade-runner-2049.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BladeRunner2049" />
    <published>2017-10-17T19:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-17T19:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/10/17/blade-runner-2049</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s possible to be too good at your job. In the case of <em>Blade Runner 2049</em> the dystopic grandeur each frame of the film reveals threatens to overwhelm a simple, but powerful, story. On the first viewing, anyway.</p>

<p>Director Denis Villeneuve has smuggled an intimate meditation about a universal desire for family connections, and the cost of the entirely contrived tribal distinctions we all perpetuate, into a vast and complex near future landscape.</p>

<p>That landscape, and its inhabitants, are so precisely and powerfully rendered that it easy to lose the story to a kind of awestruck reverence. Your camera tends to linger on vistas filled with monolithic architecture of desolate beauty. These structures loom up out of the perpetual rain like Lovecraftian ziggurats and this aesthetic undergirds much of the tension between the straightforward narrative and how each individual—no matter how seemingly consequential—is a speck of dust at this scale. It would be almost be distracting if it wasn’t so perfect.</p>

<p>The first <em>Blade Runner</em> was a film whose big themes correlated strongly with it’s visual ambitions. Questions like: what is it to be human? And is that a category that is open to interpretation? <em>Blade Runner 2049—w</em>hile these questions do echo in the background—is centrally concerned with something else.</p>

<p>Ryan Gosling’s K, a new version replicant, is a creature adrift. Like the humans he’s a perfect simulacrum of, once his work is done all he seeks is the same connections his womb born colleagues crave: friends, family, lovers, and a sense of his place in the world. How those basic and universal desires play out, and are realized or denied, is the core of the film.</p>

<p>In the contrast between your masterful depiction of an endlessly sprawling L.A. (with a brief cameo by a dirty-bombed and almost vacant Las Vegas) and the small scale ambitions of the story lies a particular danger. As in the film itself, it is easy to lose track of the little people in these monuments to human failure.</p>

<p>The first time I experienced this film (and that is what it was, an experience—I can’t imagine describing it any other way) I left the theatre wrung dry.  But it wasn’t the exhaustion of one too many roller coaster rides. It was the same feeling you get when you first hear a profound piece of music, or finish a book you know has altered the way you see the world—and, more and more these days, anything you put your hand to.</p>

<p>With <em>Blade Runner 2049</em> there was so much visual information to unpack, and it was so compellingly presented, that I was often pushed as far back in my seat as was possible. As if those few centimetres would allow me to somehow comprehend the scope and decaying beauty of the world unfolding in front of me.</p>

<p>I missed some important character moments in my revery: pivotal pieces of dialogue, small gestures and quiet moments that were nonetheless essential. Given how mesmerizing your compositions are, it’s far too easy to miss the forest for the trees.</p>

<p>Often, when someone says “watch it again” my first thought is “why should I?” After all, if the filmmaker didn’t manage to make clear his intentions the first time around, why should I spend another two plus hours trying to puzzle them out?</p>

<p><em>Blade Runner 2049</em> is an exception. Everything was there, plain as day, the first time through. I simply lacked the processing capacity to take it all in. And if there is one thing I love in any work of creative expression, it is the feeling of being over matched—to know the first time through is just the beginning of a beautiful relationship.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>American Made</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/10/6/American-made.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AmericanMade" />
    <published>2017-10-06T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-06T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/10/6/American-made</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Airlines have long boasted that flying is actually the safest way to travel. But not for people like you.</p>

<p>You’ve worked on what seems to be <em>every single major Hollywood action film</em> of the past three decades: <em>Die Hard, Jurassic Park, Speed, True Lies, Air Force One, Pearl Harbour, Fast &amp; Furious, The Italian Job, Transformers, Star Trek, Batman v Superman</em>—just to name a few.</p>

<p>Seriously, the list of 146 films is unreal. Yet your legacy will forever be tied to one film: <em>American Made</em>, the mid-budget Tom Cruise vehicle about a reckless pilot. A film during which you lost your life in a plane crash.</p>

<p>Irony isn’t the right word. By all accounts, you were a consummate professional, meticulously planning each and every aerial stunt. Bad weather during production appears to be what caused your crash, in which your co-pilot for the film, Carlos Berl, also died. There’s nothing to suggest your love for flying ever led you to willingly put yourself in harm’s way. Certainly not like Barry Seal, the former TWA pilot turned CIA-backed drug/arms runner. Seal’s life seems surreal and wholly unique, even if pieces of it parallel the story of George Jung (who was played by Jonny Depp in <em>Blow</em>). But I’m sure, after having read the script, the story resonated with you more than the big-budget shoot-em-ups you typically worked on.</p>

<p>After all, the way screenwriter Gary Spenelli writes Seal, he’s a fairly sympathetic family man. He just can’t seem to say no to an exciting opportunity. Director Doug Liman doubles down on this easy-breezy attitude by keeping most of the scenes light and never letting the drama weigh down the highs: zipping through the skies with bags full of cash, dodging DEA agents in the air and paramilitary bullets from the ground. Cruise is operating at his most likeable throughout, flashing his big smile without ever coming off as cocky. He is able to convey an everyman’s shock at the opportunities he’s being given, as well as the naivety to never fully accept that he’s in over his head.</p>

<p>The film also does away with any precocious moralizing, which would have been easy with a character who is in bed with the U.S. government and Pablo Escobar at the same time. Instead, the film tries to maintain the same middle ground as Seal himself: recognizing the absurdity of it all without ever fully embracing the darkness.</p>

<p>As a result, though, the story feels a bit too much like we’re following a handsome swashbuckling Forrest Gump through an American history lesson, while the interesting parts are happening on the sideline. It says something about Seal’s role that he only appears in a single episode of <em>Narcos</em>—that’s how much larger and insane the world of South American drug smuggling was in the 80s and 90s (Jung, by comparison, isn’t represented in <em>Narcos</em> at all).</p>

<p>The knowledge that there was a richer world out there (narratively speaking—though, considering Seal’s tens of millions of dollars, in the literal sense, too) hurt the film (for me, at least). It makes <em>American Made</em> feel like a spinoff rather than an essential story. But it was still certainly worth being made. Which is small consolation, I suppose, since no film – and no amount of money – is worth the price you paid.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>It</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/9/25/it.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=It" />
    <published>2017-09-25T08:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-25T08:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/9/25/it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>From the release of <em>It</em>’s first <a href="http://variety.com/2017/film/news/it-trailer-record-views-fate-of-the-furious-1202020299/">record smashing</a> trailer, to its second week at the box office, people just can’t get enough of Pennywise, the dancing clown. <em>It</em> currently sits at 85% on Rotten Tomatoes and 8/10 on IMDB. The sequel was quickly announced (with you at the helm), and fans are already drumming up their fancasts for the eventual adult versions of the Losers Club.</p>

<p>So how did you do it? Which clown god did you sell your soul to in order to find a diamond in the horror genre rough? Did you obsessively hit refresh on YouTube over 37 Million times to rack up the trailer view count? Or did you somehow plan and execute the obscene <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_clown_sightings">clown sighting</a> trend of 2016, like some marketing prodigy?</p>

<p>The reason I ask is because after viewing <em>It,</em> I’m a bit confused by all the hubbub.</p>

<p>I’m not saying <em>It</em> was bad. Not at all. In fact, you accomplished another feat by getting me to park my ass in a movie theatre for a horror movie. I usually avoid the genre, because it absolutely terrifies me. But all the hype that <em>It</em> generated was enough to get me to succumb to peer pressure.</p>

<p>But after my viewing, I couldn’t help but wonder, <em>is that it for It?</em> The reason I say this, and I’m sure you’re keenly aware, <em>It</em> is a by-the-book, conventional horror movie. It follows the standard horror movie format; something creepy terrorizes a group of unsuspecting individuals, a lot of spooky stuff goes down, a legend is uncovered that details what is happening and why, and eventually, the main character(s) confront the ghost/demon/murderer in a climactic battle that usually takes place in a horribly lit room. And of course, the jump scares. Who could forget the jump scares?</p>

<p>Once the rose-coloured glasses come off, <em>It</em> really isn’t that much different than any ol’ horror film. It’s in the same playing field as <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/7/23/the-conjuring.html"><em>The Conjuring</em></a><em>, Insidious,</em> or <em>Mama</em>, the 2013 film which you also directed. In fact, I would go as far as to say it’s <em>less</em> terrifying than any of the films I just mentioned.</p>

<p><em>It</em> ventures dangerously close to comedy with Bill Skarsgard’s over-the-top performance of Pennywise. Couple that with the adorable -- and surprisingly vulgar -- banter between the kids of the Losers Club, <em>It</em> comes off more as a coming-of-age tale with some horror elements, rather than the other way around. Perhaps that teetering balance between horror and comedy is the secret to your success. Because where <em>It</em> fails at being a flat-out horror movie, it flourishes in all other aspects.</p>

<p>One of the biggest complaints about the horror genre from many moviegoers is that outside of the jumps scares, the plot is always a basic attempt at stringing a narrative together and the characters have zero appeal aside from how loud they can scream. In <em>It</em>’s case, the chemistry between the child stars is so captivating, it elevates the film.</p>

<p>You created a steady stream of exhilaration for the audience by never letting up on the adrenaline. We, the viewers, were constantly at a heightened state through either fear or laughter -- and then just when we thought we were comfortable, you added a surprise element of empathy by incorporating something twisted enough to punch us right in the gut, like having to watch one of the young characters grapple with her own domestic horror.</p>

<p>It seems that for a horror movie to be truly successful, critically and financially, it shouldn’t just focus on the emotion of fear but rather, the full spectrum of emotions. It’s a similar approach that <em>Get Out</em> used earlier this year and we all know how well that was received.</p>

<p>I hope you float (pun intended) on the wave of success that is coming your way thanks to <em>It</em>. You really did create a very enjoyable movie-going experience. While <em>It</em> could’ve definitely been scarier, you chose to be clever in your delivery and focused the movie on the characters and plot, effectively building something more memorable and worthy of its hype.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>mother!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/9/12/mother.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=mother!" />
    <published>2017-09-12T13:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/9/12/mother</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Congratulations, motherfucker! You just got the best movie credit of the year.</p>

<p>It was no accident, I‘m sure. Getting to play &quot;Fornicator&quot; in Darren Aronofsky‘s super secretive project <em>Mother!</em> is the kind of wink-and-nudge dream casting that an actor will dine out on for the rest of his life. But you‘re clearly a favourite appearance-maker of the director, having showed up in his first film <em>Pi</em>, and his two most notable features: <em>Requiem for a Dream</em> and <em>Black Swan.</em> You‘re his lucky &quot;fucking&quot; charm, which I have to believe is part of the in-joke of your character name.</p>

<p>In a movie where no character gets an actual name, Fornicator is about as good as any.</p>

<p>It‘s all part of the mystery of <em>Mother!</em>, I suppose. Though after seeing the film, I have to believe that  it had more to do with the bewilderment of how to market this movie rather than preserving any plot secrets.</p>

<p>After all, the first hour (plus) is painfully straight-forward. A woman is working on a home while her husband struggles to write his next project when a stranger drops by and disrupts their (not so) perfect lives. Sure we get some flash frames and cutaways that suggest something supernatural or surreal, but because the film isn‘t paced like a straight-up horror film, any genre indulgence is delayed to the point of feeling like it‘s denying the audience of simple satisfaction. Jennifer Lawrence does a rather remarkable job of keeping the emotions grounded when reality starts to slip, but by the time it happens we feel like we‘ve been pushing off the climax so long that a satisfying release is never going to come.  But it did – at least for me. Even if the pleasure I took felt a little selfish (hey, it happens, right?).</p>

<p>Though I enjoyed the bonkers finale, I may have been distracted by the walkouts I saw – which is not always a sign of failure at a festival as big and demanding as TIFF, but it did seem to reflect a pervasive ennui that permeated a large portion of the middle section of the film. I‘m sure your buddy Darren purposely designed the story as such, like the classic character-based horror films of the 60s and 70s.  In fact, the debt owed to <em>Rosemary‘s Baby</em> is one the <a href="http://birthmoviesdeath.com/2017/08/22/in-which-mother-gets-a-very-familiar-looking-poster">marketing department</a> has at least embraced. But the questions the film raises never feel compelling enough to tease out the answers. Once the film seems to finally operate in full dream logic, the nightmare becomes complete and the film is taken over by manic energy. But until that point, the obsessive close-ups and claustrophobic set-piecing verges on filmed theatre. Not a criticism usually levelled at Aronofsky, I know.</p>

<p>But this is certainly a different film for him, and even more for Lawrence. I have no idea what kind of commercial appeal it will have, but maybe if you get in front of this thing you can help it out. You know what they say – fornicating sells.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Good Time</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/9/6/good-time.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=GoodTime" />
    <published>2017-09-06T08:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-06T08:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/9/6/good-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There are so many ways music can be used in film making. Sometimes it is as a counterpoint to what’s happening on screen—like when a subtle piece of music underpins an otherwise frantic scene. Occasionally it’s diegetic: music that’s organically part of the film, a direct connection between the soundtrack and the narrative. It can also be used as an ironic commentary on a characters behaviour, or a way to lead the audience astray. But music is usually just one of many aspects of any movie going experience. Important, but not necessarily essential.</p>

<p>Then there are times when the music becomes a part of that experience in a much more fundamental way—so much so that if you removed the soundtrack, it would completely change the film.</p>

<p>One good example would be this summer’s <em>Baby Driver</em>. The whole movie is built around the music, diegetic or otherwise. Another example is your film, <em>Good Time</em>. The difference being, while <em>Baby Driver</em> is using music as a kind of organizing principal—each song is used as a template for an action set piece, determining the pace and composition—<em>Good Time</em> is a film where the soundtrack is all about atmosphere. Often piercing and dissonant, other times menacing and anxiety inducing, each piece of music is essential to how the directors, the Safdie brothers, want the audience to experience the scene. There isn’t much subtly involved, but that doesn’t necessarily undercut the effectiveness of the strategy.</p>

<p><em>Good Time</em> feels as if it were a Cassavetes movie written by the Coen Brothers. It is equal parts a sleazy, intimate drama centred on an amateurish but moderately talented conman, and brutally frank commentary on the desperation inherent in living poor in urban America. The whole film is infused with a manic energy that feels low budget and edgy, but the technical aspects (cinematography, sound, lighting) are meticulously executed. Your soundtrack follows suit. It is often invasive and overt but still perfectly calibrated. You managed to successfully parallel the film’s visual aesthetic in a way that complimented what is often an unsettling experience.</p>

<p>What <em>Good Time</em> does very well is tell the story of a low rent conman, Connie Nikas, trying desperately to disentangle his mentally impaired brother, Nick (played with real delicacy by one of the directors, Benny Safdie), from some unpleasant legal problems. That those problems were the result of Connie’s botched robbery scheme is just one of the ways the Safdie’s play with the audience’s sympathies. We follow Connie throughout the film as he digs himself deeper and deeper into trouble of his own creation. And while we do hope for his success, if for no other reason than to see Nick released, his amoral manipulation of everyone who falls within his reach is often repellent.</p>

<p>Connie is an interesting character—an outrageous, if innately talented, liar. Driven by greed, envy, desperation, but also what seems to be a sincere love for his brother, he’s complicated, fascinating, even charming. He’s also short sighted, self-indulgent, and ultimately inept. <em>Good Time</em> succeeds as a depiction of a world that isn’t often portrayed with much precision or accuracy—that of the run of the mill loser. Criminals like Connie are, whatever their natural talents, often not very thoughtful. That fact, combined with a tendency to self-destructiveness and a lack of impulse control, lead them into circumstances that are both tragic and absurd. <em>Good Time</em> traces Connie’s tangle of bad decisions to an end that is weirdly satisfying, even while it is impossible to anticipate.</p>

<p>The soundtrack follows a similar path: loud, abrasive and often off-putting. It is nonetheless true to a film that is difficult to like but still manages to get under your skin. And that’s a pretty neat trick.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Logan Lucky</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/8/22/logan-lucky.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LoganLucky" />
    <published>2017-08-22T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-22T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/8/22/logan-lucky</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The biggest surprise of <em>Logan Lucky</em> was seeing your name at the end. It was strange that I’d never heard of you before now. Female screenwriters so rarely get <em>sole</em>-credit on genre films that it felt significant. The fact that you penned Steven Soderbergh’s return to cinema – a bro-centric heist film, no less – meant I had to look you up. What did I find? Well, it seems you’re in even more exclusive company than I thought: the same ranks as Mary Ann Bernard and Peter Andrews.</p>

<p>You know, Soderbergh’s aliases.</p>

<p>This is unconfirmed, of course. There are rumours that you could also be Soderbergh’s wife, Jules Asner. Or maybe you really <em>do</em> exist, Rachel. But it seems highly unlikely, despite Soderbergh’s cagey protests and subtle <a href="http://ew.com/movies/2017/07/27/logan-lucky-writer-steven-soderbergh/">accusations of sexism</a> for questioning your existence.</p>

<p>Still, I’ll respect that concept and focus on your work – not the person.</p>

<p><em>Logan Lucky</em> is a film about robbing NASCAR but is afraid to push too hard on the gas. Rather, it’s a character piece about a dad trying to make ends meet and maintain a relationship with his daughter. There are no guns, no car chases – no real action to speak of in the “genre” sense of the word. But there are other enjoyable tropes, such as getting the gang together, pulling off the heist, and then a twisty ending that provides an alternate version of what really happened. The earlier elements all work rather well, in large part thanks to some bang-up casting with Channing Tatum, Adam Driver, and Daniel Craig as a bomb specialist named… Joe Bang. His is the kind of character name that reads like a first draft joke, but ends up feeling perfectly fine in a low stakes caper film. The women are used much more sporadically (a little <em>too</em> sporadically, “ma’am”), but include Riley Keough, Katie Holmes and Katherine Waterson. Seth MacFarlane makes a less successful appearance, and Hilary Swank seems game for her limited role, even if it’s a late attempt at larger world building that doesn’t totally pay off. In fact, the entire last third of the film feels far too much like a writer trying to be too clever, without putting our satisfaction (or basic logic) first.</p>

<p>Tricking the audience is nothing new to a Soderbergh film. His <em>Ocean’s 11</em> trilogy is the epitome of fast and loose heist films that tighten up to a stranglehold by the end (to varying degrees of success). Even within <em>Logan Lucky</em>, the redneck robbery is referred to as “Ocean’s 7/11” by the media in a knowing nod. But while the director may be willing to tip his hat in moments like this, he also takes bit too much pleasure in denying us simple facts that don’t add up to a more satisfying mystery.</p>

<p>Sound familiar?</p>

<p>The reality is this: either you’re a welcome addition to an overly homogenous screenwriting demographic, or a lazy misdirect to try and inspire change without being real change. If the answer is anything like the film itself, I’m assuming it’s the latter.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>