<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-07T23:15:37Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Queen of Katwe</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/10/7/queen-of-katwe.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=QueenofKatwe" />
    <published>2016-10-07T19:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-07T19:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/10/7/queen-of-katwe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Queen of Katwe</em> depicts the incredible true story of Phiona Mutesi, a young chess prodigy who rose to international fame through her mastery of the checkered sport, despite being raised in the slums of Katwe, Uganda, </p>

<p>In order to truly capture what life was like for Phiona and her family, your boss and Lead Costume Designer, Mobolaji Dawodu sourced her mother’s closet and the street markets of Uganda to find authentic pieces of fabric for you to work with. Mobolaji set the theme and direction, but your treatment brought it all to life.</p>

<p>Throughout the film, emotions are represented through your wardrobe choices. When we first see Phiona, she is selling corn on the street to support her mom and siblings. Though she is bright and happy - as evidenced by her her gold and green sleeveless sweater - it isn’t until she discovers chess that she sees a life outside of what she’s used to. </p>

<p>Phiona recognizes her potential but is conflicted – should she stay to care for her family and live a life full of hardship, or follow her dreams and leave an old life behind. Her once charismatic demeanour turns sallow. You show us her inner struggle on the outside, via her attire. The greys and paler tones come out, and the only time Phiona wears a loud, warm colour is when she’s in the presence of a chessboard. </p>

<p>Phiona shines when she’s face-to-face with an opponent. When she’s in control of where the pieces fall she’s charming, witty, and decisive. For Phiona, chess isn’t just a game, it’s an act of defiance against the path that’s been predetermined for her. And nothing says defiance like walking into a room full of private school-educated, uniformed snobs while sporting a bright, yellow cardigan and run-down sandals, then landing a checkmate. </p>

<p>When Phiona competes in her native Uganda, your clothing takes a stance against the class structure. Your purposeful mismatching proves a point against those who scoff at the sight of tattered clothes and elbows on the dinner table. It’s a blatant fuck you to the prim and proper clothes that the wealthy take for granted. Yet the same clothing that causes a ruckus in Uganda is used as a symbol for the country once Phiona starts travelling to international competitions.</p>

<p>Once Phiona gains the respect of not only her city, but her country as well, your clothing represents the spirit of a nation. It accompanies her as she dances and parades through the streets after a victory and reflects her newfound optimism. </p>

<p>Phiona lets her chess pieces do the talking, but your wardrobe does the yelling. </p>

<p>You made your style decisions methodically, just like any experienced chess player considers their next set of moves. Your wardrobe spoke volumes when the players were forced to be quiet. But most importantly, you helped tell the story of a remarkable young girl who didn’t let any pieces stand in her way, both in life and sport.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Deepwater Horizon</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/10/6/deepwater-horizon.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=DeepwaterHorizon" />
    <published>2016-10-06T11:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-06T11:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/10/6/deepwater-horizon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Making a big budget movie about the worst mess in U.S. history is risky business. For one, you’re leaving the door wide-open for smart-ass critics to compare one (potential) disaster with another. James Cameron famously tempted that fate before releasing his wildly over-budget<em>Titanic</em>. He, of course, was rewarded both <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/20/titanic-3d.html">critically and commercially</a> for his audacity. <em>Titanic</em>’s fate couldn’t be more different than the event it depicted. </p>

<p><em>Deepwater Horizon</em> will also diverge from its famous oil spill, but in a very different way: history will forget this film, which will quietly disappear without having left much of a mark.</p>

<p>The same obviously can’t be said of the biggest environmental disaster in U.S. history. Back in 2010, it was simply referred to as the “BP oil spill”. Week after week, there seemed to be no end in sight for the environmental catastrophe. Hundreds of millions of gallons of oil blew out from the sea-floor after an off-shore drilling unit exploded, claiming 11 lives. And it’s in this initial fiery chaos that Peter Berg focuses his (obvious) lens.</p>

<p>He leaves it to people like you to clean up his sloppy visual storytelling. Once again we are reminded that, as hard as Berg tries, Michael Bay he is not. </p>

<p>Digging for oil is dirty business. You can indulge that grit by giving your characters a romantic glow amid the mud (Michael Bay’s <em>Armageddon</em>) or cast a cold eye on crude oil for a disturbing, yet equally beautiful effect (P.T. Anderson’s <em>There Will Be Blood</em>). What you should <em>not</em> do is make an already muddy situation worse by obstructing the image in key moments and undercutting human emotion with glaringly obvious visual effects.</p>

<p>Normally, a person like you is hired to cover these seams. But while the film does a workman-like job in its first half by setting the stage and laying down the stakes with simple metaphors, I found myself strangely disengaged when it mattered most. And frankly, it was your fault.</p>

<p>There is a moment of sacrifice when a person falls to their fate from an oil rig. Compare it to the finale of <em>Backdraft</em> – also co-starring Kurt Russel – where the impact of the body hitting the steel beams is visceral. Of course in 1991, that was achieved with real fire and a life-like dummy. In 2016, it’s VFX artists like you that crunch the numbers to produce a similar moment. But in an error as old as computer graphics themselves, the effects in <em>Deepwater Horizon</em> are weightless and emotionally inconsequential. Detrimental, in fact. Especially for a film that’s already treading water. There’s a similar shot in <em>Titanic</em> of a man tumbling off the sinking ship and spinning as he hits a guard rail. It looked mawkishly fake even at the time, but luckily the rest of the drama held that story afloat. </p>

<p>By contrast, there’s a moment in <em>Deepwater Horizon</em> when Russell’s character needs to remove an awfully large shard of glass from his bare foot. That scene provided me with more recoil and emotional investment than anything else in the film. The focus was clean and clear, even if the subject was grisly and disgusting. You may have been equally involved here, in which case congrats. But it’s that principle that was missing from the rest of the film – up to and including the explosion rising up through the oil tower. It’s 2016 – we just can’t accept sloppy effects. Even in a movie that’s all about messiness and sloppy choices.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Denial</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/10/3/denial.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Denial" />
    <published>2016-10-03T05:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-03T05:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/10/3/denial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>When a movie begins with a title card stating “Based On A True Story” it can add an extra dimension to an already complex and difficult task.</p>

<p><em>Denial</em> depicts the 1999 trial involving Holocaust denier David Irving and his libel suit against the well-respected Jewish-American scholar, Deborah Lipstadt. Given the seriousness of the subject matter, and the fact that the trial received widespread media coverage, telling this particular story requires a very delicate touch.</p>

<p>Usually an editor’s sole function is to find a way to shape hundreds of minutes of footage into a coherent and interesting narrative. In some cases there are mitigating factors: if product placement is a concern, screen time for particular actors, a director that won’t budge on certain shots. But for the most part, the job, however complex in execution, is pretty straightforward--to make sure the film makes dramatic sense, moment to moment, scene to scene. Whether or not it accurately depicts “real” events, or even “real” people isn’t much of a concern, as long as the finished product cleaves to the logic of the world the story has created.</p>

<p>When you add “based on a true story” to the mix, though, it can change priorities in the editing room. If there are elements of the original story that are essential but also inherently undramatic, or if there are a large number of primary characters, it can create a tension between pure storytelling and a commitment to accuracy that is often difficult to resolve. Some of these tensions can be blunted by the choices the screenwriters and directors make, but ultimately it falls to the editor to somehow square the circle between dramatic expediencies and faithfulness to the “true story”.</p>

<p>The central thesis of <em>Denial</em> is this: in order to combat someone as factually challenged and without scruples as David Irving, it requires an approach that relies on academic rigour and an argument based on unimpeachable primary documents, rather than appeals to emotion or moral outrage. Essentially it becomes a contest between cold, hard facts and demagogic manipulation of people’s fears and prejudice. </p>

<p>On paper, this sounds like a pretty compelling logline. But <em>Denial</em> is also a fundamentally difficult story to tell in a dramatic way--largely because the events in question occur over a long period of time, and there are numerous moving parts. Maintaining narrative cohesiveness when you have to continually flip from one event to another, and from one character to another, is no easy feat. This is at least part of the reason Rachel Weisz’s central performance as Lipstadt ends up feeling a little thin, since so much time has to be spent elsewhere.</p>

<p>There <em>are</em> films that achieve the kind of balancing act between drama and truth that marks them as superior examples of this kind of storytelling. <em>All The President’s Men</em> and last year’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html"><em>Spotlight</em></a> both manage to thread the needle between a fairly scrupulous adherence to the facts of the case, and sustaining the kind of dramatic tension that can raise a film up beyond a straightforward retelling of historical events. <em>Denial</em> gets halfway there, partly because Tom Wilkinson as Lipstadt’s Barrister manages to create an interesting fulcrum for the rest of the characters, but in general the film fails to maintain the delicate balance necessary.</p>

<p>Where this film truly resonates, and what makes it a worthwhile endeavour, isn’t necessarily located in its specific details. Instead, it is the parallel between Irving and a certain orange haired grifter currently competing for the office of the most powerful human in the world that <em>Denial</em> really hits it’s mark. There is something illuminating in a story that pits an amoral, half-bright social climber, prepared to do or say anything in order to further his own ends, against a group of well-intentioned people that represent a system that requires an adherence to the rule of law and principled behaviour. </p>

<p>If you didn’t quite always manage to pull off the high wire act that this kind of film requires, you still helped create something that is both compelling and timely. <em>Denial</em> is a good, but not great, film that, simply by existing in this particular political climate, reaches beyond the already important subject matter that it seeks to convey.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Miss Peregrine’s Home For Peculiar Children</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/28/miss-peregrines-home-for-peculiar-children.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MissPeregrine’sHomeForPeculiarChildren" />
    <published>2016-09-28T05:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-28T05:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/28/miss-peregrines-home-for-peculiar-children</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>One of the few sensible expectations to have while watching a fantasy movie--with a budget somewhere just shy of 100 million dollars--is that the money will be up on the screen. It should be a given that, even if the film is incoherent, or rests on paper thin characters, it will at least look good. </p>

<p>Unfortunately that is not the case with <em>Miss Peregrine’s Home for Peculiar Children.</em></p>

<p>Concept artists like yourself can be an essential--but often underappreciated--part of any film that leans heavily on its visuals to convey mood, sense of place, and what kind of world the audience is being asked to accept. HR Giger, who was instrumental in creating so many of the singular design elements, including the iconic xenomorph, for Ridley Scott’s <em>Alien,</em> is a good example of how a concept artist can create something that is crucial to the success of a film. Were it not for Giger, <em>Alien</em> wouldn’t have the reputation as the groundbreaking genre film it now enjoys.</p>

<p>Given how workaday and forgettable <em>Miss Peregrine’s Home For Peculiar Children</em> was, especially visually, I think it’s a safe bet that it will never achieve anywhere near that level of acclaim. </p>

<p>Tim Burton is someone who often creates fantasy worlds that are filled with imaginative and memorable characters and settings, so it’s a bit of a surprise that this film is so lacking. In contrast to his other work: movies like <em>Beetlejuice</em> with it’s German Art Deco madness, or <em>Edward Scissorhands</em> and it’s suburban fever dream, <em>Miss Peregrine’s Home For Peculiar Children</em> seems to be the creation of someone whose imaginative powers have failed him. </p>

<p>Aside from the dullness of the conceptual work, this film is also miserably cast. Asa Butterfield is like watching a silhouette perform--it’s a weightless, one dimensional effort without substance or impact, and is so low key that you half expect him to nod off in the middle of any particular scene. Eva Green, as the titular Miss Peregrine, spends most of her time arching eyebrows and attempting to exude a kind of distant competence that comes off more as disinterest in the whole project than anything else. Judi Dench shows up and then disappears just as quickly, leaving me to wonder if something went seriously wrong with the script in the middle of production. And Samuel L. Jackson, while having a couple of moments, seems to be building a second career around playing characters that feel like third hand parodies of capital E-evil Bond villains. The entire film feels half baked, as if the whole crew lost interest mid-way through.</p>

<p>Usually with something like <em>Miss Peregrine’s Home For Peculiar Children</em>--a project that draws upon source material that readily supplies the framework for a fully realized world--there is something to like. And certainly there was the skeleton of a dark fantasy story that promised something much more. But your contribution, along with pretty much everyone else involved in this waste of time and money, seems to have begun and ended at the punch clock.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Magnificent Seven</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/27/the-magnificent-seven.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheMagnificentSeven" />
    <published>2016-09-27T13:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-27T13:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/27/the-magnificent-seven</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My affinity for the western did not come easy. The hokey drawls and racism were off-putting, to say the least. But six years of film theory, and a couple of professors whose unbridled enthusiasm for westerns proved to be infectious changed my mind. My guilty fondness for this genre cemented itself in a days-long marathon of playing Red Dead Redemption to numb the sting of my first layoff. </p>

<p>While the tropes of the western continue to make me a little uncomfortable, I love the landscape of the Wild West, a place where Hollywood keeps returning to work through whatever issues happen to be troubling America at the time. So I was eager to see Antoine Fuqua’s remake of The Magnificent Seven, even though “Justice has a number” is the shittiest tag line I’ve heard in a long time. </p>

<p>While traditional westerns teach us about the collective sins of a society’s past, the revisionist western tries to confront or in some way atone for them. I am a little less forgiving with the latter than the former; if you’re going to re-make a canonic western, there had better be a reason beyond, “We thought it would be fun.” Fuqua has basically made The Magnificent Politically Correct Seven, and that’s about it. Sure, it touches upon the current political climate in the United States, as well as Hollywood’s diversity problem (and will probably fuel a deluge of “Sam Chisholm = Barack Obama” term papers that will make it every film studies professor’s most dreaded release since Fight Club), but it doesn’t do any of these things well enough for me to consider it worthy of the original. </p>

<p>At work, I am surrounded by annoying corporate-speak all day. One of my least favourite terms is ‘colour’; as in, “Can you give me some more colour on that?” What it basically means is, “Why?”, “Explain, please?”, or, “This meeting just passed the 90-minute mark and I still don’t know why the fuck we’re here.” Basically, it’s a plea for detail or clarity. And so, I should now make it clear that I have no issues with your work as a colorist on the film (everything looked wonderful, you did great), I’m just picking on your title because The Magnificent Seven suffers from too many aspects needing “a bit more colour”.</p>

<p>Take the Seven; all terrific actors in their own right, and they have pretty decent chemistry with each other. Their performances ensured I liked them enough to be curious about their back stories, but the script is too weak to give us anything more than diluted facsimiles of scenes from the original film. The dialogue is peppered with some pretty decent one-liners, but I feel like the writers could have given us a bit more on old Jack Horne’s time as an eccentric mountain man, or the origins of the loyal friendship between sharpshooter Robicheaux and knife-wielding Billy. </p>

<p>As much as a remake faces certain challenges (to say nothing of a remake of a remake), there is an opportunity to take advantage of new technologies and techniques, updated tropes, and newer modes of storytelling to make a meaningful reiteration of the original. The Magnificent Seven is gorgeous, the action sequences are engaging enough, and Mauro Fiore’s cinematography pays due respect to Sturges’ original, as well as the genre’s other heavy hitters like Leone and Ford, while creating an aesthetic that is more vibrant and polished than the original. The storytelling is where the film falls short; the narrative is too paint-by-numbers, and in a way, too closely adhered to the original, to distinguish itself as a meaningful revisionist take. </p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, in terms of pure entertainment, The Magnificent Seven delivers. I saw the film in a packed theatre with a highly enthusiastic audience who laughed and gasped right on cue. I enjoyed all the gun slinging and humour, and as I said before, it looks great. But for anyone wanting more than a slick, spur-jangling shoot-em-up, it disappoints - especially when you consider all of the missed opportunities to provide that bit of extra colour. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Storks</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/24/storks.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Storks" />
    <published>2016-09-24T06:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-24T06:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/24/storks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The key to growing a business is recruitment. Without it, the bubble can burst on any industry. Take movies, for example. Ticket prices keep going up because attendance keeps <a href="http://variety.com/2016/film/news/box-office-hits-record-but-frequent-moviegoers-down-1201751770/">going down</a>. As a mode of delivering films, movie theatres are simply becoming old fashioned (you know, like a storks and babies).  So Hollywood is grasping at new survival tactics – usually involving 3-D glasses and shaking seats. But their best option is turning to people like you – headhunters who attract top talent, the right businesses partners, and potential brand ambassadors (aka hardcore fans). None of which, as a strategy, was obvious to me when I sat down to watch <em>Storks</em>. Until the show started, that is. </p>

<p>Before the movie itself, a trailer for Lego Batman was followed by a Lego short film called <em>The Master</em>. In it, the fighting Ninjago characters are constantly crashing through a Lego-fied version of the Warner Animation Group logo. All this heavy branding effort was a not-so-subtle way to queue in movie buffs like me that Christopher Miller and Phil Lord – the do-no-wrong directing duo behind <em>The Lego Movie</em> – are on board for <em>Storks</em> as executive producers. And not just in name – their smart, funny, sassy-but-sweet, fast-paced energy is everywhere in the film.</p>

<p>Starting with the voice talent. Somewhere in the late 90s (probably after Robin Williams played Genie in <em>Aladdin</em>), it became oddly important to cast A-list actors to do the voices of characters that looked nothing like them. Sometimes that marriage works wonders (like the original <em>Shrek</em>), but generally animated films are best served by using the right voices, not the most well-known. The best example here is having the lead female character, Tulip, voiced by Katie Crown – an otherwise unknown actress, but who actually makes her living doing voice-work on animated series’ like “Adventure Time” and “Bob’s Burgers”. Sure, Jennifer Aniston is in <em>Storks</em> as well, but they certainly paid for her name on the poster more than for her unique vocal talents. After all, good recruitment is about getting the right mix of people too.</p>

<p>So what about potential brand ambassadors? Who is this movie for, where storks have updated their business model from delivering babies to delivering mail parcels? It’s a cute concept, and all the marketing focused on big googly baby eyes feels like it’s targeting the mom crowd pretty hard. The set-up hits a certain safe-spot on the family radar that actually gave me the confidence to bring my own three-and-a-half-year-old son to his first-ever big-screen movie experience. He’s still alarmed by <em>any</em> antagonists in a story (including those stupid kitties on “Paw Patrol”), so rescue plots are usually ideal (without scary weather, if possible). In other words, not vetting the film felt like a risk, but one that was rewarded not just for him, but my wife and I. We appreciated some good solid laughs, an emotionally resonant build-up of converging storylines, while he simply was happy with bright colours and popcorn. There’s a heck of a lot more going on here than he was able to comprehend, hence his strangely excited question “Daddy, what happened in that movie?” as soon as we left the theatre.</p>

<p>Still, you’ve found not just one, but two (three, with my wife) more people willing to spread the good word on this film.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Snowden</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/23/snowden.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Snowden" />
    <published>2016-09-23T04:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-23T04:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/23/snowden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Snowden</em> is about a massive data leak. It’s your job is to keep data secure, making you the obvious person to address for a perfectly obvious movie. </p>

<p>It’s this easy access to information about Edward Snowden that makes Oliver Stone’s film such a thankless dramatic effort. Even a casual news observer knows Snowden leaked an unprecedented amount of classified government information to expose the levels of surveillance being wrought upon not just U.S. citizens, but the entire world. Opinions about whether he’s a hero or a traitor are pretty much solidified from there. It’s just the way people process social politics – minds are made up with base level facts.</p>

<p>I was almost guilty of this myself. Not about pre-judging Snowden himself, but the film. Stone’s track record has been abysmal for decades, but as an eternal film optimist, I held out hope. After all, Laura Poitrais’s Oscar-winning documentary on the subject, <em>Citizenfour</em>, was a true artistic and journalistic achievement. So much so that she’s a character in the film, not unlike the way documentary filmmakers Joe Berlinger and Bruce Sinofsky are represented in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/19/devils-knot.html">terrible dramatizations</a> of the West Memphis Three trail. But the step back that the film takes to give us more details about Snowden’s personal life and what he left behind (high-paying job, hot girlfriend, Hawaiian climate), doesn’t raise the stakes – it just adds more detail. And as Snowden himself knew, it’s not the quantity of the data that matters, but the quality. And in the case of the National Security Agency, they collect a shocking abundance of both.</p>

<p>The real issue with this film is a question of tone. While I would at least give Bill Condon an E for effort for trying to <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/22/the-fifth-estate.html">zazz up a very similar story</a> in <em>The Fifth Estate</em> about Julian Assange, <em>Snowden</em> is such a straight-up-the-middle account that it fails to inspire any new feelings at all. It’s not dark enough to be a mood piece, it’s not tight enough to be a thriller, and it’s not romantic enough to lean on the love story. The only real stand-out is the physical likeness that Joseph Gordon-Levitt manages to bring, which isn’t much of a recommendation. I’d prefer the head scratching casting of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/29/steve-jobs.html">Steve Jobs</a> if we at least got a similarly artistic treatment of the narrative. </p>

<p>Instead, the film simply exists, like metadata that isn’t properly analyzed. And this is not bias confirmation.  I was in this situation before – just last week – entering a film where I thought nothing new could be gained by getting a big screen version of a familiar story. But where <em>Sully</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/9/9/sully.html">sticks the landing</a>, <em>Snowden</em> simply malfunctions.  </p>

<p>Control, Alt, Delete.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bridget Jones&#39;s Baby</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/21/bridget-joness-baby.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BridgetJones&#39;sBaby" />
    <published>2016-09-21T10:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-21T10:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/21/bridget-joness-baby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As a woman who is child-free by choice, I doubt our paths will ever cross. Professionally, at least—I decided long ago that my ovaries would just be for show. I suppose I view motherhood the same way I view the <em>Bridget Jones</em> series: some women seem to enjoy it but I just don’t understand what all the fuss is about. </p>

<p>Look, I don’t want to take a big preachy dump all over a woman’s choice to have a baby just because it’s not something that interests me. But watching a movie where the entire premise is predicated on which handsome, wealthy man might be the father of a child being carried by an attractive yet clumsy (always clumsy) and maddeningly indecisive woman was as excruciating to me as fifteen hours of contractions. True, I don’t know what contractions feel like. But if they’re even half as painful to experience as this movie, I have a renewed respect for mothers across the world. </p>

<p>In the third and final (please be final) film based on Helen Fielding’s popular Bridget Jones book series, we find our heroine in need of a good shagging. Sure, her career as a news producer is going well, and she has many strong friendships, but what she really needs is a stiff willy, or better yet, a child to complete her. Her sexual drought comes to an end in one weekend where she ends up in the yurt of Jack, a ruggedly sexy American, and in the arms of her will-they-won’t-they ex, Mark Darcy. When she finds out she’s “up the duff”, she has to tell both men that they might be the father of her baby. </p>

<p>This movie isn’t my cup of tea, but I do appreciate that many people love this character, so it hardly seems fair for me to rip this film to shreds. But it is. Because it’s crap. To my surprise, I actually liked the first film, <em>Bridget Jones Diary</em>, (but not enough to bother watching the second film). In 2001, Bridget was the kind of character we rarely got to see: chubby, unstyled, charmingly insecure, and trying to get her shit together while staring down the business end of 30. Now, she’s a beautiful 43 year old woman dithering <em>yet again</em> over two hot guys who, despite her myriad flaws, think she hung the moon. </p>

<p>I suppose a lot of this film’s appeal is in its heteronormative wish-fulfillment. It’s a retrograde fantasy so rife with stereotypes that I kind of want to join in the fun! Here goes: was this movie focus-grouped by a gaggle of white women in chunky-knit scarves that the studio found sipping pumpkin spice lattes after a particularly intense barre class? Because it’s straight up Basic Bitch porn. Bridget meets Jack (a billionaire, natch) after falling face-first into a mud-pile at a Glastonbury-type festival, where he helps her on with her shoe a la Cinderella, and when Jack and Mark accompany Bridget to pre-natal classes they are presumed to be a same-sex couple with their surrogate (cue the gay jokes!), then Jack shows up to woo Bridget with flowers, dessert, a stuffed animal, and Ikea furniture to assemble together <em>as a couple</em>. And in case you were worried that Bridget found herself in the family way due to unprotected sex, fear not, she merely used faulty eco-friendly vegan condoms! Oh, Bridget! You loveable dipshit, you!</p>

<p>I’m not exactly sure how much responsibility you had in bringing this film to term, but I wish someone would have spoken to the filmmakers about their, ahem, <em>options</em>. Sure, maybe most people will see it as a mildly entertaining couple of hours, but it actually angered me in the same way <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/12/19/grudge-match.html"><em>Grudge Match</em></a> angered me. It left me wondering who exactly these movies are for. Both films celebrate one-dimensional, gender-stereotypes that are borderline harmful when reinforced with such unrepentant, big-budget glee. Poor Patrick Dempsey, whose surfeit of chemistry with Renee Zellweger’s Bridget was matched only by the flimsiness of his character. So much so that I actually had to google his character’s name because I’d forgotten it. This despite the fact that every marketing ad I’ve seen for the film proudly proclaims “Are you Team Jack or Team Darcy?” (because there can only be two choices, between two almost identical upper-class white men). The option that Bridget might raise the child alone (or, <em>gasp</em>, consider an abortion) isn’t even on the table. </p>

<p>The other possible sperm-donor, played by poor Colin Firth, whose expressions range from moderately aggrieved to fifth consecutive day of constipation, was the only character for which I had any sort of passing pity. His sidebar plot involves his character, a human rights lawyer, defending a Pussy Riot-esque protest band. As Bridget watches him from the courtroom gallery and muses “I forgot how hot he was in that wig and gown,” I felt compelled to bare my chest and shout “Free Mark Darcy!” A protest in support of the band erupts, snaring traffic just as Bridget goes into labour, and Jack and Mark take turns carrying her to the hospital. A joke is made of how difficult it was getting to the hospital because of the protest; Mark weakly mutters, “it’s actually quite a significant victory for human rights.” Those damn meddling feminists are always getting in the way of Bridget’s fun! I’d congratulate the writers for their wry humour here but I’m afraid any irony in this film would be just like Bridget’s pregnancy: purely accidental. </p>

<p>You of all people are aware of the kind of complications an older woman can face while pregnant. You’d think after so many times around the block with the same character, the filmmakers would have been able to take the necessary precautions to ensure that this film was as healthy as it could be. Instead they played it safe with banal music choices (<em>We Are Family</em> during the neo-natal class montage—brill!), clunky art direction, and stale dialogue that even Emma Thompson couldn’t save. By the end it wasn’t clear which unfortunate man would be stuck raising this kid with Bridget, and frankly I didn’t care. My one regret is that I didn’t ask for an epidural before this whole bloody mess got started.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Beatles Eight Days a Week: The Touring Years</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/20/the-beatles-eight-days-a-week.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheBeatlesEightDaysaWeek:TheTouringYears" />
    <published>2016-09-20T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-20T06:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/20/the-beatles-eight-days-a-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>So Sir Paul and Sir Ringo decide to make a documentary on The Beatles’  brief but tumultuous touring history. Academy Award-winning director Ron Howard is approached to direct. You get the opportunity to mix the movie’s sound. I can imagine that, like Beatlemania itself, your experience was both exhilarating and overwhelming.</p>

<p>This is the biggest band in the world, after all. </p>

<p>Even 50 years later, the term “bigger than The Beatles” is still purely hyperbolic. So it’s difficult to fathom that there might still be something we don’t know about the band’s meteoric rise to fame. Their story has become so much of what we understand about the Sixties, rock and roll, youth culture, and the shift of the collective consciousness, that it’s almost impossible not to take them for granted. <em>The Beatles Eight Days a Week: The Touring Years</em> filters through this white noise to give context to a phenomenon that all these years later still seems unbelievable. </p>

<p>Through restored footage and new interviews, the documentary pieces together a closer look at the brief time that the band extensively toured. Howard focuses the narrative on the live shows, beginning with performances for their 1962 album <em>Please, Please Me</em>, until their final show at Candlestick Park in San Francisco in 1966. </p>

<p>When it comes to mixing the Beatles live shows, there’s one instrument that matters most: the screaming. The sheer hysteria The Beatles inspired was literally unprecedented, and, we learn, was something “the lads” themselves didn’t quite understand. Even with five decades to reflect on it, the interviews with Paul and Ringo reveal that they are still quite mystified by much of what transpired in the early days. Paul admits that much of their success is due to the vision of their manager, Brian Epstein, which, he says, “was beyond the vision we had of ourselves.” </p>

<p>Howard (and by extension, <em>you</em>) manages to make hearing The Beatles playing live seem revelatory. He doesn’t always show them singing their most popular songs, and he lets the songs play out. It allows us to see just how in sync they were, despite the fact that they could rarely even hear each other. Ringo reveals how he would sometimes have to watch John’s and Paul’s asses shake to know where they were in the song. Throw in the fact that many of the stadiums had no monitors (the sound was played on garbage P.A. speakers), and, as one interviewee suggests (and you might agree), you can truly appreciate just how in tune they were.</p>

<p>As a pretty substantial Beatles fan, I also thought I was in tune with their history. But through the film, I found out that it was law enforcement that urged The Beatles management to hold shows in stadiums – a concept never before imagined. They worried that playing at 8000-seat auditoriums would mean being responsible for the safety of 20,000 more fans outside. Nor did I realize that the Beatles refused to play segregated stadiums in the Southern U.S. It made me respect them even more. </p>

<p>By the end of the film, Howard amplifies the hysterical fervour to match the band’s growing disenchantment with performing live. So when the band finally decides to focus solely on recording, it comes as a relief. Their camaraderie is most evident in the studio, when they’re experimenting with new sounds and new personas. Looking at what is now considered archaic recording equipment, and hearing the first cuts of a song like “Tomorrow Never Knows”, it’s obvious that quitting touring allowed them to make music no one else was making. The changed the way music was played, and then they changed the way music was made.</p>

<p>This doc isn’t pretending to be anything but hagiographic, but despite its obvious fandom, it does a great job of reminding us just how ground breaking and popular the Beatles really were. More so than Elvis, and yes, maybe even Jesus.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sully</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/9/9/sully.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Sully" />
    <published>2016-09-09T03:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-09T03:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/9/9/sully</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My eyes rolled when I heard the “Miracle on the Hudson” was being adapted into a big Hollywood movie. The story of Captain Chesley “Sully” Sullenberger safely landing an aircraft on the Hudson River felt devoid of any drama. And casting Tom Hanks so soon after <em>Captain Phillips</em> seemed lazy. The whole premise lacked invention and creativity, I thought. A movie made from an elementary studio math equation: big star + big news story = big deal. More like “meh, big deal”, right? Why bother recreating something still so fresh in everyone’s memory?</p>

<p>Well, as it turns out, that’s the whole point of <em>Sully</em>. What happens when a mock-up meets reality?</p>

<p>Computer simulations done within a day of the incident showed that despite the dual engine failure Sullenberger claimed to have experienced, he should have been able to safely land the plane at two separate airports only minutes away. And giving the audience this information so early in the film re-orients the entire way we watch events unfold. If the computer mock-ups don’t lie, then where does that leave Sully, the so-called Hero of The Hudson? </p>

<p>As a result, <em>Sully</em> has more drama, tension, and real emotion than it ever could on paper. Getting a movie like this right is kind of like like landing a passenger jet plane on a river: it sounds simple, especially after you know how it turns out, but it takes countless perfectly executed invisible decisions to be successful. Luckily, Clint Eastwood is the Sully of Hollywood directors. He’s infamously relaxed on set. He trusts his team, on camera and off, to deliver their best. He then orchestrates each scene with ease: adding an extra beat to a scene, using the take where the actor fumbles hanging up the phone, repeating key sequences after giving the audience new clues to watch for. His personal touch feels both unperceivable and undeniable. </p>

<p>And it’s these small details that change the way we experience the landing of US Airways Flight 1549 over a taught 95 minutes. Filmed entirely (and almost counter-intuitively) in IMAX, the visuals are clean and simple, but never anything less than utterly engaging. Most of the story is grounded, with only occasional flights of drama (and even fantasy). But never does the film feel like it’s milking a moment, a memory, or an emotion for more than it deserves. </p>

<p>There could be, and probably are, dozens of re-enactments of this incident available to people like you, John. Those who need to study the incident in order to recreate it. But to capture the human experience is something else entirely, and <em>Sully</em> does it with uncommon elegance—even if, at first glance, the numbers don’t add up.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>