<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-25T16:29:51Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Before We Go</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/21/before-we-go.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BeforeWeGo" />
    <published>2015-10-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/21/before-we-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s been a while. About 18 years or so. Hope you’re doing well. I’m happily married, no kids, nice house, great job. Great life, actually. How about you? I’ve often wondered what you’ve been up to. I googled you once, about ten years ago, but came up empty, and I’ve since forgotten your last name. But that one intense and adorably chaste night we spent together is still vivid in my memory. Do you remember it as fondly as I do?</p>

<p>We met-cute at about 2:00 am on a Saturday night in 1997 when you noticed me struggling to escape through a trap door in the basement of the bar where I worked. I was ducking out to avoid a guy I’d been dating; he was incapable of gracefully accepting our break-up. You pulled me out of a literal hole in the wall and recognized me as the bartender who had been shamelessly flirting with you all night. It seemed like fate, so we spent the night wandering the city and falling in the kind of love only early 20-somethings and Hollywood screenwriters believe in (the kind who write movies I usually hate).</p>

<p>As a self-identifying cynic, by-the-numbers romantic movies invariably induce my gag reflex. But my fond memories of our single, cinematic evening together made me fall for the premise of <em>Before We Go</em>. If I hadn’t lived such a similar experience, I’d probably dismiss the film as a blatant rip-off of the <em>Before</em> _Sunrise trilogy, rather than the charming homage I believe first-time director Chris Evans intended it to be. I found myself completely enchanted by the rhythms and complications of two strangers reluctantly falling in love. </p>

<p>When we met we were both 24 years old, and neither of us had been around long enough to have real baggage. But the leads in <em>Before We Go</em> are a bit older and have a lot more to lose, making their night fraught with tension. Nick and Brooke meet as Grand Central Station is closing for the night. Brooke has had her purse stolen, broken her phone, and missed the last train back to Boston. Nick is killing time while he decides whether or not he should attend a wedding reception where he knows his ex will be. Nick offers to help get Brooke back to Boston before 7:00 am, because she has convinced him that her life – and broken marriage – depends on it. While they spend the next several hours trying to get Brooke back home, they bare their souls to one another, and make some serious life decisions in the process. </p>

<p>Let’s face it: if I looked like Rhea Pearlman, you might not have been so eager to pull me out of a beer chute to spend a chilly night wandering through the streets with me. And if you looked like Danny DeVito, I probably would have crawled back in that hole. The plot of <em>Before We Go</em> hinges on the believability of two people being attractive enough to actually fall for each other so quickly. Chris Evans is Captain America and Alice Eve is a petite blue-eyed blonde with girl-next-door written all over her. They’re good-looking, but not in the usual, unbelievable Hollywood way. A lot happens to these two in a scant five hours, but both actors sell the narrative convincingly. You have to really root for these crazy kids in this mixed-up world, or the whole thing doesn’t work, and I <em>wanted</em> to believe that they could fall in love, so the willing suspension of disbelief wasn’t especially hard to muster. Sound familiar?</p>

<p>Evans and Eve are well-paired here, and handle the dialogue-driven film with natural ease and subtlety. Both characters are given equal weight and depth, with neither falling into rom-commy conventions. This makes scenes like the ones where they employ New York City’s dwindling phone booths as “time machines” – where they can talk to their future and past selves – seem more endearing than corny. Evans recognizes that the strength of this film is in the performances, and he doesn’t try to make Manhattan into <em>Manhattan</em>. There are no adoring montages of the city, no unnecessarily complicated shots. This story is about two people, and could have been set anywhere. Like, say Ottawa, in November 1997.</p>

<p>We stayed in contact after you returned home to Toronto. We got back to our regular lives. But after a while it seemed forced, didn’t it? Plans to meet up fell apart—you were busy with school, and I decided to try again with an ex. I think we both knew that wanting to recapture the magic of that one sublime night was futile, and would risk sullying its memory. <em>Before We Go</em> manages to harness that magic and trap it in a bottle at the perfect moment. </p>

<p>I admit, it was difficult for me to approach this film with a critical eye. As much as I’m proud of being able to keep my emotions in check (even, sadly, when it’s to my detriment). Sometimes I can’t help but let reason take the back seat. Nostalgia played a big part of my engagement with <em>Before We Go</em>, but I wasn’t blinded by it. From time to time, letting go of my acerbic tendencies and indulging in my sappy, romantic side pays off. </p>

<p>Thank goodness or I’d still be stuck in that trap door. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/20/pan.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Pan" />
    <published>2015-10-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/20/pan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In all fairness, you can’t defend a choice that was made for you posthumously. Nevertheless,  your involvement with <em>Pan</em>—however tangentially, and seemingly in opposition to what you stood for as an artist—is a metaphor for everything wrong with this ill-conceived mess of a movie.</p>

<p>And that’s a lot.</p>

<p>I had my first misgivings about this wannabe origin story for <em>Peter Pan</em> when, walking into the screening, I noticed the poster proudly proclaiming “<em>From the studio that brought you Harry Potter</em>”. That’s right; Not the director. Not the writer. Not the producer. Hell, not even the generic we’re-out-of-all-the-other-options catch-all, “creators”. When the main driving force behind a film’s creation is the entity responsible for financing, packaging and distributing, and then repackaging and redistributing the product ad nauseam, you know exactly what they’re going to go for: a sure bet.</p>

<p>And in Hollywood, the only sure bet is to copy what has come before. Play things as safe as possible in a desperate attempt to use nostalgia as a business plan. Everything you railed against, Kurt.</p>

<p>What we get is supposedly the untold origin of Peter Pan, because, as the opening voiceover informs us, “Sometimes, to truly understand the end, you must know the beginning.” Right.</p>

<p>I read that as; “Sometimes to create a franchise, we need to make a convoluted mythology that rips off previous, better works in a lazy attempt to reap profit.” Sure, many great works of art have been assembled from the structures and details of what came before. You even said as much about your seminal <em>Smells Like Teen Spirit</em>, claiming it was your attempt to write a Pixies song. You mimicked their style and structure to make your own song. </p>

<p>That worked. This doesn’t.</p>

<p>Let’s break down the aforementioned Harry Potter kinship, shall we? The abandoned child, his horrible upbringing (one could claim this has a Dickens influence to it, but who are we kidding here?), his mysterious “destiny” that will be revealed to us – but not too fast, as there are future films to be made.</p>

<p>In <em>Pan</em>’s one fun bit, the orphanage has secretly been selling boys to the pirates who arrive via flying sailing ships and bungee jump through the roof and steal children right from their beds. It’s an exciting image that also taps into that basic childhood nightmare logic, and is something <em>Pan</em> desperately could have used more of.</p>

<p>The inventiveness mainly stops there, and unfortunately, another main influence for <em>Pan</em> is <em>Star Wars</em>. No, not the good ones. The Prequels. Having died in 1994, you mercifully did not have to watch George Lucas do his best to undo everything audiences loved about his franchise. Yes, <em>Pan</em> introduces all the future major players with the subtlety George Lucas used when Obi-wan Kenobi told Anakin Skywalker, “Someday, you’ll be the death of me.” Even though Hugh Jackman’s Blackbeard is <em>Pan</em>’s central villain, there’s room to force in Captain Hook as a pal Peter makes working in Blackbeard’s mines, searching for <del>unobtainium</del> pixie dust. This version of Hook is a wise-cracking rascal with a heart of gold in the mold of Han Solo wearing an Indiana Jones hat. Apparently, writer Jason Fuches thought Harrison Ford’s IMDB page was enough research to create this character. I suppose that idea’s not bad on paper, but since Garret Hedlund plays Hook with all the charisma of a Jai Courtney, we’ll never know if it could work off the page.</p>

<p>How, you might wonder, did you get mixed up in all of this? For some reason, someone, at some point, thought it would be a great idea to incorporate modern alternative and punk songs as anthems chanted by Blackbeard’s slave army. It’s used as diegetic music <em>within</em> scenes. Whenever Blackbeard makes an entrance, soot-covered children and motley pirates shout in unison “Here we are now, entertain us!”. They also shout out “Hey, ho, let’s go!’, because, yes, The Ramones’ also got sucked into this. How? Good question. My best guess is that while hurriedly gathering the books and DVDs to pilfer for story ideas, your CDs accidentally got mixed in, and whoever received everything just went with it, whether it made sense or not. That theory would at least explain why this conceit is used exactly twice in the movie then abandoned.</p>

<p>Maybe director Joe Wright is to blame. While this is a pretty impersonal piece of filmmaking, the addition of these songs—as badly conceived and executed as their inclusion is—seems born from the kind of out-of-left-field approach that would never make it through a committee-driven process. And apart from you and Joey Ramone, I worry that Wright is the other casualty of <em>Pan.</em> Coming in at just under two hours, things move so fast and make so little sense, it feels like a good hour of story was left on the cutting room floor. Maybe Wright’s vision was bigger and bolder and had more nuance. Maybe he wanted Amanda Seyfried to do more than drop Peter off at the orphanage, or have Cara Delvingne to do more than literally pop her head out of a pool and smile, before swimming away. I could try to list every slapped together element in <em>Pan</em> but the plot is such a mess hurtling towards something, <em>anything</em>, that much of it left my mind as I left the theatre.  </p>

<p>What remains is the little good and much of the bad. Performance-wise, Jackman actually brings a surprising amount of depth to Blackbeard, considering none of it seems to have been into the script. As Tiger Lily, here reimagined as a kind of tribal Princess Leia/Arwen/, the biggest impression Rooney Mara makes is in how out of place she looks in an aboriginal tribe. (Note to the casting department: the “Lily” in Tiger Lily’s name does <em>not</em> stand for “lily white”.)</p>

<p>So that’s what your music is being used for in the absence of your control. While I’m sorry I don’t have better news to report, I though you needed to know. And, if there is any sort of bright side, it might be this: as appropriate as it may have been to comment on how <em>Pan</em> has its way with J. M. Barrie’s original source material, at least no one decided to use “Rape Me”.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Goosebumps</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/19/goosebumps%20copy.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Goosebumps" />
    <published>2015-10-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/19/goosebumps copy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I must confess, you never scared me all that much. By the time I discovered R.L. Stine’s work, I was a little too old for <em>Goosebumps</em> (I was all about <em>Fear Street</em> with its dead cheerleaders and terrorized prom queens ). But I understand that you’re one of Stine’s most memorable monsters, so it’s fitting that you were brought back for a night of mayhem in Rob Letterman’s movie adaptation of the <em>Goosebumps</em> books. </p>

<p>I’ve become pretty wary of these increasingly common pop culture revivals, which is a polite way of saying that every time I hear another thing I loved as a youngster is about to be remade (and likely ruined), I die a little inside (see: <em>Jem</em> <em>&amp; the Holograms</em>). I have to say, though, I was pleasantly surprised by <em>Goosebumps</em>. I enjoyed it way more than I thought I would. </p>

<p>In keeping with Stine-ian prose, “cold is the night” when new kid in town, Zach, must team up with new friends Champ, Hannah, and her dad – acclaimed author and reclusive weirdo, R.L. Stine – to save the town of Madison, Delaware, from an army of monsters and freaks led by you. After being cooped up in musty pages of books for so long, you understandably have some energy to burn, and you do some pretty serious damage. It was fun to put myself in your tiny shoes and think about where I would go if I was suddenly unleashed into the world like that. Truth be told, I’d probably break into a bakery or a knitting store and go nuts—not my proudest realization, but an honest one.  But you choose to besiege a high school dance instead, and that’s fine. You do you. </p>

<p>The plot is simple enough to keep younger audience members engaged, and it’s quite entertaining watching Stine and the kids race to get all you monsters back into your books. The effects team makes you and the other terrors look good, but my quibble is that there are just too many of you. I get that having every single <em>Goosebumps</em> monster come alive is a cool premise, but we don’t get to fully appreciate most of your friends. Other than you, we really only get significant time with the Werewolf of Fever Swamp and a band of alarmingly agressive lawn gnomes. Relegating the rest of the roster of rampaging rogues to blink-and-miss-it cameos will likely disappoint old school fans of the books and give neophytes no frame of reference as to why they’re supposed to be excited to see the evil clown or giant praying mantis. </p>

<p>While Zach and Hannah are obviously the main couple in the film, I thought the Stine/Champ pairing emerged as the real team to root for. Their angry-grown-up/goofy-teen schtick is charming and greatly entertaining. If our childhood pop culture favourites must be resurrected, I can definitely see the two them in their own spin-off, should you decide to come back for some more fun. Just don’t mess with my beloved <em>Fear Street</em> books, that’s all I ask.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hyena Road</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/14/hyena-road.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HyenaRoad" />
    <published>2015-10-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/14/hyena-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There it is Paul—that’s the problem right there. Your fingerprints are all over every single aspect of <em>Hyena Road</em>. Maybe if it were a smaller, less ambitious work—say a TV series about a struggling, small-town playhouse in Midwestern Canada—your omnipresence would have made sense. But this is a big sprawling, multi-faceted story with multiple locations and complex set pieces that never reaches the heights it seeks, which strongly suggests you had one too many balls in the air. The result is a competent movie that never manages to rise above that particularly Canadian metric of “not bad”.</p>

<p>This is a story of the convoluted circle-jerk that inevitably results from western military interventions—specifically, in this case, Afghanistan and Canada’s role there. It is a role that is so ill defined that a simple task like getting the titular Hyena Road completed (a highway that is meant to create a transport link in a highly contested region) becomes a surreal exercise in realpolitik. There are so many splintered factions that simply identifying allies and enemies is like playing darts blindfolded: it’s all a vague hope guided by a desire not to put your friend’s eye out.</p>

<p>There is the requisite interaction between soldiers and civilians, each suspicious of (and misunderstood by) the other. There is also a failed attempt to delineate exactly why these relationships really never evolve, something that seems a promising thread, but is abandoned in the increasingly diffuse second and third act. <em>Hyena Road</em> is a weak echo of films like <em>Zero Dark Thirty</em> or even <em>Black Hawk Down,</em> and is too reliant upon nondescript action sequences that lack the kind of visual creativity that those other films possess—so that <em>Hyena Road</em> ends up, in these big moments, feeling like a B-grade straight to streaming flick.</p>

<p>The performances are capable—with the exception of you and your  enigmatic Afghani counterpart Neamat Arghandabi. You both push too hard in scenes that require a nuance this film often lacks.  Rossif Sutherland (son of the good Donald) makes a strong impression as a Canadian Special Forces member—but he and the rest of the cast are really just fodder for a movie that is singularly on point in its message and yet somehow flabby and remarkably un-agile.</p>

<p>I admire your ambition, Paul, but it has apparently gone unchecked. It is a rare creative force that manages to wear so many hats and pull it off. Maybe it would have been hard to get this film made had you not agreed to take on so much, but ask yourself this: what good is it to create something that is the mere ghost of what it might have been? It seems to me far better to scale down the project to something manageable or conversely to maintain the scale but delegate some of the work to others. The only time it makes sense a person to have so many slashes in your titles is when they produce something really exemplary. See: Kenneth Branagh, Christopher Guest, and Charlie Chaplin.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Martian</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/10/6/the-martian.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheMartian" />
    <published>2015-10-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/10/6/the-martian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’ve ruined duct tape for me, but in the best possible way.</p>

<p>Let’s back up. </p>

<p>When you read the screenplay for the <em>The Martian</em>, did your skin prickle with goose bumps? It’s a movie that, through a series of noisy calamities, builds to near-unbearable levels of stress. A movie replete with hissing airlocks, whirring gizmos, and the beeps and boops of computers operating on a planet prone to loud and ferocious weather. A sound designer’s dream, I imagine. </p>

<p>A dream that you realize with mighty talent.</p>

<p>From the moment astronaut Mark Watney is violently separated from his NASA crewmates during a storm on Mars, you announce yourself. You’re there when the crew, believing Watney dead, blasts away from Mars in a terrifying roar of rockets. You’re there when we return to Watney, wounded, half-buried, suddenly regaining consciousness amid the cacophony of his spacesuit’s many alarms. When he climbs to his feet and staggers towards the crew’s abandoned habitat (or “Hab”), you’re there again in the crush of his boots on the sand, the creak of his stiff spacesuit as he undresses, the squelch of blood and muscle as he fishes a hunk of space-shrapnel from his own guts with a pair of surgical forceps. </p>

<p>Though extraordinarily visceral, these moments of high-octane catastrophe do not represent your most affecting work in the film. Instead, it’s the way you score Watney’s lonely, day-to-day experience—the steady drumbeat of everyday noises in and around the Hab—that gives the film its emotional momentum. </p>

<p>That momentum builds from moment Watney delivers the first of many frank “lay of the land” talks under the guise of a daily video log. Pale, hoarse, barely holding his terror at bay with a steady offensive of sarcasm, Watney breaks down the numbers: thirty days until the Hab reaches its expiration date, three hundred days until he starves to death, and, most significantly, at least four years until a rescue mission can reach him (<em>if</em> he manages to contact earth). It’s a movie based on ruthless math. And it’s a movie in which adrenalin-pumping disaster sequences are separated by plenty of interstitial time—time that Watney must fill with a plebeian cycle of solving problems, coping with boredom (via an obscene amount of disco music), and laboring through daily chores.  </p>

<p>That’s when you do your best work, Oliver. Not in the emergencies, but in the routines. I empathize with Watney most deeply when he lifts a shovelful of dry soil, hauls a wagon with a squeaking wheel, taps a sign into the ground, runs his fingers across a wall dewed with condensation. When he eats, I hear every gluey mastication, am witness to every gulp. When he writes, I hear the scratch of his marker on paper. When he sleeps, I hear his breaths as though he is laying next to me (be still, my heart!). </p>

<p>All of these sounds are part of my boring old life down on boring old earth, and that’s exactly what makes them so poignant. You manage to infuse these ordinary sounds with a sense of unease, of anxious claustrophobia. Watney’s chewing signals the rapid depletion of his food source. When he writes, it is to record the bleak facts of his situation (more ruthless math). Even the chemical makeup of air moving in and out of his lungs intensifies his peril in the Hab’s fragile atmosphere. By hijacking these banalities and using them as signposts in Watney’s terrifying ordeal, you’ve hijacked <em>me</em> as well. You’ve made me more than a passive observer. Not quite a participant in his struggle, but close. Uncomfortably, unforgettably close.</p>

<p>So, the duct tape. </p>

<p>Each time Watney tears a length of it from a roll, that sharp ripping noise, augmented by the hyper-realistic audio immersion of a movie theatre, triggers within me a series of flashbulb memories, like a song I haven’t heard in years. Wrapping a Christmas package, repairing a punctured tent, labeling a Rubbermaid bin: I’ll never do these things again without recalling, in some distracted part of my mind, the contours of Watney’s nightmarish struggle. </p>

<p>You’ve ruined duct tape for me, but in the best possible way. You’ve made it so much more than a benign object—like eating and writing and breathing, your soundscape has raised this element of ordinary life to extraordinary importance.  </p>

<p>That gives me goose bumps, too.</p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong></p>

<p>Megan </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Intern</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/28/the-intern.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheIntern" />
    <published>2015-09-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/28/the-intern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re not just a baked good. You’re so much more.</p>

<p>I should explain: during the filming of the new feel-good clashing-generations comedy <em>The Intern</em>, Anne Hathaway allegedly <em>refused</em> to eat a piece of birthday cake for a scene because it would clash with her vegan diet. As a substitute, you were brought in so that she could continue the scene.</p>

<p>Anyone who has ever tried to ruin their lives by going on a diet understands the determination that is required to see it through—despite all the obstacles that stand in the way. Sure, Anne Hathaway inconvenienced the production of a major motion picture for her diet, but isn’t that in some way commendable? To stick to your goal even if there are negative outcomes? To want something so bad that you’ll do whatever it takes to make it happen?</p>

<p>Don’t you see, pastry? You represent Anne Hathaway’s uncompromising determination. And <em>The Intern</em> is a film <em>all about</em> determination.</p>

<p>Anne plays the founder and CEO of About The Fit, a e-commerce fashion company, which has grown in less than two years to employ over 200 people, and, like most modern female protagonists in these sorts of films, struggles to juggle her work life with her personal life. Why? Because she’s determined to have every aspect of her company match her vision. When the decorative paper in an About The Fit package isn’t up to her standards, she stops in at the distribution warehouse so she can show the workers exactly how she wants it done—then heads to the office to start her day. She’s the sort of woman who knows what she wants (the same way Anne Hathaway knows that she wants <em>you</em>.)</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Increased pressures threaten to break her, investors suggest bringing in an experienced CEO to keep up with increasing customer demand, but she finds solace in an unusual place: her <em>senior</em> intern, played by Robert DeNiro, who ends up in that position through a new community outreach program designed to educate senior citizens on modern life. </p>

<p>Similarly, DeNiro is determined to prove that despite his age, he’s still an asset. He refuses to spend his final stretch of life in an empty home. To him, old age is just an excuse to live young.</p>

<p>With his help, Hathaway is able to deal with the unending heap of shit thrown her way, and leads her company to even greater successes.</p>

<p><em>The Intern</em> plays heavily on the emotional end of the scale. It touches on themes like old age, the still-existent patriarchy, and declining human connection. To be honest, when I saw the trailer, I was convinced that this movie is going to be pretty mediocre, but, to my surprise, it left me feeling a tad bit inspired. </p>

<p>It’s also pretty funny. De Niro and Hathaway have good chemistry, and the tried-but-true comedic interactions between the old, out of touch sage and the tech-savvy Millennials is a great recipe for decent laughs.</p>

<p>Gen X-ers are getting older and Gen Z-ers are making waves. Our world is moving faster and we’re going to need to adapt quicker—and one of the best ways to do that is stick to your guns and order some vegan cake.</p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong></p>

<p>Ankit</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pawn Sacrifice</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/25/pawn-sacrifice.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=PawnSacrifice" />
    <published>2015-09-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/25/pawn-sacrifice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Tricking out a beautiful car out with chrome—its silhouette distorted by superfluous crap—is a sin. Venal perhaps, but still a sin. <em>Pawn Sacrifice</em>, a perfectly good film, is at least partially undermined by distracting technical flourishes—the movie equivalent of pimping out a BMW M4.  </p>

<p>Sometimes beauty, truth and clarity lie in a clean spare line, not a bunch of rococo embellishments. This story—a compelling moment in history when a problematic American wunderkind held the world’s attention as he engaged in a mythic battle with <em>the</em> Russian chess grandmaster—doesn’t need any garnish. Unfortunately your director, Edward Zwick, (<em>Glory, _Last Samurai</em>) is not known for his restraint. Zwick is someone who has never met a dramatic moment he didn’t yearn to heighten with some kind of visual hyperbole. </p>

<p>Art house close ups of a bloodshot eye pulling out to a destroyed hotel room are the kind of nonsense that is simply not required. You could have someone narrate this script in front of a blackboard, pausing occasionally to chalk out a complex chess problem, and it would still be compelling. I was ten years old when this match took place—and only marginally familiar with chess—yet I still remember how this competition held the world’s attention.</p>

<p>In 1972 Russia was still a monstrous shibboleth for most of the West. So the idea of a self-taught Grandmaster from Brooklyn laying waste to the otherwise invincible chess royalty of the Soviet Union made for the kind of copy newspapers and television could only dream of. Everyone started playing chess or at least became involved enough that they could tell you what a rook was and how it moved on the board. It was one of many surrogate wars that the USSR and the West would engage in before the bubble finally popped in the late eighties with the advent of Perestroika and the fall of the Berlin Wall. It was also perfectly cast: the quirky American, Fischer, acerbic and rumpled (and probably already in the throes of some kind of serious psychopathy) versus the robotically cool example of White Russian perfection, Boris Spassky.</p>

<p><em>Pawn Sacrifice</em> works best when it maintains a distance and reads most like a documentary with superb access. This is where I feel you had the most input. The scenes where the camera is quiet and unobtrusive; when there are no animated chess formula leaking from Fischer’s head like ghosts from <em>The Computer Who Wore Tennis Shoes</em>. Scenes like a bar full of people watching closed circuit feeds of two men hunched over a chessboard, the only noise an occasional click of a clock being stopped. This is when the film captures the moment, when it feels like something true.</p>

<p>As far as performances go Liev Schreiber is close to perfect as Spassky. Schreiber’s Russian is superb and adds a tremendous credibility to a restrained performance. Tobey Maguire as Bobby Fischer already looks like he’s on the edge of a nervous breakdown, so he didn’t have far to go. Still, he was perfectly serviceable. The most surprising performance was Peter Sarsgaard as one of Fischer’s handler/minders. For the small amount of screen time he had to work with, Sarsgaard made an outsized impact and was a necessary balance point to Maguire’s manic presence.</p>

<p>The scenes in Reykjavík, where the competition takes place, forces a kind of minimalist visual sensibility—simply by dint of the actual landscapes (both the exteriors and the interior sets)—so it is here that the film leans most heavily on just telling the story. Not co-incidentally it is the strongest part of the film. The third act is tremendous and salvages the film from mediocrity.</p>

<p>Your work on <em>Selma</em> and particularly _A Most Violent Year clearly demonstrate your capacity for an understated aesthetic that privileges coherence over stylistic embellishments. I simply wish that you had managed to leverage a little more of that into this film. There were teasing glimpses of what this film could have been in quieter hands and I wish I had seen more of that and less of the intrusive, showy Zwickisms.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Black Mass</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/23/black-mass.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BlackMass" />
    <published>2015-09-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/23/black-mass</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Both of you have been in the dialect game for a long time. Lots of experience making British actors sound American and American actors sound British. And both of you previously worked with Johnny Depp on the <em>Pirates of the Caribbean</em> films, helping him perfect his boozy, burnt-out, Keith Richards slur. But in the Whitey Bulger biopic <em>Black Mass</em>, you tackle the ever-elusive Boston “Southie” accent. And your actors do an admirable job (or <em>jahb</em>) adding another layer to help the film achieve its high standard of authenticity. And the film <em>is</em> authentic. Almost to a fault.</p>

<p>Early in <em>Black Mass</em>, one of the characters tells us that Southie kids would play “cahps an rahbbehs,” and then grow up to become them. James “Whitey” Bulger is probably the most notorious of them all; as leader of the violent Winter Hill Gang, Bulger and his crew were responsible for running a lucrative and bloody crime racket from the 70s to the late 90s. In 1975, Bulger entered into an unholy alliance with John Connolly, a childhood friend turned FBI agent, and <em>Black Mass</em> documents their mutually-beneficial union from its nascence to its humiliating downfall twenty years later.</p>

<p>Luckily for you, your clients are some of the most talented actors working today: Joel Edgerton, Benedict Cumberbatch, Kevin Bacon, Jesse Plemons, Rory Cochrane, W. Earl Brown, (<em>deep breath</em>), Adam Scott, David Harbour, Corey Stoll, Dakota Johnson, Julianne Nicholson, and, of course, the Master of Disguise himself, Johnny Depp. </p>

<p>All these actors are committed to a veracity that obviously comes from the top down. Director Scott Cooper recreates the world of South Boston in the 70s, and lets them play in it. By doing so, he grounds the film in reality. There is no shaky hand-held camera work, no overly saturated colour correction, no fussy editing. From the cars to the costumes to the coiffes, <em>Black Mass</em> is not a nostalgia trip, it’s a time capsule. </p>

<p>Maybe that’s why at times I felt like I was watching the most expensive <em>America’s Most Wanted</em> re-enactment ever.</p>

<p><em>Black Mass</em> borrows from a lot of other classic American gangster movies, but it lacks an essential element that those other films possess: heart. It’s near impossible to make a memorable gangster movie without glamourizing some aspect of the crime world, and that’s usually part of the appeal. But <em>Black Mass</em> refuses to do so. It doesn’t give us anyone to root for, which makes it difficult to get truly invested in where the characters end up. As good as your coaching was, I always knew I was watching a movie. I didn’t once get lost in the story the way I get lost when I watch other true-crime dramas like <em>Goodfellas</em>, or <em>Casino</em>, or <em>Donnie Brasco</em>. And the reason I enjoy re-watching those films is that, despite their grim subject matter, they all have stand-out moments that excite me—be it dialogue, or music, or slick camera-work. </p>

<p>What <em>Black Mass</em> lacks in big cinematic moments, it makes up for with Depp. Or tries to, at least.</p>

<p>Depp as Bulger is absolutely electric. After adjusting to the fact that he looks like a weird hybrid of his Mad Hatter and Raoul Duke characters, Depp’s portrayal of the charming, psychopathic, egomaniacal crime boss is exactly what we’ve come to expect from him. He’s smooth and scary, and we never know when he’s going to snap. He provides the film with its only real tension. When he isn’t on screen he is missed. </p>

<p>It’s difficult to pinpoint exactly what makes a good crime/gangster movie great. It’s a combination of memorable characters, solid acting, and a thrilling narrative. <em>Black Mass</em> has some of these qualities, but never all of them at the same time. Bulger starts out bad, stays bad. Connolly starts out slimy and gets slimier. Bulger’s homicidal henchmen are only remorseful when they realize the jig is up. The female characters, though exceptionally portrayed, are background nags. Besides Depp, the lone bright spot is the deliciously twitchy cokehead played by Peter Sarsgaard. Or, as Connelly calls him: “a coke-snahtin piece ah shit,” Some might pick at the inconsistencies of a faux-Southie accent, but as a former bartender I can tell you, Sarsgaard’s sweaty, powder-hound paranoia is something I’ve seen too often, and his is the perfect mix of funny and pathetic. </p>

<p>Perhaps it’s because we know the outcome of the story before we even hear the first mutton-chopped bad guy say, “you’re breakin’ my fahckin’ hath!” that it’s difficult to sustain any suspense. Cooper’s reluctance to glorify Bulger is understandable, but the narrative reads like it came from the desk of a true-crime reporter: lots of players, lots of murders, but not a whole lot of thrills. Don’t misunderstand, I applaud your attention to detail. If you’re going to make a movie set in South Boston you have to “go hahd or go home”, or else the locals will take you to task. But by being too married to authenticity, <em>Black Mass</em> fails to be cinematic in the way a classic gangster movie should be. Even Johnny Depp will tell you: a little fugazi goes a long way.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Maze Runner: The Scorch Trials</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/22/maze-runner-the-scorch-trials.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MazeRunner:TheScorchTrials" />
    <published>2015-09-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/22/maze-runner-the-scorch-trials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There isn’t much you can do to save a film if the script is poor—but every once in a while a film will possess qualities that can help mitigate the weakness of the source material. For instance, with an action driven, post-apocalyptic tale like <em>Maze Runner: The Scorch Trials</em> you can hide a lot of bad with inventive production design.</p>

<p>If the visual elements that inform a world are compelling and well executed they can help take the audience’s attention away from gaping plot holes, generally poor performances and a story that loses its way in the second act. And while your production design on <em>Scorch Trials</em> doesn’t raise it above competent it does save it from being a complete waste of time.</p>

<p>Your work on this film—from the creatures that inhabit the burnt out hell hole that Earth has become, to the design of the government’s special forces uniform—was outstanding. It is a difficult thing to create the details of an imagined world, to strike a balance between plausibility while still remaining visually compelling. Somehow you managed to walk that line throughout this otherwise forgettable mess of a film.</p>

<p>In the same way that every clichéd character in this film meanders aimlessly through the umpteen nameless, deserted cities that dot the landscape of this world, the plot follows the same path. There was never any kind of internal logic established that went beyond a kind of Pavlovian response to stimulus. The characters are saved by a mysterious group that is not at all what it seems—so characters flee into <em>The</em> <em>Scorch</em> (a term that rocketed pretty quickly from mildly hyperbolic to annoying by dint of overuse). Characters are threatened by (super creepy and well articulated) mutants—they flee. Characters are also chased by mysterious government agents with opaque motivations—yep, more fleeing. Finally the characters end up at an ostensibly mythic sanctuary and are betrayed by one of their own (which normally would be a spoiler but that piece of plot was so telegraphed, and telegraphed so early, that it was nothing but inevitable—yawn). </p>

<p>This kind of plot can actually work just fine, if it is handled correctly. But since no one in this film is anything other than a ‘character’—who is going to give a damn about what happens to any one of them? That is not only a failure of the script but of performance as well. No one in this film, not even Patricia Clarkson (all hail), gives us anything at all to hang on to. The direction, aside from a couple of lovely images involving characters in silhouettes trudging through the waste, is pedestrian at best. The whole project has the feel of either a paycheck generator or people padding their resumes. It seems that no one is actually engaged with the material beyond a baseline kind of expediency.</p>

<p>Well, almost no one. You managed to bring something to the table, Dan. And all of us who sat through <em>Maze Runner: The Scorch Trials</em> thank you for your effort. The visual landscape you articulated made the unbearable slightly more bearable and gave me something positive to write about instead of simply pouring venom onto the page.</p>

<p>Thanks again.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mistress America</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/9/4/mistress-america.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MistressAmerica" />
    <published>2015-09-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-09-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/9/4/mistress-america</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Mistress America is one of those films that left me grinding my teeth in frustration at the waste of intelligence that, for me, is intrinsic to your work. There is something base in commidifying the banality of your own existence. Moderately clever, over-educated people bereft of any real meaning in their life magicing up this daily theatre of the absurd, mostly in an effort to insulate themselves from existential despair, makes for some pretty shite filmmaking.</p>

<p>Look, it is clear that I’m hostile to your aesthetic sensibilities, making it difficult for me to address this film in a way that isn’t going to reek of contempt. It may be that I’m missing something significant in <em>Mistress America</em>, some subtle nuance that is obvious to others. But to me this film was so utterly tone deaf, so buried in its own navel, that I could not find a moment that redeemed it.</p>

<p>With one exception.</p>

<p>Early in <em>Mistress America</em>—before the descent into a literal farce that occupies the last third of the film—there is a scene where the failed Manic Pixie Dream Girl Brooke (that’s you Greta) and the naïve freshman ingénue Tracy (your soon to be step sister played by Lola Kirke) are having a drink in a dive-y Manhattan bar. A former schoolmate of Brooke’s recognizes her and comes over to the table. Initially Brooke seems delighted, perhaps expecting some sycophantic murmurings. Instead the mood shifts abruptly when Brooke’s former classmate details some particularly cruel behavior she had suffered at Brooke’s hand—behavior that apparently spanned the whole of the former classmate’s high school experience. It is a really lucid and well-articulated scene where Brooke is faced with the distance between her perception of herself and the reality of who she really is.</p>

<p>If the whole film had been in that key this would have been a more interesting experience. Instead that moment and all its implications are disappeared like a mouthy protester in a banana republic—never to be seen again. After that the film descends into a messy parable about the ethics of using the personal experience of others as a career booster for your burgeoning writing career. </p>

<p>Tracy, having been taken under the fluttery and inconstant wing of Brooke, uses the low comedy that she witnesses as a springboard to minor literary success. This, of course, leads to a contrived rift between her and Brooke, who after spending a good two thirds of the film drenched in an endless and very public self-revelation, suddenly takes exception to the details being shared with some first year lit students.</p>

<p>The only other contact Tracy has in New York (she has just arrived as a college freshman) is among the many clichés that dot the landscape of this film—the Woody Allen–esque, bird-necked Lothario, played fitfully by Matthew Shear. There is also the regretful hedge fund manager and his self-admitted golddigger of a wife, as well as the usual assortment of wind up dolls that often populate Baumbach’s films. There isn’t a character in this film that doesn’t scan as a ‘character in a film’. <em>Mistress America</em> rarely escapes from its own cleverness. </p>

<p>Hasn’t this kind of particularly New York-centric dramedy passed its expiration date? <em>Mistress America</em> feels listless and played out, and most of all irrelevant. The performances are both somehow manic and flat and the whole exercise seems small-minded in its obsession with people who can’t decide which of thirty-five different options of ice cream they might choose, especially when so many of their fellow New Yorkers would be happy with any one of those cones.</p>

<p>Or maybe it’s just me.</p>

<p>Nah.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>