<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-19T00:24:47Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2016 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sausage Party</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/17/sausage-party.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SausageParty" />
    <published>2016-08-17T11:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-17T11:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/17/sausage-party</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>This last year or so seems to be a bit of a watershed when it comes to studio films where you feature prominently. First it was <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/hail-caesar.html"><em>Hail Caesar</em></a> (although that was mostly allegorical), followed by the mediocre <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/27/risen.html"><em>Risen</em></a>, and then, finally, the lamentable <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/24/miracles-from-heaven.html"><em>Miracles From Heaven</em></a>. After that I was sure that Hollywood had exhausted the piety circus for at least another quarter.</p>

<p>So imagine my surprise when the single most prominent theme running throughout an otherwise moderately transgressive--and often truly funny--adult cartoon called <em>Sausage Party</em> was how it may be desireable to throw off the shackles inherent in religious faith. In fact, perhaps that liberation was an absolute necessity for any individual to fully actualize themselves, no matter what food group they belong to.</p>

<p>Vague Nietzschean allusions aside, this is a pretty fucking funny film. And I use that swear word carefully because this is some deeply R-rated food porn at times. As well, <em>Sausage Party</em> never shrinks from some imaginative and often disturbing violence--so much so that I’m sure Disney is rolling over in his cryogenic chamber. </p>

<p>The voice work by a talented cast is clever and surprisingly affecting--Danny McBride and Ed Norton being just two examples of any number of noteworthy turns. The production and character design are perfectly modulated and the script hums along nicely. This is definitely a funny and often surprisingly deep piece of entertainment.</p>

<p>But.</p>

<p>Message movies, no matter how cleverly disguised, or even how in tune they may be with my particular sensibilities, are destined to always be less than the sum of their parts. And <em>Sausage Party</em>, for all its impiety and joyous mischief, undercuts itself in a dreary and predictable way. It’s got something to sell: the same way <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/22/tomorrowland.html"><em>Tomorrowland</em></a> did, the same way <em>Risen</em> did, and especially the same way <em>Miracles From Heaven</em> did. All of these films were less about an unfolding narrative, and much more about underlining a worldview.</p>

<p>Stories always suffers when there is an agenda tacked on. It closes potential doors, it removes a sense of chaos and possibility that informs what is so compelling about ‘Once Upon A Time’--which is that you may be familiar with the opening refrain but the joy comes in not necessarily being able to anticipate the resolution.</p>

<p>As much as I enjoyed this film, I wish you had been an absent father--mostly because your omnipresence is, to me at least, more boring than anything else.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Weiner</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/16/weiner.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Weiner" />
    <published>2016-08-16T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-16T07:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/16/weiner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s kinda brilliant that the filmmakers decided to open this doc on disgraced politician Anthony Weiner with one of your lesser known but perfectly apropos quotes - <em>“The name of a man is a numbing blow from which he can never recover.”</em> It could have opened on the quote you’re most famous for - <em>“The medium is the message”</em>. After all, this is the story of a man trying to get a second chance on the national stage and a prime example of how politics in the 21st century are informed by media and technology.  To wit, it is the tale of a once-rising Democrat, whose name is a synonym for <em>penis</em>, brought down by a dick pic. </p>

<p>Is this how you imagined what the web would be when you predicted it back in the Sixties? </p>

<p>Anthony Weiner was a passionate and popular up-and-coming congressman with a bright future ahead of him. His wedding to Huma Abedin, a close advisor to Hillary Clinton, was officiated by none other than Bill Clinton. But in 2011 he admitted to sending sexually explicit photographs and messages to at least six women, and his career in congress ended with his resignation. In 2013, Anthony allowed Elyse Steinberg and his former congressional chief of staff Josh Kriegman to document his run for Mayor of New York City. What was supposed to be a comeback story takes an unexpected turn when news of further sexual transgressions come to light.</p>

<p>Weiner’s meteoric rise and tragic-comic demise are shown in news clips, print headlines, Tweets, late night monologues, and roundtable punditry. The sophomoric, Weiner-pun headlines from the covers of the New York Post scroll across the bottom of the screen like a lurid, cable news crawl. The first obstacle the nascent campaign must hurdle is the media’s incessant rehashing of the scandal, and Weiner’s team is prepared. Huma is supportive but apprehensive. Being an advisor to the most powerful woman in politics is one thing, but being the wife of a disgraced politician hoping for a second chance is a lot to ask. As the campaign rises and falls, it is the moments between Anthony and Huma that are the most fascinating, perhaps because we are rarely invited behind the scenes to be an audience to a scandal taking place in real time. </p>

<p>Kriegman and Steinberg are given an almost inconceivable level of access, but I suppose in this day and age, allowing cameras to film your every move – good, bad, or ugly –for a politician at least, isn’t seen as a sacrifice. It would likely come as no surprise to you, of all people, that today the line between an elected official’s private and public life isn’t just blurred, it’s dotted if it’s even there at all. And we, the public, accept this as business as usual, because it is just that. Business. Weiner is trying to re-launch his brand, but it’s the media who ultimately decide how it will be sold.</p>

<p>As Weiner attempts to steer his campaign back to the issues, we see just how little control he has over his own narrative. And yet, he remains remarkably unfazed, and even sanguine about his part in the process saying, “They love talking about the scandal, but I did the thing, so it’s not their fault they played their role. It’s the frog and the scorpion.” As the second scandal unfolds, and Huma becomes the target of attacks, Weiner doubles down. He lashes out at reporters and strangers on the street alike, and it’s all caught on not just one, but multiple cameras – the press, documentarians, and average Joes with Smartphones. By this time, regardless of how we feel about Weiner, we all just desperately want to move on.</p>

<p>In probably the most effective scene, we see Weiner alone in a television studio being filmed via satellite for an interview with Lawrence O’Donnell whose opening question for the mayoral candidate is, “what’s wrong with you?” The doc flips from both sides of the interview to finally just showing Weiner in the studio literally yelling into a camera in an empty room. The metaphors here are endless. </p>

<p>Part of what makes <em>Weiner</em> so compelling is its prescience. Obviously, the film-makers couldn’t have predicted the rise of Donald Trump – another thin-skinned, media money-maker - as a serious Presidential contender, but they realize how frighteningly powerful the media is at shaping political discourse. Just as they understand the force of name (read: brand) recognition, be it Clinton, Trump, Weiner, or Carlos Danger. Near the end of the campaign Weiner declares, “If I had more time, I could rebound again.” And it’s easy to believe that he might. The unstoppable juggernaut that is the “news cycle” is shown here to be beyond anyone’s control, and just as we are powerless to stop it, we are all complicit in its endless revolution.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jason Bourne</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/11/jason-bourne.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=JasonBourne" />
    <published>2016-08-11T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-11T04:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/11/jason-bourne</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>On a list of exciting (and sometimes dangerous careers) working a Steadicam on a Bourne film would probably rank pretty high. The bragging rights alone, if you happened to survive the shoot, would guarantee you wouldn’t have to buy any drinks for a year. Minimum.</p>

<p><em>“Remember that time I jumped from one building to another, across an alley, through a window, all the while wearing a 200 pound Steadicam rig? Vodka shot please.”</em></p>

<p>Paul Greengrass, The director of two previous Bourne films as well as _Jason Bourne, loves shooting guerilla style. And while his films are filled with quick cuts and often look like they are filmed just with handheld camcorders, Steadicam technology allows Greengrass to create unique action sequences that seem to have their own gravitational field; So instead of simply watching them, it feels like you’re being pulled inside of them.</p>

<p>There is an interesting visual conceit at work in his Bourne films—including this one—that involve the contrast between how serene and conventional the interior shots are (specifically scenes populated by CIA analysts and their superiors) versus how kinetic and disorienting the camerawork is when shooting outdoors, or in less-controlled circumstances. This contrast underlines how bloodless technocrats think and live in a world of <em>real-politik</em>, often untouched by the fallout of their intrigues, while the rest of us (including Jason Bourne) are stuck negotiating the messy, disjointed, and often baffling hurricane of consequences these intrigues cause.</p>

<p>Bourne’s real talent is his ability to operate in this whirlwind with clarity and precision—to see what really matters while filtering out the rest. And to make use of whatever tools that come to hand. My wife Sarah remarked after the screening that one of the things she enjoys most about Jason Bourne is the anticipation of his competence—that it is as much fun waiting for him to put some mundane article to good use (a pen or a towel, just for instance) as it is to actually watch it play out on screen.</p>

<p>These are oddly cerebral films, given how much they utilize stunt work and action sequences to anchor what is essentially one long bout of existential angst. But it is the logistical complexity of these scenes, along with their exquisite technical execution, that raises them above most other films in this genre.</p>

<p><em>Jason Bourne</em> is definitely not for everyone. It requires close attention, and often the audience is required to make leaps, that while clearly delineated, aren’t always overt. There is the occasional moment that seems a little trite, like when a flash drive actually has the word <em>encrypted</em> written on it, but that is likely an attempt to expedite what is often very fast moving exposition.</p>

<p>The last thirty-five minutes of this film must have been strenuous for you and your fellow camerapersons. There is non-stop, on-the-ground motion involving foot chases, crowded hotel lobbies, casino interiors and endless Las Vegas traffic—not to mention an unforgettable, if slightly absurd car chase. </p>

<p><em>Jason Bourne</em> is exactly what you want from one of these films, and if it has any real weakness, it might be just that—there were moments where I felt that maybe the filmmakers had leaned a little too hard on what had come before. But those moments were few and far between. And the amazing work you did is the cornerstone of what was best about <em>Jason Bourne</em>.</p>

<p>So, if we ever happen to meet, the first vodka’s on me.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Suicide Squad</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/10/suicide-squad.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SuicideSquad" />
    <published>2016-08-10T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-10T04:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/10/suicide-squad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re good with secrets, so here’s mine: I really wanted to like <em>Suicide Squad</em>. </p>

<p>Sadly, no matter where on the <a href="">objective</a>/<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong.html">subjective</a> spectrum you might fall, I think most people with eyes and ears and a capacity to think critically – even those like me, who, despite overwhelming evidence to the contrary, were still kind of excited to see it – would agree that it’s pretty terrible.</p>

<p>But I’m more curious to know <em>why</em> it’s so terrible. What happened, in the course of this movie’s development, that turned the end results so lumpy and schizophrenic and abhorrent and sometimes thrilling but mostly confusing and basically one of the strangest and most disturbingly fetishistic major studio releases of the last decade?</p>

<p>Somewhere beneath all the muddy special effects and egregious story inconsistencies, lies the fun, cool, unique film that fans were hoping to see. Every so often, you catch glimpses of it: a clever exchange of dialogue; a moment of genuine surprise; a well-crafted ten-second sequence. But all around those small moments of delight swirls an impenetrable electric garbage-storm. You know, like the impenetrable garbage-storm that our onscreen heroes spend much of their time marching towards. Its purpose is completely unknown – it’s just inexplicably <em>there</em> and serving no function other than to, I guess, look kinda neat.</p>

<p>So, Fedor, as the production assistant who was responsible for controlling the outgoing flow of information from the set – letting slip those blurry photos and gossipy bits that might ignite excitement, suppressing the others – I have to ask: when, exactly, did the cast and crew give up? Because there is a tangible sense that portions of this movie were lovingly crafted. But the stuff around it is so sloppily executed, so tangibly the afterthought of an afterthought of an afterthought, that I can’t bring myself to believe that the people responsible for bringing it to life – yourself included – could possibly think that it’s representative of their best efforts (even though many of the cast members seem far more committed to the material than they have any rational reason to be).</p>

<p>A few years ago, I called <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/15/sabotage.html">David Ayer’s <em>Sabotage</em></a> “sadomasochistic, obscene, hyper-violent, obnoxious, inhumane, dim-witted, turgid, and generally unpleasant.” Those descriptors feel just as true for <em>Suicide Squad</em>, even though this particular expression of Ayer’s militaristic worldview somehow managed to get a PG-13 rating. But it was another  adjective that stuck in my head as I sat through the sound and folly. When I used the term <em>fetishistic</em> earlier, I wasn’t talking about Harley Quinn’s high-cut sequined underpants or The Joker’s predilection for lovingly caressing people’s faces, but rather the film’s creepy pseudo-sexual obsession with firearms. </p>

<p>For a film about people with superpowers – flame projection, crocodile strength, teleportation – a lot of people are carrying guns. And a lot of people get shot. A lot. A <em>lot</em>. The film does its best to mitigate the horror of the high body count by introducing a nonsensical plot element by which the average citizens of Midway City are turned into morphing blob-monsters, giving our anti-heroes plenty of human-shaped (but not quite human) targets to shred with bullets.</p>

<p>But it’s not the actual enactments of that violence that freaked me out; it was the prelude to those moments, in which guns of various types are gazed at and caressed and whispered to and whipped out in heroic slow-motion. We get that now-classic boot-level shot of the shell casings tinkling on the ground. Even the blob-monsters are, for some reason, carrying assault rifles, and exchange fire with our heroes. </p>

<p>These are the “lovingly-crafted” moments of the movie I was referring to above. And maybe they answer my question about how <em>Suicide Squad</em> ended up in such a sad state. Forget the <a href="http://www.ew.com/article/2016/04/11/suicide-squad-reshoots-david-ayer">rumors about reshoots</a>, Jared Leto’s <a href="http://www.mtv.com/news/2913661/suicide-squad-cast-jared-leto-joker/">method madness</a>, or <a href="http://screenrant.com/suicide-squad-reshoots-budget-directors-cut/">studio micro-management</a>—if the premise of the film is indeed build around the vulgar notion that the guys with the bigger guns and better aim are, despite the moral code to which they subscribe, heroes, then maybe there was never any hope. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Star Trek: Beyond</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/3/star-trek-beyond.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StarTrek:Beyond" />
    <published>2016-08-03T11:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-03T11:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/3/star-trek-beyond</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Star Trek has been a pop culture institution for more than fifty years, now. Since its initial television run in 1966, it has been the North Star for legions of nerds and/or geeks. But that love used to come at a cost. For most of that fifty years to admit that you liked Star Trek was akin to claiming comics were a viable art form—more often than not you would be laughed out of the room.</p>

<p>These days, however, the pop culture pyramid has been inverted. Science fiction, comics and fantasy now occupy the apex rather than the dark antechambers. </p>

<p>In short: the inmates are running the asylum. People like Simon Pegg, a prototypical first generation uber-geek, are writing and starring in <em>Star Trek: Beyond</em>. And with that change there has been a reorientation of what a hero can look like. Your turn as Chekov, as well as your work in films like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/4/27/green-room.html"><em>Green Room</em></a>, are just a couple of examples of how significant the shift in cultural preferences has been. Your quiet, almost folksy charm is married to a physical presence that is difficult to categorize, but definitely leans into a skater boi aesthetic, and is an entirely different species than Chris Pine’s James T. Kirk. Chekov is more congenial and team oriented, and as such he’s an overt repudiation to Kirk’s Great Man archetype. </p>

<p>You are a clear marker of the messy evolution propelling big budget filmmakers. They are attempting to come to grips with an audience that simply doesn’t respond to over muscled bellicosity the way it used to. So that an actor like you, who is far more Paul Newman than Matt Damon, becomes the new template. A lot of your appeal comes from your ability to maintain a youthful enthusiasm that is never unwise. It’s a world weariness untouched by cynicism—which could very well be your most compelling attribute.</p>

<p>What is appealing about both your performance and the overall tone of <em>Star Trek: Beyond</em> is how closely they echo certain aspects of the original iteration of Star Trek. Your character Chekov, and the new film itself, are giddily enthusiastic, filled with an optimistic faith in humanity’s ability to overcome any problem if we just work together (and with just the right amount of shirt tearing heroics). It is in this spirit that <em>Star Trek: Beyond</em> is a direct response to the unhappy mess that was <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/16/star-trek-into-darkness.html"><em>Star Trek: Into Darkness</em></a>.</p>

<p>You might have noticed that I’ve avoided mentioning the tragic fact that you will never read this letter. If anything about <em>Star Trek: Beyond</em> sticks with me, it will be that it was your last film. I have followed your career since <em>Terminator: Salvation</em> and genuinely felt like you were an actor who would soon find your niche. You were possessed of that ineffable <em>thing</em> that makes people take notice of you—even in spite of your low key approach. I was truly sad when I heard of your passing.</p>

<p><em>Star Trek: Beyond</em> is a charming—but otherwise forgettable—summer movie. But because it holds your last performance, and because it’s a decent addition to the larger pop culture jigsaw that is the Star Trek franchise, it’s a film that more than justifies its own existence. </p>

<p>Sometimes fun is reason enough.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Nerve</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/8/2/nerve.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Nerve" />
    <published>2016-08-02T06:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-02T06:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/8/2/nerve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>If you’re reading this, you’re committed to having kids soon. As your past self, I assume you’re still worrying about the kind of societal pressures your kids will face once they reach their formidable teenage years. I sure as hell am at age 23 – especially having just walked out of <em>Nerve</em>. </p>

<p>Today, I see the rise of mobile apps like Snapchat and Pokémon Go and witness what adolescents need to be doing in order to fit in. Back when we were in high school, a student wasn’t even spoken to if they didn’t have a shiny flip phone to text all your friends during class; and considering that we didn’t have a phone until grade 12, the first three years of high school were just peachy, weren’t they? That was the extent of what we had to deal with. Today, there are a whole slew of apps that determine how well teens rank in popularity — and what they do on those apps determines the hallway fame they so desperately crave.</p>

<p>That’s the concept behind <em>Nerve</em>, a thriller starring Dave Franco and Emma Roberts. In <em>Nerve</em>, if you don’t remember, teens are flocking towards the latest digital craze, a new app called Nerve that takes truth or dare to a whole other level. In the game Nerve, you decide whether you’re a ‘Watcher’ or a ‘Player’. Watchers set dares for Players to accomplish. If Players successfully complete the dare, they’re rewarded with a cash prize. The tougher the dare, the higher the cash value. </p>

<p>The premise is simple, solid and impactful. <em>Nerve</em>, in my opinion, is 2016’s sleeper hit. </p>

<p><em>Nerve</em> is essentially one giant PSA for teens to stop seeking admiration online, but it tackles the subject in a very subtle manner. <em>Nerve</em> provides suspense, humour, mystery, and entertainment. Rather than pandering to a youthful demographic, like Hillary Clinton trying to ‘Whip’ and ‘Nae Nae’ in what has to be the most cringe-worthy Ellen segment, ever, <em>Nerve</em> sticks to the script and focuses on being a movie first, and a message, second. </p>

<p>A movie that sends a message is one thing, but a movie that provides entertainment and sends a message is a star in my book.</p>

<p>As we progress further into <em>Nerve</em>, we begin to see the dark side of the internet. The side of the internet that feeds off the misery and pain of others. One such moment is when Dave Franco’s character, Ian, is dared to dangle from a construction crane — with one hand. As a human being with pretty stand-up morals, I was very much against Ian going through with the dare, but as a moviegoer, I was on the edge of my seat. The theatre was pin-drop silent during this scene, with the only noises being faint gasps and squirms. </p>

<p>It’s these type of scare tactics that help <em>Nerve</em> get their point across. We’ve all seen the strange and extremely <a href="">dangerous</a> online trends that people participate in to obtain their 15 minutes of internet fame. Dangling off a crane doesn’t seem so out of the ordinary when put into perspective — which is terrifying and thought-provoking. Since we get to know Ian during our time viewing <em>Nerve</em>, the thought of him dying terrifies us, but when we see some teens doing something similar on our Facebook feed, we laugh it off as a bunch of dumb kids doing dumb shit. </p>

<p>Why don’t we have the same breath-held reaction as we did in the theatre? Why are we encouraging their behaviour by sharing the content? Are these kids really stupid or desperate for some type of belonging? </p>

<p><em>Nerve</em> paints an alarming picture of the fate of our world as online trends get more inclusive and sharing our lives through our phones gets more and more normalized. </p>

<p>I know you’re worried about the type of dangers that await your offspring, and truth be told, there isn’t anything you can do to stop it. Every generation will bring new challenges. You will just have to try your best and pray to your Supreme Leader Trump that nobody creates an app like <em>Nerve</em> in real life.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Rashomon Effect</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/27/the-rashomon-effect.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheRashomonEffect" />
    <published>2016-07-27T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-27T06:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/27/the-rashomon-effect</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The Rashomon Effect<br>
<em>The Rashomon effect is contradictory interpretations of the same event by different people. The phrase derives from the film Rashomon, where the accounts of the witnesses, suspects, and victims of a murder and possible rape are all different.</em></p>

<p>Since I have a little bit more to say about <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html">Jared’s piece</a> I’ll start with that, and then I’ll have a run at <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong.html">Christopher’s take</a>.</p>

<p>I find it both fascinating and crazy frustrating that two people can experience the same film in such entirely different ways. And while I certainly think that the circumstances surrounding the experience—the theatre, the individual’s state of mind, beer or no beer, the relative quality of the popcorn—all matter to one degree or the other, I still believe we would have probably ended up in roughly the same place regarding <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/23/de-palma.html"><em>De Palma</em></a>.</p>

<p>One of the reasons for that is pretty obvious. We all live in our own bubbles of consciousness, our own little universe. We see the world from a fundamentally subjective viewpoint that is utterly distinct from any other, so inevitably any common experience—when held up in comparison—will be out of sync.</p>

<p>Given that inevitability, it is kind of wondrous that any of us manage to communicate at all. But we do, and for the most part we find enough common ground that we can share, with varying degrees of coherence, our worlds. Where this all becomes interesting to me is when two interpretations of the same experience vary so completely, especially when the people involved (in this case  and I) share a lot in common.</p>

<p>We’re both white males, both fairly astute, both committed to the idea that film is worth the time and energy to try and appreciate beyond simple consumption, and we both think <a href="">Denis Villeneuve’s</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/10/26/sicario.html"> Sicario</a> is at, or near, the apex of a particular type of filmmaking. We share a common culture and seem to have similar points of reference. But our experience of the same film, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/23/de-palma.html"><em>De Palma</em></a>, couldn’t have been more different.</p>

<p>Some of that difference is baked in, but it is the degree to which we differ that is what I find so fascinating, and is the primary reason why film criticism, or cultural criticism of any stripe, is sometimes so valuable. It is those differences, and how coherently they are expressed, that help bracket a film, that creates a context for others to see what is, or isn’t, intrinsically valuable about a particular work. That we can manage to express our experiences and POV in a way that is comprehensible to others is miracle enough, but to be able to overlay that with an analysis that can sometimes enhance someone else’s experience is really something special.</p>

<p>There are probably as many reasons as there are De Palma films for why we differ so completely in this case, but I think there is one specific difference that is built on a first principle. Our perception of De Palma as both filmmaker and human is diametrically opposed. You see a ‘charismatic guy sitting in a chair’ whereas I see a broken old man. You see ‘an artistic complexity and ambition of vision’ whereas I see a fundamental emptiness of spirit compensated for by technical sleight of hand. And the most baffling of truths in all of this is that I suspect we are both right—as much as that means anything at all.</p>

<p>That is why all this writing and talking and listening and arguing matters. Every time I take on board someone else’s view of a shared experience, my own little universe gets slightly bigger.</p>

<p>Every time I’m required to re-examine and re-evaluate my own experience because someone differs with me, it means I’m less likely to get stuck in the mire of my own neural pathways. And for me that is pretty much what life is—the evolution of your own pocket universe. And what that universe looks like, how fecund or arid it is, comes down to a person’s capacity and willingness to engage with viewpoints that contrast with their own. </p>

<p>Which brings me round to Christopher’s piece and how I think that he is very correctyet , I would add one caveat. Since one of the things about what we do at DCAC is to write to specific cast members, I sometimes find that I’m thinking more about the filmmakers and less about potential audiences when I write. And while I hardly expect what I’m writing to be read by its intended recipient, it stills strikes me as a valuable exercise for one very specific reason. What we do, what all film and culture is really about, is this ceaseless back and forth, this exchange of opinion, knowledge, creativity, criticism and most importantly, our specific experiences interacting with some or all of the above.</p>

<p>So maybe I’m less clear about the boundaries than you are, Christopher, but perhaps that is as much to do with my tendency towards the autodidactic as anything else. What I do agree with is maintaining the balance point between literary onanism and pertinent self-reference (for instance—using terms like onanism). The problem being, even the line between excess and useful is almost entirely arbitrary, and has as much to do with the reader as it does the writer.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, I will never stop being surprised that everyone doesn’t see the world the way I do, but I also will never stop trying to find ways to clearly articulate what it is that I think and feel about the culture I experience. And in the end whether we agree or not is utterly inconsequential, because what matters is that we can manage to express those differences in ways that change the colors in someone else’s world, even just a little bit.</p>

<p>So, thank you both for doing a little bit of painting.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>There Are Two Ways to Judge a Film. And the Other One is Wrong.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ThereAreTwoWaystoJudgeaFilm.AndtheOtherOneisWrong." />
    <published>2016-07-27T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-27T03:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/27/there-are-two-ways-to-watch-a-film-and-the-other-one-is-wrong</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Let’s talk about the nature of criticism and the role of a critic.</p>

<p>There are micro conditions (popcorn quality, sleep deprivation, theatre setting) and macro conditions (time of year, proximity to similar releases) that affect our reaction to a film. We’re human, and reviews shouldn’t be written like a multiple choice exam. But there is a necessary balance between cold-hearted calculations and masturbatory extra-textual analysis. </p>

<p>Our job as critics is not to dive inward and explain why a certain moment at our junior high dance made us feel a certain way about a certain scene. The more you try to decode your subjectivity, the more you abdicate your role as a critic. You become an investigative reporter on your own emotions, and the result (while often pleasant to read) is ultimately only relevant to a single viewing experience. If you’re always interrogating your personal history and circumstances in relation to a film, then you’re still just reacting to films. You’re not being a critic. </p>

<p>No one is asking you to divorce yourself from your subjectivity (<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html">that which makes your perspective unique</a>), but you do have a responsibility to control it. In fact, you <em>have</em> to if you want to build trust with your audience. </p>

<p>There’s a reason professional critics are creatures of routine. They usually sit in the same theatre seats, arrive at approximately the same time before a screening, and get used to the hallow of empty press screenings or the over-enthused energy of advance public screenings. Like a professional athlete, you need to learn how to tune out as many distractions as possible. And the more you’re able to do that without losing your talent and energy, the more you become a star. Everything else is bush league.</p>

<p>We’ve all seen YouTube videos of dazzling plays by junior athletes, or marveled at impossible trick shots. The same can be said about amateur critics who give blistering sarcastic reviews or blow up with emotion praising a new franchise film that gave them a reason to live again. But professionals provide us something else. The roll of the critic is to stick handle personal emotions with finesse and beauty, without ever forgetting that there is a goal in mind. The audience wants to walk away knowing the score – otherwise it feels like watching a skills competition or backyard practice.</p>

<p>In that spirit, major film festivals and the awards season are akin to the playoffs. The stakes are high and pressure is ever-present. Everyone is prone to over-praising certain moments or pilling on the under-performers. So should a critic’s job be to judge every film by these extra-textual conditions? Are those the critics you trust when trying to decide where to spend your time and money as an audience member? If a bad burrito gave a blogger indigestion before a screening, is it your responsibility as a reader to separate out that stink from his review?</p>

<p>The best critics of our time understand how to make an experience relatable to an audience. They look at art and engage a special set of skills to blend formal analysis with personal context. And the ones we dismiss outright are usually the ones we know can’t trust their own reactions because they are too easily influenced by circumstance. Their contribution to the larger cultural discussion becomes muted, and even less beneficial over time.</p>

<p>All this to say, I still can’t decide if <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/6/23/de-palma.html">I want to watch the De Palma</a> documentary.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lights Out</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/26/lights-out.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LightsOut" />
    <published>2016-07-26T19:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T19:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/26/lights-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Lights Out</em> is adapted from a well-regarded short film of the same name. </p>

<p>…and in that statement lies the central difficulty that plagues this inconsistent, only occasionally interesting film: how do you manage to expand a perfect little three minute short into a feature length film.</p>

<p>In some ways you succeeded. There is some real depth of character here, with a couple of performances that hint at a rich backstory. However, what you didn’t manage to develop—and this is crucial to a film that mixes the supernatural with the mundane—is a compelling mythology.</p>

<p>Effective horror depends upon creating a world that allows and encourages the suspension of disbelief. For a film to really crawl into your head, it must convince the you that the monster, whether it’s a relentless xenomorph, a young child inhabited by a devil, a pagan harridan preying upon an isolated New England family, or even a robotic assassin, is grounded in a reality that is credible in the context of the central concept. </p>

<p>To achieve this without bogging the film down in endless, dry exposition is difficult. In <em>Lights Out</em> you manage, for the most part, to avoid the dreary exposition. But you didn’t manage to create a mythology that felt like anything other than a cut and paste horror franchise origin story. Your monster had no depth, and because of that everything else felt kind of weightless. </p>

<p>Often the most tragic element (and therefore most compelling) of horror films is how the creature came into being, but if you fail to convey that in a plausible way, it undermines what gives these kinds of film their visceral power. One of the better examples of this is <em>Ringu</em>, a Japanese horror film from 1998 (a film which <em>Lights Out</em> shares more than a little DNA with, especially visually). In <em>Ringu</em> we’re given evocative hints about how the demonic apparition came to be, and moreover we are led to feel more than a little compassion for the creature. This doesn’t happen with the fumbling and perfunctory attempts that <em>Lights Out</em> makes at creating a similar mythos.</p>

<p>There are some effective visual conceits throughout <em>Lights Out</em> that involve light and the absence of it, but too often the story seems pushed into corners to accommodate these sequences. And while the performances range from solid to exceptional (Maria Bello’s interpretation of a mentally disturbed mother is unsettling in its authenticity) the contrast between them and the cobbled together feeling of the creature’s backstory only serves to highlight the film’s central weakness.</p>

<p>Where <em>Lights Out</em> works best is in set pieces common to this genre. There are a couple of scenes involving Maria Bello and her young son, as well as one other unseen participant that are masterfully blocked to maximize tension. In these moments <em>Lights Out</em> creates a sense of dread that is not just about the shock of the reveal, but also about how something in the dark can be whispering your death into the ear of someone who you expect to protect and nurture you.</p>

<p>If the whole film had lived more fully in these moments, if you had managed to ground something fantastic in something that felt convincing, <em>Lights Out</em> would have been something more than an occasionally watchable genre film. </p>

<p>Horseshoes and hand grenades.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My De Palma is Better Than Your De Palma</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=MyDePalmaisBetterThanYourDePalma" />
    <published>2016-07-26T12:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T12:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2016/7/26/my-de-palma-is-better-than-your-de-palma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>This is a thing I’ve long wondered about criticism in general and film criticism in particular: how can one disassociate the experience of art with the object of art itself? </p>

<p>No one reads a book or listens to music or watches a film in a total vacuum of objective critical focus. These are entertainments, and the whole notion of entertainment is to distract or edify or otherwise conjure good feelings inside one’s brain and/or heart. A book that you read on a beach in Mexico during a much-needed vacation from the crushing responsibilities of your professional life is experienced in a very different way than the book you read in fifteen-minute iterations over the course of a month on the bus that carries you each day to and from the crushing responsibilities of that professional life. A song that you first hear faintly playing in the background at a friend’s barbecue certainly affects you in a different way than the song that was playing at your junior high mixer when you looked across the gymnasium and saw Jessica Harbicht slow-dancing with Eric Forbes and <em>his hands</em> were <em>in her back pockets</em>! </p>

<p>And films. Films are the worst. Particularly when you see them in theaters. Because orbiting around the theater experience are numerous considerations: arrangements to be made (with friends, Tinder dates, babysitters); snacks (salty, sweet, unhealthy, <em>extremely</em> unhealthy); and, worst/best of all, other people sitting around you, each having their own unique moviegoing experience. </p>

<p>We like to think, as aficionados, that our arcane knowledge trumps our subjectivity—that somehow our understanding of, say, Auteur Theory or Apparatus Theory, or our devotion to Pauline Kael or Andrew Sarris, colours our ability to rationally judge an experience more than, say, whether you were able to time your arrival at the front of the concession to coincide with a freshly-popped batch of popcorn, or whether you got stuck with one of those limp three-quarters-full bags that has been sitting under a heat lamp for twenty minutes and turns out to be, once you dig to deeper strata, mostly composed of broken, burnt bits scraped from the bottom of the machine hours earlier. I can’t understand how a person can <em>honestly</em> say that the middle act of <em>Interstellar</em> is too self-serious and meandering when there’s a chance they might have been eating a bag of popcorn like that.</p>

<p>So what can I tell you, Tim, of my experience watching Noah Baumbach and Jake Paltrow’s documentary, <em>De Palma</em>, that isn’t deeply influenced by the physical conditions of my immediate environment and precise circumstances of my life in that particular moment of time? </p>

<p>I arrived at the VanCity Theater in Vancouver in a state of existential unease. The kind that is unique to business travel, wherein one is simultaneously relieved to be away from the routine of the 9-to-5 workday – the small talk with colleagues, the big talk with bosses – and also perturbed by the uncertainties of the foreign workday that awaits: the new people to make small talk with, the big talk one must inevitably engage in to justify the cost of cross-continent plane fare and deluxe accommodation. Not to mention the part where one misses one’s family and resents being taken away from them, yet simultaneously feels guiltily glad to be away from them and have a bit of freedom to, say, eat an entire pizza for dinner and then go to a movie alone.</p>

<p>The VanCity Theater is an exceptional little place. It’s not one of those old repertory cinemas with an ornate marquee, columns and lintels, velvet curtains and vintage, musty odors. They <em>do</em> have a little exterior ticket window, and the interior is laid out like the lobby of a hip hotel, all plain white walls, tall windows, café tables and couches. I arrived early enough to buy a beer and a package of licorice and lounge around for a while. The others waiting in the lobby with me were so typical of the demographic you might imagine to be loitering in the lobby of a nifty modern theater in Vancouver that it seems somehow cruel to describe them in further detail other than to say they were wealthy and middle-aged and predominantly white.  </p>

<p>When the doors eventually opened, we poured in and selected our seats a respectful distance from one another, passing the last few minutes before showtime watching the screen upon which an upcoming retrospective on mid-century Cuban cinema was being promoted. The place smelled like a classroom. The seats were soft and deep and ergonomically supportive. My cold beer sat sweating in the cupholder, waiting. This, the beginning of things. </p>

<p>I was overcome with such a sense of peace and excitement in that moment of prologue that I felt it physically; like there was a nozzle in my chest and someone had attached a hose and released into my body a hissing blast of ice-cold helium. The iris closed and blacked out the whole complicated fractal spread of my life – the myriad responsibilities both professional and personal and the myriad fears and anxieties attached to each of them – and I was <em>there</em>, in the theater, <em>present in the cosmic moment</em> in that Zen Buddhist way that self-help books about mindfulness try (and fail) to teach you how to conjure at will. </p>

<p>So, Tim, here’s the essential question I want to ask you:</p>

<p>Was <em>De Palma</em> a sublime moviegoing experience because it was a terrifically constructed and materially fascinating film which in its deceptive simplicity – basically just a single-take of a charismatic guy sitting in a chair in what appears to be his dining room, chatting unreservedly about his long and controversial career – is able to convey an artistic complexity and ambition of vision that on the surface of Brian De Palma’s <em>actual</em> films is difficult to identify (and maybe, in some cases, completely invisible)? </p>

<p>Or was the sublimity I experienced an effect of my mood, and of my physiological reaction to the hoppy IPA and perfectly supple licorice whips and the library-like quiet of the lobby and my desperate need, that particular evening, to remove myself from the world?</p>

<p>What we often pretend at, in criticism, is that we are not people, but rather these free-floating consciousnesses—bodiless intellectual machines that can process the pure data of a Thing and output an absolute empirical answer about whether or not that Thing sucks or is awesome or is just kinda okay. But movies – even analytical documentaries like this – are not expressions of pure intellectual substance. And people – even knowledgeable, tasteful people like me (self-proclaimed) – have memories and desires and are subject to unknowable subconscious prejudices. </p>

<p>The answer to the question I’ve asked above (which I’ll admit I don’t know) probably goes a long way to explaining my <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/3/iron-man-3.html">own</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/8/thor-the-dark-world.html">curious</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/30/x-men-days-of-future-past.html">reaction</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/7/27/the-dark-knight-rises.html">to</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/18/captain-america-civil-war.html">superhero</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html">movies</a>, as well as the dissonance many critics feel between their immediate instinctive response to a film and the broadening (or shrinking) of perspective they experience after the passing of a few days or weeks or even years (after that time has passed, they must reconcile their memories of that film with their experience of seeing it, which has been amplified or shrunken by their autobiographical memory). </p>

<p>When the end of the year arrives and we start compiling our lists of the best films of the year, <em>De Palma</em> will be at the top of mine. Perhaps by then I may have a sense that it wasn’t <em>objectively</em> the best motion picture released in the last 12 months. But our favorite things are never objective. They <em>belong</em> to us. We possess them, and we do so because they are meaningful beyond the simple diegetic expression of what we have seen onscreen and heard on the soundtrack. Our favorite movies mean something—not just because they are good, but because, in some way, they made our lives good, too.</p>

<p>For those two hours in Vancouver, at a time when I desperately needed it, <em>De Palma</em> made my life better. Which, on its own, is no criteria by which anyone should decide to rush out and see it. But is reason enough for me to judge it, empirically, unfairly, but totally accurately, a five-star film. </p>

<p>For whatever that’s worth. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>