<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-06T15:52:26Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Spectre</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/6/spectre.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Spectre" />
    <published>2015-11-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/6/spectre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Spoilers Throughout</em></p>

<p>You and I are the same age James (at least your movie incarnation) both being born in the black and white world of 1962. That you—or at least a very specific iteration of you—died so early seems inevitable. That I lived to see it is just disappointing</p>

<p><em>Spectre</em> is an unintentionally apt title for this film James, since you are now a ghost of what you once were—and a pitiful, declawed ghost at that. The brutish, unmannered pig we were introduced to in <em>Casino Royale</em> has evolved into a character that is close to indistinguishable from some overwrought Roger Moore/Pierce Brosnan hybrid. Sans the invisible car, thankfully. Although we do get the front half of a plane skiing down a hill.</p>

<p>Jesus.</p>

<p>There were hints of this in <em>Skyfall—</em>intimations of a return to the smarmy, ludicrously heightened Bond. The old Aston Martin, the return of a male M, Moneypenny back in the office. I had hoped those moments were just a bit of fan service, a bump in the road before we got back to what makes your character so compelling: the fact that you are a blunt instrument of realpolitik; the ugly, twisted tip of the spear.</p>

<p>Instead, in this new installment, over the course of one hundred and forty eight minutes, you are utterly de-balled. The film begins well enough, with an effectively tense and well-choreographed opening sequence. Superb really. But at the very end of that sequence something occurred that made me cringe—and that small moment made it clear that Bond was back. But it was the small b-Bond, with the dad jokes and the annoying visual gags, not the Bond that you actually believed might be worthy of a double O designation.</p>

<p>And here’s the thing: the world has moved on. The character you were initially modeled on was repugnant. Ian Fleming’s Bond was a racist homophobe who couldn’t comprehend the term cultural sensitivity, let alone practice it. He was the epitome of a kind of colonialism that was, and is, completely toxic. The fact that the filmmakers choose to move you along with the world may have been expedient, but it destroyed the very thing that made you such a durable and interesting character. </p>

<p>That Bond was also someone who would much rather die than evolve. He smoked seventy cigarettes a day and drank like a fish. Jittery and bleak-minded he epitomized a life that absolutely precluded dying old and in bed. He was a spy with a license to kill, and he enjoyed the shit out of that prerogative.  </p>

<p>That Bond was a nasty dinosaur, a man literally out of time, and by far the most interesting incarnation by any standard. The man who, bare-handed, beat another man to death in <em>Casino Royale</em>—in black and white no less—has now given way to a man who throws his weapon of choice aside in order to ride off into the sunset with his girlfriend.</p>

<p>For you to exist in any meaningful way James, you have to contrast with your environment—you have to be the antithesis of a chameleon. For you, to <em>adapt</em> is to <em>die</em>. And if you continue down this road, it will be a slow, undignified expiration.</p>

<p>A <em>Spectre</em> of your former self indeed.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Warrior</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2012/2/24/warrior.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Warrior" />
    <published>2012-02-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2012/2/24/warrior</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I think you&#39;ll agree,there&#39;s one thing sports movies often have trouble getting right, particularly those that aspire to verisimilitude: the voice of the broadcaster. I&#39;m talking about the announcers, the color commentators, the play-by-play men. The guys who describe, in the most melodramatic, bombastic manner possible, exactly what is happening right in front of your eyes.</p>

<p>The drama of sports can be measured in two equal parts: the sudden occurrence of something unexpected, and how that unexpected moment is called. Watch the 1980 Olympic hockey semi-finals or George Foreman&#39;s surprise knockdown of Joe Frazier with the audio turned off; it&#39;s certainly a different experience. Perhaps no less significant, athletically, but palpably less thrilling. Al Michaels made a career out of his incredulous rhetorical question, and Howard Cosell&#39;s breathless bellowing has probably been recorded on a wax disc sent into deep space as a message of our cultural complexity to alien civilizations.</p>

<p>What I&#39;m saying is: play-by-play is important. It has much the same role in sports broadcasting as a musical score does in film: to amplify, emotionally, the action taking place on screen. And so, in a way, the play-by-play in a film is doubly important: it scores a scene, but mustn&#39;t obscure the emotion; it describes the action, but mustn&#39;t subvert it.</p>

<p>And that, Bryan, is where you come in.</p>

<p>I&#39;m curious to know what you thought of the script when you saw it. Because Warrior is an interesting specimen. At times it follows by rote the classic framework of an underdog sports story (the training montages, the fighting-through-the-tournament montages, the supporting characters gathered around televisions montages), and, at others, casts them aside completely (the opening ten minutes is a restrained, intense conversation that seems like something lifted from one of Mike Leigh&#39;s darker efforts). In telling the tale of two pugilistic brothers and their reformed-alcoholic father, the movie takes unabashed pride in its grittiness and realism - how else to explain the way the camera, in jittery close-up, lingers adoringly over every crag and fissure of Nolte&#39;s face - yet moves, in its third act, to Atlantic City, where our down-to-earth trio, until now seen only jogging the concrete-gray streets of Philadelphia or teaching physics in beige suburban classrooms, are drawn into a neon-bright international gladiator tournament that seems a contrivance worthy of a Bruce Lee movie.</p>

<p>It&#39;s here, as the action builds to the implausible, inevitable, ineffable confrontation, that Warrior feels in danger of slipping into absurdity. At any moment, a false note threatens to collapse the carefully crafted mood. This is where you showed up, Bryan, and I think you deserve a little credit for keeping the things on the up-and-up.</p>

<p>I totally recognized you right away. You had some pretty memorable cameos in Old School and The Hangover, and I&#39;ll admit, under duress, to being an aficionado of MadTV when it first arrived on the scene as the profane, frat-boy younger sibling of Saturday Night Live and alt-nerdy Kids in the Hall. In the credits, you&#39;re listed as playing yourself, but you&#39;re playing yourself as a fight broadcaster, and I wonder if that made the performance more difficult for you, particularly since you don&#39;t seem to have any experience in sports broadcasting. But, like the best play-by-play men, you (alongside author Sam Sheridan) call the fights with just the right mix of sympathy and self-consciousness, which captures perfectly the bravado and boyish enthusiasm inherent in MMA culture.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve read other reviewers complain about your hyperactive, hyperbolic commentary--but I think that&#39;s precisely what makes it work. As a sport still in its infancy, MMA broadcasts are in their infancy, too, and despite the massive numbers UFC events pull in on pay-per-view, they lack the polish that most networks bring to big sporting events. Think about it: there are no legacy broadcasters. No Costas&#39; or Bermans&#39; or Ron MacLeans&#39;. Who are you supposed to emulate? Joe Rogan?</p>

<p>Nonetheless, you&#39;re able to capture that intangible quality of cockiness that is so often used as mortar to fill in the seams of not quite knowing everything. Hyperbole is the whole point. Editorializing is the whole point. You don&#39;t know what these two brothers have been through, but we (the audience) do, and this secret-sharing amplifies our affection for them.</p>

<p>Warrior isn&#39;t necessarily a film that seeks to immerse the viewer in the experience of being a fighter inside the ring - the camera often hovers at a remove on the far side of the chain-link cage - but it does strive to keep things real.</p>

<p>Real brothers with real problems. And you, my friend, kept it realer than most.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>