<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-30T11:33:37Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>C. Redmond&#39;s Top Films of 2015</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/30/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2015.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=C.Redmond&#39;sTopFilmsof2015" />
    <published>2015-12-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/30/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Dear Readers,</p>

<p>We gave up on trying to create a single year-end Top 10 on Dear Cast and Crew long ago, and good riddance. Critics secretly love these year-end assessments, as reductive as they might be. Ranking and categorizing films help us to not only define the year in cinema, in some ways, define ourselves over the past year. So feel free to puzzle together my personal psychology through list, or just keep it handy when you’re looking for what to see in the coming months, and what to avoid.</p>

<p><strong>Top</strong> <strong>10</strong> <strong>Films of 2015</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Inside Out</li>
<li>Mad Max: Fury Road</li>
<li>Wild Tales</li>
<li>The Look of Silence</li>
<li>Furious 7</li>
<li>Deephan</li>
<li>Kurt Cobain: Montage of Heck</li>
<li>Room</li>
<li>The Martian</li>
<li>What We Do in the Shadows</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Better Than They Needed To Be:</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Pitch Perfect 2</li>
<li>Spy</li>
<li>The DUFF</li>
<li>Straight Outta Compton</li>
<li>The Man from U.N.C.L.E.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Inexplicably Underseen</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Black Sea</li>
<li>Red Army</li>
<li>Love and Mercy</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Overrated Everywhere Else:</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Ex Machina</li>
<li>It Follows</li>
<li>Slow West</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Unexpectedly Awesome</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Creed</li>
<li>San Andreas</li>
<li>Kingsmen: The Secret Service</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Didn’t Disappoint</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Star Wars: The Force Awakens</li>
<li>Mission Impossible: Rogue Nation</li>
<li>Trainwreck</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Extra Special Indies</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Backcountry</li>
<li>Man Vs.</li>
<li>99 Homes</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Wasted Potential</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Steve Jobs</li>
<li>Black Mass</li>
<li>Tomorrowland</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Avoid at All Costs</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Hot Tub Time Machine 2</li>
<li>Blackhat</li>
<li>Preggoland</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>This Year I Finally Saw (And Loved)</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>The Sting (1973)</li>
<li>The Bridge on the River Kwai (1957)</li>
<li>Serpico (1973)</li>
<li>Tokyo Story (1953)</li>
<li>Mr. Smith Goes to Washington (1939)</li>
</ol>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Carol</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/29/carol.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Carol" />
    <published>2015-12-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/29/carol</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The 1950s was an era of unprecedented prosperity and hope. Increased wealth, conspicuous consumption, and booming industry were the hallmarks of post-WWII America. Cars, in particular, had become the physical embodiment of the American dream; powerful machines built by proud, hard-working men and women, who were basking in the triumphant glow of global victory. Cars transported the luckiest people in the world on boundless journeys, the open road a symbol of the bright and exciting future that lay ahead. </p>

<p>But in the 1950s, the luckiest people in the world were predominantly white, heterosexual, American men. For most everyone else, the dream was still out of reach. </p>

<p><em>Carol</em> tells a story of forbidden love that is very much a reflection of its times, but like the most heart-wrenching and universal love stories, it is timeless. The titular Carol is an upper class wife and mother who falls in love with a shop-girl named Therese. Though Carol and her husband Harge are estranged and planning to divorce, her indiscretion drives Harge to force an ultimatum: break off the affair and cancel the divorce or lose custody of their young daughter, Rindy.</p>

<p>Director Todd Haynes has covered themes of longing and loss before, most notably in 2002’s <em>Far From Heaven</em> and the 2011 mini-series <em>Mildred Pierce</em>, which both featured female protagonists struggling to overcome the restrictive cultural expectations that were the norm in the not-so-distant past. Indeed, in 1948 when author Patricia Highsmith wrote the novel, <em>The Price of Salt</em>, upon which <em>Carol</em> is based, her publishers refused it and she had to resubmit it using a pseudonym. And though <em>Carol</em> explores themes of class, parental rights, and homosexuality, it is first and foremost a love story. </p>

<p>Therese is working at a department store when she first sees Carol shopping for Christmas toys for her daughter. In a display case, hundreds of dolls are behind glass, but the doll Carol wants is sold out. Therese recommends a train set instead. Both women could be display case dolls themselves; Cate Blanchett’s Carol, is a cool and elegant Barbie to Rooney Mara’s younger, wide-eyed kewpie doll. They are cautious and mannered - neither wanting to be the first to break the character she has carefully constructed for herself. </p>

<p>In a time when keeping up appearances was paramount, Haynes created a sumptuous visual landscape for his characters to inhabit.</p>

<p>The costumes, hair, make-up, set decoration, and props are period perfect, yes, but the art direction in general is mesmerizing. The characters seem to constantly interact with reflective surfaces, like store and apartment windows, mirrors, and in particular, the windows of cars. It’s a dream-like effect that mimics both the state of being in love, and the pain of love lost. The glass provides a window into their lives as well as a barrier. They can only come so close to being themselves without letting the rest of the world see them for who they really are. </p>

<p>The cars you provided, like Carol’s Deluxe Packard, her best friend Abby’s convertible, Harge’s black Cadillac (with a driver), and the yellow cabs Therese takes, illustrate their literal and figurative mobility. When Harge takes Rindy away from Carol prior to their first custody hearing, Carol decides to get in her car and drive, “wherever the car will take me”. Therese joins her on this journey west, and she and Carol grow closer to one another the way people do when confined together on a road trip. With every pit stop at a roadside diner or a motel, they begin to drop pretenses and revel in the freedom that comes from this break in their regular lives; the freedom of being able to get behind the wheel and drive away from your problems. Except, in the case of Carol and Therese, their problems follow them.  </p>

<p>It’s a joy to see female characters written with such depth and played so achingly well by actors at the top of their game. We’ve been spoiled by Cate Blanchett, having come to expect her to deliver award-worthy performances, and she deserves every accolade for playing Carol with such restrained determination. But it’s Rooney Mara’s Therese who seems to grow before our very eyes, and her portrayal of a young woman coming into adulthood is both gut-wrenching and inspiring. </p>

<p>Carol’s Packard is where Therese comes of age, and experiences a full range of emotions, from elation to despair. Anyone who has been in love and felt the all-consuming anguish of a broken heart, will understand that it’s a rare gift to travel the road of self-discovery and make it to the other side intact. <em>Carol</em> itself is a rare cinematic gift, and it was a privilege to follow these characters on their journey.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sisters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/27/sisters.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Sisters" />
    <published>2015-12-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/27/sisters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>“Hae-Won? Hae-Won? Hae-Won? <em>Hae</em>-Won? Hae-<em>Won</em>? <em>Hae-Won</em>?  Hey-one?” </p>

<p>That’s my rendition of the <em>hi-larious scene in _Sisters</em> when Amy Poehler’s character, Maura, has trouble pronouncing her Korean manicurist’s name. Annoying isn’t it, Lee? Now imagine two hours of that and you’ve got the gist of <em>Sisters</em>.</p>

<p>It was so funny that I practically had to restrain myself from walking out of the theatre. Yes, I’m being sarcastic. No, I’m not kidding about almost walking out. <em>Sisters</em> is some grade-A b.s., and your lack of editing shoulders much of the blame.</p>

<p>This type of <em>funny-then-not-funny-then-funny-again</em> joke has to be handled carefully. If used sparingly, and at the right time, you’ve got a quality piece of comedy on your hands. Take the infamous rake scene in <em>The Simpsons Cape Fear</em> parody for example. The amount of times Sideshow Bob accidentally gets bashed in the face with a rake (eight, I counted) gets tiresome after the fourth or fifth go, but soon after, the reality of the scene settles in. Sideshow Bob has been dragged through a cactus patch and had hot coffee spilled on him; the last thing he needs is a recurring rake to the face. Your empathy towards the character turns to laughter and comedic history is made. </p>

<p><em>Sisters</em> takes this concept and cranks it to 11.</p>

<p>Amy Poehler and Tina Fey are hilarious—together and separately. Their work on <em>SNL</em> and their respective TV shows, <em>Parks and Recreation, 30 Rock,</em> and <em>The Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt</em>, are some of the best comedies to come out in recent years. I have huge respect for both of them, but the lowbrow humour in <em>Sisters</em> is just insulting. The premise of two sisters who reunite to throw one last party in their childhood home before it’s sold isn’t exactly a knee-slapper, but I like to be optimistic. Still, I wasn’t expecting <em>that</em> many anal-related gags.</p>

<p><em>Sisters</em> stretches every joke to an unbearable point. Any time there’s a bit that could be milked for an extra few seconds, everyone runs with it. I suspect a lot of these jokes were the product of improv. When the cast is as tight-knit as the one in <em>Sisters</em>, silliness is a healthy side effect. They have a personal connection to the content. But it’s your job to dial back the foolishness when it goes too far. You should have slashed any joke that repeated itself more than twice.   </p>

<p>If viewers make it to the end of the film, they’re treated to a blooper reel where Maura repeats Hae-Won another fifty times! Which begs the question, why did you stop where you did? Couldn’t you have shaved another minute or two off the Hae-Won scene? Or any other scene for that matter? Couldn’t you have used your years of experience in editing comedies to fix the broken try-too-hard that is <em>Sisters</em>?</p>

<p>To <em>Sisters</em> credit, there were at least one or two nuggets of gold. When Maura says that she’s taken up cheese-making as a hobby, I chuckled at the line’s subtle delivery. Miraculously, she didn’t try to go ahead and name every cheese she’s made. There wasn’t anything more to that line and it was just fine without the embellishment. Tina Fey and Amy Poehler are funny ladies; they’re sharp and witty. They don’t need to be so obtrusive in their approach, and you shouldn’t sit idly by and let a hot mess like this happen again.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>2015 Silver Stamps</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/22/2015-silver-stamps.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=2015SilverStamps" />
    <published>2015-12-22T01:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-22T01:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/22/2015-silver-stamps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Dear Readers,</p>

<p>Every week, we try to evaluate films from a slightly different slant than your average review site. And every year, we like to sharpen that perspective by awarding the less heralded achievements in cinema. The Silver Stamps are, therefore, not just a way to review the year that was, but the highest and lowest honours we can bestow. So for the fourth consecutive year, we congratulate all those who made an indelible mark in cinema.</p>

<p><strong>Award For A Most Misleading Title:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html"><em>A Most Violent Year</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best STD Metaphor:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/2/it-follows.html"><em>It Follows</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best Sandwich Metaphor:</strong> <em>What We Do In the Shadows</em></p>

<p><strong>Best STD Sandwich Metaphor:</strong> <em>Bang Gang</em></p>

<p><strong>Freakiest Film:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/5/going-clear-scientology-and-the-prison-of-belief.html"><em>Going Clear: Scientology and the Science of Belief</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Funniest Film</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/6/jupiter-ascending.html"><em>Jupiter Ascending</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst Physical Alteration of Johnny Depp</strong> Tie: Moustache, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/24/mortdecai.html"><em>Mortdecai</em></a>,  Contact Lenses, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/9/23/black-mass.html"><em>Black Mass</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Most Unexpected Tear-Jerker:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/7/furious-7.html"><em>Furious</em> <em>7</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Most Unexpected Crowd Pleaser:</strong> <em>Straight</em> <em>Outta</em> <em>Compton</em></p>

<p><strong>Most Distracting Breasts:</strong> Alexandra Diddario, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/3/san-andreas.html"><em>San Andreas</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Most Exciting Casting News:</strong> Alexandra Diddario, <em>Baywatch</em> (2016)</p>

<p><strong>Best Road Trip Movie:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/8/27/the-end-of-the-tour.html"><em>The End of the Tour</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst Road Trip Movie:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/21/hot-pursuit.html"><em>Hot Pursuit</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best On-Screen Duo:</strong> Tom Hardy and Tom Hardy, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/4/legend.html"><em>Legend</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst On-Screen Duo:</strong> Will Farrell and Kevin Hart, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/27/get-hard.html"><em>Get Hard</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best 7th Film of a Beloved, Decades-Old Franchise, Starring Original and New Cast Members:</strong> Tie: <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/27/creed.html"><em>Creed</em></a> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/18/the-force-awakens.html"><em>Star Wars: The Force Awakens</em></a></p>

<p><strong>2nd Annual Jeff Bridges Award for Excellence in Bridgearian Acting:</strong> Jeff Bridges’ Voice in <em>The Little Prince</em></p>

<p><strong>Best Adaptation of the Frankenstein Story:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/8/ex-machina.html"><em>Ex Machina</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst Adaptation of the Frankenstein Story:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/3/victor-frankenstein.html"><em>Victor</em> <em>Frankenstein</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Most Disturbing Sexual Content:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html"><em>Kurt Cobain: Montage of Heck</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Least Disturbing Sexual Content:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/13/fifty-shades-of-grey.html"><em>Fifty Shades of Grey</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Hottest Robot:</strong> Alicia Vikander in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/8/ex-machina.html"><em>Ex Machina</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Hottest Spy:</strong> Alicia Vikander in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/8/16/the-man-from-uncle.html"><em>The</em> <em>Man from U.N.C.L.E.</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Hottest Danish Girl:</strong> Alicia Vikander in <em>The</em> <em>Danish Girl</em></p>

<p><strong>Best Looking Cast:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/8/16/the-man-from-uncle.html"><em>The Man from U.N.C.L.E.</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best Sounding Cast:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/22/inside-out.html"><em>Inside Out</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Most Unexpectedly Exciting Theatrical Event:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/12/jurassic-world.html"><em>Jurassic World</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Most Unexpectedly Dull Theatrical Event:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/avengers-age-of-ultron.html"><em>The Avengers: Age of Ultron</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst Reimagining of a Fairy Tale Since <em>Hook</em>:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/10/20/pan.html"><em>Pan</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst James Bond movie:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/6/spectre.html"><em>Spectre</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best James Bond movie:</strong> <strike><em>Mission Impossible: Rogue Nation</em></strike> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/4/spy.html"><em>Spy</em></a></p>

<p><strong>The 4th Annual Roger</strong> <strong>Deakins</strong> <strong>Award for Excellence in Being Roger</strong> <strong>Deakins <em>–</em></strong> <em>Roger</em> <em>Deakins</em> <em>for</em> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/10/26/sicario.html"><em>Sicario</em></a></p>

<p><strong><em>The 1st Annual Hoyte Van Hoytema Award for Falling Short of Being Roger Deakins:</em></strong> <em>Hoyte Van Hoytema for</em>  <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/6/spectre.html"><em>Spectre</em></a></p>

<p><strong><em>The Jai Courtney Achievement in Ruining a Beloved Franchise:</em></strong>  <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/7/4/terminator-genysis.html"><em>Terminator: Genisys</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Best Everything:</strong> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/20/mad-max-fury-road.html"><em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em></a></p>

<p><strong>Worst Everything:</strong> <em>Hot Tub Time Machine 2</em></p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Force Awakens</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/18/the-force-awakens.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheForceAwakens" />
    <published>2015-12-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/18/the-force-awakens</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Surely you served milk during those long days of shooting in dusty yellow deserts and crowded green-screen studios. And surely some of the cast and crew drank it, poured it on their cereal, stirred it into their coffee. And surely others didn’t.</p>

<p>Trying to apply any sort of objective critical thought to <em>Star Wars</em> is like trying to evaluate milk. There is no objective angle from which to approach it. You either grew up drinking milk, or you didn’t. You’re lactose intolerant, or you’re not. There are no rational metrics by which to measure milk’s thickness or sweetness or creaminess. Milk is simply milk. Just like the air is simply air, and the blue sky simply blue. <em>Star Wars</em> is <em>Star Wars</em>: you either love it, or you don’t. And if you love it, it’s impossible to explain why, and even more impossible to understand why other people don’t.</p>

<p><em>Star Wars: The Force Awakens</em> is a tall, cold, delicious glass of milk. If you’re a milk drinker, it may be one of the best glasses of milk you’ve ever had. If you’re agnostic about milk, you might find it thirst-quenching, or you might find it flavorless. And if your body can’t digest lactose, you’ll still get sick. </p>

<p>So what can I really say about this movie? I am a lifelong milk-drinking <em>Star Wars</em> fan. I didn’t see the original trilogy in theaters – I was too young – but nonetheless grew up wearing out VHS cassettes and playing with Tusken Raider action figures and scraping my eyelids with cardboard stormtrooper masks cut out from the backs of cereal boxes. But I was never obsessed enough to delve too deeply into the expanded universe. All those novels and comics and out-of-continuity characters had no heft for me; it was scripture written by apostles, and I cared only for The Word of God. I convinced myself to get excited about the prequels, saw them all, and tried hard to appreciate the (few) things they got right. And the disappointment I felt at the (many) things they got wrong only intensified my affection for the whole wonderful universe that, in my youth, had helped me through so many dreary, depressive teenage afternoons. </p>

<p>In short, when I walked into the theater to see <em>The</em> <em>Force Awakens</em>, I was, like many others, bringing a lot of baggage with me. Because this is the first Star Wars film in a decade. The first post-prequel apologia. The first Star Wars revival to take place in the Era of Nostalgic Revivals. It’s a big deal.  </p>

<p>And what’s my verdict? How do I rate this film?  </p>

<p>Well, it’s a new Star Wars film, and, as is the case with all new Star Wars films, it’s the best of all the Star Wars film. Why? Merely because it <em>exists</em>. There are X-wings and lightsabers and wookies and tie fighters and stormtroopers with terrible aim and massive death-ray space-stations and lots of new-age intergalactic mysticism. I love all those things, and therefore loved this movie. I frankly can’t bring myself to give it any less than five stars.</p>

<p>Yes, it’s good. Maybe great. The more time elapses between me the actual experience of sitting there in the theater, the more perspective I have for all the things it does well. And it does many, many things well (not the least of which is managing to surprise an audience that is expecting surprises).  </p>

<p>But it’s important to remember the intoxicating daze that close proximity to a Star Wars film elicits. Audiences rightly loved <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> when it was first released. Our Prime Minister said that <em>Return of the Jedi</em> was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XqjQ6gqgi0w">“better than Empire Strikes Back and Star Wars”</a> after stepping out of a screening in 1983. <a href="http://www.slashfilm.com/fans-react-to-the-phantom-menace/">Fans were ecstatic</a> about <em>The Phantom Menace</em> when it first hit theaters, and I can even recall feeling somewhat buoyed after emerging from <em>Attack of the Clones</em> (which, looking back, was probably the same relief a prisoner of war feels after the waterboarding is finally over). And then there was <em>Revenge of the</em> <em>Sith</em>, which, with its much-vaunted Tom Stoppard script-polish and Spielberg-directed Yoda/Emperor fight-scene, seemed to be such a step above the other two prequels that it was immediately bestowed the not-entirely-trivial title of <a href="http://boards.theforce.net/threads/revenge-of-the-sith-vs-return-of-the-jedi.50016954/">Third-Best Star Wars Movie</a>.</p>

<p>Director J.J. Abrams faced an even more difficult task than George Lucas did in the late-90s when the <em>Star Wars</em> creator began his billion-dollar vanity project (and turned the word <em>prequel</em> into a pejorative) . Not only must Abrams live up to the impossible-to-live-up-to originals (the sublimity of which are inflated by nostalgia with every passing year), but he has to make up for the prequels. And has there ever been a greater pop culture disappointment than Lucas’ ill-conceived trilogy of economics melodramas? Abrams has been tasked to atone for those sins, to rescue a franchise brought low by <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/15/the-phantom-menace.html">Gungans</a> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/16/attack-of-the-clones.html">digital backgrounds</a>.  </p>

<p>Is <em>The Force Awakens</em> perfect? No. But the flaws are the same flaws that every blockbuster epic suffers these days: it sometimes feels like there’s too much happening onscreen, and there’s a thinness and weightlessness to some of the CGI, and there are too many references to things that have (or are about to happen). The narrative and mythological simplicity of that very first film has been lost. But those are contextual complaints; this is simply how movies are made in 2015. In this manner, <em>The Force Awakens</em> is a film of its time. </p>

<p>Which is perhaps my only nonpartisan disappointment. The original <em>Star Wars</em> franchise was so out of place in the late 1970s; earnest, eager, optimistic—with its innocent moral code of light vs. dark, it seemed almost subversive, a response to the cynicism and verisimilitude of the New Hollywood movement. <em>The Force Awakens</em>, however, seems, by the standards of blockbuster filmmaking in this early part of the century, pretty conventional. For better and worse.  </p>

<p>But here is the best part. Perhaps the most unexpected part.</p>

<p>Harrison Ford. </p>

<p>He seemed so utterly bored with Han Solo by the end of the original trilogy; some of his line readings in <em>Return of the Jedi</em> have the flavor of an insubordinate kid trying to ruin the school play. And over the course of the last three decades he made no secret of his antipathy. But here he is, back behind the wheel of the Millennium Falcon, wisecracking, blasting stormtroopers, and even providing a bit of gravitas. I don’t know what reinvigorated him (maybe it was the food you were serving, or maybe it was a particular plot point late in the film), but, watching this, you realize that this is the same guy who played Richard Kimble and Rick Deckard and Jack Ryan, and that, yes, he can act.</p>

<p>The other familiar faces acquit themselves well. Carrie Fisher’s gravelly voice suggests that the preceding decades have been hard on poor Princess Leia. Chewbacca and Threepio are simply themselves, which is all you can possibly ask for. The new faces, too, are terrific. Much has been made of the cast’s diversity, but it’s their enthusiastic, unpretentious performances that make this new band of heroes feel special. </p>

<p>But none of this will be clear to me for another few months, or years, or perhaps even longer. <em>Star Wars</em> is all about legacy – in both its subject matter and its cultural significance – and only the passage of time can provide the necessary perspective. As a true believer, it’s impossible for me to guess whether this film will convert any non-believers. But I’m fairly certain it might recruit some new ones. </p>

<p>In fact, that might be the best way for fans like me to approach <em>The Force Awakens</em>. To imagine that this is the first <em>Star Wars</em> film you’ve ever seen. To think of it as your very first taste of an essential nutritional substance full of vitamins and complex proteins that will either keep you healthy or turn your stomach. To ask yourself: is this the glass of milk that will turn me into an instinctive milk-drinker?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Revenge of the Sith</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/17/revenge-of-the-sith.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=RevengeoftheSith" />
    <published>2015-12-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/17/revenge-of-the-sith</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Let me just start by saying that writing this letter was not my idea. I have always maintained a respectful (if somewhat scornful) distance from the <em>Star Wars</em> franchise. I saw the original trilogy for the first time a couple years ago, just to put an end to hearing: “YOU’VE NEVER SEEN <em>STAR WARS</em>??!!” That conversation had begun to end friendships. When I tried saying, “It’s okay, I’ve seen the first one,” someone would inevitably smugly point out, “You mean the fourth one?” And more friendships ended. I hoped all things <em>Star Wars</em> would leave me the hell alone, but then the folks here at Dear Cast and Crew were all like, “Please write about <em>Revenge of the</em> <em>Sith</em>” and I was all like, “Which one is he, again?” and my Companion was all like, “... you need to clear your schedule.”</p>

<p>And that’s how a perfectly good weekend was ruined. </p>

<p>While preparing myself mentally for the onslaught of siths and wonkies and whatever else, I found myself wishing – not for the first time – that someone had just showed me these damn movies when I was a kid. I think early exposure is key to liking <em>Star Wars</em>, nostalgia being the only thing that helps you look past its many, many weaknesses. I had to watch all three prequels so that <em>Revenge of the Sith</em> would make any sense at all, so I resolved to approach them with softer eyes, promising myself that, by the end of it, I would be able to list three things I liked about <em>Star Wars</em>. </p>

<p>This optimism lasted about ten minutes. What followed was six hours of me going, “Who wrote this shit?” My sympathies were with you, Fraser, as I sighed through scene after scene of clunky dialogue and performances that would have made the cast of my Grade 1 production of <em>The Very Hungry Caterpillar</em> raise a snide eyebrow. I pictured you watching each day’s footage, and I can’t even imagine what it was like to sift through multiple takes of Hayden Christansen muttering, “My strength has doubled since we last fought” (because that’s what apparently passes for smack talk in a galaxy far, far away) and having to pick the best one. You had to go through all the raw material to make sure it was fit to turn into a film worthy of franchise devotees’ loyalty and passion. It must have been awkward knowing they were going to get a steaming pile of wookie doo-doo instead. </p>

<p>So I decided to adjust my expectations, because I didn’t want to be one of those grumpy, stuck-up people who shits all over <em>Star Wars</em>. I was going to jump on this bandwagon if it killed me. And I managed to come up with one thing that could have been truly great if it didn’t suck so much, and another that actually <em>was</em> great. </p>

<p>If the Force was strong in me, I would, without a doubt, be Team Dark Side. I thought Darth Vader was the most compelling character in the original trilogy, so I thought I would enjoy watching his story unfold. It’s just too bad Anakin/Vader was portrayed with the intensity of a soaked badger. Vitriol aside, by the time I was ready to watch <em>Revenge of the Sith</em>, Anakin’s story did have me hooked. Even though I knew how it would end, I felt for him—but I really had to reach for it. To me, the most tragic aspect of Anakin’s story is that he was failed by people who loved him. Their inability to see past his Chosen One-ness and reach out to a boy who was clearly suffering a crisis of identity and faith is pretty heartbreaking when you think about it. And don’t even get me started on Padme. Whenever Anakin tries to express doubt or disillusionment, her stock response of, “But but the Republic!” was unhelpful, insensitive, and frankly, a bit dickish. Eventually Anakin goes full Vader, and it’s all quite sad, but I was kind of glad to see him packed off to the Death Star so that he could finally have a chance for some much-needed Vader-time. I guess I should say I liked the <em>idea</em> of Vader more than what I saw onscreen.</p>

<p>As for the one thing I ended up loving, Yoda, my little green homeboy, walks away with that distinction. I think there is a parallel to be drawn between Yoda and you, in that you both watched a massive clusterfuck unfolding and were ultimately powerless to stop it. I realize that, had Qui-Gon Jinn listened to Yoda in Episode I, there would be no Episodes II through VI, but I couldn’t help but remember Yoda, all the way back in <em>The Phantom Menace</em>, basically warning everyone, “Train that kid we must not, shady as fuck he is.” Likewise, I pictured you watching day after day of dailies with your head in your hands, going, “Turn out badly this will...” </p>

<p>(It’s also to my everlasting disappointment that, before going into exile, Yoda didn’t find Obi-Wan Kenobi, bitch slap him hard, and yell, “TOLD YOU SO I DID!” Just another missed opportunity that might have made the film truly great.)</p>

<p>Ultimately, I’m glad I’ve finally (sort of) climbed aboard the <em>Star Wars</em> bandwagon, if for no other reason than I now get all the <em>Star Wars</em> references in other movies and TV shows. I should also probably track down that guy on the subway who tried to hit on me with his best Chewbacca impression; I now understand what that was, and I’m very sorry for hitting him with my purse and pulling the emergency alarm.</p>

<p>I will probably see <em>The Force Awakens</em> at some point. Maybe in a few months, when the horde of costumed weirdos currently lined up outside the theatre has had its fill. Because it is, undeniably, a great story, and no amount of scorn I or anyone else choose to heap upon the films ultimately detracts from that. My fingers are crossed that this next iteration will be the truly great film series that all the Trekkies deserve. </p>

<p>Wait, that’s not right, is it? </p>

<p>Shit.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Attack of the Clones</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/16/attack-of-the-clones.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=AttackoftheClones" />
    <published>2015-12-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/16/attack-of-the-clones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You knew this was coming.</p>

<p>With <em>Star Wars: The Force Awakens</em> being released tomorrow, fans are bound to revisit the previous six films to prepare themselves for what’s to come. Which means your inbox is going to get filled with a ton of hate mail. </p>

<p>Again.   </p>

<p>I grew up with prequels. I was a kid addicted to action, and your CGI action sequences were my bread and butter. All that boring old man stuff in the original trilogy didn&#39;t interest me. What <em>did</em> interest me was the all-out war at the end of <em>Attack of the Clones</em>—droids, clones, and Jedis, oh my! When the Jedi reinforcements rescued Padme, Anakin, and Obi-Wan from the gladiator dome and proceeded to charge into battle against the droids, I lost my shit. It was so cool. </p>

<p>But when I re-watched Episode II the other day, I had to face a harsh truth: the movie I loved as a child is actually just a clunky mess.</p>

<p>It shouldn’t’ surprise me. <em>Attack of the Clones</em> is touted as the worst of all the <em>Star Wars</em> films. This is due, in large part, to the shocking amount of green screen used throughout the two hour span. When the original trilogy came out, the visual effects blew people’s minds; a thing as relatively simply as the beam of the Death Star’s superlaser left moviegoers in awe. In <em>Attack of the Clones</em>, that awe was replaced by disgust. Fans were in an uproar about the blatantly fake landscapes, sticky character movements, and the digitized characters and sets. It kept fans from being immersed in the beautiful world of <em>Star Wars</em>. In short, they weren’t transported to a galaxy far, far away.</p>

<p>But bashing <em>Attack of the Clones</em> is beating a dead horse. Everyone at Lucasfilm and Industrial Lights and Magic—a subdivision of Lucasfilm and the studio you work for—has learned from it. It’s not like you didn’t know what you were doing. What ended up onscreen is exactly what George Lucas was aiming for: he wanted the world’s first all-digital film (a lofty goal in the yesteryear of 2002). It must have been hard work, and I have to give you and your team serious props for being able to bring things to life with the tech you had available at that time. </p>

<p>That being said, the animation work on <em>Attack of the Clones</em> – which used to be my favorite thing – is now my biggest complaint. The interactions between actor and green screen are flat and lifeless, almost as if the actors had to move slowly enough to keep pace with the rendering of the backgrounds. Whenever we have a shot of an actor walking next to a computer-generated character, there’s a sluggishness which is hard to shake. </p>

<p>The slightly-off movements of digitized characters is a blatant distraction, too. Such is the case when Obi-Wan mounts the Reek. The transition when Obi-Wan jumps and sticks the landing is just cartoonish. He practically flies. There’s no struggle—you know, the kind of struggle you’d expect when someone tries to climb on top of an angry alien rhinoceros. </p>

<p>But the best example of the shoddy animation work has to be when we get our first glimpse of the clone army marching into formation. Their walking has no weight. The small subtleties of the human body in motion are completely missing. It’s the stuff you just can’t capture without advanced mocap suits, which you didn’t have, and which make the clone army look like they’re gliding across the ground into the Republic Gunship. If you’ve seen <em>The Force Awakens</em> trailer, you’ll agree that the snippet of Stormtroopers stepping into position (real human extras in costume) already feels more authentic than what we saw with the clone army. </p>

<p>I understand you did your best. You’ve gotten a lot more slack than you deserve. <em>Attack of the Clones</em> was a digital breakthrough, and paved the way for many of the digital advancements that have been made since. But there <em>is</em> such a thing as too much of a good thing. Your effects stripped away any sense of realism, and a with a film featuring Hayden Christensen in a lead role, believability is already a concern.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Phantom Menace</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/15/the-phantom-menace.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ThePhantomMenace" />
    <published>2015-12-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/15/the-phantom-menace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I wonder how things could have turned out if you had just said no, Rick. If you had listened to your gut and challenged George Lucas. Deep down you must have known his ideas were contrary to everything that made Star Wars such a beloved cultural institution in the first place. In an ideal world, there would be a whole new generation of Star Wars fans looking back at the prequels with the same level of reverence as the original trilogy. Instead, with <em>The</em> <em>Phantom Menace</em>, we get a baffling nightmare chock-full of half-baked political ideas, characters too thin to even be considered one-dimensional, and zero consistency in the internal logic of the plot.  </p>

<p>I understand there&#39;s a certain level of redundancy in critiquing the prequels in our post-Red Letter Media world, but I&#39;ll ask you to bear with me. Rewatching <em>Phantom</em> for the first time in at least twelve years, what flew over my head as a child served only to confuse and irritate me as an adult. It even got to the point where, an hour in, I had to send a series of increasingly desperate texts to a friend in an attempt to piece together the story. I began to feel like the embattled detective in a film noir, face to face with a massive conspiracy, desperately trying to find a connection between seemingly disparate elements. But instead of having a grand &quot;Eureka!&quot; moment, I came away sad and dispirited.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s what I think I know: a conflict has been staged by future-evil-emperor Palpatine in order to gain political power. But, past that, the whole thing begin to fall apart. Why would the Trade Federation, a merchant coalition, be interested in (and even having the means of) launching a full scale planetary invasion? Furthermore, what incentive would the Trade Federation have for attacking Naboo? They don&#39;t know that they&#39;re inadvertently helping Palpatine, and don&#39;t really seem to get anything out of the deal. Why does a disguised Palpatine insist that Queen Amidala sign a treaty legalizing her planet&#39;s invasion when that very action foils his plan? (By the way, as someone who studies criminal law, I&#39;m pretty sure forcing someone to sign a consent agreement does not equate to consent—even in a galaxy far, far away). And, most importantly, why do the Jedi let Jar Jar Binks tag along instead of abandoning him the first chance they get?</p>

<p>That covers about the first 20 minutes. I could go on, but you surely get the gist. A weak story could theoretically be overlooked if <em>Phantom Menace</em>&#39;s biggest problem wasn&#39;t everything else. Consider Liam Neeson, who looks like he wants to crawl into bed every time he&#39;s onscreen,and delivers his lines with the enthusiasm of a fast food drive-thru attendant. Or Natalie Portman, who seems like she was injected with animal tranquilizers during the climactic battle.  </p>

<p>And what about the mind-numbing action sequences, where our heroes fight cannon fodder without even coming close to being in danger—over and over and <em>over</em> until I began howling gibberish and yanking out fistfuls of hair. If our protagonists look like they can&#39;t be bothered when their lives are on the line, than neither can I. Not even the two-on-one fight with Darth Maul excites, despite some occasionally impressive choreography. Since we know absolutely nothing about any of the participants, the whole thing feels like an elaborate Cirque-Du-Soleil performance rather than the life and death struggle it&#39;s supposed to be.  </p>

<p>George Lucas has seemed to surround himself with people too afraid to raise dissenting opinions. I wish I knew why you didn&#39;t make the most of your position, maybe try to salvage some of the wonderment and originality that got buried beneath all the nonsense. Maybe just tell him that having racist Asian caricatures as the villains wouldn&#39;t add to the film&#39;s lasting appeal. Or that the mess of a story is alienating to both children and adults alike. Or that the whole thing just feels lifeless and lacks the spark that made the originals endure for long as they have.  </p>

<p>Sad to say, Rick, some of the blame for how this all turned out ultimately rests in your hands.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Return of the Jedi</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/14/return-of-the-jedi.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ReturnoftheJedi" />
    <published>2015-12-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/14/return-of-the-jedi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>All you had say was: “No, George.”</p>

<p>That is one of the prerogatives of being a co-writer—you can just say no. Because those fucking Ewoks are the first step on a slippery slope that leads to—well, you know who.</p>

<p>Somewhere in the midst of writing <em>Return Of The Jedi,</em> your collaborator lost contact with what made the first two Star Wars movies more than the sum of their individual parts. As his writing partner you had an opportunity to halt this particular cancer—before it metastasized. If you had just reminded him of the works in which he found his initial inspiration—Kurosawa’s <em>Hidden Fortress</em>, John Ford westerns, the 30’s <em>Flash Gordon serials, _Metropolis</em>, the Harryhausen <em>Sinbad</em> films—he may have seen the error of his ways. Because, while all of these films share a basic earnestness and an often fantastical tone, they were never created specifically for children. </p>

<p>Certainly children could (and did) enjoy all of the various Star Wars properties, but they enjoyed them in the same way that they would have enjoyed Edgar Rice Burroughs or Greek Myths. On one level, they were simple adventure stories: populated by monsters and heroes and whatever subtext existed could be happily ignored. But trying to square the circle of films that feature planet destroying technology <em>and</em> a cloying, rabbit-eared buffoon requires a defter pen than the one your partner wielded—and that really was where you should have stepped in, Lawrence.</p>

<p>When <em>Return Of The Jedi</em> was released in 1983, I had just turned 21—yet it was still clear to me that something had gone astray. It wasn’t difficult to pin down the exact moment, either. </p>

<p>When Leia first encounters the Ewoks about halfway through ROTJ, the unsettling cuteness that had just marginally tainted the first two films—from Jawas to Yoda to R2-D2—really kicked in. Up to that point, <em>Return Of The Jedi</em> had managed to maintain a goofy weekly serial vibe with bits like the stop motion <strong>Rancor</strong> and Jabba getting hoisted on his own petard by Slave Leia™. These beats were perfectly consistent with the tenor of the first two films. But then you and your co-writer began to construct a Frankenstein’s monster—grafting a one-note tribe of children’s discarded plushies onto a relatively complex space opera. It was as if, in a coke-fuelled haze of the likes of which defined American filmmaking in the late seventies, one of your buddies (maybe Francis Ford or Mr. Schrader) dared you to find a place to insert a rag-tag band of cannibal teddy bears into this magnum opus.</p>

<p>Wait. No. That makes Ewoks sound waaaaay more interesting than they are. The truth is they are more like a nicotine stained Chihuahua. Kind of cute from a distance but annoying as hell when you spend more than half a minute in their presence.</p>

<p>The problem with the second half of <em>Return Of The Jedi</em>, which is the same problem that plagues the films that came after, is that they lost the thread; they occupied a tonal space that was completely at odds with the original concept. Neither beast nor fowl, the two different approaches never coalesced. Instead, this fundamental discordance infected what came afterwards—to the extent that, in trying to reconcile the completely irreconcilable halves, they collapsed into an orgy of mismatched pairings: Senate trade deliberations attended by Bugs Bunny with a speech impediment;  a tow-headed Ani growing up into a monster that slaughters a roomful of small children.</p>

<p>All I can really say Lawrence is that I wish you had bullied your pal a little bit and made him <em>pick a fucking lane</em>. Then maybe all the pointless vitriol and hand wringing of the last decade could have been avoided.</p>

<p>I’ve always thought that the cultural significance of the Star Wars films is more deep and meaningful than the actual films themselves. The world they hint at is fascinating but it sort of feels like a tour of Rome with a really shitty guide: you can see the coliseum off in the distance, but you never get to see it close up, to feel the age of the marble, to smell the blood baked into the ancient sand. And the Ewoks and everything they presaged feels like being herded into a junk shop filled with keychain tchotchke versions of the real buildings you’ll never get to experience.</p>

<p>Still. I’m really stoked about December 17<sup>th</sup> .</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Empire Strikes Back</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/13/the-empire-strikes-back.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheEmpireStrikesBack" />
    <published>2015-12-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/13/the-empire-strikes-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve wanted to write some version of this letter for a long time.</p>

<p>This is probably not the most original insight, but I’ve long maintained that the stature of the entire Star Wars saga is due mainly to the halo effect caused by <em>The Empire Strikes Back.</em> I’m not casting aspersions on all of the other films – <em><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/12/star-wars.html">Star Wars</a></em>, specifically, is of course its own, different kind of masterpiece – but, let’s be honest: ever since <em>Empire</em>, the <em>Star Wars</em> movies have been a study in diminishing returns. And that downward trend coincides with one obvious event: the end of your involvement as producer.</p>

<p>As you know, much of the producer’s job is to say no. Whether it’s budget, schedule, or the worst tendencies of a filmmaker, a good producer keeps a holistic view of a project and reigns in anything that threatens the original vision. If necessity is the mother of invention, then it could be argued that a producer’s duty is to sometimes force necessity—to create boundaries that force creative decisions.</p>

<p>But I’m not writing this letter to bitch about what happened after George Lucas surrounded himself with spineless yes-men. I’m writing to praise <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em>, a film I can comfortably say is nearly <em>perfect</em>.</p>

<p><em>Empire</em> is that rare occurrence that results from every decision being right. So let’s talk a few of them out.</p>

<p>First of all, this film <em>moves</em>. It benefits from the heavy (if seemingly effortless) lifting that <em>Star Wars</em> did in establishing the universe. With the world-building and character introductions out of the way, <em>Empire</em> hits the ground running at a full sprint and never lets up. As a precursor of things to come, about a minute after we catch up with Luke, he gets his face smashed in and is dragged off to a cave (of course, this was also a necessary event, to explain the scars Mark Hamill received from a car accident between films). The intended message comes through loud and clear: no one is safe. We’re in darker territory than <em>Star Wars.</em> </p>

<p>This is made even more clear by the decision to reverse the plot structure of <em>Star Wars</em>, placing the big, show-stopping battle in the first act instead of the third. This establishes the fact that <em>Empire</em> is essentially an extended chase sequence, with not a lot of time to slow down for long expository exchanges. Thank god.</p>

<p>The go-for-broke narrative works its way into the performances as well. Leigh Brackett and Lawrence Kasdan amp up the exchanges, particularly between Han Solo and Princess Leia, giving them a classic Hollywood screwball comedy zing (not surprising, considering Brackett’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0102824/">bona fides</a>). Re-watching Harrison Ford and Carrie Fisher exchange insults, I could imagine director Irvin Kershner using <em>His Girl Friday</em> as a reference point for his actors: talk as fast as you can, and force the audience to try and keep up. There’s no hand-holding here—we don’t need it anymore (strangely, this approach was jettisoned for <em>Return of the Jedi</em>, whose first 30 minutes is nothing <em>but</em> a series of character reintroductions.)</p>

<p>Speaking of Kershner, I’m not sure how involved you were in selecting him as director, Gary, but it was a very smart move. <em>Empire</em> is the most well-directed of all six <em>Star Wars</em> films—by a country mile. But it’s not his visual flair that wins the day (even though <em>Empire</em> is also the best-looking film of the series), it’s his focus on the basics: performance and character. As an outsider to this cinematic universe, Kershner was able to hone-in on what he knew how to do best, which was to push out all the superfluous crap that traditionally clogs up storytelling (c.f. <em>The Phantom Menace</em>).  </p>

<p>This kind of laser-sharp attention is what makes Yoda work as the heart and soul of the film.  <em>Empire</em> has its share of action centerpieces (the extended lightsaber duel between Luke and Vader has never been topped in emotional intensity) and mind-blowing plot twists (yes, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/12/10/how-to-avoid-the-star-wars-syndrome.html"><em>that</em></a> one), but Yoda is what gives the film its depth. I can only guess at your reaction when you saw that the emotional heft of your production was going to rest on the performance of a 3-foot tall muppet, but whatever reluctance (or sheer terror) you may have felt was for naught. And your faith in Kershner was rewarded, as he treated Yoda the only way he knew how: as an actual character. This might sound obvious, but Yoda’s subsequent appearances have proven that the presence of muppeteer Frank Oz is not enough to make him work onscreen. Again, it comes down to decisions – character and performance – and they were perfect.</p>

<p>I could go on – the ingenious cliffhanger with Han Solo, edited to look like a possible last-minute rescue; the way you showed just enough of Darth Vader to prove there’s a human inside the armour – but I’m going to leave you with a simple thanks. </p>

<p>Thank you for helping assemble – and then <em>trusting</em> – the production team to make their own decisions. Thank you for having the faith in the audience’s ability to keep up. But most importantly, thank you for having the backbone to keep George Lucas disciplined. Because no one has since, and that’s why <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> is the only perfect <em>Star Wars</em> film.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>