<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-13T13:54:47Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2015 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Star Wars</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/12/star-wars.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StarWars" />
    <published>2015-12-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/12/star-wars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Before I’d ever even seen <em>Star Wars</em> (which I begrudgingly admit was less than 48 hours ago), your character was my entry point into the story. As the only little girl in my neighbourhood, when the boys wanted to play <em>Star Wars</em>, I always had to be Princess Leia. I wasn’t a fan of dolls, or dresses, or princesses. Princesses sit around in castles looking pretty, waiting for princes. I wanted to be the <em>Bionic Woman</em>. But when the boys told me Princess Leia was smart, and she gets to shoot a gun, fight bad guys <em>and</em> tell Han Solo off, it seemed like a gig I was born for.</p>

<p>I have a feeling you know what I’m talking about.</p>

<p>Coming to the <em>Star Wars</em> universe at this very late date has had its disadvantages. Even though I’ve only seen the first film in the series, I’m all-too-aware of the plot, the characters, the relationships, and the minutiae. The franchise’s popularity is just too ubiquitous <em>not</em> to. When I sat down to watch <em>Episode IV</em> for the very first time the other night, I knew I would struggle to maintain objectivity. So I imagined myself as a kid in the Seventies (which I was), seeing <em>Star Wars</em> for the first time. What would I have laughed at? What would I have found exciting, or scary, or confusing? Would I have understood the stakes? The relationships? The very concept of The Force? Who would I consider the hero of the story? </p>

<p>Here’s how my kid-brain would have broken it down: Droids and Wookies = funny, Darth Vader = bad, Obi Wan = pretty much Santa with a light saber, Luke = kind of goofy, Han Solo = kind of a dick, Storm Troopers = useless,  Cantina Bar =  cool, The Force = …uh, I’m still not really sure what the Force is. But then there’s Princess Leia, and Princess Leia = <em>awesome!</em> Seriously. Right from the get-go she insults Darth Vader, she cleverly plans her own rescue by hiding a message in R2D2, she gets tortured but doesn’t give anything up, and when she gets out she chides her rescuers for sucking at rescuing her. Then, when they’re stuck in the trash compactor, she figures out how to brace it open, and when her planet gets destroyed she keeps calm and carries on, shoots tons of bad guys, and, yes, she tells Han Solo off. A lot. She’s in control, she’s a rebel, and she’s got attitude. </p>

<p>Obviously, she’s the hero. </p>

<p>To be honest, over the last several decades, I never really felt I was missing out by not seeing the <em>Star Wars</em> movies. I appreciate their pop-cultural significance, I respect the ingenuity that went into them, and I understand why they are so beloved by so, so many. I love great sci-fi, and action movies, too, and I now know why this one is considered to be the ultimate. It was fun, and thrilling and I really did feel like a kid watching it; I managed to experience the excitement, suspense, and camaraderie of joining this ragtag group of misfits as they tried to take down a ruthless dictator intent on world domination. </p>

<p>As far as stories go, however, these aren’t necessarily the ones that grab me by the gut. I’ve always been more intrigued by reality—in seeing the good and evil of regular people played out in all its awkward, hilarious, pathetic wretchedness.
I have a feeling you know what I’m talking about.</p>

<p>Viewing this movie for the first time as an adult means that it comes with a little bit of backstory. Through your hilariously frank autobiographies <em>Postcards</em> <em>From</em> <em>the Edge,</em> and <em>Wishful Drinking</em>, I know about your upbringing, your bipolar disorder, your drug addiction, relationships, and unease with your <em>Star Wars</em> related-fame. As much as I tried to watch <em>A New Hope</em> through a kid’s eyes, I couldn’t separate what I know about you, the person, with what I saw in your portrayal of Leia. And maybe that’s why I loved you so much in this role. </p>

<p>You were 19 years-old when you made this movie, with many of your life’s biggest obstacles and triumphs still ahead of you. And yet you were able to give Leia a sophistication, determination, and playful cynicism that was well beyond your years. It’s a role that, for better or for worse, has defined your career, and it’s impossible to imagine anyone else coming even close. </p>

<p>I do plan on watching <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> and <em>Return of the Jedi</em> (in their unadulterated, pre-’97, VHS versions, by decree of C. Redmond,  C. Tourangeau, and J. Young), mainly because I want to see what else you bring to Leia. I may even watch the rest of the series, if only so I can get to see you play Leia in <em>The Force Awakens</em> with some context. Or instead I may just continue to follow your brilliant, <a href="http://time.com/4137685/carrie-fisher-star-wars-the-force-awakens-good-morning-america-interview/">DGAF publicity</a> for the movie. </p>

<p>Either way, it’s obvious to me that you’re still the hero.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Star Wars Week</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/11/star-wars-week.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=StarWarsWeek" />
    <published>2015-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/11/star-wars-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Review, we will, a film each day until The Force Awakens!</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to Avoid the Star Wars Syndrome</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/10/how-to-avoid-the-star-wars-syndrome.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=HowtoAvoidtheStarWarsSyndrome" />
    <published>2015-12-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/10/how-to-avoid-the-star-wars-syndrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In the Star Wars universe, it’s called manifest destiny. But on this planet, it’s just lazy storytelling.</p>

<p>Once upon a time, in a theatre far, far away (from this writer, anyway, born in small-town Alberta in 1983), a movie came out that simultaneously thrilled and shocked the world. <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em> is widely considered the high point of the most beloved franchise in movie history, and remains the gold standard against which sequels are measured. So why have so many storytellers taken the exact wrong lesson from a movie filled with countless technical accomplishments and visceral pleasures?</p>

<p>When Darth Vader reveals to Luke Skywalker (shortly after slicing off his hand) that they share the same blood, it’s a barely-foreshadowed brain-buster that seems to make little-to-no sense in the galaxy-spanning story. So incredulous was the claim that, even after wrapping up the trilogy, George Lucas decided he needed another three films just to make sure that the overly convenient plot-twist didn’t go down as the most cosmic coincidence of all-time. Lucas has claimed that the pre-occupation of father and son, and the ways in which we forge our identities through family relations, has been his sole focus from the very start. No need to play in this billion dollar sandbox any longer, <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/business-20146942">thank you very much</a>. </p>

<p>But the idea of making the hero and villain related has become so ubiquitous in recent years, you’d think it’s an official step along The Hero’s Journey. And in fact, much of the blame could no doubt be traced back to Joseph Campbell and <em>The Hero with 1000 Faces</em>, which Lucas drew from in order to build his archetypes and make his space opera relatable. But archetype is just the well-spoken cousin of <em>stereo</em>type, and when a media-saturated world is keeping up with Lucas <em>and</em> the Kardashians, a shortcut to depth is too often forced through family ties.</p>

<p>Take the latest James Bond film, <em>Spectre,</em> as one of the most egregious recent examples (spoiler-waring). To one-up the emotional climax in <em>Skyfall</em>, which is accomplished through a symbolic maternal relationship, the only direction the filmmakers felt they could go was to double-down with daddy issues, shared between Bond and his nemesis. Well, phew. I don’t know about you, but I’m finally ready to enjoy the past 50 years of James Bond knowing every world-threatening event was the evil brainchild of a jilted brother.  The series would just be silly otherwise.</p>

<p>Television is just as guilty of committing these sins. Everything from <em>24</em> to <em>Alias</em> has been reduced, at some point, to a Thanksgiving-dinner squabble played out with nuclear launch codes. Not to mention all the blockbuster franchises that have relied on a family twist to either shock us, or try to squeeze out renewed sympathy—from <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em>, to <em>Indiana Jones and the Crystal Skull</em>, to <em>A Good Day to Die Hard</em>, etc. Recent North American democracies are dominated by family dynasties, from The Bushes, to The Clintons, and now The Trudeaus.  We’ve surrendered the everyman element that makes elections and action adventures relatable. It’s no fun imagining that our heroes are only heroic because of nepotism—we get enough of that in real life.</p>

<p>And in case there are any doubts that this trend links back to the original <em>Star Wars</em> trilogy, look no further than the groan (and barf) -inducing revelation that Princess Leia is actually Luke Skywalker’s twin sister. I may have been born the year <em>Return of the Jedi</em> came out, but I can guarantee that golden bikini buzz-kill plot twist wasn’t to thank. Write this down, everyone. Family stories, good; family twists, bad.</p>

<p>I can (almost) look back and laugh at such an ill-conceived plot point. But it’s not so funny when it’s inspiring so many modern stories. There’s a hell of a lot to learn from those original movies, but family dynamics aren’t one of them.Maybe if Darth Vader had been rejected from art school, the series would have been just as good. Better, actually. He doesn’t need to be Winston Churchill’s dad for me to care.</p>

<p>I hope J.J. Abrams takes note.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>I Smile Back</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/8/i-smile-back.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=ISmileBack" />
    <published>2015-12-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/8/i-smile-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>In <em>I Smile Back</em> you have written a direct, if unintentional, rebuke to mumblecore bullshit like Greta Gerwig and Noah Baumbach’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/9/4/mistress-america.html"><em>Mistress America</em></a>. Where the latter is coy and hides its arch and ultimately empty purpose behind layers of artifice, <em>I Smile Back</em> just spits it intentions right in your eye.</p>

<p>Sarah Silverman is not high on my list of actresses that I ever expected to admire. But in <em>I Smile Back</em>, Silverman displays the same fearlessness that Charlize Theron so readily employed in 2003’s <em>Monster</em>. There is, however, an ambiguity to Silverman’s performance that is finely tuned. Is she simply someone who suffers from a quiet but profound mental illness? Or has she succumbed to an unrepentant self-indulgence that is only made more unpalatable by her state of cartoonish privilege?</p>

<p>This is a film and a performance that has one thing on its mind—an unsentimental portrayal of just how ugly and existentially empty life can be, even in what seem to be idyllic circumstances. And if that is not necessarily an original concept, the depth and unflinching nature of this film certainly holds it apart from its lesser brethren. </p>

<p>One of the most interesting aspects of a film that is otherwise episodic and choppy—the narrative concerns itself far more with chipping away at the core of Silverman’s character than any specific plot points—is how often the tropes inherent to films about addiction and recovery are subverted. Each time the usual event occurs—reuniting with an absent father or the now clichéd epiphany about how some behaviors are destructive not only to the person engaged in them but to everyone attached to that person—the film turns away from what is expected. Instead we have a scene of a drunken Silverman masturbating on her young daughter’s bedroom floor, while holding a teddy bear. <em>I Smile Back</em> is filled with moments just like that.</p>

<p>The unsettling core of the whole project is the effort made to present Silverman’s illness as part of her character rather than the whole of it. <em>I Smile Back</em> refuses to shift the weight entirely off of the protagonist’s shoulders despite her obvious and very real illness. It is here that the film treads on some dangerous but important ground: it understands that while mental illness is tangible and real there comes a point that whatever the initial circumstance, choices we make often have irrevocable consequences. And that no one, especially when children are involved, has carte blanche—however unfair the circumstances of their existence.</p>

<p><em>I Smile Back</em> is a vaccination against a particular kind of Oprah-esque, feel-good nonsense that is often employed in portrayals of addiction and depression. It is also a tremendous performance by a woman playing an almost entirely unsympathetic character. Silverman makes a strong case for herself as a modern day female equivalent to Travis Bickle. Both are repugnant and still also caught in the throes of something they can’t really control or understand.</p>

<p>I believe Sarah Silverman would have made John Cassavetes a happy man, and I can’t think of higher praise for an actress. You gave her the raw material to make that hyperbolic praise difficult to refute, Paige, and while I won’t thank you for it, I still respect the hell of out what you both managed to create.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Legend</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/4/legend.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Legend" />
    <published>2015-12-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/4/legend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>While it may seem like the obvious choice to address this letter to you, it’s also the only choice. Because what <em>Legend</em> is really about—rather than an exploration of the infamous London gangsters, the Kray twins—is displaying your mercurial talents.</p>

<p>When people use the term “star vehicle” <em>Legend</em> could be held up as the platonic ideal. And what a purring E-Type it is—every moment onscreen is filled an inescapable Tom Hardy-ness. From the opening frame of this rose colored paean to a mythic 1960’s London, <em>Legend</em> is far more interested in you as a performer than telling any particular story. </p>

<p>You are the most interesting English language male actor in the last thirty or forty years: half Paul Newman, one part Cary Grant and more than a little Robert Mitchum. You are also one of the few artists that is worth paying money to see for your performance alone, regardless of the writing, direction, or subject matter. And every scene of <em>Legend</em>—whether you are playing the unapologetically gay, batshit insane Ronnie, or the smooth-as-glass, bespoke-suited Reggie—is possessed by your presence. The whole film’s center of gravity lurches around after you whenever you move through the frame.</p>

<p>The fact that you are so compelling as an actor can be both a feature and a bug. In a film where your character(s) is/are the focal point that magnetism is generally useful since your talents tends to soften some of the elements that would undermine the narrative—whereas in a something like <em>Lawless</em> you tend to overwhelm lesser actors (cough—LaBeouf—cough) to the extent that the film feels lopsided and uneven. </p>

<p>There are only a few scenes when you are on camera with yourself and these are the high points of the film. The sheer virtuosity of one individual playing twins while creating two entirely differentiated personalities is a goddamn magic trick. Aside from the comparison to Jeremy Irons in Cronenberg’s <em>Dead Ringers</em> (a film that gave the central performance far more support) there isn’t anything that comes close. One specific scene early on in the film—where you both kick the piss out of some rival gang members—is technically proficient and also a great example of how it’s possible to express character through action, rather than dialogue. Director Brian Helgeland doesn’t always make great choices (the voice over really was terribly clunky and inept) but he was astute in giving your characters space to breathe as individuals, while still underlining the inexorable and ultimately destructive pull each of them had on the other.</p>

<p>The fact that it is possible to evaluate Reggie and Ronnie as separate performances is probably the highest praise I can give. You managed to turn a glossy nothing of a film into something pretty memorable. Next time I hope the film surrounding you rises to your level. </p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Victor Frankenstein</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/3/victor-frankenstein.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=VictorFrankenstein" />
    <published>2015-12-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/3/victor-frankenstein</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>Victor Frankenstein</em> is a film of such obvious conceits that you can almost hear the elevator pitch. “So… imagine Guy Ritchie directing a gothic romance/monster movie with homoerotic overtones.”</p>

<p>“Magic!”</p>

<p>The film is a tired and largely unimaginative retelling of Mary Shelly’s <strong>Frankenstein.</strong> The only potentially interesting change is that it is told largely from the POV of Igor—played gamely by Daniel Radcliffe. Even that conceit falls prey to your tendency to see every narrative as a way to stitch together various genre tropes in what you consider new and interesting ways.  </p>

<p>Max, you are the epitome of self-circumscription (pun intended). Your definition of screenwriting, as it currently exists on your IMDB page, all but guarantees what you write will always end up as creatively vacuous as <em>Victor Frankenstein,</em> or this year’s underwhelming <em>American Ultra.</em> You might want to consider that the emptiness of your work has more to do with your writing than it has to do with the environment you lament. </p>

<p>It is not the visual excess, or the overt genre busting, or the playful edges that exist in the protagonist’s relationship that drag this film into the swampland of mediocrity—the same mire that the aforementioned Ritchie’s <em>Sherlock Holmes</em> or even the <em>Underworld</em> series swim in. No Max, it is the relentless lack of any kind of real character that wrecks this film utterly. There is not one genuine human voice anywhere in this work.</p>

<p>James McAvoy, as the titular Victor, chews every single ounce of the set he can sink his teeth into in a failed effort to inject some heart into what is essentially a filmmaking exercise rather than an actual movie. That McAvoy fails miserably is not for lack of effort, but simply there is nothing here for him to grab hold of. The story is literally a series of obvious signposts that see it lurch forward with no more intention or purpose than if a drunk followed a single high-banked road. It is as if you think it is possible to just skip the basics of plot and character by using visual and literary tropes to stand in for these essential elements.</p>

<p>Every scene is played as a nod and a wink at what came before (if I see one more iteration of the “it’s alive!” moment I will remove my own eyes with an ice cream scoop). As a consequence, the film rests on the idea that its weight comes from what <em>Victor Frankenstein</em> references rather than creating it’s own center of gravity. There is no skeleton here to hang the meat of the monster on—so the whole thing falls to pieces.</p>

<p>For a film that works hard to incorporate every Frankenstein moment <em>ever</em>—from the Hammer films to a half-clever nod to Mel Brooks <em>Young Frankenstein—</em>there is an undercurrent of dismissal that permeates <em>Victor Frankenstein.</em> If you don’t understand or respect the underlying strength of the source material, then why bother Max?</p>

<p>In fact, if there is one question I would really be curious to ask you Max, it is this: why should any of us bother when you clearly do not?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Trumbo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/12/1/trumbo.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Trumbo" />
    <published>2015-12-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/12/1/trumbo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Combing through a script to verify historically accuracy, pointing out legal conflicts and continuity errors, making suggestions for alternatives—you don’t have an easy job, Malcolm. Even under the simplest of circumstances. And with <em>Trumbo</em>, you were given a script about one of the darkest moments in Hollywood’s history: the jailing and blacklisting of screenwriters accused of Communism in post-WWII America. </p>

<p>So, you know—no pressure. </p>

<p>I can imagine your conundrum. You have a real-life story that takes place during a time of great cultural and political change, colourful characters and toothsome subject matter, but the script itself is jokey, plodding, and decidedly small-screen in its scope. Do you speak up? Or do you just keep mum to stay employed? 
The real crime here is that 
this period of history – so bleakly fascinating, and featuring the most famous of all blacklisted writers -  is given such humdrum treatment.  </p>

<p>Dalton Trumbo was already living comfortably as one of the most famous scribes in Hollywood when his support of striking film workers singled him out as an agitator. With the threat of the Red Menace reaching panic levels, U.S. Congress called a hearing to determine which writers in Hollywood were Communists. Trumbo and nine others, dubbed the Hollywood 10, were held in contempt and jailed for their political beliefs. Once released, Trumbo continued writing under pseudonyms, employing his family as a scriptwriting sweat-shop to get his work out. When word leaked that Trumbo had, by proxy, written Oscar-winners <em>Roman Holiday</em> and <em>The Brave One</em>, it became difficult to keep Hollywood heavyweights like Kirk Douglas (<em>Spartacus</em>) and Otto Preminger (<em>Exodus</em>) away. Trumbo was determined to get his name back on the credits and off of the blacklist. </p>

<p>But the film <em>Trumbo</em> is nothing more than proof that we have reached “peak biopic”. It’s full of big name actors – Bryan Cranston as Trumbo, Helen Mirren as gossip-columnist Hedda Hopper, Diane Lane as Cleo Trumbo – all playing one-dimensional characters who meander through a by-the-numbers story intent on showing audiences <em>just how far we’ve come</em>. In your research you must have found so many interesting sub-plots and lesser-known players that could have given this film a little more depth. Instead, it strives so much to be an <em>Important _Film</em> that, much like the House Un-American Activities Committee, it becomes a victim of its own hubris.</p>

<p>The stuff the script gets right, like Trumbo’s huge personality and self-righteousness, are well-served by an actor like Bryan Cranston. It’s clear that his mugging on <em>Malcolm in the Middle</em> prepared him to chew some period-appropriate scenery. Director Jay Roach, better known for helming <em>Austin Powers</em> and <em>Meet the Parents</em>, doesn’t seem to know whether he’s making a comedy or a drama, and both elements suffer. His mis-casting of Louis CK as a doomed member of the Hollywood 10 proves this point. It seems like CK was given free rein to re-write his own dialogue. I feel for you, Malcolm; keeping up with his anachronisms must have given you writer’s cramp.</p>

<p>CK’s character is a composite, which in itself must have been a head-scratcher for you, considering the wealth of fascinating real-life writers screenwriter John McNamara could have brought to life (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0488057/?ref_=fn_al_nm_1">Ring Lardner Jr.</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0778789/?ref_=fn_al_nm_1">Adrian Scott</a>, to name just two). Or maybe you tried and failed to get clearance from the families who wanted nothing to do with this trifle.</p>

<p>The real heart of the story is supposed to be Trumbo’s difficult relationship with his family, who must suffer his verbal abuse while he writes in the tub, high on Bennies. But the more interesting relationship is the one he has with actor Edward G. Robinson, who sold out others to save his career. Michael Stuhlbarg looks nothing like Robinson, but he and Cranston generate the film’s most honest moments. One is a man who refuses to give up his ideals, the other is a man torn between doing what’s right and doing what’s best for him, and they’re both trying to stay alive in the cutthroat world of the Hollywood film industry. </p>

<p>It’s a shame that a movie about one of the greatest screenwriters who ever lived is so uninspired. A story like this deserves more gravitas, fewer guffaws. Instead of telling a serious story and injecting it with humour, we got a lot of slap-happy hijinks and over-the top moralizing. I’m not sure who exactly on this film should be held responsible for turning in such a mess, but I don’t expect you to name names. You’ve been through enough.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Good Dinosaur</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/29/the-good-dinosaur.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheGoodDinosaur" />
    <published>2015-11-29T07:00:01Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-29T07:00:01-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/29/the-good-dinosaur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You’re a staple at Pixar studios. You’ve used your expertise in 3D set modeling to provide Pixar with some of their most visually striking films, such as <em>Wall-E</em>, <em>Brave</em>, and <em>Up</em>. But your work on <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> is a whole new level of magic.</p>

<p>Watching a Pixar film always guarantees two things: a warm feeling in your chest, and tears. Pixar has mastered the art of playing our heartstrings like a fiddle. Try mentioning <em>Up</em> to anyone without being told how much they cried during the opening few minutes. You can’t, it’s impossible. Pixar has become synonymous with raw emotion, which is what makes your set modeling all the more impressive. You steered the conversation away from heart strings to eyeballs. </p>

<p>Inspired by the picturesque Jackson, Wyoming, your expert layering and texturing created an atmosphere so lifelike, moviegoers have had trouble distinguishing a computer-generated image from a real fly-over of Snow King Mountain. Your attention to detail and command of Presto, Pixar’s in-house 3D animation software, was paramount when modeling the varying densities in the foliage, the ripples in a calm body of water, and the precision ridges in distant mountains. It was awe-inspiring.</p>

<p><em>The Good Dinosaur</em> is Pixar’s second 2015 release—which is a pretty big deal. Following the monumental firestorm that was <em>Inside Out</em>, <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> takes place in an alternate universe where the asteroid that wiped out the dinosaurs, missed. After losing his father in a severe storm, Arlo, an easily frightened Apatosaurus, must learn to fight his fears and make his mark in a vast and unknown, yet beautiful landscape. </p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, every Pixar film is stunning, but the lumps in people’s throats are always part of the chatter as they leave the theatre—and <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> provides a hefty one. But the pace is a lot slower and a tad darker here than what we’re used to with a _Pixar vehicle. There are recurring themes of death and loneliness that will warrant some consoling for the younger viewers—as was the case for the two small children sitting behind me. Despite that, your environment is the main takeaway for audiences.</p>

<p>Your set design is further enhanced by the recognizable caricature design style of Pixar. The protruding, gangly shape of Arlo complimented your detailed landscape surprisingly well. They both shared the screen without stealing each other’s thunder. Speaking of thunder, I’d classify your set as a character of its own. Although Arlo meets a slew of characters on his journey, it’s his relationship with the force of nature that strikes a chord. Arlo is constantly interacting with nature, whether it’s scaling up a jagged cliff, powering through a strong river current or trembling as a thick storm cloud brews; the set is the ultimate test of dino manhood and your greatest work yet. </p>

<p>I wouldn’t be surprised if <em>The Good Dinosaur</em> has been your most rewarding experience. It was a pleasure to watch, but probably a bitch to create.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Steve Jobs</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/29/steve-jobs.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=SteveJobs" />
    <published>2015-11-29T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-29T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/29/steve-jobs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>Clearly, you’ve taken a completely different approach than writer Matt Whiteley did with the biopic <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/8/21/jobs.html"><em>Jobs</em></a>  in 2013. You didn’t for a second <em>try</em> to cram Steve Jobs’ entire life into a 122-page script. Rather you constructed your script as the most specific thesis paper imaginable. And though I longed for more flashbacks and chronological context (show –don’t tell, remember!), I have to commend you for succeeding admirably in your intention. Thank you for making an honest film about people, and not simply the glorification of one man. </p>

<p>Your script for <em>Steve Jobs</em> is distinguishably presented in three acts depicting the moments leading up to three separate product launches that define Jobs’ career –the 1984 launch of the Macintosh, the 88’ NeXT computers launch of the Black Cube, and finally the 98’ launch of the iMac (outlined narratively as failure, redemption, and victory). Like Walter Isaacson’s book, of the same name, and upon which the script is based, <em>Steve Jobs</em> is comprised almost entirely of dialogue. The most intimate conversations Jobs shares with those closest to him; his marketing exec. Joanna, his ex-girlfriend Chrisann, his daughter Lisa, the co-founder of Apple, Steve Wozniak, and of course, the only other CEO – John Sculley. </p>

<p>You had each of these characters confront Jobs with a concern or query during the opening launch. The topics of conversation persist throughout all three acts, cross-cutting between past and present and what could have been. It is through the persistence of these secondary characters, and their inability to be silenced that we as spectators come to learn about the other side of Steve Jobs. You subject the viewer to full disclosure – and apart from the occasional check in with Kate Winslet’s Joanna -  we remain present in the room with Jobs. </p>

<p>You captured the culmination of the film in a moment of truth between Jobs and Wozniak, the final sequence that truly defines the film’s purpose – to acknowledge the Apple 2 team. A request that ‘Woz’ makes and Steve refuses. Thankfully, <em>you</em> didn’t. Your secondary characters are stand-ins for what the “Apple 2 team” represents – characters that shed some light on who Jobs really is, 40 minutes before he steps out on stage. You let us stand and bear witness to the truth, before ethics are engulfed by sleek design, net result and thunderous applause. You have designed the operating system of this film as an <em>open</em> system. We’re given a lot to process, but modifications are condoned. So again, thank you Aaron Sorkin, for finally playing the second version of the same song. </p>

<p><strong>Sincerely,</strong></p>

<p>Matt</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Creed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2015/11/27/creed.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Creed" />
    <published>2015-11-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2015/11/27/creed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>The <em>Rocky</em> universe wouldn’t exist if it wasn’t for you. As an angst-ridden, out-of-work actor in 1976, you created the boxer Rocky Balboa as the ultimate underdog. The first movie was a fluke and almost didn’t happen. That it went on to win multiple Oscars Including Best Picture, then spawned a lucrative and beloved franchise is nothing short of miraculous. </p>

<p>I knew before walking into the theatre to see <em>Creed</em> that I would address this letter to you. How could I not? After successfully bookending the series with the surprisingly satisfying - albeit fantastical - <em>Rocky Balboa</em> in 2006, if <em>Creed</em> failed I could hold you to task for letting the franchise down again (ahem, <em>Rocky V</em>). If <em>Creed</em> was good, I could congratulate you for backing the right horse in director Ryan Coogler, and the right jockey in actor Michael B. Jordan. What I didn’t expect was that after seeing you reprise your role as Rocky that I would genuinely want to address this letter to you, the actor.</p>

<p><em>Creed</em> isn’t just the best <em>Rocky</em> film since the first one, it’s the best Rocky <em>you’ve</em> been in decades. </p>

<p>I’ve made no secret of my love for the <em>Rocky</em> franchise <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html">here before</a>, and of my love of boxing movies in general. My first review for DC&amp;C was of your forgettable <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/12/19/grudge-match.html"><em>Grudge Match</em></a>, a film that left such a foul taste in my mouth, it might be part of why your portrayal of an aged Rocky Balboa is such a revelation. But being a fan of the <em>Rocky</em> movies means accepting certain idiosyncrasies - cheesy dialogue, treacly sentimentality, repetitive montages, and a predictable plot – as part of the deal. This is why <em>Rocky Balboa</em> was such a great film to end the series on, as it eschewed many of the more cringe-inducing moments of the previous five films. But it’s also why I was reluctant to see <em>Creed.</em> I was worried that it would either stick too close to the franchise’s winning but tired formula, or go too far in a new direction and alienate the die-hards.</p>

<p><em>Creed</em> stands on its own, and as a lifelong fan, I am happy to stand behind it.  </p>

<p>We meet Adonis “Donnie” Johnson as a kid who has lost his mother and is stuck in juvie, where he is constantly in trouble for fighting. Donnie is taken in by Mary Anne Creed, widow of World Heavyweight Boxing Champion Apollo Creed, who knows he is the product of her husband’s infidelity. Flashing forward to present day, Donnie, though raised in the lap of luxury, gives up his cushy job to pursue his dream of being a boxer. Not finding anyone willing to train him in L.A., Donnie moves to Philadelphia and convinces Rocky to train him. When word of Donnie’s parentage leaks, he is invited to be the longshot on a ticket fighting against the reigning world champion, “Pretty” Ricky Conlon. </p>

<p>The set-up is a tweak on the original <em>Rocky</em> movie, where you were the unknown in a fight against the champ, except Donnie isn’t broke and fighting for a purse. Like Rocky, he’s fighting because it’s all he knows how to do. Of course there’s a love interest, but unlike your Adrien, Bianca is confident, successful, and determined, which makes her Donnie’s equal. She’s more than just a cheerleader, and it’s a welcome change. Obviously Coogler, who co-wrote the script with Aaron Covington, was careful to keep the spirit of the franchise intact, but he also borrows from one of my other favourite boxing films, <em>The Fighter</em>. Coogler makes the streets of South Philly look almost exactly like they did when you first ran through them in ’76, but he filmsthem like David O. Russell filmedLowell, Massachusetts – the camera constantly moving; the cars, storefronts and faces almost pastiche; the pace rapid-fire but steady; the background subliminally reminding Donnie of where he, and you, came from.</p>

<p>For the fight scenes Coogler cribs a page from Scorsese (but not specifically from <em>Raging Bull</em>, the boxing film upon which all others are measured). In one of the standout scenes, he films the match as one continuous take: through the crowd, into the ring with the corner men, and from Donnie’s POV. For the Big Fight Scene, Coogler follows behind you as you walk to the ring beside Donnie, your hand never leaving his shoulder. Because Coogler knows what we all know; boxing movies are really about relationships. They’re about family. We see it when Donnie puts the fight between Rocky and Apollo up on a big screen TV and shadow boxes his dad. And though it wasn’t as saccharine as <em>Rocky</em> fans are used to, we all know what’s coming – by the end, you’ve become the father Donnie never had. I couldn’t have predicted, though, that you would almost steal the whole movie.</p>

<p>Michael B. Jordon is the perfect fit for Creed, and the two of you have natural chemistry, perhaps because he was written to be more humble than his father. But <em>Creed</em> isn’t just about introducing audiences to a new hero, it’s about giving the old one his due. Even though you’ve owned the character of Rocky for close to four decades, and you wear him as comfortably as Rocky wears his trademark porkpie hat, perhaps you had become <em>too</em> close to him. This is the first <em>Rocky</em> film where you haven’t written your own dialogue, and the writers inject some much needed dimension into the character, which you deliver in spades. Rocky has his own fight here and you make it just as compelling as any he’s had in the ring. Donnie may be the muscle in this film, but you are the heart. </p>

<p>I’d like to end with a prediction, which you should take with a huge grain of salt, because I loved this movie so much so that my judgement might be clouded, but here goes: I predict you might just get an Oscar nom for this role. Think about it, the Academy creams over these kinds of stories, and I’m not just talking about the one up on the screen. If you get nominated for Best Supporting Actor, it would be the first time any actor has been nominated for playing the same character twice, years apart. I’m not saying it would be a lock.  <a href="http://www.indiewire.com/article/2016-oscar-predictions-best-supporting-actor-20150525">So far it looks like</a> you’d be up against some heavy hitters. But who doesn’t love a good underdog story?</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>