<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;While on the surface &lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night&lt;/em&gt; is a vampire story, it seems far more interested in conveying atmosphere and emotion than it does in giving us a traditional narrative experience, and you set up a wonderful shot near the halfway mark of the film that perfectly encapsulates this mission statement. In a completely dialogue free scene, the titular &lt;em&gt;Girl&lt;/em&gt; stands facing away from co-lead Arash as he approaches, then ever-so-slowly turns around and relaxes her head against his chest. It&amp;#39;s a lovely bit of visual storytelling, and says so much more about these characters and what they&amp;#39;re feeling than words could. This one shot makes it perfectly clear that this is a movie about two lonely people finding a connection, however improbable it may be.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have taken the easy route and lent this a film a drab visual style to mirror the despair of living in Bad City, a heavily industrialized wasteland whose residents enjoy varying states of isolation and suffering, choosing either to slip into drug abuse or seek companionship from the wrong sort of people. Though it must be said that the movie isn&amp;#39;t nearly as heavy as all that; it certainly never exploits its characters. Instead, your evocative black-and-white cinematography makes even the mundane and ugly appear beautiful. Which is quite an achievement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curiously absent are the visceral thrills typically associated with this type of genre picture; outside of dispatching one of Bad City&amp;#39;s more loathsome inhabitants, writer/director Ana-Lily Amirpour doesn’t rely on violence to give her story momentum, which, in an age when cinematic thrills come cheaper than ever, is a classy decision that reflects an intent to make &lt;em&gt;Girl&lt;/em&gt; more of a mood piece than a full on horror film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coupled with ingenious costume design that has the Girl&amp;#39;s chador double as both traditional garb and billowing cloak, you work wonders when it comes to lending The Girl a screen presence that feels truly unique and iconic.  Whether it’s a hooded figure slipping in and out of the city&amp;#39;s all-encompassing shadows while stalking her prey, or, in what might be my favourite shot in the film, riding a skateboard down the street with the edges of her chador billowing around her like  a bat’s wings.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I&amp;#39;d be remiss without mentioning how agreeable your camera finds lead actress Sheila Vand. Her remarkable performance runs the gambit from palpable vulnerability to great savagery. She promises to inflict grave harm upon a child if he were to ever stop being a &amp;quot;good little boy&amp;quot;—and we believe her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breathing a new life into a stale sub-genre, &lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night&lt;/em&gt; is being sold as &amp;quot;the first Iranian vampire-western.”  Here&amp;#39;s hoping it won&amp;#39;t be the last.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/2/a-girl-walks-home-alone-at-night.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/2/a-girl-walks-home-alone-at-night.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Focus</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Do you think the &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; production office sent out a secret call sheet on the day you arrived on set reminding the cast and crew to leave their valuables at home? You call yourself a “gentleman thief,” but one can never be too careful. A con artist must cultivate a certain kind of sociopathic charm in order to be successful; a talent for knowing what people secretly want and then giving it to them—or at least delivering the illusion. Pickpocketing, it seems, requires a different set of skills: the ability to blend in, to be simultaneously seen and not seen. You came to fame by pickpocketing President Jimmy Carter’s Secret Service agents, relieving them of the keys to his motorcade. You must have talked a pretty good game, because instead of ending up behind bars, you became a consultant for law enforcement and security agencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that 
the Secret Service and the makers of &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; can agree on at least one thing; clever and charming criminals are a lot of fun to be around. At least for a while. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot of &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; is typically convoluted: veteran con-man Nicky takes neophyte pickpocket Jess under his wing for a multi-million dollar operation during the Super Bowl in New Orleans. Three years later, after hearts and trust have been broken, they meet again in Buenos Aires where Nicky is helping a billionaire Formula One race-car team owner (and Jess’ new boyfriend) cheat his way to a win. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After meeting-cute in a failed “jealous husband” scam, Jess begs Nicky to show her some of his tricks (which are actually yours). As he casually chats with her about the art of pickpocketing, he relieves her of various belongings – a ring, a watch, a wallet – and returns them to her while she watches, dumbfounded. He tells her that the trick is in diverting a mark’s focus, making them see what they want to see. &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; takes this advice to heart. Con/Heist films are best when they (a) don’t take themselves too seriously, and (b) give the audience lots of beautiful things and people to pay attention to. Will Smith’s Nicky is all brooding suaveness in dark bespoke suits, and Margot Robbie’s Jess pops like bubblegum with bright pink dresses and wide-eyed enthusiasm. Their chemistry is palpable, their romance inevitable, but we’re always anticipating the bait and switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve given TED talks on the science behind awareness manipulation and why we’re psychologically wired to want to believe what we see. The pickpocket design you delivered for &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; – specifically the one protracted scene in New Orleans – is certainly exciting to watch. As Nicky’s team introduces Jess to their system, the camera follows a series of expertly executed lifts and boosts as it skims through a crowd of revelers gathered in the streets. Post-scam, the loot is displayed in a satisfying sequence reminiscent of that ode to excess, &lt;em&gt;Lifestyles of the Rich and Famous&lt;/em&gt;: hundreds of Piagets and Rolexes, jeweled rings and necklaces, and piles of money laid out in velvet lined cases. A high-stakes gambling scam during the Super Bowl involving the goofily creeptastic B.D. Wong is particularly nerve-wracking. This pace is exhilarating. But, unfortunately, isn’t sustained throughout this otherwise perfectly fun and funny con-man flick. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the film changes locales to Buenos Aires, it loses some of its lustre, despite the dizzyingly sumptuous backdrop of brightly coloured cars, buildings, and women. It’s only a matter of time before alliances are broken and double-crosses are double-crossed. Up until now, the film could have lifted whatever it wanted from my purse, but, by the end, with only the obvious love story left to hold our attention, my focus was wandering. With some hilarious supporting performances by Gerald McRaney, Adrian Martinez, and the aforementioned Wong, &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; does it’s best to divert our attention from its barely-better-than-average plot twists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left feeling like many of the audience members you’ve amused with your theatrical pickpocketing: it was a harmless good time, and I didn’t mind feeling a little bit cheated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/1/focus.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/1/focus.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Tale Of Princess Kaguya</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It must be a thankless task to try and translate a work so thoroughly drenched in the folklore of a specific culture; because no matter how well you perform, something will be inevitably lost. There is no way to transmit the fundamental conceits that underpin the whole of the narrative. To do that would require a lifetime of work for both you and the audience. However, even if what you managed is a lesser work than the original, it still shines very brightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Tale Of Princess Kaguya,&lt;/em&gt; an animated film from Studio Ghibli, is a beautiful, meandering film. Like much of traditional Japanese cinema, it is least troubled with pacing and plot. Tone and mood are the primary concerns here. The animation is loose and seemingly naturalistic, the score is haunting and subtle and the dialogue is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inherently pastoral film &lt;em&gt;The Tale of Princess Kaguya&lt;/em&gt; expresses a love of nature and a thoughtful examination of the cycles of birth and death. The sometimes misguided aspirations that parents force on their children is also one of the central themes, as well as a lot of gentle nudging about greed and social posturing and the often ridiculous pomp that props up rigidly defined class systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choices that director Isao Takahata makes (he also directed &lt;em&gt;Grave of the Fireflies&lt;/em&gt;, one of the most appallingly effective anti-war films I have ever seen) to tell a story so filled with myth and the supernatural are at the heart of its effectiveness. Compared to almost any animated film these days &lt;em&gt;The Tale Of Princess Kaguya&lt;/em&gt; is noteworthy for it’s complete lack of visual pyrotechnics. This is a simple story told simply. The magic is in how that becomes so affecting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole film is less a fable and more a series of metaphoric observations about some pretty universal concerns. What is truly valuable in life? Is it possible to be yourself as a young person and not disappoint your parents? Mostly though there is no lesson other than we are all variable creatures with many flaws and some strengths. Life is often filled with meaningless obligation and trivial strife so the moments of joy are inevitably tinged with melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that seems trite it is only because I am failing in the translation. How the film evokes these sweeping, universal themes is earthy and quiet and utterly lacking in pretension. There is both a quiet joy and a pervasive sadness that every frame of this film somehow transmits. Part of this comes from the animation. The figures are simple and expressive and move with grace and elegance (except when they shouldn’t). The background art is exquisite, seamlessly reinforcing or contrasting whatever is happening in the foreground without drawing attention to itself. That it seems hand drawn is not just a stubborn adherence to tradition but a calculated, aesthetic choice that underlines the rustic slant of the whole project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Tale Of Princess Kaguya&lt;/em&gt; is an art house film in the best sense of the word. It requires engagement on the part of the audience and the capacity to let go of your preconceptions about what a story is and how it can be told, but it rewards those efforts with a film that was truly beautiful and moving. Long-winded and meandering in a very Japanese way, the payoff is nonetheless extraordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite what must be countless moments that simply don’t line up with my Western sensibilities and background this film and your translation of it connected with something fundamental in me. Studio Ghibli is perhaps the single most able advocate of a kind of honest reverence for the natural world that I can think of, and you captured that reverence beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/26/the-tale-of-princess-kaguya.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/26/the-tale-of-princess-kaguya.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The DUFF</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed since I was in high school. Back in 2000, my “unique” ability to use editing software packed a real punch to my student campaign videos. With the help of a few spinning graphics – KAPOW! I was Batman. I even had a Robin: that slightly awkward friend recruited to make me seem cool. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, a DUFF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term isn’t mainstream and probably never will be. As an acronym (Designated Ugly Fat Friend), it’s far too front-and-center in all the film’s marketing to ever gain true cultural traction (or a pornographic sub-genre) the way MILF did after &lt;em&gt;American Pie&lt;/em&gt;. But damn if you and the filmmakers don’t try. Through playful graphics, you literally spell out the word (and countless other things) for people throughout the film. Everything is given the early iMovie treatment, with tweets, texts, and imaginary fireworks splashed all over the screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder I dug it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mae Whitman also helps, completely owning her starring role as the sub-sexy, totally approachable, literal girl-next-door. Her chiseled neighbour, played by Robbie Amell, is a jackass jock and childhood friend who gets recruited to give her the &lt;em&gt;She’s All That&lt;/em&gt; hair-shake transformation. The story and stock characters continue to evoke every teen comedy ever made since the 80s, right up to the advertising that tells us &lt;em&gt;The DUFF&lt;/em&gt; is this generation’s &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; (as your graphics stress). And yeah, it might be. Not by redefining anything, but simply by being funny, confident, and accessible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the DUFF of teen movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in a world where geeks and geek-culture &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;does rule the world, that’s not an insult. The more Whitman’s character gets humiliated throughout the film, the more we love her. The “attack ad” videos created by the resident school hottie are complete with auto-tuning and slow-motion – the special sauce of many embarrassment-enhancing viral videos. But it’s the moments when the film doesn’t try to be era-specific that really work. We know exactly where everything is going (the prom), what’s going to happen (a big kiss), and who’s going to end up with who (duh), but be damned if I wasn’t rooting for it all to happen anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flare you added was nice, but it’s not what makes the film shine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/25/the-duff.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/25/the-duff.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Birdman&#39;s Win is Bad News for TIFF</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;So you lost another potential feather in your cap. Big deal, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, yes, it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years now, the Toronto International Film Festival’s identity has been built around launching “important Oscar films” to the world. It started around 1999, when &lt;em&gt;American Beauty&lt;/em&gt; claimed top prize at both the Oscars and TIFF. The next year, &lt;em&gt;Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon&lt;/em&gt; was the people’s choice winner and a Best Picture nominee. This hot streak went cool until 2008’s &lt;em&gt;Slumdog&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Millionaire&lt;/em&gt;. That’s when things got serious. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danny Boyle himself &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.torontosun.com/2014/08/08/tiff-2014-a-look-back-at-the-festivals-biggest-champions&quot;&gt;credited the TIFF award&lt;/a&gt; with saving &lt;em&gt;Slumdog&lt;/em&gt; from a straight-to-DVD release, and unfortunately (if not understandably) the praise went straight to your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year you position yourself as the ideal launching pad for films that hit the sweet-spot between critical and popular appeal. And you aren’t wrong. Every TIFF People’s Choice award winner since &lt;em&gt;Slumdog&lt;/em&gt; has either been nominated or won the Best Picture Oscar (save 2011’s out-of-nowhere and never-heard-from-again &lt;em&gt;Where Do We Go Now?&lt;/em&gt;). But it’s getting harder and harder to claim any pride in those victories—especially when films like &lt;em&gt;The King’s Speech&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;12 Years a Slave&lt;/em&gt; played to most of America’s top critics in Telluride before you were able to debut them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year seems to be proving the point. Your 2014 winner, &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, lived up to the promise with a Best Picture nomination, but just couldn’t gather enough steam to be a break-out hit (with either critics or the public). Instead, &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; swooped in and took Oscar’s top prize. Or, as you probably remember it, the film that everyone at TIFF lamented they couldn’t see because it had opened the Venice Film Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s the problem. Critics, studio reps, and sales agents can only earmark so many festivals each year. Without the prestige of Cannes, bustling market of Berlin, caché of Venice, or discovery-factor of Sundance, you have always struggled to find a true identity. So you’ve opted for size and spectacle, becoming “the people’s festival” where the city’s diverse population stands in for the tastes of the world. But in that big, generic label, you’re getting lost in the shuffle—especially when so many other festivals are doing a better job of launching big films into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sundance has been the biggest success story of the past few years by developing both breakout directors and seasoned visionaries through films like &lt;em&gt;Beasts of the Southern Wild&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Whiplash,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;. The Sundance Labs are also proving to be breading ground of talent, where producers can get an early peek at rising stars. Venice and Telluride are also a more appealing film going experience for critics, curating manageable schedules which prominently feature each of the 20-odd titles (as opposed to the hundreds that play at TIFF).  And then Cannes. Well...it’s Cannes. Even after holding a whole months-long exhibit dedicated solely to the work of David Cronenberg, Toronto’s prodigal son took his latest film &lt;em&gt;Maps to the Stars&lt;/em&gt; to La Croisette for its premiere instead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you blame him, though? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than ever, festivals matter. This year, every film nominated for Best Picture premiered at a film festival (compared to &lt;a href=&quot;http://variety.com/2015/film/news/2015-academy-awards-analysis-87th-oscars-who-won-1201440039/&quot;&gt;60-80% in the past five years&lt;/a&gt;). The battle lines are no longer just drawn between studios, but savvy programmers from Cannes, New York, Venice, Sundance, and Telluride. The days when a film could sneak overseas and surprise audiences in North America are over. Online reviews make a film’s reputation, and, for better or worse, it’s virtually set in stone after the first premiere (even if it’s hidden from the public in the high altitudes of Colorado or canals of Venice). You know this all too well, which is why your artistic director, Cameron Bailey, implemented the controversial first weekend rule of TIFF, creating a two-tier status between Toronto world premieres and first-time Toronto screenings.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might have to take things even further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s going to be hard to argue that playing hardball has paid off in the first year, but you’re going to need to do something more than just pack theatres to make a splash in the film world. With the New York Film Festival taking more and more titles every year, Tribeca finding a groove, SXSW becoming a hub of innovation, and a slew of other festivals carving out niches, the “people’s festival” needs to do more than play the imitation game with Oscar winners if it wants to remain important.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2015 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/24/birdmans-win-is-bad-news-for-tiff.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/24/birdmans-win-is-bad-news-for-tiff.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Still Alice</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was curious to see how they would do it. How would the filmmakers of &lt;em&gt;Still Alice&lt;/em&gt; show the audience what it feels like to have early-onset Alzheimer’s? How would we understand Alice’s fear and confusion when she begins to lose her memories? How would they visualize the details of her life as they flicker in and out of focus? They did it simply, eloquently—and quite literally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty year-old Alice Howland is out for a run on the campus of Columbia University, where she works as a linguistics professor, when suddenly she realizes that she has no idea where she is. It comes as a frightening shock to her (but not to us, since we’re waiting for the tell-tale signs of her disease to appear). What was once familiar – buildings, the quad, a staircase – suddenly appear to her as fuzzy, abstract splotches. As the camera pans to face her, she is shown in sharp relief against her fading reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s is an ugly disease. My grandmother, who lived with us for most of my life, suffered from it. And so did we. It’s a disease that significantly affects the family. I was particularly interested in how &lt;em&gt;Still Alice&lt;/em&gt; would deal with the hopelessness of watching a once competent and highly respected woman regress to a helpless, child-like state. I was worried that using a beautiful, relatively young actress as our window into this world would diminish the disease, giving it it that Vaseline-lensed sheen that makes these types of unpleasant stories palatable to the masses. And it would have been a complete wash, if you – and we – had anyone less skilled than Julianne Moore to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your relationship with actors is surprisingly intimate. In many ways, they are acting just for you. With every take you have to execute your duties flawlessly by keeping the actor perfectly in focus. The audience’s attention is automatically drawn to a sharper image, but as Alice’s focus is diminished, it’s the soft, faded edges of her world that draw us in. Julianne Moore appears in nearly every scene, and often the camera focuses on her face as she struggles to remember words or people or places. It’s a performance that works hard to defy the stereotype of the “beautiful lead with a terminal illness” trope; after all, this is an illness that we rarely see onscreen, and never before portrayed so fearlessly and without self-pity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the many things the film teaches us is that Alzheimer’s is impervious to time. So we’re not sure how long it takes for Alice to slip away from herself. But you give us some clues. Before she is diagnosed, the camera is almost always fixed on her face. As the disease takes hold and Alice must let go of the life she once had, the camera follows her – through the Columbia library, or when she goes out for a run – like a proxy for her memories, trying desperately to catch up to her, but always falling short. Seasons pass; leaves change colours and fall, leaving branches bare; Alice and her husband John embrace on a rock by the ocean, the bokeh effect around them evoking a tender melancholy; flares bounce off the snowbanks that butt up against their brownstone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all very pretty. &lt;em&gt;Too&lt;/em&gt; pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Still Alice&lt;/em&gt; blurs the line between wanting to authentically portray the effects Alzheimer’s has on the patient and the family, and trying to soften the truth for those unable to handle the grim reality a disease like this presents. When it gets it right, it feels like a sharp punch to the gut. But when it errs on the side of restraint it edges dangerously into Movie of the Week territory. Thankfully, Julianne Moore’s powerful performance rescues these latter moments from their maudlin potential. Having been a renowned professor, she is invited to give a speech to an audience of Alzheimer’s patients and doctors. When the camera pans to the faces of people in the audience slow clapping with tears in their eyes, I nearly laughed at such a tired cliché. But earlier, when Alice laments that she wishes she had cancer because at least she wouldn’t feel so ashamed, I cried, because, having dealt with both diseases, I know how painfully true that statement is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alice’s situation – surrounded by a loving family, in a gorgeous New York brownstone and ocean-side summer home, nary a medical bill in sight – is not representative of the reality for most Alzheimer’s patients. But the conflict between Alice and her youngest daughter Lydia is familiar to anyone who has struggled with parental disapproval, and is refreshingly sugar-free. Kristen Stewart’s trademark mumbling is welcome here as Lydia and Alice are faced with an abrupt reversal of roles. This is when the film shifts from being a story about Alice to one about the people she is leaving behind. The difficult choices and daily frustrations an Alzheimer’s family faces is worthy of its own film, and though it takes up minimal space here, it is handled deftly and with dignity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Still Alice&lt;/em&gt;, takes an uncomfortable topic and wraps it in an easy-to-swallow format; a beautiful woman, pretty surroundings, and a happy-ish ending. Unlike the far superior 2012 Cannes Palme D’or Winner &lt;em&gt;Amour&lt;/em&gt;, which tackles similar subject matter but without the soft-focus pretense, &lt;em&gt;Still Alice&lt;/em&gt; aims for mass appeal. As a family member of an Alzheimer’s patient, I realize the importance of awareness, so I don’t necessarily think mass appeal is such a bad thing. And yet, as heartbreakingly amazing as Julianne Moore is in this film (as evidenced by her shiny, new Oscar), her performance still pales in comparison to the gutting brilliance of &lt;em&gt;Amour&lt;/em&gt;’s Emmanuelle Riva (who lost the Best Actress Oscar to Jennifer Lawrence a few years ago). But I guess Julianne Moore wasting away before our eyes gets more butts in seats than an old, naked, scared French lady played by an actress no one has heard of. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all about perspective, and no one knows that better than you do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/24/still-alice.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/24/still-alice.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Timbuktu</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I will admit I knew next to nothing about Timbuktu prior to seeing Abderrahmane Sissako’s film. For me, it was just the place the evil butler tried to send the kittens in &lt;em&gt;The Aristocats&lt;/em&gt;. I certainly had no idea about its past as a hub of Islamic language and culture. I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; remember when it was briefly taken over by the Maghreb arm of al Qaeda, which brings us to the events depicted in the film. All I knew going in was that it was about a town that gets taken over by jihadist militants. I was expecting it to be brutal and depressing. What I saw instead was a beautifully crafted portrayal of life under extremist control. I knew a bit about the Big News Story of occupation and liberation, but the film gave me a closer look at the smaller picture (which I think might be the more important one), and the ways in which people confront the loss of the smallest freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central plot follows Kidane, a guitar-strumming cattle herder and his family who live peacefully in the desert, beyond the reach of the militants. Of course, they don’t &lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt; beyond that reach for very long. While Kidane and his family are the heart of the narrative, the rest of the characters are every bit as compelling, even those who are only in one or two scenes. Though we don’t see more than a couple of brief moments in their lives, they stayed with me long after the film ended. Your long takes and frequent use of close-ups afforded the actors near-total command of my attention, from the girl glaring in sullen defiance at members of a Sharia tribunal, to the misery and regret on the face of a young jihadist as he briefly recalls his former life as an aspiring rapper. I say &lt;em&gt;near&lt;/em&gt;-total command of my attention because I can’t ignore the profound impact the film’s other visual and stylistic elements had on me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a film about people rebelling at every opportunity, from the subtlest of expressions to outright defiance, against the constraints forced upon them. I feel like you were in lock step with these many tiny rebellions. The militants in the film spend a lot of time droning on and on about everything that is forbidden, and it’s a long bloody list. But for every forbidden pleasure, we see a character indulging in it. And you aid and abet the townsfolk by infusing each shot with colour and beauty. No bright clothing allowed? Boom - voodoo priestess parading through town in vivid blues and reds with a pet chicken and zero fucks given. Football is forbidden? Cut to kids joyfully kicking an imaginary ball around. No music allowed? Secret midnight jam session captured with a sense of intimacy and romance that would most certainly not fly with the ‘Chef Djihadiste’. Not everyone gets away with their acts of defiance, and here we see the kind of cruelty of which the jihadists are capable. Mercifully, you don’t dwell on these images. We all know how brutal their ‘justice’ is. We don’t need to see it play out in any detail. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film uses a gentle yet unyielding touch in underscoring the absurdity of the jihadists’ attitudes and actions. That it also uses humour to this end was surprising, and one of the things that makes &lt;em&gt;Timbuktu&lt;/em&gt; unique. There are moments of flat-out mocking - I noticed you frequently had a donkey wander in and out of the shot whenever the jihadists approached. Well played. But there are also moments of softer derision that treat their targets with grace and empathy. ‘Jihadist doing tai chi in a trance’ isn’t something I ever thought I would see, and it makes no sense at all. It’s ridiculous and we all have a good laugh at his expense because (in the words of my companion),“fuck that guy”, but it is also one of the most serene and beautiful moments in the entire film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the film isn’t all that optimistic. French and Malian forces would drive the jihadists out within a year, but I couldn’t help thinking about all the other places and people who continue to struggle under the control of Islamist extremists. You could have easily clubbed us over the head with the mindless cruelty and destruction wrought by such groups but I, for one, am glad you chose to go with a hopeful reminder that while extremist ideology may exert control over one’s body, the spirit puts up one hell of a fight. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Two Days, One Night</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;“Too slow” is a complaint I often overhear when leaving a theatre after a film. “Nothing really &lt;em&gt;happens&lt;/em&gt;” is another. I heard both immediately after seeing Jean Pierre and Luc Dardenne’s &lt;em&gt;Two Days, One Night&lt;/em&gt;. I didn’t say anything, but had I chosen to stop and drop some film geek wisdom on that total stranger, I would have pushed my glasses up the bridge of my nose and informed him that the film’s slow pace and deceptively simple plot actually complement an ambivalent, complicated narrative that unfolds far quicker than they realized. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One Friday evening, factory worker Sandra is informed that she is to be laid off. Her boss grants her one last chance to save her job; She is given the weekend to convince her colleagues to vote for her to remain at the factory, the catch being that in doing so they must forego their own bonuses. Faced with her family’s financial ruin and battling her clinical depression with some highly inadvisable over-medicating, Sandra spends her weekend calling on each of her co-workers, pleading for their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if viewed as a simple character study, the film is well worth the price of admission. Marion Cotillard makes it impossible to take your eyes off Sandra, even when you feel compelled to look away, as though that would somehow spare her the slightest amount of shame and humiliation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as I said before, there is so much more going on. You set a pace that matches Sandra’s demeanor at the outset of the film: somnambulistic and hesitant. However, it allows us to really feel Sandra’s desperation build. Given the episodic feel to Sandra’s encounters with her co-workers, a more rapid or frenetic pacing would have made the plot feel repetitive quite quickly. Instead, there is a cushion of time in between plot points that allow the viewer to contemplate the film’s bigger questions and issues; Between Sandra and her colleagues, some in even more dire circumstances than hers, who is more deserving? What is the likelihood that Sandra keeping her job will mean someone else losing theirs? What kind of shitty boss pits his staff against each other like that?! How would &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; vote? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the heavy political concerns raised by the film, I wouldn’t have been surprised if you had gone for a more hard-hitting, crowd-stirring approach in the editing room. But this is a Dardenne Brothers film, not &lt;em&gt;Les Miserables&lt;/em&gt;. Come Monday morning, Sandra will either get to keep her job—by now a hollow victory—or be turned out by her peers. She will not find her inner Norma Rae, and there will be no “I am Spartacus” moment right before the vote. Instead, you allow the highs and lows of the plot to gently flow into an elegant and poignant conclusion, as though you shared my need to see Sandra retain or regain at least a modicum of dignity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/19/two-days-one-night.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/19/two-days-one-night.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Kingsmen: The Secret Service</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You have achieved an unenviable immortality since your ignominious passing., haven’t you? The last thing I was expecting when I walked into the theatre to watch Matthew Vaughn’s &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; was a vicious skewering of your Ubermensch John Galt. But given how much philosophical cover you have afforded the latest iteration of morally challenged free marketers I suppose I shouldn’t be entirely surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there it was, that skewering splattered across the screen—from the remote island filled with the elite movers and shakers to the class-consciousness that fills almost every frame of this movie. &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; is informed by every James Bond joint that Roger Moore ever made —coupled with a Picketty-like critique and the idea that a Gentleman (or Gentlewoman) is made, not born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all there, plus some of the old Ultraviolence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samuel L. Jackson might seem to be an odd avatar for &lt;a href=&quot;about:blank&quot;&gt;John Galt&lt;/a&gt;, with his lisp and Flavor Flav fashion sense, but in all ways that matter he is a note perfect melding of a James Bond megalomaniac and the fatuous ideal of your Objectivist ethos.  Both are equally cartoonish, in their conception and motivations, and the combination works remarkably well within the confines of Vaughn’s surreal, amped up world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaughn himself seems particularly scattershot with his chosen targets. It is a laundry list of the unpleasant and woefully mislead. Religious fundamentalists, the lads down the pub, Old Money types and Venture Capitalists as well as brutal climbers like Michael Caine, who is so eager to eradicate any trace of his humble beginnings that he gleefully subverts his life’s work to maintain the Kingsman’s class driven purity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also some confusion about what exactly is appropriate as an object of aspiration. Is it excellence? Power? Sexual Conquest? Saville Row smoothness? All of the above? But it is a glorious kind of manic confusion and Vaughn and the remarkably strong cast make it work eighty-five percent of the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Firth was a happy surprise, a kind of Henry Higgins with a bulletproof umbrella and a remarkable facility for all sorts of ruckus. The set piece that features him annihilating an entire Jesus Camp-type Congregation was a personal favorite. Vaughn does Guy Ritchie slow motion progressions far better than Guy Ritchie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the truly retrograde artifacts of &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; is its sexual politics. Women are either the competent and emasculating nemesis, vague paragons of virtue or simply a sexual reward. Here Vaughn seems stuck in the Old Bond trope most purely. This is a film about men and their various ticks and affectations. And in the same way that the Moore Bond films were Walter Mitty-level fantasies about urbane, smoove talking killers this film seems entirely comfortable inhabiting the same conceit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film sits squarely on the shoulders of its young protagonist, played with a remarkable depth and confidence by Taron Egerton. Eggsy is a lad from a Council Estate (the British equivalent of inner city projects) the kind of Public Housing that your adherents see as ground zero for all the ills of socialist parasitism. That he is the eventual architect of the demise of the Galt-clone is both pointed and surprisingly satisfying. I usually don’t care for these kind of simplistic revenge fantasies but Vaughn managed to target most of my personal peeves so well, and with a kind of nasty wit, that I enjoyed this movie thoroughly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose in a lot of ways this is the perfect film to put the final nail in your coffin. A chimera that meanders all over the map with a kind of pyrotechnic competence anchored by the inimitable Mark Strong: a working class Scotsman who, in the end, sides with the slightly anarchic kids as they summarily execute the 1% that you fetishized so slavishly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is to ludicrous and enjoyable confections that put you in your place, Ayn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/17/kingsmen-the-secret-service.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/17/kingsmen-the-secret-service.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>5 Radical Ways to Rejuvenate the Oscars</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Academy,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look, I know the Academy Awards are not a public institution, bound by oversight committees, regulatory reforms, and never-ending calls to accountability. But they might as well be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t missed an Oscar telecast since I was 10 years old – back when I insisted Spielberg &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to “finally win for &lt;em&gt;Schindler’s List&lt;/em&gt;, dammit” (so what if I hadn’t seen the film?). Like millions of people, that unreasonable sense of ownership, outrage and interest has never changed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor, I think, would you want it to. That we the people care enough to complain is a testament to your cultural relevance (and, by extension, economic well-being). The Grammy’s only &lt;em&gt;wish&lt;/em&gt;people were passionate enough to nitpick changes to Album/Record/Song of the Year awards. So please, read on with an open mind. No one is asking you to throw out the&lt;em&gt;Million Dollar Baby&lt;/em&gt; with the bath water, but here’s a few ways you can stay on top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Eliminate Male/Female Actor Distinctions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a biggie, and it would be revolutionary. But it shouldn’t be. Like all affirmative actions, the idea of having male and female actors compete for different awards is rooted in good intentions. It’s also a sign of progress when their time has passed. Yes, women’s roles have historically been paltry compared to their male counterparts. Actually, you can (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiewire.com/article/sorry-ladies-study-on-women-in-film-and-television-confirms-the-worst-20150210?utm_campaign=sorry-ladies-study-on-women-in-film-and-television-confirms-the-worst-20150210&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=Facebook&amp;amp;utm_content=sorry-ladies-study-on-women-in-film-and-television-confirms-the-worst-20150210&quot;&gt;quite easily&lt;/a&gt;) argue that not much has changed – except each year when ten famous actresses and supporting actresses get to pretend like all is well in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt; A single Best Actor (Male or Female) award would change the conversation about how women are portrayed in films. We could finally compare characters to characters, instead of pretending that acting is like a sport where men have some sort of physiological advantage. To ease the transition, I would earmark three nomination slots for men and three for women – but only have one winner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead. Imagine it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“Men and women don’t compete for the same roles! It doesn’t make sense!”&lt;/em&gt;  Really? Tell that to Tilda Swinton (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), Angela Bassett (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/22/olympus-has-fallen.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Olympus Has Fallen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), Angelina Jolie (&lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jul/22/entertainment/la-et-salt-20100722&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), or any number of other actresses who have had to win roles away from men. Moreover, do you think Tom Hanks could have auditioned for &lt;em&gt;Ray&lt;/em&gt;, or Jamie Foxx was considered for &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;? Malarkey! We don’t divide awards by race, and we shouldn’t by sex. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acting is acting, period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Divide Fictional/Biographical Acting Awards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; Remember back when I said acting is acting, period? Yeah, about that... You Academy voters have an unnatural obsession with rewarding actors who portray real-life people. To wit: 7 of the past 10 male actor winners and 8 of the past 15 female actor winners have played characters based on real people. This year alone, 4 of the 5 Best (Male) Actor nominations are for biographical roles. It’s getting a bit silly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt;If nothing else, having separate character categories would keep the acting races more interesting. But it would also draw more attention to the craft of communicating human emotion rather than mimicking mannerisms. Of course that’s reductionist and not always the case. There’s a lot to be said for evoking the spirit of a real noteworthy individual – even ones who aren’t well-known to the public (like Ron Woodroof from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/19/dallas-buyers-club.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dallas Buyers Club&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). But it should be a separate category. For your sake, if not ours. Bonus: it would also fill the two empty categories (main and supporting) you’ll have when you eliminate the male/female acting distinction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“Just because a character is based on a real-life person doesn’t change the actor’s craft. And where do you draw the line with ancient historical figures?”&lt;/em&gt; Great question! As you know, it’s one that the Writer’s branch of the Academy has been dealing with forever. And that’s your answer: if writing has to be divided into “original” and “adapted” screenplays for having even a whiff of source material origins, then the same staunch logic should apply to actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Create an Award for Best Stunts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea&lt;/strong&gt;: Big budget, tent-pole films are the only thing holding Hollywood studios together. Scale of spectacle is often what justifies the theatrical experience, so it’s high time that one of the last unheralded departments of the industry – the one that often shines in these types of films – finally gets their turn in the spotlight. They’re literally putting their lives on the line to provide people a fleeting moment of entertainment. I think they’ve earned it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result&lt;/strong&gt;: Everyone has, at one point, complained about digital effects “looking fake”, which too often diminishes the emotional stakes on screen. However, people can’t get enough of the thrilling skyscraper sequences from movies like &lt;em&gt;Mission Impossible: Ghost Protocol&lt;/em&gt;, or the gritty realism of fight scenes in movies like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raid 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Great stunts are still being performed, but they’re too often eclipsed by a digital revolution that takes away as much credit as it absorbs blame. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;There’s not enough industry support for a Best Stunts category. It was voted down just&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/race/academy-votes-creating-oscar-category-202123&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;back in 2011&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt; Like outlier sports that have to earn their way into the Olympics, it’s normal for old establishments to resist change. Heck, it wasn’t until 1981 that you guys even had an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/12/12/the-make-up-of-2012-pt-1.html&quot;&gt;award for Best Make-Up&lt;/a&gt;. But it’s not too late to right an old wrong – and, at the same time, get people more excited about the art of filmmaking. That’s the point of this whole thing, isn’t it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Turn the Best Foreign Language Film Category into a World Cup-style tournament&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; This category should be a major prize, and not a clandestine sideshow. Currently, each country (via a closed committee) submits one film for consideration. Then, all the submissions (around 80) are cut down to a shortlist of nine, before five nominees are selected. That secondary step of selecting nominees from a shortlist was recently revamped, but only at a procedural level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a way to get people around the world much more involved, right from the start: borrow the format of the World Cup. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt; Dividing countries into pools who compete against one-another to advance to the next round would not only bring awareness to a greater number of films, but get the public watching more foreign content. The pools would be statistically weighted (based on previous award wins and whatever else), but a film would need to pass three or four rounds before being a nominee. The decision would still rest in the hands of the Academy, but the public could be along for the ride, and hopefully have access to screenings as the process happens, just like a sporting event.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“No way, it will only draw attention to an already contentious process – not to mention the difficulty of arranging distribution rights for all the films around the world”&lt;/em&gt;. Oh, stop it with your facts and reality. Think big: a public tournament format of narrowing down the films would go a long way for gaining exposure and interest in this award, and all the associated films (not just the winner). Sure it’s more work, but also more reward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Remodel Academy Membership&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; People have complained about your “steak eater” membership for years, and this year’s #OscarsSoWhite campaign drew enormous attention to the lack of diversity in your ranks. So how do you address this issue, without advocating tokenism or lowering the bar to membership? I can’t believe I’m saying this, but you might have to take a page from the Canadian Senate, or UN Security Council: setting term limits on appointed members and/or rotating voting powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt; It takes many people the better part of their career to be invited into the Academy, so it’s hard to begrudge its older skewing demographics. Yet begrudge we do, and this membership remodelling won’t just transform your statistics, but get you in touch with a younger audience (ie. increase TV ratings). Rather than the current opt-out policy, capping term limits and/or rotating voting years would ensure a diversity of worthy voices get a chance. Moreover, you could have an established number of permanent members in each branch (like the Security Council), but by allocating a fixed number of permanent spots, you could avoid the full-on death watch for new spots to open up in the current membership-for-life model.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“People work hard to join the Academy – it’s unfair to take that away.”&lt;/em&gt; The new focus should aim to recruit the best members in the industry, not just lifetime achievers or friends of insiders.  Fixed terms would mean people have to stay working hard to keep membership, and as a result, have one more motivation to create more great films. Change like this would add legitimacy to the Academy, not take it away. Plus, it’s not like fewer stars would show up to the Oscars – you’ve been to the Golden Globes, right? Only 90 foreign journalists vote for those, and it’s the second biggest award show in town. Your membership credibility isn’t going anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/16/5-radical-ways-to-rejuvenate-the-oscars.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/16/5-radical-ways-to-rejuvenate-the-oscars.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
