<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Seriously, Birdman is the Best Film of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Fellow Critics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching &lt;em&gt;Birdman (or The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance)&lt;/em&gt; is like watching a sparrow navigate the interior of a building. It is an agitating, beautiful, visceral experience. There is a tension inherent to something that lives one wrong choice away from utter disaster every second of its 119 minutes of life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alejandro González Iñárritu’s fifth feature film is a construction overrun with masculine virtues. Brash and loud, egoistic, childish in its impetuousness, and more ambitious than it is prudent, you careen along its narrow corridors, barely allowed a moment to breathe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a film that lives or dies on its technical virtuosity, brilliant performances, and its foundation is a narrative that allows for multiple, but equally viable, interpretations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That it works on any level is as much luck as intention. And that is the wonder of it. To see that kind of ambitious overreach, to see a whole company of players risk a kind of &lt;em&gt;Death To Smoochy II&lt;/em&gt; (I’m talking specifically to Ed Norton here) and come out the other side is a rarity—especially these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are living in a time where risk-averse bean counters have become cultural gatekeepers. So we often end up with the movie equivalent of pyramid building—overwrought structures that have no discernible value other than to make people crane their necks. But people will pay and pay and pay to stare at a monument to nothing simply because we are so easily amused. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of filmmaking—the Christopher Nolan-Joss Whedon-Michael Bay School, for lack of a better label—is a specific peeve of Iñárritu’s and something that both he and his characters hyperbolically reject as “cultural genocide”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet this film is anything but a scold, despite the amount of time and dialogue the characters spend trying to justify their art or condemn those that don’t understand it. There is a wonderful scene where Keaton’s character, Riggan Thomson, and the platonic ideal of a theatre critic, played by Lindsay Duncan, engage in a bar. Keaton gets up a head of steam and what follows is an eloquent, beautifully constructed monologue about the absolute ballsiness of getting on a stage and risking that most precious and fragile of human appendages, the ego. This is quickly followed by a terse description of how critics could well be the lowest form of life to ever crawl from the ooze. It is a beautiful, almost transcendent moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that Duncan (an actress that &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; get at least half of the roles that Meryl Streep ends up in) skewers both Riggan and his pretensions with one brief observation about the vast distance between his ambitions and his reality. This is the true beauty of the work; it continually expresses the paradox of how the whole is greater than the sum of its parts. How a facile, spiritually bereft man-child can somehow create a moment of beauty, an instant of real honesty, even as he continues to destroy himself and every significant relationship he has ever had. The fact that the apex of Riggan’s creative life, both critically and as an artist, is largely the result of a single, darkly pitched failure simply underlines that truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some obvious parallels to the lives of the principals involved and that is also more a truth than it is simply a narrative construction. Keaton and Norton’s career arcs are nothing new. The sell out and the unmanageable but god-touched &lt;em&gt;enfant terrible&lt;/em&gt; are well-worn archetypes but they exist as templates because they are so accurate to life. Iñárritu himself has been accused of flagrant pretensions and as a purveyor of “the theatre of the miserable”—accusations which he seems to accept and acknowledge as true. But he makes a strong case that those very negative attributes are as essential to the creative process as discipline, or talent, or even inspiration. &lt;em&gt;Birdman (or The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance)&lt;/em&gt; is the concrete example of that thesis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything about it, from the faux continuous shot, to the merging of the surreal and hyperreal, even the expansive and talky script demarcate an ego that truly believes it has something useful to say to the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iñárritu requires a level of engagement that few directors dare ask of an audience. Because it is set in a world of magic realist physics its value is mediated by your ability and willingness to engage with its themes. The piece requires your active participation to function properly. And to add to Iñárritu’s presumption, the last five minutes of this film is essentially a cinematic Rorschach test—what you make of it says far more about you than anything else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iñárritu risks everything on his ability to draw you into this confusing, fragmented world and make you care enough about characters that are flawed in the most banal ways. Neither monsters nor saints, every character (with the serene exception of Amy Ryan as Riggan’s ex) is barely hanging on by their fingernails in a narrative that manages to speak to something larger than any one person’s sad little story. Instead of providing a cathartic dénouement, Iñárritu offers you something that is either profoundly tragic, starkly redemptive, or simply an end. It all depends on you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that and many other reasons: the score, the astonishing cinematography, even the bleak laughter it sometimes elicits, &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(or The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance)&lt;/em&gt; should claim the title of best film of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/8/seriously-birdman-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/8/seriously-birdman-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Actually, Wild is the Best Film of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Fellow Critics, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grudge Match&lt;/em&gt; was the last film I saw in 2013 and the first film I reviewed for Dear Cast and Crew. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the last film I saw in 2014, and the first film I reviewed in 2015. *&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was more excited to see &lt;em&gt;Grudge Match&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a sucker for an underdog story, especially a boxing one, but what disappointed me most wasn’t the hackneyed narrative or the phoned-in performances (both of which I expected). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/12/19/grudge-match.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grudge Match&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was just so blatantly misogynistic and homophobic that it was almost satire. A dude-bro recruitment film. I left the theatre feeling cheated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; already had a strike against it when I heard that it had been adapted from an Oprah Book Club pick, a memoir by a woman who walked 1100 miles of the gruelling Pacific Crest Trail alone. I steeled myself for treacly sentimentality and faux-earnest narration over an Enya-heavy soundtrack. I apologized in advance to my sci-fi-loving husband who would much rather have been watching &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But from the first few moments that Reese Witherspoon appeared onscreen, bleeding and swearing, I was captivated. Humbled, even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike my esteemed colleague Christopher, I did not see 200 films in 2014. I didn’t see 100. I doubt I even saw 50. This has less to do with the state of modern cinema and more to do with the fact that I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; dislike going to the theatre unless I absolutely have to. I’m always the first member of the DCAC crew to volunteer to watch a screener from the comfort of my couch. Based on the paltry number of films I saw in 2014, it may not even be fair for me to weigh in on which one was the best. But I can make an argument for why &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; was the most important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent almost fifteen years watching movies professionally, but rarely do I watch them for myself. Every once in a while a film manages to sneak past my critical gaze and move me, not just as a critic, but as an individual. &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Diving Bell and the Butterfly&lt;/em&gt; are some recent examples. &lt;em&gt;C.R.A.Z.Y.&lt;/em&gt;, as well. All of which feature male protagonists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time a female-driven film touched me so profoundly was &lt;em&gt;Thelma &amp;amp; Louise&lt;/em&gt; in 1991. Is &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; as good as &lt;em&gt;Thelma &amp;amp; Louise&lt;/em&gt;? Jean-Marc Vallée might be a better director than &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/12/exodus-gods-and-kings.html&quot;&gt;Ridley Scott&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, but not better than he was in his prime. And, yes, timing is everything. &lt;em&gt;Thelma &amp;amp; Louise&lt;/em&gt; was the movie the 18 year-old me needed. For a young feminist and writer, its influence was undeniable. Thelma and Louise were thrust into a situation that required them to react quickly and violently; they became accidental poster girls for third-wave feminism and unwittingly ignited a cultural shitstorm. Critics called the film misandrist, the protagonists poor role models. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,287998,00.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; accused &lt;em&gt;Thelma &amp;amp; Louise&lt;/em&gt; of being &amp;#39;&amp;#39;tapped into a wild-rushing subterranean stream of inchoate rage and deranged violence.&amp;#39;&amp;#39; They killed exactly one guy. A rapist. It always struck me odd that their contemporary male counterparts – John Rambo, John McClane, Riggs &amp;amp; Murtaugh – were never held to task for their collective quadruple-digit body counts. But hey, boys will be boys, amirite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; arrived at the end of a game-changing year for women. Jian Ghomeshi, Bill Cosby, and the #beenrapedneverreported hashtag. Ray and Janay Rice and the #whyistayed and #whyileft phenomenon. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b1XGPvbWn0A&quot;&gt;Hollaback catcall video&lt;/a&gt; and #yesallwomen. Gamergate. Regardless of personal opinion, there’s no denying that these events forced a dialogue that was long overdue. And yet a quick perusal of the comments section for any of these news stories (or sadly, even for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tn2-GSqPyl0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; trailer) is a nasty reminder of just how far we need to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There persists a tangible &lt;a href=&quot;http://womenagainstfeminism.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;resistance&lt;/a&gt; not just to the concept of feminism, but to the very word itself. I was pleasantly shocked when &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;’s protagonist Cheryl Strayed is asked point blank if she is a feminist and she responds without hesitation in the affirmative. Alone on the trail, Cheryl experiences dangerous terrain, dehydration, rattlesnakes, and other potentially fatal circumstances—and yet her most terrifying encounter is with a man. Yes, this film is about overcoming odds, facing personal demons, and finding redemption. But it’s also about consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It matters that Cheryl’s choices are frustrating and make her difficult to like. She is the kind of heroine we need to see more of: &lt;em&gt;she’s interesting&lt;/em&gt;. She’s a former junkie. She’s promiscuous. She’s angry, funny, determined, intelligent, and deeply wounded without ever being tragic. She owns her mistakes. She has no regrets, and the only person she feels the need to apologize to is herself. It’s refreshing to see a powerful female lead that can be complicated and vulnerable without giving up her own agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my response to &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; is about more than just the simple fact that Cheryl is unapologetically feminist. It’s not merely a better-than-average chick-flick. It transcends genre because technically and tonally it’s a really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good film.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the page, it might seem pretty simple; no explosions, car chases, complicated CGI sequences, or hordes of extras. But too often these quiet stories of personal triumph get mired in maudlin cliché. Or worse, fall into the biopic trap of trying too hard to impose a clever framing device that encompasses and explains someone’s life, which more often than not results in weak, forgettable characterization. Vallée is one of the few directors assured enough to understand that his role is to be in service to the story. Maybe that’s why so many of his choices seem instinctual rather than contrived. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vallée assembled a team that elevated this film beyond its &lt;em&gt;Eat, Pray, Love&lt;/em&gt; on a Mountain premise. Nick Hornby’s unadorned script, music supervisor Susan Jacob’s period-sensitive yet surprisingly original soundtrack, and Yves Belanger’s understated cinematography all work together to tell Cheryl’s story without polishing it to a sheen. Reese Witherspoon’s transformation is every bit as noteworthy as Jake Gyllenhaal’s in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Laura Dern’s performance as Cheryl’s mother is characteristically unaffected and heartbreakingly powerful. The dynamic of a daughter entering adulthood and questioning her mother’s life choices is rarely seen, let alone translated so succinctly. When Cheryl asks, “Does it bother you that I’m more sophisticated than you were at my age?” Dern’s reply is gutting: “That’s all I ever wanted for you, but I can’t say it doesn’t hurt sometimes.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grudge Match&lt;/em&gt; insulted me as a viewer. But to be fair, it’s no more insulting than the countless cookie-cutter rom-coms starring Katherine Heigel or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/29/the-other-woman.html&quot;&gt;Cameron Diaz&lt;/a&gt; (or Reese Witherspoon, for that matter), who unfailingly play successful (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2011/10/03/flick-chicks&quot;&gt;but klutzy, always klutzy&lt;/a&gt;) women whose lives are only fulfilled when they find a man (not to be confused with their action movie counterparts: the buxom, ass-kicking, but one-dimensional “&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedissolve.com/features/exposition/618-were-losing-all-our-strong-female-characters-to-tr/&quot;&gt;Strong Female Characters&lt;/a&gt;” designed to placate female audiences without alienating male viewers). What’s revolutionary about &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; is how it breaks those stereotypes without really trying. Cheryl is a college drop-out, raised below the poverty line, who completes her journey and is left with no money, no job, no home, and no man. That’s her happy ending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feminism is just one of many themes in &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;, and it’s not the most important. When a story is this compelling, the gender of the protagonist becomes irrelevant. Films as thoughtfully crafted as &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; have the ability to resonate with more than just their target demo. If that’s not equality, I don’t know what is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to wait a year, but I finally got to see that underdog film about a fighter who overcomes the odds. I just hope I don’t have to wait another 24 years to see the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/7/actually-wild-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/7/actually-wild-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>No, The Trip To Italy is the Best Film of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Fellow Critics, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;As you know, picking a best film of the year is a special sort of ethical dilemma. Your selection doesn’t just define your aesthetic tastes, but who you are as a person at that particular moment in time (if I was writing this essay in 1996, you’d be hearing all about the hyperkinetic genius of Michael Bay’s &lt;em&gt;The Rock&lt;/em&gt;). *&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take the process of annointing a “best film” seriously (and you half-should), you have to make some important decisions about how you approach the act of criticism itself. Is the best film your favorite film? The film that you enjoyed the most, that seemed to speak most directly to your experience, your worldview, your personal tastes? Or is it the film that, in some explicit and objective way, best exemplifies the potential of cinema as an art form? Something empirically superior? If you’re lucky, you’ve seen a film that represents some amalgamation of those two noble goals. Otherwise, you’re making an objective judgment of something inextricably subjective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, how you choose your favorites says a lot about how you watch films. I have no pretensions of being an exhaustive, scholarly filmgoer (not like I did back in 1996). Frankly, I lack &lt;a href=&quot;https://film500.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;the Lou Bloom-like dedication of some people&lt;/a&gt;. I must rely on my instincts, and my instincts are guided by that fundamental principle of art: to alter the way we see the world. In 2014, there &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a film that made me reconsider the way I see the world, the way I live my life, and the way I distinguish between Welsh and Scottish James Bonds. And that film was Michael Winterbottom’s &lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what affected me about the film has to do with my fond feelings for the first installment: Coogan and Brydon cruising through Northern England, bickering, debating, the former perpetually annoyed, that latter perpetually eager. Coogan has a series of affairs, but can never quite find the contentment that Brydon and his young family possess. Brydon, on the other hand, doesn’t have Coogan’s ambitions, and has achieved only a fraction of his success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, in the sequel, Coogan is a bit more stable (he has a regular TV gig), and Brydon’s ambitions have expanded (he’s auditioning for a role in a Michael Mann film). Which is perhaps what makes &lt;em&gt;The Trip To Italy&lt;/em&gt; so fascinating to me. It’s an experiment in character building; take two established characters, switch their circumstances, stand back and see how they react. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coogan and Brydon are playing versions of themselves, sure, but it’s not quite the same trick that the gang in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/12/this-is-the-end.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This Is The End&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; plays. These colorful caricatures are sketched against a plain white background. The semi-documentary style employed by Winterbottom is more than just the same stylistic conceit adopted by modern sitcoms and found footage flicks. It manages to fix the characters in a real and recognizable world while also amplifying their comedic eccentricities. The way the story resolves – by not quite resolving at all – is indicative of the film’s non-traditional narrative structure. The sweet conclusion of Coogan’s paternal about-face, and the ambiguity of how Brydon will deal with his compromised morals, is a perfect ending, and deeply affecting to anyone who has gained an affinity for these two men over the course of two films. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ruins of Pompeii, when Coogan – who throughout both films demonstrates a spiritual allergy to notions of death and mortality – gets his hackles up at Brydon’s fun-making at the expense of a thousand year-old corpse is both funny and poignant and speaks simply to big ideas of impermanence and empathy. Sure, those are the same big ideas that other important films of 2014 addressed. But no other film addressed them with such subversive ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the formula is simple. Two actors playing lightly fictionalized version of themselves, let loose to improvise about squabbling movie stars and obscure British chat show hosts. Some might argue that in a year of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;decades-in-the-making passion projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/yes-nightcrawler-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;dark dissertations on the state of the American soul&lt;/a&gt; a film about two blokes conversing over dinner and wine is too unambitious, too ordinary to be the best film of the year. But no one discounts the power of a film like &lt;em&gt;My Dinner With Andre&lt;/em&gt; for modesty of scope. Nor should you discount &lt;em&gt;The Trip To Italy&lt;/em&gt;, which is the best (aka. my favorite) film of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/6/no-the-trip-to-italy-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/6/no-the-trip-to-italy-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Yes, Nightcrawler is the Best Film of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Fellow Critics,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This letter is addressed to you, but, admittedly, it’s an attempt to validate my own convictions. I wish I could have leaned back, stretched out my arms in self-satisfied comfort, and submitted my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/31/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;Top Films of 2014&lt;/a&gt; with the same confidence &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/1/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2013.html&quot;&gt;(and perfect photo) as I did in 2013&lt;/a&gt;. But that hasn’t been the case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I knew &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/13/the-act-of-killing.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Act of Killing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was unequivocally the most impressive, entertaining, and important cinematic accomplishment of the year. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has garnered similar praise from many of you this year, yet I can’t comply in calling it the best of the best. True, Richard Linklater’s 12-year character study is brilliant, poignant, and deceivingly simple, but I left the theatre without that instant appreciation. It took a few days for the film’s lackadaisical rhythm and fleeting preciousness to work me over. My own son is quickly growing before my eyes, so the film certainly has a special place in my heart—but it’s only second place on my list. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I almost didn’t trust &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-4-nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;my initial reaction to &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Toronto International Film Festival. I was giddy when the credits rolled, both thrilled and relieved to have found a film I could enthusiastically champion. The experience was all the more surprising since I walked in to the theater knowing only two things: the title and the star. The only promotional still frame I saw of Jake Gyllenhaal – eyes bulging, arm carefully outstretched with a flashlight fixed on the door of a van – was enough to get me curious about what awaited. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my spoilerphobic delight, that particular frame comes in first scene of the film. As Gyllenhaal’s Lou Bloom is caught sneaking around an industrial compound by a security guard, we get the first of many strange, stilted interactions with authority figures. Appearing to acquiesce to the man’s demands, he suddenly notices the guard’s wristwatch and pounces on him like a wild animal. He becomes a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Force Majeure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; more revealing than a controlled avalanche. And in that moment, the rules of the universe are established immediately: if you want something, take it. Consequences are a burden of the weak. And, in the case of the guard’s fate, never even revealed. Within the first five minutes, I felt a rush of excitement. Anything could happen in this film. It’s a thrill I rarely receive in today’s sequel-heavy, reboot-filled, regurgitation-plagued movie landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a master class of narrative clarity and character ambiguity. As a seasoned Hollywood scriptwriter, Dan Gilroy knows all the beats of a studio script and gleefully undermines them at every turn. There’s no clashing of what the hero wants vs. what he needs. No sympathetic background to get us invested in his character. No mid-point turn or all-is-lost moment of self-doubt. Gilroy doesn’t&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savethecat.com/&quot;&gt;save the cat&lt;/a&gt;—he strangles it, and doesn’t sacrifice a thing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we need to know about Lou Bloom is revealed through action or inference. His dialogue is all lifted from corporate HR manuals and every human interaction is purely transactional. He’s the living embodiment of &lt;em&gt;The Corporation&lt;/em&gt;. Not even Jordan Belfort in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/7/wolf-of-wall-street.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; could outmaneuver this coyote of the Sunset Strip. The biggest difference between the two men, in fact, is not their occupations, but rather the decade in which they exist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/28/spring-breakers.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spring Breakers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2013, &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; is the 2014 film that best taps into the Millennial experience. The pursuit of happiness is exaggerated to expose the depraved benchmarks of those ideals. There are no shades of grey along the way to success, only neon signs, black lights, and hot red cars. Lie, steal, cheat, sabotage, kill—just don’t lose focus. It’s the only way to get ahead. You will be justified and rewarded. The audience will even be on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sure as hell was. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My unexpected support for Bloom’s sociopathic drive came, in part, from 2014 marking my first year as a full-time freelancer. The otherwise abstract notion of the “Economy” has had a very real effect on my quality of life. The deck always feels stacked against you, and working for almost nothing in order to “establish a business relationship” (as Bloom agrees to when selling stolen copper piping), is not an introductory step, but a &lt;em&gt;Groundhog Day&lt;/em&gt; reality in an industry that’s struggling to survive. Not just in creating media content, but the very spirit of entrepreneurialism. &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedissolve.com/reviews/1181-nightcrawler/&quot;&gt;just a modern version of &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; satirizing local journalism. It’s a critique of the entire capitalist system. Lou is a wired intelligence playing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with the human race; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/the-imitation-game.html&quot;&gt;an enigma&lt;/a&gt; of the free market cracked by the Axis of Evil. To take a quote from Ridley’s Scott’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/12/exodus-gods-and-kings.html&quot;&gt;undeservingly derided &lt;em&gt;Exodus: Gods and Kings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: “That’s the irony, isn’t it? The people most suited to attaining power are the least suiting to having it.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most films, Rick the Intern (played to perfection by Riz Ahmed) would have served as an audience surrogate to help us see through the madness; a Bud Fox to Bloom’s Gordon Gekko. Instead, Rick is a disposable partner whose pink slip is a meager handful of blood-covered cash. But in the business world, them’s the breaks (or the lack-thereof, in the case of Lou’s rival). The high gear the film reaches in the third act gave me &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It felt both earned and appropriate. The implausibilities that &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.indiewire.com/criticwire/nightcrawler-reviews-taxi-driver-meets-network-20140906&quot;&gt;many argued&lt;/a&gt; over were completely irrelevant to me because the allegory was so strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what makes &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; so poignant. Lou Bloom is not a hero, he’s a victor. A tribute who not only survives the contemporary &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but learns to control them. The incongruous musical score by James Newton Howard underscores this triumph with synthesized fervor, playing more like a soundtrack in Bloom’s mind than a cue for tension to the audience. I never felt inspired by his amoral actions—but I did understand them. And that’s a mighty tall order for someone as contemptible as Lou Bloom. No film has used black comedy and biting social commentary to to such an effect since &lt;em&gt;A Clockwork Orange&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again I say, with bolstered confidence: yes, &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; is the best film of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/yes-nightcrawler-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/yes-nightcrawler-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Interview</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Deep down, you knew that &lt;em&gt;The Interview&lt;/em&gt; would eventually be released. You had to. Sure, you illegally leaked embarrassing emails, financial statements, and several upcoming Sony Pictures films, but even when victory seemed possible, it wasn’t. Your disgusting bluff about attacking cinemas that screened &lt;em&gt;The Interview&lt;/em&gt; was mercifully undermined by an arthouse alliance of 300+ independent theatres that stepped up at the last minute. And since the film’s on-schedule release at Christmas, all talk about you has disappeared. Thank fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to focus on the real fart fest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth Rogan and Evan Goldberg are no strangers to scorn. However, it’s usually from middle-aged critics and jaded Gen Xers who maxed out on the pair’s bromance humour after &lt;em&gt;Superbad&lt;/em&gt;. Although the two Canadian ex-pats have written some horrible comedies (&lt;em&gt;Drillbit Taylor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Watch&lt;/em&gt;), their co-directorial debut &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/12/this-is-the-end.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This Is The End&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was very well-received. So penning a politically relevant end-of-the-world showdown in &lt;em&gt;The Interview&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t the ambitious leap it may have initially seemed. It was the plot about a TV host and his producer being recruited by the CIA to assassinate North Korea’s leader Kim Jong-un, that ignited a real-life global incident that no one expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that, assholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully now we can forget the unnecessary democratic importance you gave the film. By bringing more attention to the title than it could have ever earned on it’s own, many people patriotically paid to download the film, only to realize that it was just another comedy, packed with far more homoeroticism than activism. This seemed to skew a lot of the early reviews, but personally, I thought it was pretty much right on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the film, of course, contains drug montages, naked chicks and poop jokes, it does at least qualify as a beginners guide to dictatorship. A Potemkin village turns James DeFranco’s character into a Dennis Rodman-esque apologist for the regime. Myth’s about Jong-un’s divine right to rule are used as the butt (hole-less) of jokes but paint him as a pitiful man rather than powerful monster. And in a late confrontation, actual stats are used about the millions of people starving in the country and living without basic human rights. Nothing you can’t find from the first few paragraphs of the country’s Wikipedia page, but still – it’s in there. And the film is better for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving at a solid clip, the film manages more than a few laughs from its (apparently) brazen premise. Even the aforementioned tropes – especially the drug sequences – are kept mercifully short and used to energize the film rather than indulge in tired psychedelic imagery. But here’s the real kicker – Kim Jong-un, or rather Randall Park’s portrayal of the man, is the real star of the show. By making the man more adorable than abhorrent, the filmmakers imbue a humanity that the real leader probably doesn’t deserve. Which makes the final confrontation all the more impactful and satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But alas, it’s only a stupid movie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/the-interview.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/the-interview.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Wild</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You make your mark early, as &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; opens on a craggy California slope. A young woman, her skin burnished by the sun and streaked with dirt, sits beside her oversized backpack . She pulls off her boots and socks to reveal blistered, bloody feet, skin rubbed raw, toenails barely attached. What happens next informs the tone of the film. For anyone who thought they were coming to see a glamourously windblown actress trekking across a softly focused vista, the first scene issues a harsh warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ain’t gonna be pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the four years since the death of her mother, Cheryl Strayed goes from promising college student to a heroin and sex addict who effectively drives away those closest to her. In the summer of 1995, she sets out to hike 1100 miles of the Pacific Crest Trail, which stretches across several mountain ranges from Mexico to Canada. A novice hiker alone on the PCT, Cheryl will encounter physical and emotional obstacles unlike anything she has ever faced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the first time you’ve had to ugly up an A-list actor, nor is this the first time you’ve worked with &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;’s Canadian director, Jean-Marc Vallée. You won an Oscar for convincing audiences that Matthew McConnaughey and Jared Leto were wasting away from AIDS in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/19/dallas-buyers-club.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dallas Buyer’s Club.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This isn’t even the first time you worked on a movie about someone walking alone in the wilderness. On &lt;em&gt;Into The Wild&lt;/em&gt; you made Emile Hirsch’s Christopher McCandless’ malnutrition seem painfully real. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/articles/arts/culturebox/2014/12/wild_and_into_the_wild_cheryl_strayed_and_christopher_mccandless_compared.single.html&quot;&gt;The comparisons between &lt;em&gt;Into The Wild&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are inevitable and not altogether unwarranted. But the idealistic McCandless was trying to find himself. Cheryl just wants to be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What brings Cheryl to the PCT isn’t initially clear. Even she isn’t entirely sure why she’s there. The trail isn’t a metaphor for her life. It’s not redemption. But for almost a hundred days it is her closest friend and fiercest enemy. Cinematographer Yves Bélanger films it as such, equal parts stunning and humbling, serene and relentless. When Cheryl dreads each monotonous footstep, so do we. When she takes a moment to appreciate the majesty of the Sierras, we do too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheryl’s past haunts her throughout her journey. Vallée uses razor-sharp cuts as flashbacks - Cheryl having sex, injecting heroin, fighting with a man - which eventually become whole scenes as she gets further into the trail. He saves the tenderness for the flashbacks of Cheryl watching her mother singing and dancing, or driving her and her brother away from their abusive father. One is a set of memories Cheryl hopes to exorcise, the other she is desperate to hold onto. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your job was to believably transition Cheryl from college kid to junkie to weary traveller, and luckily Reese Witherspoon was your canvas. Witherspoon (who also produced) carries this film like her “Monster” – the enormous backpack Cheryl hauls across the backcountry. This is the kind of role that screams “Oscar bait!” but thankfully Reese’s performance never does. Though Cheryl was 26 when she hiked the PCT, Witherspoon delivers a cynical vulnerability that perhaps younger actresses might not have done as convincingly. Witherspoon’s Cheryl is the kind of complicated female lead we rarely see onscreen; a frustrating and reckless mess with nothing to lose. She is not easy to root for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vallée is careful enough to maintain the film’s vast scope without sacrificing intimacy, and smart enough to trust that an actor of Witherspoon’s talent doesn’t need much accoutrement. He uses the Simon &amp;amp; Garfunkel song “El Condor Paso” as a powerful yet unobtrusive leitmotif, its lyrics “If I could” perfectly echo Cheryl’s inner monologue. She could quit, she could keep going. She - and the audience - is never quite sure what she will do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through you, Cheryl’s face and body tell her story. Dark under-eye circles, dried blood and fading bruises fill in the blanks that Nick Hornby’s mercifully underwritten script omits. The patches of inflamed skin on Cheryl’s back and hips, rubbed raw from the weight of Monster, scab and toughen as she adjusts to carrying her burden. Facing demons and making amends is painful and it isn’t pretty, but when stripped to the bone, there’s beauty to be found in the fight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Into the Woods</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0589174/?ref_=ttfc_fc_cr497&quot;&gt;CV is amazing&lt;/a&gt;. You’ve brought lions, tigers, bears, and pretty much every other man-eating predator to Hollywood’s biggest film sets (which explains your upcoming consultant role on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0369610/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Yet that’s not why you were hired on &lt;em&gt;Into the Woods&lt;/em&gt;. Rather than actually bringing something authentic to the screen, it seems the filmmakers wanted you to create a passable facsimile of an authentically powerful auditory experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Now I get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t waste time critiquing the singing voices of the stars, which, by-and-large, are perfectly passable. Rob Marshall’s film adaptation of the Broadway classic (of which I confess, I’m not a fan) is lacking in much more egregious ways. Still, the stage origins are painfully obvious: from the clumsy staging of actors (always “accidentally” running into each other), to the confined framing of the physical environment itself (padded constantly by budget-saving fog and shadows). All of this is expected and forgiven in live theatre. On screen it felt like one big cheat after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the giants. And the wolf sequence. And a certain death scene off a cliff.  None of which embraced the power of cinema to immerse, impress or enhance the storytelling experience. All Marshall does is repeat the stage beats while keeping his camera at the same disadvantage as a seated audience member. There are occasional exceptions, but none of the ingenuity that Marshall employed to elevate &lt;em&gt;Chicago&lt;/em&gt; from hit theatre to Oscar-winner is apparent here – especially when you consider the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, let’s talk about that material. When Stephen Sondheim penned &lt;em&gt;Into the Woods&lt;/em&gt;, the concept of what happens after happily-ever-after was considered nothing short of brilliant. Today, reviving fairy tales has become as tired as rebooting superhero franchises. Every princess story is getting a rethink, so saving that twist for the last half of the film means the narrative feels like it’s on auto-pilot for the first half. Had the film treatment been interpreted as joyously campy, or self-consciously satirical, that might have been okay. But instead, all we have to carry us through the familiar story beats are Sondheim’s quirky music and his aversion to catchy melodies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the man is considered nothing short of a musical messiah in the theatre community. But I can’t help feel as though his musicals are for people who are sick of musicals. That might explain why not a single song was stuck in my head after leaving the theatre, other than my trying to rationalize the tacky instances of rhyming the same word with itself (&lt;em&gt;Witches can be right. Giants can be good. You decide what’s right. You decide what’s good&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fault may be mine for wanting &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/1/2/les-miserables.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Les Misérables&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gravitas in a story that was never designed as such, but I still found myself vastly preferring the mediocre remake of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/20/annie.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; over this. I would have much preferred the money going into better effects than bigger stars. Nobody needed to see Johnny Depp’s knee-jerk interpretation of The Wolf – that kind of casting is about as obvious and lazy as, well, rhyming a word with itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, those crashing tree sounds you created were as crackling as we would expect in any film. But as the old saying goes – if I hadn’t been there to here it, I could have believed it all never happened.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/2/into-the-woods.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/2/into-the-woods.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>C. Redmond&#39;s Top Films of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you read the site frequently, you’ll know that we are home to B-movie aficionados, superhero apologists, and film school theorists alike. Read a few reviews and you’ll quickly get to know who has a soft spot for everything Canadian, and who refuses to bestow perfect praise on anything &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet we did attempt to create an authoritative Dear Cast and Crew list of the year’s top films. We thought of everything: democratic voting, socialistic slotting, even secret autocracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of it worked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each review is written from the perspective of an individual critic, and subject to their own personal criteria for what it worth seeing (and what isn’t). My list is no different. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing just over 200 films this year, here are the highlights. You can judge me accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Top 14 Films of 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;Boyhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html&quot;&gt;Whiplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html&quot;&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html&quot;&gt;Force Majeure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/6/edge-of-tomorrow.html&quot;&gt;Edge of Tomorrow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mistaken for Strangers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/7/mommy.html&quot;&gt;Mommy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/3/the-overnighters.html&quot;&gt;The Overnighters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;Under The Skin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/20/blue-ruin.html&quot;&gt;Blue Ruin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/28/nymphomanic-vol-1-and-2.html&quot;&gt;Nymphomaniac Parts 1 and 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Ida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/1/only-lovers-left-alive.html&quot;&gt;Only Lovers Left Alive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Ten Favorite Canadian Films&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Mommy&lt;/em&gt; memorial list)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/12/afflicted.html&quot;&gt;Afflicted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-postcard-2-tu-dors-nicole.html&quot;&gt;Tu dors Nicole&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/11/enemy.html&quot;&gt;Enemy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-1-corbo.html&quot;&gt;Corbo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bang Bang Baby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/the-f-word.html&quot;&gt;The F Word&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trailer Park Boys: Don’t Legalize It&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloody Knuckles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/the-captive%20copy.html&quot;&gt;The Captive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Special mention – Had &lt;em&gt;The Dirties&lt;/em&gt; (2013) been eligible (I didn’t catch it until this year), the film would have topped this list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Surprisingly Good&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/10/locke.html&quot;&gt;Locke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/12/robocop.html&quot;&gt;Robocop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/7/the-lego-movie.html&quot;&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Superior Sequels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/19/22-jump-street.html&quot;&gt;22 Jump Street&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/12/dawn-of-the-planet-of-the-apes.html&quot;&gt;Dawn of the Planet of the Apes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/21/planes-fire-rescue.html&quot;&gt;Planes: Fire &amp;amp; Rescue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unapologetically Awesome&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/16/godzilla.html&quot;&gt;Godzilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;The Raid 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overrated Everywhere Else&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/24/birdman-or-the-unexpected-virtue-of-ignorance.html&quot;&gt;Birdman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/12/life-itself.html&quot;&gt;Life Itself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Immigrant&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Didn’t Disappoint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/13/how-to-train-your-dragon-2.html&quot;&gt;How to Train Your Dragon 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html&quot;&gt;Dumb and Dumber To&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/9/gone-girl.html&quot;&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/a&gt;*&lt;br&gt;
*Yes, I acknowledge &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html&quot;&gt;the irony&lt;/a&gt; of listing the film here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extra Special Indies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/4/obvious-child.html&quot;&gt;Obvious Child&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Guest&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html&quot;&gt;The Babadook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid at All Costs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin City: A Dame to Kill For&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/9/a-million-ways-to-die-in-the-west.html&quot;&gt;A Million Ways to Die in the West&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-3-revenge-of-the-green-dragons.html&quot;&gt;Revenge of the Dragons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/20/open-windows.html&quot;&gt;Open Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
They Came Together&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/19/devils-knot.html&quot;&gt;Devil’s Knot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 20:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Jared Young&#39;s Top Films of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s true. Our attempts to compile a comprehensive, democratic list of Dear Cast and Crew’s favorite films of 2014 was scrapped after an epic email thread replete with name-calling and threats of physical harm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is to be expected. The disagreements between our staff of writers has expressed itself in all &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/13/the-cabin-in-the-woods-1.html&quot;&gt;sorts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/13/the-cabin-in-the-woods-2.html&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/16/star-trek-into-darkness.html&quot;&gt;wonderfully&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/6/out-of-darkness-revisiting-the-wrath-of-khan.html&quot;&gt;passive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/9/skyfall.html&quot;&gt;aggressive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/17/five-reasons-skyfall-fell-flat.html&quot;&gt;ways&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/summer-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;over&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html&quot;&gt;the years&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the spirit of healthy rhetorical debate (and petty one-upsmanship), here is an alternative to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/31/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;C. Redmond’s Top Films of 2014&lt;/a&gt;. While I haven’t seen quite as many films this year, the ones that resonated represent a broad range of genres, budgets, and artistic ambitions. From an indie thriller that channels early John Carpenter, to a blockbuster animated flick adapted from a building toy, the year’s best flicks were as diverse (and satisfying) as any in recent memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(But let’s be honest. Christopher and I agree on a lot of these films. Ultimately, this alternate list is just an excuse to lavish more praise on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/a&gt;, which was the catalyst of the aforementioned slander and abuse).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Top 10 Films of 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol reversed&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;Interstellar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;The Raid 2: Berendal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html&quot;&gt;The Babadook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;Boyhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/20/blue-ruin.html&quot;&gt; Blue Ruin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;Under The Skin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/7/the-lego-movie.html&quot;&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Guest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 19:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/jared-youngs-top-films-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/jared-youngs-top-films-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Imitation Game</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In your lifetime, you were as impenetrable and enigmatic as the oracular machine you are most famous for reverse engineering. &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt; is a relentlessly competent attempt to understand you as a person while also deconstructing that pivotal moment in history when you managed to break Nazi Germany’s most important code machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There it is, though—“relentlessly competent” sounds like half a compliment. And it is. There was something lacking in this film. It felt like a compromise between subjects: the endlessly fascinating story of how Enigma was cracked, and your very personal trials and tribulations. Both are worth an hour and fifty-four minutes of screen time, and both are certainly well-represented. But neither felt like they were investigated and explained in a way that was anything more than perfunctory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the manner that some biopics feel shallow despite the lead character eating-up all the available screen time, I felt cheated in some fundamental way at the end of this film. Here is one of the pivotal characters of the twentieth century, a singular person of real significance, yet I feel I know little more about him than if I had read a moderately competent 3000-word essay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s far too easy to second-guess something as fragile and complex as a feature film – especially one that takes on such a heady mix of subjects – however, I really feel like something essential was lacking, some connection to who you were as a person, something more than just the tortured genius or shunned deviant. Part of the difficulty in adapting a story like yours is figuring out where to begin. Your history is essential to what you did as an adult, but that’s always a fraught exercise onscreen; flashbacks are too easily expressed as clunky backlighting. So often with historical biopics, we essentially get a highlight reel: names, dates, significant moments and interactions. To really succeed in the time allotted, a film requires a level of nuance that &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, while exquisitely shaped, doesn’t ascend to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more than most people, you deserve the cinematic equivalent of a long form essay. You are someone worthy of six-plus hours of screen-time. You require that depth of characterization and backstory. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html&quot;&gt;Strong cases have been made&lt;/a&gt; for how some subjects beg for the kind of depth you can only achieve with a mini-series, and I can’t think of a better example than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly the performances were adept, the cinematography lush but restrained. And there was little to complain about onscreen. I suppose it was what &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; there that irked me. I would have liked to have seen more of the essential you and your life and less of the highlight reel. Ultimately this was a safe, competent rendition of a life that deserved more than that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/the-imitation-game.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/the-imitation-game.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
