<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Riot Club</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hot British bad boys certainly have (maybe not-so-niche) appeal. Even I was curious what female director Lone Scherfig would bring to Laura Wade’s adaptation of her male-centric play, &lt;em&gt;The Riot Club&lt;/em&gt;. And after the opening scene, which dives head-first into big breasts and unrepentant Renaissance debauchery through a wily sense of humour, I buckled up for a wild ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too bad the film never really went there. Despite this early filmic treatment and &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;-esque promise, the film doesn’t amount to much more than &lt;em&gt;The Skulls&lt;/em&gt; at Oxford. The play’s spacial limitation in the climax start to feel unnecessarily confined for the big screen (especially in the massive Princess of Whales Theatre, which signaled a certain importance for a press-only screening). But alas, it was ultimately as disposable as the women they talk about but rarely engage. To re-quote the characters, I suppose there are films for today, and films for tomorrow.  This was just a film for today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-1-the-riot-club.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-1-the-riot-club.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Two</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Saturday, September 6.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-2014-day-three.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-2014-day-three.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>St. Vincent</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Bill Murray has a few &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/writers/coryh/&quot;&gt;big fans&lt;/a&gt; at Dear Cast and Crew.   Just last week, we had a 10-review marathon series &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/ghosts-of-ghostbusters.html&quot;&gt;dedicated to Ghostbusters&lt;/am&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But today, you guys and the City of Toronto one-upped us by declaring it Bill Murray Day, screening some of his classic films and culminating in the premiere of &lt;em&gt;St. Vincent&lt;/em&gt;. All this saintly canonizing was all just a warm-up, it seems, to preparing us for the film itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;St. Vincent follows a familiar story between a doe-eyed boy and curmudgeon old man (like &lt;em&gt;Bad Santa, Bad Grandpa, Denis the Menace&lt;/em&gt;, etc). But it’s hard to fault a film that had me laughing multiple times before the opening credits were done. It was smart for the festival to capitalize on this assured debut by writer/director Theordore Melfi, who leverages Murray’s natural appeal without letting him rest on the usual charms—and it just might earn the comedy legend some Oscar love. The film itself doesn’t elevate much past the feel-good material, but remains enjoyable throughout due to a strong supporting cast in Naomi Watts, Melissa McCarthy and Chris O’Dowd (not to mention delightful newcomer Jaeden Lieberher).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, it’s really all about Murray. As it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-4-st-vincent.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-4-st-vincent.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Goodbye to Language 3D</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re gonna play a new Jean-Luc Godard film, darn tootin&#39; I&#39;m gonna sit through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At age 83, The master French provocateur has not slowed down nor sanded the edges off of his aggressively experimental cinema. I quite willingly embarked on the 70 minute masochism that is &lt;em&gt;Goodbye to Language 3D&lt;/em&gt;. The mischief this time includes an assaultive sound design that punched new holes in my ears and splitting the dual camera system required for native 3D to create double exposure images that effectively raped my retinas. Not to mention the philosophical debates between a naked man and woman while they were expelling a case of the runs (which at least meant the fart sounds were coming from within the film, &lt;a href=&quot;#sunshine-superman&quot;&gt;for once&lt;/a&gt; ). There were also some gem lines of spastic voiceover dialogue, saying how &quot;Images are the murder of the present&quot;, and how &quot;soon everyone will need an interpreter to understand the words coming out of their own mouth&quot;. Only Godard could make these statements ring so true.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-3-goodbye-to-language-34.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-3-goodbye-to-language-34.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sunshine Superman</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m so so so sorry. I don&#39;t know what happened to me. Well, yes I do. I was rushing into the screening - pulled pork sandwich dripping in-hand - because I didn&#39;t want to miss a moment. Good thing, too, because the visual treats in Sunshine Superman come fast and early. You couldn&#39;t ask for a more visual subject than a documentary about the first BASE jumpers. Especially one that follows Carl, and accomplished director of (free-fall) photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as I sat there being consumed by the story, I also had to wolf down some lunch. Quickly, too, so I could capture some quotes from these odd balls in the late 70s who parachuted off cliffs and buildings. And as the story reached it&#39;s ominous ending, I couldn&#39;t dare leave. Which is why, in the film&#39;s most dramatic and extended silent pause, I accidentally let one rip. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not in my head. People turned around three rows away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, I&#39;m coming clean. If someone complains that the screening stunk, it wasn&#39;t the film. It was me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-2-sunshine-superman.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-2-sunshine-superman.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Force Majeure</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This is what I come here to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Force Majeure made waves at Cannes, and deserves a much bigger audience than the Swedish family drama will probably find. Tense and hilarious, Ruben Östlund has crafted a damn-near perfect exploration of modern masculinity and heterosexual relationships. The film is laser-focused on the very filmic principle that action reveals character, and entertainingly explores how a single instinct can overpower our entire understanding of a another human being. If only the film had stuck to its guns and ended one scene earlier to maintain the principle indictment, I would have fallen for the film whole-heatedly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Two</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Friday, September 5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-2014-day-two.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-2014-day-two.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Dead Lands</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The first ever film in the Maori language? And it’s all about Maori warriors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sign me up!&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This film was getting some nice buzz before the festival, largely because it was singled out by your head programmer, Cameron Bailey, as one to watch. But does it elevate itself past the novelty factor of a Kiwi beefcake action film? Not really. But it doesn&#39;t disappoint, either. The (many) fight scenes aren&#39;t always well framed, but it&#39;s satisfyingly bloody and often eye-opening (watching a Maori warrior take a shit on the skull of his ancestor will have that effect). All the macho posturing before battle – the literal tongue-wagging – worked for me, and represents the kind of fare you showcase so well: audience-friendly films that might otherwise get lost in the shuffle. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-3-the-dead-lands%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-3-the-dead-lands%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Whiplash</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What a perfect way to kick-off the festival. (No, I&#39;m not taking about The Judge.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whiplash was the first film I actually saw this year, since it played for the press as part of Thursday&#39;s programming of previously premiered films.  And, wow, did it ever live up to the Sundance hype.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Miles Teller gives a career-defining performance as an aspiring concert drummer. On top of his own ridiculous musical talents, which simply can&#39;t be faked, he manages to endear us with the same laser focus as writer/director Damien Chazelle, who has crafted a film that demonstrates a wisdom beyond his relatively young 29 years. As one might expect in a film about jazz rhythm, the pace is wonderfully unpredictable; the big moments are somehow expected and surprising, and the ending is a white-knuckle marvel. A must-see for every aspiring musician and fan of small, marvellous films.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Judge</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What does the official opening night film say about this year&#39;s festival? Everything, really. Safe, standard, and, if nothing else, reliable. The Judge parallels my overall feelings about this year&#39;s line-up in both form and content. There are solid performances, a bevy of stars, a mix between moments of artistic flourish and populist appeal, and a well-worn script that teeters on being overlong without ever actually being boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we all know the opener plays a very particular role here. You want to set a celebratory tone, while only teasing what&#39;s to come. However, between the new get-tough-on-premieres stance and outright scoops by the New York Film Festival (taking both David Fincher and P.T. Anderson&#39;s new titles), I fear that the real story this year will be the films that you&#39;re not playing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-1-the-judge.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-1-the-judge.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
