<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Mortdecai</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think you’re good at your job. I really would. As you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0892255/fullcredits?ref_=tt_cl_sm&quot;&gt;already&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0374569/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm&quot;&gt;know&lt;/a&gt;, Benicio Del Toro is known for disappearing into his roles, and portraying real-life drug kingpin Pablo Escobar in &lt;em&gt;Escobar: Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt; must have meant many long hours of research for you. At least, I think it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there’s not a whole lot of your work on display in Andrea Di Stefano’s debut feature film. Even though Escobar’s name is in the title, Di Stefano has instead chosen to focus on the fictionalized love story of a Canadian ex-pat who falls for Escobar’s niece and becomes caught up in the chaos surrounding the final days of the infamous Colombian’s drug empire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nick, Josh Hutcherson continues the long, sad tradition of fictional white characters tasked with helping a white audience acclimate to an unfamiliar foreign world. This decision is a little depressing in that it perpetuates the notion that an audience can only relate to characters that look like them. But it’s made worse by the fact that Hutcherson brings exactly two notes to his performance: lovestruck (happy) and worried (less happy). To be fair, I can’t lay all the fault at his feet, as Di Stefano’s script doesn’t give him much to do beyond that. The theme Di Stefano is trying to establish is one of blind love; a man unwittingly pulled into terrible events. The actual result is character who just seems sort of stupid. While attending a lavish birthday party for Escobar, NIck asks his true love where all the money comes from. She answers simply, cheerfully, “Cocaine!” Hutcherson expresses brief worry, but quickly shifts back to his puppy-love face. Not long after, he tells his brother that Escobar is “not as bad as everyone says.” You start feeling that whatever Hutcherson’s character has coming is his own damn fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a plot structure, that isn’t necessarily a bad thing. If the young lovers burned brightly enough, we’d believe that he’d ignore all the warning signs just to be with her. But it doesn’t. Claudia Traisac, as Nick’s beloved Maria, is about as broadly sketched as he is: pretty and nice and selfless (she works with the poor!). Did I mention pretty? As a screen couple, they do a lot of talking about being in love without ever actually showing it. If Di Stefano wants us to see them as as a drug-era Jack and Rose heading towards a Pablo Escobar-shaped iceberg, he plotted his course all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the idea was that you and Del Toro would create such a magnetic presence in Escobar that everyone, including the audience, would be drawn to him. I can’t say for sure, because little of that ended up onscreen. Like the romance, there’s a lot of talk about how beloved Escobar is – he’s referred to as “Papa Escobar” by the poor – but we don’t get much evidence beyond that. An early speech given by Escobar hints at his charisma, but the camera is more interested in focusing on the dopey white boy scanning the crowd for the sexy Latina. He looks everywhere &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the stage. This scene might as well play as a metaphor for the experience of watching &lt;em&gt;Escobar: Paradise Lost.&lt;/em&gt; Hutcherson is that too-tall concert-goer standing right in front of you, blocking your view of the performer you actually want to see. If he’d just move out of the way, you might enjoy yourself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s s shame, because there’s an early scene that shows how the work you did with Del Toro might have brought the film to life. After Escobar’s birthday party, Nick is paid a late-night visit by the man himself. Escobar is basically feeling him out to see if he’s a worthy suitor for his niece, but in the course of their conversation, the young man mentions some local thugs giving him and his brother a hard time. Silently, Escobar takes a pen out of his pocket and jots a note on his palm. Nothing is said, but we all know it’s bad news for those thugs. It’s a small moment, but it demonstrates, powerfully, the way fates are decided in the smallest of moments. As the talk winds down, Escobar says, “This was good conversation.” He’s right: it’s a genuinely interesting scene. I just wish that when Escobar left the room, the camera had followed him instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/24/mortdecai.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/24/mortdecai.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Escobar: Paradise Lost</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think you’re good at your job. I really would. As you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0892255/fullcredits?ref_=tt_cl_sm&quot;&gt;already&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0374569/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm&quot;&gt;know&lt;/a&gt;, Benicio Del Toro is known for disappearing into his roles, and portraying real-life drug kingpin Pablo Escobar in &lt;em&gt;Escobar: Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt; must have meant many long hours of research for you. At least, I think it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there’s not a whole lot of your work on display in Andrea Di Stefano’s debut feature film. Even though Escobar’s name is in the title, Di Stefano has instead chosen to focus on the fictionalized love story of a Canadian ex-pat who falls for Escobar’s niece and becomes caught up in the chaos surrounding the final days of the infamous Colombian’s drug empire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nick, Josh Hutcherson continues the long, sad tradition of fictional white characters tasked with helping a white audience acclimate to an unfamiliar foreign world. This decision is a little depressing in that it perpetuates the notion that an audience can only relate to characters that look like them. But it’s made worse by the fact that Hutcherson brings exactly two notes to his performance: lovestruck (happy) and worried (less happy). To be fair, I can’t lay all the fault at his feet, as Di Stefano’s script doesn’t give him much to do beyond that. The theme Di Stefano is trying to establish is one of blind love; a man unwittingly pulled into terrible events. The actual result is character who just seems sort of stupid. While attending a lavish birthday party for Escobar, NIck asks his true love where all the money comes from. She answers simply, cheerfully, “Cocaine!” Hutcherson expresses brief worry, but quickly shifts back to his puppy-love face. Not long after, he tells his brother that Escobar is “not as bad as everyone says.” You start feeling that whatever Hutcherson’s character has coming is his own damn fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a plot structure, that isn’t necessarily a bad thing. If the young lovers burned brightly enough, we’d believe that he’d ignore all the warning signs just to be with her. But it doesn’t. Claudia Traisac, as Nick’s beloved Maria, is about as broadly sketched as he is: pretty and nice and selfless (she works with the poor!). Did I mention pretty? As a screen couple, they do a lot of talking about being in love without ever actually showing it. If Di Stefano wants us to see them as as a drug-era Jack and Rose heading towards a Pablo Escobar-shaped iceberg, he plotted his course all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the idea was that you and Del Toro would create such a magnetic presence in Escobar that everyone, including the audience, would be drawn to him. I can’t say for sure, because little of that ended up onscreen. Like the romance, there’s a lot of talk about how beloved Escobar is – he’s referred to as “Papa Escobar” by the poor – but we don’t get much evidence beyond that. An early speech given by Escobar hints at his charisma, but the camera is more interested in focusing on the dopey white boy scanning the crowd for the sexy Latina. He looks everywhere &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the stage. This scene might as well play as a metaphor for the experience of watching &lt;em&gt;Escobar: Paradise Lost.&lt;/em&gt; Hutcherson is that too-tall concert-goer standing right in front of you, blocking your view of the performer you actually want to see. If he’d just move out of the way, you might enjoy yourself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s s shame, because there’s an early scene that shows how the work you did with Del Toro might have brought the film to life. After Escobar’s birthday party, Nick is paid a late-night visit by the man himself. Escobar is basically feeling him out to see if he’s a worthy suitor for his niece, but in the course of their conversation, the young man mentions some local thugs giving him and his brother a hard time. Silently, Escobar takes a pen out of his pocket and jots a note on his palm. Nothing is said, but we all know it’s bad news for those thugs. It’s a small moment, but it demonstrates, powerfully, the way fates are decided in the smallest of moments. As the talk winds down, Escobar says, “This was good conversation.” He’s right: it’s a genuinely interesting scene. I just wish that when Escobar left the room, the camera had followed him instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/23/escobar-paradise-lost.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/23/escobar-paradise-lost.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Song of the Sea</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;First off, my congratulations to you and the entire production team of &lt;em&gt;Song of the Sea&lt;/em&gt;. It’s been a few years since Tomm Moore’s Academy Award nomination for &lt;em&gt;The Secret of Kells&lt;/em&gt;, and I’m so glad to see him back on the list of nominees for Best Animated Feature. In a field now completely saturated with mind-melting 3D and geeky-cool, I appreciate the occasional return to an elegant, hand-drawn 2D look and a story that is enchantingly simple and sweet. No cheeseburgers flying out of the screen at your head here – just a wee tale of love, loss, and magic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben lives in a lighthouse and spends his days with his dog, Cù. He misses his mother, and loves remembering the stories she used to tell. He has neither the time nor the patience for his adoring little sister, Saoirse, who is painfully cute and has never spoken a word. Neglected by their father, who is still wracked with grief over the loss of his wife, Ben and Saoirse are bundled off to live in the city with their Granny, who takes no guff from anyone. Far away from their home by the sea, Saoirse falls ill. She is revealed to be the last of the Selkies, mysterious half-seal-half-humans of Irish myth. And so Ben must race to save his sister, and other various fairies, witches, and elves kicking around the Irish countryside.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All animated films walk the line between art appreciation and entertainment, usually dipping more towards one or the other. There were moments during the film when I wondered if this one was perhaps more for the grown-ups, given its softer, more meditative pacing compared to – well – fast food flying at one’s head. But the littlest filmgoers in the theatre were drawn right in, all saucer eyes and slack jaws. I think it had something to do with the wonderful use of contrast. I loved the powdery watercolour backgrounds blending together the ‘normal’ world with the world of magical beings. Eye-catching on their own, they are the perfect backdrop to the sharper, more vivid character designs, like that of Granny, who somehow looks wonderfully round and pinched at the same time. The visual contrasts in the artwork complement the thematic contrasts between ancient and present-day, ordinary and magic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much to take away from the film, depending on your outlook. I saw it as a cautionary tale against helicopter parenting and exerting too much control on a child’s behaviour (basically don’t tell your kids to calm down or behave or they will literally shrivel up and turn grey). My companion saw a surprisingly dark tale of grief and emotional repression, and also came away with a sense of guilt over all the times he was ‘a shitty big brother’. The soft pacing and lilting lullaby soundtrack allow for a degree of contemplation you just don’t get with giant 3D ice-cream sundaes, or lemurs who like to move it-move it. I’m a huge fan of the aforementioned lemur, but I could definitely go for more of this sort of quieter, gentler animated offering. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/22/song-of-the-sea.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/22/song-of-the-sea.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Selma</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve had a rough week. Since the 2015 Oscar nominations were announced, you’ve been accused of racism, sexism, and even Lego-ism. It’s enough to make you throw your nine-iron into a sand trap and listen to some Jimmy Buffet to calm down, isn’t it? Sorry, I know not all of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2014/03/oscar-voters-94-white-76-men-and-an-average-of-63-years-old/284163/&quot;&gt;you are old, white men&lt;/a&gt;. Only 76% of you are men, and only 94% of you are white. And on average you’re 63 years old. But to assume you all listen to Jimmy Buffett was mean. I’m sure some of you listen to Coldplay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; ticks off all the boxes on the Oscar-bait Bingo Card. It’s historically significant, features a Great Man righting Great Wrongs, and is full of British actors affecting American accents. There’s even an explosion. But &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is not a spectacle, and the Academy loves spectacle. It loves sweeping sentimentality and chewed scenery, but above all, it loves triumph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is not a triumphant movie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of you are old enough to have firsthand memories of hearing Dr. Martin Luther King Jr deliver his iconic ‘I Have A Dream’ speech. Perhaps you remember seeing footage of Civil Rights activists getting sprayed by fire hoses or being beaten with billy clubs in places like Selma, or Mobile or Birmingham. Witnessing these dramatic highs and lows at such an impressionable age may or may not have influenced how you make and watch movies. But it certainly seems to have influenced the way you judge them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, the bone I have to pick is with specific branches of the Academy – namely the Actor’s branch and the Director’s branch. The entire Academy only votes after all the nominations are made by the specific branches. That vital distinction is missing in a lot of Oscar coverage. The Academy as a whole actually nominated &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;, and its Best Picture nomination is indeed a huge honour, but in this case it feels like a consolation prize. To nominate &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; and overlook the the two people who are overwhelmingly responsible for its distinction as a great film borders on the absurd. But I think I know how this happened. You didn’t snub &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; director Ava DuVernay and its star David Oyelowo because you’re racist or sexist. You snubbed them because you’re restraint-ist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1965, Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and his supporters planned a march from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama in order to secure equal voting rights for African Americans in the South. &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; chronicles the public and private struggles that Dr. King had with President Johnson, Alabama Governor George Wallace, his wife Coretta Scott King, and other leaders and members of the Civil Rights movement leading up to this historic march. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were expecting &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; to be a biopic you must have been confused. We never see MLK as a child, or witness that pivotal moment that defined his life’s work. There is no clever framing device that drives the narrative from flashback to present time. There are no flashbacks. The film deals with a specific and strategic battleground in the Civil Rights struggle, and with MLK’s relationships within that timeline. There is a lot more talking than marching in &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;, but those conversations are fraught with tension. The one device DuVernay employs to great effect are the FBI communiques that tap across the screen like teletype. It’s a reminder that despite the spirit of cooperation that President Johnson publicly extended to MLK, he continued, albeit begrudgingly, to allow Hoover and his men to spy on and attempt to smear the Reverend Doctor’s name and undermine his efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were you disappointed that in their portrayal of MLK, DuVernay and Oyelowo chose not to indulge in hero worship? Or were you hoping that a portrayal of MLK would expose greater flaws and a more profound sense of his humanity? Oyelowo plays a man who is constantly on the brink of failure – in his movement and in his marriage – who must remain calm and composed, not because he wants to, but because he knows it is what’s required of him. This strain is especially palpable in the scenes between him and his wife Coretta (played with painful dignity by Carmen Ejogo). MLK’s transgressions are only hinted at, yet DuVernay’s framing of the shots of husband and wife allow the spaces between them to tell us all we need to know. Oyelowo’s performance of a man who can’t show the incredible pressure he&amp;#39;s under is riveting. It’s exactly the type of complex and nuanced performance that you should reward, but never do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must have been frustrating to expect a capital ‘I’ important film and then realize that it bears none of the hallmarks you typically celebrate. &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is decidedly matter-of-fact and yet it bursts with emotion. When confronted with scenes of shocking brutality, DuVernay knows exactly when to turn the camera away. She understands the power of moderation and the balance between show and tell. When the heroes claim their prize there is no exultation, no glorious swell of music, no single tear slowly tracing down a humble, black face. Because there is no victory in finally getting something you were owed all along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know others will continue to chide you for your lack of diversity this year, and for choosing to recognize films and performances that predominantly represent the white, male experience. But your inability to see beyond convention is just as disheartening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selma is triumphant only in its restraint. Unfortunately that’s not the kind of triumph the Academy rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Most Violent Year</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;1981 was a year I would like to forget. I was 19, badly dressed, and listening to some of the worst music the Western world has ever created. But thanks to you and director J.C. Chandor—as well as art director Doug Huszti—I now will never be able to erase those stains from my memory. You have etched that year and its sensibilities into my brain forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forgive you that unwanted imposition because &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt; is note perfect in tone. The fidelity of its depiction of a particular period is only one of the things that make this film close to flawless. Choosing Oscar Isaac as the almost impossibly stubborn Small Business Owner/ Protagonist (of an oil distribution company no less), Jessica Chastain as his wife and business partner, and Albert Brooks—in a role originally intended for Stanley Tucci—as their family lawyer was also touched with a quiet genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in New York, it also evokes a period that was formative for me in my love of films. This is the dirty, knockabout New York of &lt;em&gt;The French Connection,&lt;/em&gt; a time before the whole city was castrated by Disney and it adherents. Smoky back rooms filled with a remarkably diverse cast of players, engaged in the some of the most Machiavellian examples of business relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world that these people inhabit is made seamless and utterly believable by the maturity of the script, the nuanced and incredibly competent direction, as well as a cast that never takes a wrong step. It is also a cast that has a Guatemalan/Cuban lead, features an African man as an incorruptible authority figure, and a woman who is not only the equal of her husband in every way but also the spine of their shared business. All of these components simply exist, they are never underlined or trumpeted but are simply part of the tapestry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there is your contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the clothes to the cars to the architecture to the choice of locations, you managed to capture a New York made of rusting steel, wood paneling and slightly ludicrous wardrobes. The tans and washed-out polyester tones, the overly styled hair and nouveau riche sensibilities contrasting with the stripped down aesthetic of an industrial park were pitch perfect. This is a New York in transition, spiritually, economically and demographically. And it is a painful transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been some comparison of this film to Coppola’s &lt;em&gt;Godfather&lt;/em&gt; pictures, largely because of the themes of dynasty and violence that permeate &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt;. But I think a better point of reference is Sidney Lumet. His films so often had as their central theme a struggle between expedience and doing what was right. Think &lt;em&gt;Serpico&lt;/em&gt; or even 1981’s &lt;em&gt;Prince of the City.&lt;/em&gt; Set in this New York with these kind of ethical quandaries at their centre, they were mature, thoughtful films filled with real characters, facing the often mundane complexities of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt; is simply pastiche, but the pedigree is far more Lumet than it is Coppola. There is something distinctly un-operatic and kitchen-sink to this film that makes it more realist than impressionistic. It is a film about people first and then it engages its larger themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you and Chandor decided that, like Japanese artists who create an intentional flaw in their work, you needed to remain humble. That is the only reason I can fathom for the clunky, tacked on nature of the epilogue. It stood out like cotton in a disco and came close to unraveling all you had built. I hope against hope it simply disappears in the DVD version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, this was a film that is otherwise a masterpiece of what I hope cinema is moving towards again—a balance between the tentpole Gotterdammerung of the summer and quietly brilliant character studies like &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year.&lt;/em&gt; That would be the best of all possible worlds. And I truly appreciate your efforts in trying to make that a real place we can all inhabit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Blackhat</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hollywood films love their technical advisors, be they military, science, or in your case, criminal. But being a technical advisor on a Michael Mann film must be a different kind of gig. The characters in Mann’s films are defined through their action—for Mann, action &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; character. And since much of the action of &lt;em&gt;Blackhat,&lt;/em&gt; exists in the netherworld of computer hacking, your expertise was no doubt essential in helping Mann create this very meticulous world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Mann’s pedigree, &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; presents a problem that has flummoxed filmmakers for decades: How do you make a person sitting in front of a computer screen seem exciting, even cinematic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on most of &lt;em&gt;Blackhat,&lt;/em&gt; Mann’s answer seems to be that you don’t—or, at least, that you don’t try too hard. He’s a savvy enough storyteller to know that the drama in any scene is about the shifting power dynamics between characters. Two men punching each other in a boxing ring, a gang of bank robbers shooting their way down an L.A. street, or a group of journalists simply trying to determine the legal ramifications of tortious interference can all create the same electricity for Mann, because what’s happening, no matter how small, matters to the characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say “most of” &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; because its opening scenes had me worried that Mann no longer trusted the audience—or himself—to experience action through character. As the film opens, we are assaulted by some pretty standard CGI-crafted shots that zoom in and out of computers, zipping along circuit boards, pushing almost to the atomic level in an attempt to visualize semiconductors coming to life in a mainframe as it is hacked by, well, by someone like you. I assume none of this sequence fell under your technical advisory, as it’s not very effective and more than a little silly. It had me worried that Mann had bought into the overpraise of special effects that a furious light and sound show could better deliver what a simple edit could convey: action and reaction. A man taps a keyboard, and somewhere on the other side of the world in China, a nuclear power plant’s cooling fan overheats and causes a meltdown. Anything in between those two events is only noise, reducing their impact. To see a filmmaker whose style is known mainly for its austere beauty fall victim to this at the film’s outset was disheartening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully that’s the only such indulgence in &lt;em&gt;Blackhat,&lt;/em&gt; and after that opening scene, we move quickly into territory Mann is familiar with: criminals and the people who hunt them. Even though &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; purports to be about your world’s particulars, it’s really about what all of Michael Mann’s movies are almost always about: the hunt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; might seem perfectly timed —especially for those of you in the Hollywood cyber security business— Mann has never been particularly interested in timeliness as much as he has been interested in his own pet themes; loyalty, friendship, vengeance. And although it is a film that takes place in a very modern world, &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; feels most aligned with Mann’s 1981 debut film, &lt;em&gt;Thief.&lt;/em&gt; Structurally, these films are about as close to each other as anything Mann’s made (not counting his fill-in remake of 1989’s &lt;em&gt;L.A. Takedown&lt;/em&gt; as 1995’s &lt;em&gt;Heat&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Hemsworth plays Nick Hathaway, an incarcerated hacker who is the only person who can possibly track down the mysterious man glimpsed in &lt;em&gt;Blackhat’s&lt;/em&gt; opening sequence. After the aforementioned nuclear reactor meltdown, Hathaway’s old college dorm mate who just happens to be a high level Chinese officer, convinces the United States government to free Hathaway (with a full pardon, of course) if he can help the authorities find and catch their man. When it comes to crime thrillers—even techno crime thrillers— the ground doesn’t come more well-trod than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mann takes pleasure in showing a seasoned team of professionals excel at their craft. He takes the same strategy when directing actors, but the results are mixed. Some of the more famous faces, like Viola Davis’, take underwritten roles, and create characters that make an impression even when their place in the plot is a little too obvious. Other key roles suffer. Taiwanese actress Wei Tang benefits from Mann’s love of quiet moments, and though she’s an appealing screen presence and clearly talented, at times it sounds as if she learned the script phonetically. Hemsworth is solid, if unexceptional, as Hathaway, valiantly channeling his inner James Caan, but never matching the much-needed charisma of Mann’s best leading men. Yet for all its faults, and reliance on cliché, &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; manages to stay its course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treading that edge between cliché and nuance is something Mann’s done throughout his directing career. He’s not afraid to write his themes in bold and then mark them with a highlighter. And if you’re not on Mann’s wavelength, it can be disastrous; earnestness becomes comical, big moments fall flat. But if you are in sync with him, a lot can be forgiven when those emotional highs lift you up. For a movie set in the impersonal world of computer hacking, and structured around the most familiar of genre conventions, &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; succeeded for me—if only in a minor way—when it became truly personal. Its climactic scene is rooted in the low-tech in a very up-close-and-personal confrontation that unfolds amid what’s filmed to look like waves of humanity. It climaxes about as far away from cyberspace as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, it was only when your technical contributions—authentic as I’m sure they were—faded out of view that &lt;em&gt;Blackhat&lt;/em&gt; worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/19/blackhat.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/19/blackhat.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>American Sniper</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Great action movies demand great villains. What fun is a hero that parachutes into trouble, eliminates enemies with ease, and never once feels legitimately challenged? Hollywood has known this forever – and Clint Eastwood knows Hollywood. More importantly, he knows America. That’s important. As much as the “Sniper” part of this film might be the differentiator, it’s actually the ultra-classic “American” shooting style that makes the film work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which includes manufacturing and dispatching a parallel villain like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now before you cry “spoiler alert!”, let me reiterate the American-ness of this film. America comes first in the title, and first for Eastwood. Failure is not an option, and ambiguity is not a strong suit of big studio films – especially old fashioned heroic myth-making like this one. Though I think they tried (more on that in a moment). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the autobiography of American NAVY Seal Chris Kyle, credited with over 150 confirmed kills (and maybe a 100 more), this is the story of the deadliest sniper in American history. From the moment the novel was published (or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/making-american-sniper-how-an-760963&quot;&gt;planned, in fact&lt;/a&gt;), it was impossible that this story wouldn’t become a feature film. The question was, would it be another chest-pumping &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/9/lone-survivor.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lone Survivor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a politically detached &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/1/18/zero-dark-thirty.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zero Dark Thirty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or something in between? The first scene handles that question rather well, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positioned on a rooftop in Iraq, your counterpart Kyle (played by a wildly bulked-up Bradley Cooper), is trying to decide whether or not to kill a “military-aged” man who is casually watching U.S. soldiers and making a phone call. See, unlike those easy target Americans you get to pick off, Al-Qaeda members don’t wear uniforms. So the deadly decision is Kyle’s alone to make. There’s also a woman and her young son below, who look like they’re handling a bomb and approaching the military convoy. Kyle’s spotter reminds him how, if he makes the wrong call, he’ll be shipped back to bootcamp (or something like that). Finger on the trigger, the story cuts away to life in America - pre-NAVY Seals, and pre-9/11 – to when Kyle was just a proud, rootin’ tootin’ Texas cowboy. Living the dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s actually a line in the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more where that comes from. Rodeos, beer and fistfights are used less for character building than for familiar texture to cleanse our palette from the (other) dusty sand bowl of the Middle East, where most of the film takes place. Flashing back even further to when Kyle was a kid, we get some schoolyard bully scenes, child stoicism, and daddy issues. All text-book biopic back story. Maybe it’s true, maybe it’s not. It doesn’t matter. When Americans want to go to war (in a movie or otherwise), they know how to set it up to get the public on their side. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And viewed through the lens of classic American filmmaking,  &lt;em&gt;American Sniper&lt;/em&gt; actually hits all the required emotional beats with surprising ease and deftness. The cinematography is clean and easy to follow (with the notable exception of the finale), and the details seem to matter – from always having mud on the muzzle to wearing out the paint on the scope. It would be a little too easy for someone like me, or you, to stick a big target on this film and shoot it down for flag-waving patriotism. After all, the script at least introduces characters conflicted by the morality of their decisions (not you of course – the villain must stand for evil as truly as the hero stands for good).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more daring director might have taken cues from the script more seriously in the way it handled you. Making you a former Olympic champion does imbue a broader sense of accomplishment and humanity. But I can’t help but feel the conclusion was more wish fulfillment on Kyle’s part than objective resolution. Despite the textual evidence for that possibility, Eastwood wouldn’t dare deprive his American audience of the money shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, &lt;em&gt;American Sniper&lt;/em&gt; gets to be a little bit of everything for all people: a pure recruitment tool for the army, proof of the psychological consequences of war for pacifists, and an emotionally charged drama for the general public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for everyone on your side, probably just one more reason to hate America.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/16/american-sniper.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/16/american-sniper.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Inherent Vice</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What more to expect from a film adapted from one of your novels than to be utterly confused, utterly compelled?  Your work sometimes feels like one big practical joke played on the reader - knotted allusions that may or may not connect, may or may not loop back on themselves, may or may not be allusions at all. And one might see Paul Thomas Anderson’s film adaptation of &lt;em&gt;Inherent Vice&lt;/em&gt; as a cruel trick perpetrated on the audience. And it might be. But if you’re in on the joke, if you’re willing to laugh at yourself, it’s a satisfying – and sometimes hilarious – experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inherent Vice&lt;/em&gt; was your take on the hard-boiled Raymond Chandler mode of detective story. The film version, to greater and lesser degrees, is Anderson’s take on Altman’s &lt;em&gt;The Long Goodbye&lt;/em&gt; (which, of course, was based on a Chandler novel). It’s the sort of fantasy drafting that film geeks propose over pints of craft beer. The Los Angeles described in your novel is the same peripheral Los Angeles that Anderson has been plundering for inspiration since &lt;em&gt;Boogie Nights&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Magnolia&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a drowsy, yellowed, desperate L.A full of drifters, druggies, and losers, far from the mansions of Beverly Hills, the hip night spots, and the movie premieres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;Inherent Vice&lt;/em&gt; was published in 2009, it was greeted with much respect but little enthusiasm. Sam Anderson ripped the novel in &lt;em&gt;New York&lt;/em&gt; Magazine, writing that you were “clearly having a postmodern blast warping the building blocks of detective fiction—causation, probability, significance, suspense. But it’s not quite so much fun for the reader. It’s hard to stay invested in a plot in which everything is so casually interconnected.” He implies that there’s nothing at stake in your narrative. Therefore, is there nothing at stake in P.T. Anderson’s interpretation of it? I’ll admit, yes, there’s something static about his cinematic interpretation of &lt;em&gt;Inherent Vice&lt;/em&gt;. But while the overarching narrative sometimes feels a bit inert, the individual scenes have their own velocity. As a series of comedy sketches, they are divine. The film is aligned with the approach you’ve taken throughout your career of dismantling the traditional structure of the novel: the parts are the whole and the sum doesn’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make whatever sense there is to be made of this, Anderson takes a minor character from the book and makes her your stand-in: Sortilege appears, in the first frames of the film, almost as a ghost, double-exposed over the beachside landscape. As she reappears throughout the film, she communicates exclusively with Doc and is never acknowledged by any other characters onscreen. That enigmatic Pynchonian presence is transferred to her. She has the voice of a precocious little girl playing cool, a pre-teen reading aloud from one of your novels found on her parents bookcase, and her narration provides that aloof, absurdist, self-referential editorializing that your prose is known for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both yours and Anderson’s reputations are rooted in your technical proficiency (Anderson’s complex tracking shots, your complex plots), and your care with composition. Anderson shot this film in 35mm – just like he did with his last film, &lt;em&gt;The Master&lt;/em&gt; – and director of photography Robert Elswit should win some kind of award just for the way he shoots Eric Roberts’ face in the last act of the film. It’s a moment that reinforces that old actor’s adage that the one person on set you want to be friends with is the cinematographer. Roberts has about four minutes of screen time and has never been more compelling. Everything is dark, muddled in shadows. Even when Joaquin Phoenix, as paranoid private dick Larry “Doc” Sportello, is lounging around his sunny beachside pad, his face is overcast, only dimly visible. It’s perpetually evening in this film. Even in the middle of the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also share an infantile sense of humor. The movie, just like the book, is at its heart a comedy. It’s full of spit takes, double-takes, and startled yelps. There are some amazing bits of physical comedy: Josh Brolin sucking on frozen bananas, Martin Short tripping about with his pants around his ankles. But no one is better than Phoenix, who channels Peter Sellers: he’s a stoner Clouseau, tiptoeing through bedrooms, getting knocked over by cops while crossing the street, getting cracked on the head with a blackjack, half-turning, raising a finger as if to ask a question, and collapsing—all in one fluid movement. There’s nothing objectively funny about an angry cop ordering pancakes in Japanese, but I haven’t laughed harder in a theater all year (with one &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/6/no-the-trip-to-italy-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;important exception&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inherent Vice&lt;/em&gt; occurs at the nadir of the counterculture the same way &lt;em&gt;Boogie Nights&lt;/em&gt; takes place at the death of the porn-on-film era (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cH0kOWNtLFo&quot;&gt;damn you, Floyd Gondoli!&lt;/a&gt;). This perhaps explains the current of melancholy that runs throughout. The good times are ending, flower power proven finite. Katherine Waterson (who plays the dame who kicks the whole thing off, in classic Spillane style) is the vessel for this sadness and fatigue. She’s the real star of the film. In her performance is all the earnestness that your body of work consciously despises, which makes Anderson’s vision of your scummy 70s underworld of cults and conspiracies several degrees more human. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, none of it matters. Plot threads dangle, important characters disappear, knots remain unknotted. But Anderson gives it all just enough warmth to counteract the coldness of the joke that’s being played. And for that I’m sure you’re grateful. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/15/inherent-vice.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/15/inherent-vice.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Guest</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Okay. I get it, now. It’s all starting to make sense.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, though, I didn’t understand. You left one of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1606375/&quot;&gt;most popular television series&lt;/a&gt; in the English speaking world at the peak of its popularity to pursue other roles. But there was no blockbuster superhero flick on the horizon, no colorful supporting part in a Paul Thomas Anderson ensemble. Instead, your first post-Downton gig was the lead in a low-budget thriller that pays homage to low-budget thrillers. Which, forgive me, didn’t seem like the wisest career decision. Even Hugh Grant knew well enough to milk his stuttering English charm for a few more flicks before trying his hand as the star of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0116259/?ref_=nm_flmg_act_25&quot;&gt;a Hollywood suspense film&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it turns out that &lt;em&gt;The Guest&lt;/em&gt; is more than just a movie-geek trifle. And if you were looking to exorcise the elegant, befuddled specter of your Downton Abbey alter ego Matthew Crawley, there was no better role than this. As the mysterious stranger who shows up to pay his respects to the family of a fallen army comrade, you have established your place in the company of cinema’s all-time great tough guys. You, sir, are no Hugh Grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guest&lt;/em&gt; might as well have been subtitled &lt;em&gt;A Series of Gratifying Revenge Fantasies&lt;/em&gt;. Throughout the film, schoolyard bullies are brutally punished, lecherous ex-boyfriends are publicly shamed, and professional rivals disappear under suspicious circumstances. But simply bringing to life juvenile daydreams of comeuppance doesn’t a great film make. And &lt;em&gt;The Guest&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a great film (one of 2014’s best, according to at least two &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/31/jared-youngs-top-films-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;highly-respected&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/31/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;film critics&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this greatness is in the film’s clever confounding of expectations. Director Adam Wingard achieves this by rooting the style and narrative in a familiar place: the world of cheap, violent videocassette thrillers (think early John Carpenter, or &lt;em&gt;The Stepfather&lt;/em&gt;). But as the film progresses, he begins to break the rules. Our assumptions are, every few minutes, recalibrated. Apprehension turns to attraction. Attraction turns to suspicion, then repulsion. And in the very last moments of the film, impossibly, that repulsion becomes admiration. It’s classic sleight-of-hand. It looks like he’s playing a familiar magic trick, but while you’re watching closely for wires and mirrors, you realize he’s pulling off something much grander.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a difficult feat for any filmmaker. And an even more difficult feat for the actor who must embody all those subtle (and not-so-subtle) shifts. But both of you pull it off. Even the carefully-curated soundtrack is proof of Wingard’s movie-nerd bonafides: it gets the tone exactly right, all drum machine beats and ominous synth swells. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.myfonts.com/fonts/adobe/friz-quadrata/&quot;&gt;typeface&lt;/a&gt; of the titlecard, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m making it sound like a &lt;em&gt;The Guest&lt;/em&gt; is some kind of esoteric metatextual experiment. It’s really just an excellent capital-M &lt;em&gt;movie&lt;/em&gt;, built from a series of excellent movie moments. All of which focus on your character. Ultimately it’s your performance that elevates &lt;em&gt;The Guest&lt;/em&gt;past the conventions of the genre. The uncompromising stare, those blazing eyes, that swagger, that smirk—in most films, all of that coolness would simply be in service to the star’s ego. But your seduction of the audience, here, is to a greater purpose. And somehow you pulled it off while wearing a hoodie and a crisp golf shirt.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/14/the-guest.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/14/the-guest.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Top Five</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;On a Hollywood film, there’s only one job that belongs &lt;em&gt;uniquely&lt;/em&gt; to the director: coaching the actors. Hair, make-up, costumes, set design, special effects, editing—pretty much every other responsibility is delegated to one degree or another. Even choosing camera angles and the look of a film can fall disproportionately on a good cinematographer’s shoulders (which is how they earn their reputations as the hardest working person on set). So when I saw you in the credits for &lt;em&gt;Top Five&lt;/em&gt;, it confirmed what I had suspected: Chris Rock can’t direct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, when you’ve been hired, it’s to train actors for a very specific – and often technically difficult – level of specificity, like hitting the Kennedy brother’s broken Boston cadence (like you did in &lt;em&gt;Thirteen Days),&lt;/em&gt; achieving a believable stutter (like you did in &lt;em&gt;The Green Mile)&lt;/em&gt;, or helping someone master a foreign accent or speak a second language (like you did with Jet Li in &lt;em&gt;Lethal Weapon 4&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it&amp;#39;s possible that &lt;em&gt;Lethal Weapon 4&lt;/em&gt; is where you met Rock. And maybe he kept you in mind for &lt;em&gt;Top Five&lt;/em&gt;. Or maybe he just learned from his first two films – &lt;em&gt;Head of State&lt;/em&gt; in 2003 and &lt;em&gt;I Think I Love My Wife&lt;/em&gt; in 2007, that he needed all the help he could get. I certainly won’t fault him,&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/29/unbroken.html&quot;&gt;or anyone&lt;/a&gt;, for stacking the deck in their favour. But in this case, it just makes the failure all the more inexcusable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the acting. Chris Rock may or may not have actually suffered from alcoholism in his life, but, if so, he sure doesn’t know how to translate that into a believable performance. His deficiencies as a dramatic actor would usually have no bearing on his comedic delivery, but &lt;em&gt;Top Five&lt;/em&gt; isn’t just a straight-up comedy. It meanders with the overreaching ambition of Richard Linklater’s &lt;em&gt;Before&lt;/em&gt; series, yet tries to anchor its meandering with a conventional Hollywood plot—minus any of the necessary turns or emotional beats that might qualify the film as a proper drama (or even a dramedy). Much of this failure has to do with Rock’s own high-pitched, always in-on-the-joke delivery, which makes him more than ever feel like the Black Seinfeld (who, speaking of which, makes a very amusing out-of-character cameo). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that’s on you. I can’t imagine who else you were hired to help. Rosario Dawson is always great, and gives her performance more heart than the script does. Most of the other actors are simply playing variations of themselves, or characters we’re familiar with them playing. That, at least, allows for enjoyable bits scattered throughout the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are still too many scenes that drag on a little too long, a story structure that complicates instead of clarifies, and a title that’s as throw-away as many of the scenes. &lt;em&gt;Top Five&lt;/em&gt; can’t help but disappoint. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe next time, coach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/12/top-five.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/12/top-five.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
