<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Tomorrowland</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When your primary intention in making a film is advocating for a specific political viewpoint, you’re no longer making art, you’re making a piece of propaganda. That isn’t necessarily a negative. There is some Soviet-era cinema chock full of overt political intentions that works just fine. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland,&lt;/em&gt;  however, it is a poisonous way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your film concerns itself with our species’ impending, self-inflicted, apocalypse. More specifically, it is about how that apocalypse might be averted, if only those of us who still remember how to dream can find common cause. As an elevator pitch I have heard worse, but during the trip from the elevator to the screen it seems that the movie got “Lindeloffed”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Clooney and Britt Robertson (he is a broken, cranky, inventor genius, she is a young, cranky, inventor genius) don’t ever connect with each other, or the audience. And the story itself is poorly told, relying on hackneyed plot devices and almost cartoonishly one-dimensional character types. These are just the most obvious indications of how &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland&lt;/em&gt; was influenced by a man who once wrote &lt;em&gt;Nash Bridges&lt;/em&gt; episodes. (I’m looking at you Damon.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also true—at least for you, Brad—that most of your earlier movies were already teetering on the edge of this kind of polemic scolding. &lt;em&gt;Iron Giant&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Incredibles&lt;/em&gt; especially weren’t particularly subtle about their political leanings—a weird mix of exceptionalism and finger wagging about the dangers of the Military Industrial Complex. They were redeemed by their charm and an earnest commitment to story that muted some of the more irritating evangelizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most egregious example of &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland&lt;/em&gt;’s failure as an entertainment is how transparent its creator’s intentions are. Every beat of the story is telegraphed in a way that makes the whole project inevitable, and in the dullest way possible. It’s a tricky enough thing to lace a story with ‘meaning’, but when half the writing team is someone responsible for things like &lt;em&gt;Prometheus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cowboys and Aliens&lt;/em&gt; it becomes an impossible task. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another irritating byproduct of this kind of clunky narrative is that the characters flatten out and become gossamer thin. What comes out of their mouths is driven by expositional need. There is no depth to their portrayal because they are just mouthpieces, rather than people with their own inherent contradictions and idiosyncrasies. Even Tomorrowland itself is less an aspirational destination than it is a leaden and uni-dimensional MacGuffin that drives the plot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Laurie is the only one of the cast that manages to imbue his character with something resembling complexity and that is because, like all British actors, he can say one thing while very clearly meaning something else entirely. Every other character is little more than a wind-up automaton. Except the robot—who is, oddly, the most unpredictable character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland’s&lt;/em&gt; failure may have been inevitable in some ways. I remember reading one critique of &lt;em&gt;The Incredibles&lt;/em&gt; that pointed out its could be read as a little authoritarian and elitist. I scoffed but it was a scoff that secretly lacked conviction. Unfortunately, in this film those minor themes have become pre-eminent. In fact, &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland&lt;/em&gt; is so weirdly upside down that Hugh Laurie gives a lengthy speech in the third act of the film—a monologue that is supposed to be his manifesto of E.V.I.L.—that turns out to be the most heartfelt, genuine, and true moment in the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the movie concludes with an overtly manipulative visual that looks like a mash-up of a Socialist Realist Poster and a Benetton ad from the early 2000s. It felt like a moment born in a boardroom much more than an earnest expression of hope. And there is nothing worse than subverting genuine hopefulness in the aid of cynical ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a lot of splainin’ to do, Mr. Lindelof and Mr. Bird&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/22/tomorrowland.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/22/tomorrowland.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Hot Pursuit</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You are in a very small club of actresses that can open both a high-concept comedy and a heavyweight Oscar-bait film. In fact, the only other (current) member of that club is Sandra Bullock, who anchored both the Academy Award-nominated &lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt; and scored a hit with Melissa McCarthy in the buddy-cop comedy &lt;em&gt;Heat&lt;/em&gt; in the same year. So when &lt;em&gt;Hot Pursuit&lt;/em&gt; previews started popping up a few months ago I did something I almost never allow my cynical, critic-self to do: I got excited. I realize this isn’t your fault. It wasn’t you that got my expectations up. But after your raw performance in last year’s &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; (which you also produced), it seemed like you were poised to continue the femme-forward momentum with this screwball, odd-couple comedy (co-starring and produced by Sofia Vergara). “It’s not a fluke”, I thought, “women over 35 are finally staking their claim at the box-office!” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a moment during the funniest part of &lt;em&gt;Hot Pursuit&lt;/em&gt; when you look in the camera and sarcastically say, “I was giving the performance of a lifetime”. It’s obvious you knew you weren’t making a cinematic masterpiece. And that’s fine. No one was expecting &lt;em&gt;Hot Pursuit&lt;/em&gt; to rival &lt;em&gt;Citizen Kane&lt;/em&gt;. It’s unfortunate, though, that the funniest part of the movie was in the outtakes reel that played as the end credits scrolled past. By that time my hopes weren’t just dashed, they were hiding under the seat in shame. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reese, I’m not mad at you. I’m just disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hot Pursuit&lt;/em&gt; follows Cooper, a by-the-books cop who must transport Daniella, the high-maintenance wife of a crime lord’s accountant to testify as a state’s witness. When Cooper discovers that two of her co-workers are working for the crime lord, she and Daniella become fugitives who must work together to clear their names and save their lives. That premise doesn’t exactly reinvent the wheel, but it’s a formula that’s worked in the past—&lt;em&gt;Midnight Run&lt;/em&gt; did it with great success with Robert DeNiro and Charles Grodin—and it depends on the two leads having exceptional comic timing and natural chemistry, both of which you and Sofia Vergara possess. But you play Cooper as Tracey Flick without the delicious darkness, and Sofia spends the movie screeching over your Southern twang, resulting in an aural assault that can best be described as what I imagine terrified seagulls strapped to a rollercoaster must sound like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, you did almost everything right. You and Sofia decided you wanted to work together so you hired writers who’ve had success writing television for women (&lt;em&gt;Whitney, New Girl&lt;/em&gt;), and a female director with some impressive credits under her belt (&lt;em&gt;27 Dresses, The Proposal)&lt;/em&gt;. So it’s not fair for me to place the blame for &lt;em&gt;Hot Pursuit&lt;/em&gt;’s failure on your tiny actress shoulders. But as a producer, and a seasoned one at that, you should have seen this script’s stink lines quivering off the page. Maybe you thought you and Sofia could just power through the dung, and believe me, it was obvious you were trying very hard to do that. But it wasn’t just the jokes that were lame. The production design, staging, cinematography and editing were all so cheaply assembled that the few punchlines that should have soared right out of the park, instead landed with a dull thud at your tiny feet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About your diminutive stature, the film’s repeat gag involving news reports which exceedingly describe you as smaller and Sofia as older is one of the few that worked in the trailer. Unfortunately, we learn more about your characters in that two minute teaser than we do in an hour-plus of screen time, maybe because you each only get exactly two character traits; Cooper is uptight and bumbling, and Daniella is hot and spicy. If the script’s minefield of plot holes didn’t set off any alarm bells for you, its lazy stereotypes should have. Daniella constantly refers to you as a little man, and “Officer Lesbian”, while she uses her boobs or her “lady problems” to get you out of situations. At one point, after having been shot at, accidentally dosed with cocaine, and handcuffed together, the two of you steal a truck and talk about Cooper’s undateability, lamenting that she doesn’t yet have a ring on her finger. Bechdel wept!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not mad that you made a shitty movie. A-list actors like Johnny Depp, do it all the time, and he doesn’t even have an Oscar. The problem is that female actors, producers, writers and directors of a certain age don’t just have to work twice as hard to be considered half as good as their male counterparts, they have to work twice as hard just to get a foot in the door. It’s a huge responsibility and it’s not fair, but that’s how it is. I’m disappointed because you had a huge opportunity and you wasted it on &lt;em&gt;Hot Pursuit&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re disappointed too, give Sandy Bullock a call and ask her how she felt after &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;About&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Steve&lt;/em&gt; (which she produced and starred in) tanked. At the very least she can give you pointers on how to accept your Razzie gracefully.  &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/21/hot-pursuit.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/21/hot-pursuit.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mad Max: Fury Road</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;With all the sequels, remakes, reboots, and general scouring of any and all studio properties, a new Mad Max movie always felt like more of a &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; than an &lt;em&gt;if.&lt;/em&gt;  And the way your career has gone (i.e.: away), it would have no doubt been a dream to once again strap on the leather and pads, shimmy into a V8 Interceptor and roar into the wastelands once again as Max Rockatansky in &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, it was not to be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe having you star &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; director and co-writer George Miler’s original plan—you guys did make three Mad Max films together, after all—but I would hazard a guess that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnn.com/2006/LAW/08/02/gibson.charged/index.html?_s=PM:LAW&quot;&gt;your own roadside adventures&lt;/a&gt; played a role in keeping you out of this installment. The only wastelands you’ve been wandering lately are those of Hollywood unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked out pretty great for us, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of you in the tile role, we have Tom Hardy. As great an actor as he can be, I wouldn’t necessarily call this an upgrade: he’s definitely doing a gloss on your character, and let’s face it, Max has never been the world’s greatest acting challenge (as a man of very few words, though, it does require charisma, which both of you have in spades). What the recasting does, though, is allow Miller to pull of a subversive little trick, shifting the focus of the story almost without us noticing. Max is not the center of the story;he’s a way into the story. The story of Charlize Theron’s Imperator Furiosa. Max is still the central character – his is the only head we ever truly get inside, but he partakes in events more out of instinct than will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t see this being any kind of possibility if you were the star. Your clout and ego would have required (and, lets be honest, at least semi-justified) a plot center almost entirely on you. That would have been a shame. I can’t see a Mel Gibson-fronted film placing its focus so squarely on a female co-lead. After all, the last time you tried to make a movie with Feminist overtones, we got &lt;em&gt;What Women Want.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we have Hardy’s Max as our guide into the Citadel, a massive compound where the tyrannical (and, in a triumph of costume design, terrifying at first sight) Immortan Joe rules over his gang called the War Boys. These pasty-white disciples have a fanaticism for Joe’s brand of religious violence matched only by their worship of the steering wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he is captured in the film’s opening scenes, Max becomes a human blood bag for a War Boy named Nux, and as such, is attached to Nux’s battle car in the massive chase for Furiosa, who has stolen Joe’s most prized possessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s almost all the plot &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt; has. And it’s rather beautiful. It’s one of the most basic formulas you can use to create a narrative: &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; took &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt; wants &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt; returned at all costs. There are nuances and extra details, of course, but this main structure is introduced efficiently. As you know, one of Miller’s specialties is world-building, whether it’s the post-apocalyptic landscapes of the Mad Max films, or the animal inhabited hotel of &lt;em&gt;Babe: Pig in the City,&lt;/em&gt; Miller can convey more information in a single, striking image (say, a fresh back tattoo detailing blood type and donor information) than Christopher Nolan can in an entire monologue. This has the benefit of getting story mechanics out of the way to make room for the action. And that’s a smart move because my God, the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing how much mileage you can get out of an action scene when the overriding goal is to simply stay alive. The modern action movie has become so reliant on upping the stakes on everything that it&amp;#39;s led to a kind of suffocating numbness when it comes to actions spectacles. It might make logical sense that if the fate of the entire world hinges on the outcome of every action, that the audience will be all more emotionally invested. But destruction on that scale the opposite effect: it makes the concept of danger abstract and minimizes when it wants to inflate. Without a relatable, specific point of reference, it&amp;#39;s hard for an audience to feel any real connection. This explains why recent attempts at the spectacular (&lt;em&gt;Star&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Trek Into Darkness&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Man of Steel, Avengers: Age of&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ultron)&lt;/em&gt; have relied so much on 9/11 imagery: massive urban destructions is unfortunately something too many of us have relationship with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when the goal of a film&amp;#39;s hero is to just not die, you can feel the narrative freedom it creates. Not dying is the most basic of instincts – it doesn&amp;#39;t need any exposition. You know this fact as a much as anyone: you proved it with &lt;em&gt;Apocalyptico,&lt;/em&gt; a film almost as dialogue free as &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt; (your &lt;em&gt;The Passion of the Christ&lt;/em&gt; standing as an antithesis, as its character’s goal was to die, and take the longest possible time achieving that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than that, though, because the risks in &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt; are primarily physical (rendered exponentially more visceral by the reliance on largely physical effects and stunt work), Miller and his collaborators can put information—both narrative and functional—on screen with a speed and clarity I&amp;#39;ve rarely seen. The irony here is that as faster and furiouser &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt; gets, the closer it achieves its greatness through what can only be called beautifully classical filmmaking. It definitively proves that a mastery of techniques close to a century old—techniques that have formed a grammar that now exists at almost a subconscious level—can actually create something both relevant and fresh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And fast. There is a six or seven shot sequence in one of the many amazing highway pursuits that involves Max jumping laterally from one vehicle to another, grasping onto the side of speeding rig, only to be pulled vertically upward by another marauder. It lasts maybe 5 seconds on screen, yet involves multiple camera positions that travel from one vehicle to the next and then upward. Yet the editing is so crisp, and the motion carries so fluidly through every shot, we are never once unsure about where we are and, more importantly, where the characters are. It’s the kind of sequence that could be used to teach a filmmaking class the beauty of editing. It’s also the kind of sequence that can only be realized by a filmmaker with something lacking in much of today’s blockbuster environment: and overarching, coherent vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at me: getting all films school 101 on you when I know you don’t need it. You’ve worked with Miller three times; you’ve seen how he works, and I’m sure you learned from him on those sets. And I’m running the risk of making &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt; sound like something only an academic would appreciate. Let me rectify that. &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt; contains enough bizarre imagery, grotesque characters, and full-out jaw-dropping set pieces to fuel five regular movies. It’s been thirty years since Miller directed you in &lt;em&gt;Mad Max Beyond&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thunderdome&lt;/em&gt;, and every warped image and incident he could dream up in that time finds its way onscreen. After all, a blind albino death metal guitarist riding the hood of a monster truck might have felt a little out of place in Miller’s most recent works, &lt;em&gt;Happy Feet&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Happy Feet 2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t feel too bad that you didn’t get the call to return to Miller’s wastelands. You have enough other things you should feel truly bad about. Maybe you would have gotten the call if you hadn’t so thoroughly sabotaged your own career and good standing. But the Mad Max films were never all about you—or really about Max himself. He’s a through-line for the audience; a way in. Taking you out of that equation has allowed Miller to stay true to his own vision. And that’s something from which we all benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/20/mad-max-fury-road.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/20/mad-max-fury-road.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Pitch Perfect 2</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Putting together a vocal arrangement that sounds both perfect and unexpected isn’t easy. Sure, anyone with a basic understanding of music knows which notes sound good together. Just stick to intervals and, to the average ear, things are fine. But they’re also boring, and what gave a cappella groups a bad rap in the first place. You need to take risks.Be brave enough to fail. And if you do fail, own it. Or, like they say in jazz: If you make a mistake, play it twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pitch Perfect 2&lt;/em&gt; is not the repeat of a mistake (I really &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/10/3/pitch-perfect.html&quot;&gt;enjoyed the original&lt;/a&gt;), but it does take morerisks, doubles down on them, and it pays off. It’s that rarest of comedies that’s better than the original in almost every way.The jokes are crasser, and land even better. The music is more energetic, but also emotional. The film even manages to create a team-equivalent tap-along to the famous &lt;em&gt;Cups&lt;/em&gt; song that became an internet and campfire craze three years ago (for every girl under 16 years old). The odds of this happening, and working again, were next to nil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, on paper the film feels like it’s committing the &lt;em&gt;Mighty Ducks 2&lt;/em&gt; sin of needlessly jumping to the international stage when the first one was only based on a local championship. But &lt;em&gt;D2&lt;/em&gt; this is not – it’s &lt;em&gt;PP2&lt;/em&gt;, which sounds like a juvenile joke that Rebel Wilson’s Fat Amy would have made. But she probably would have made it work, too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, in the same way throwing a bunch of funny people in front of a camera won’t automatically make it  a funny movie, most people don’t understand how it’s the unexpected and borderline dissonant additions that make a vocal arrangement special. You need complimentary but unique voices that can work together to create something harmonious. Then, you need to make sure everyone isn’t trying to out-Beyoncé each other – yet still gets a moment to shine. Just like comedy. And &lt;em&gt;Pitch Perfect 2&lt;/em&gt; finds that balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film not only manages to bring in nearly every single character from the first film, but also gives us a few more to fill out the corners – from the over-eager and slightly awkward newbie played by Haillee Stanfield, to a Latino character with countless immigration horror stories, to a host of great antagonists (including Keegan Michael-Key). It takes a lot of love and care to keep this formula fresh, but razor-sharp &lt;em&gt;30 Rock&lt;/em&gt; writer Kay Cannon is once again up to the task. She’s helped in no small part by Elizabeth Banks, who makes an impressive feature directorial debut after producing the first &lt;em&gt;Pitch Perfect&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, even her own on-screen exchanges with John Michael Higgins are miles funnier than the original. As bitter a cappella commentators, it feels as though they finally found their voice in this film, as opposed to being stuck in cut-away rescue-joke mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the whole sounded just great to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/15/pitch-perfect-2.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/15/pitch-perfect-2.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Good Kill</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Like so much of &lt;em&gt;Good Kill&lt;/em&gt; your work is thoughtful and competently executed. The main title sequence, which features GPS co-ordinates running beside each credit, as if tracking the person in real time, is an interesting conceit. Unfortunately the film never quite rises to the promise of that beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethan Hawke is largely convincing as a US Air Force veteran adjusting to his new reality of remotely piloting drones from a station in the Nevada desert. The supporting cast, most notably January Jones as Hawke’s wife and Zoe Kravitz as Hawke’s rookie co-pilot, also perform admirably, given what they have to work with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film begins strongly. We witness Hawke’s gradual descent into alcoholism and emotional isolation as he struggles with the dissonance between killing at a distance of seven thousand miles and his previous experience of war. Much of his character’s struggles stem from the difficulty of managing the transition from the messy, adrenaline driven reality of war into the antiseptic labor of piloting a joystick in an air conditioned box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the film begins to falter is with the arrival of the CIA (represented by the officious and disembodied voice of Peter Coyote over speakerphone) and the split between the morally conflicted protagonists and those in the unit that are happy to kill anyone with a beard and turban. Hawke’s seemingly inevitable alienation from his wife and children also reinforces the feeling that the plot is driving the characters actions, rather than the other way around. These moments all feel like something being checked off a list rather than events emerging organically from the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some positive moments though. Not the least of which is a recurring visual device where we see the suburbs of Nevada as if through the eyes of a drone. This mirrors many of the remote combat sequences in Afghanistan—with the important difference being Hellfire missiles aren’t vaporizing the houses in Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visually the film utilizes the stark, binary nature of the Nevada desert to good effect, creating a counterpoint to the empty truck containers that house the pilot’s combat stations. Each time Hawke emerges from the dark interior into the relentless glare of the desert sun both he and the audience are reminded of the surreal nature of this kind of modern warfare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end though &lt;em&gt;Good Kill&lt;/em&gt; is too didactic to completely succeed as a drama. This is most apparent in Coyote’s performance as the CIA “voice” which is essentially a bunch of empty moustache twirling rather than the kind of moral ambivalence and careerism you can find in films like &lt;em&gt;Zero Dark Thirty&lt;/em&gt;. It is this lack of character depth and the transparency of its political leanings that prevents &lt;em&gt;Good Kill&lt;/em&gt; from being more than an anti-drone polemic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fascinating and complicated film to be made about exactly what it means to utilize drones as a means of waging war. Sadly, as I watched your lovely end credits roll, Kate, I knew I had yet to see that film.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/14/good-kill.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/14/good-kill.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Kurt Cobain: Montage of Heck</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Without you, this film doesn’t exist. Writer/director Brett Morgen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecredits.org/2015/05/brett-morgen-on-kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck-how-frances-bean-made-it-happen/&quot;&gt;has said so&lt;/a&gt; several times, in no uncertain terms. This incredibly intimate,unflinching, and insightful documentary about your father, Kurt Cobain, provides the personal access many fans have been craving for years from the late media recluse. But I can’t imagine how much the film must have meant to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world lost an important voice, but you lost so much more: the chance to grow up loved by a man who, the doc makes brutally clear, suffered many demons in his life – from drugs, to debilitating illness, to a trainwreck of a wife. The sum total became a pain he seemingly couldn’t overcome, and now Morgen is literally picking up the pieces to try and salvage the soul of the man. Partly for us curious fans, sure, but really he did it for you – Kurt’s only child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks to your involvement, warring factions from all sides of the post-Nirvana legal drama appear:  friends, family, past lovers, bandmates , and of course, Courtney Love -  your “biological mother” (as you refer to her on Twitter in between restraining orders and general estrangement). Love is certainly an important puzzle piece to the story structure, but her most essential contribution is the treasure trove of original material she provided the filmmakers, rather than anything of substance in her interviews. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your father’s early sketches, for example, play a major role in the “montage” aspects of the titular “heck”. There’s a maniacal restlessness and chaos to their design, which almost vibrate off the page with their excessive motion lines and frenetic accentuations. Mountains of home videos, diary entries, and raw recordings, and even original animation used to create re-enactments all help to construct a truly compelling portrait of a man whose legend has only grown in the music scene in the 20 years since his suicide. But most importantly, the clearance of music means that not only do we get to hear all the songs that made Nirvana the rock phenomenon they became, but even the score deconstructs and rebuilds classic tracks to help set an intimate atmosphere that always feels like an extension of your father’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most surprising is how the film doesn’t shy away from your father’s faults and foibles. One particular story, about the time he tried to lose his virginity to an overweight girl who was mentally challenged, before attempting to commit suicide, is intense and revealing. Most children would never grant permission to use a story like that when charged with preservation of their parent’s legacy. But I think you saw the bigger picture –how the need to connect meant not just giving the people the man they want, but offering a glimpse of the complex man he really was (in as much as any two hour film could ever attempt to do).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most disappointing, however, is the non-inclusion of Nirvana’s former drummer/current rock superstar Dave Grohl. Morgen has said Grohl was interviewed, but only 10 days before the film’s scheduled premiere, and that he just couldn’t fit him into the film. I won’t start any more rumours, but suffice to say that even a single line from the man would have helped make the film feel complete. Then again, I guess achieving that feeling was never going to be possible, for fans or for you. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Maggie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;After all these years of doing battle with the likes of Satan, sport-hunting aliens, assorted criminal scumbags, and a headache that was definitely not a tumor, I can say with a reasonable degree of certainty that, when word first came that you would be starring in a zombie flick, we all had the same generic shoot ‘em up playing in our heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, the whole zombie thing is a sub-genre I&amp;#39;ve burnt out on, and even with your name on the marquee I had a fair amount of reservations before sitting down to watch &lt;em&gt;Maggie&lt;/em&gt;. So you can imagine my delight when it proved to be a far more than your typical zombie film—and, on top of that, offered a performance from you that is unlike anything we&amp;#39;ve ever seen from you. After four decades, that’s pretty amazing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what makes &lt;em&gt;Maggie&lt;/em&gt; work so well is its neat sidestepping of the expected thematic beats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No petty infighting amongst the survivors. No climactic siege. No &amp;quot;perhaps &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; is the real monster after all&amp;quot; moralizing when the dust settles. Indeed, outside of an early attack scene, there are only a handful of moments where the undead are onscreen. Yet they never feel inconsequential to the story. The moody shots of a decimated landscape tell us every thing we need to know about how much the world has been impacted, and the script makes the wise decision to never provide an explanation as to how we wound up in this predicament in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the character type of “everyman” doesn&amp;#39;t immediately come to mind when one glances at your filmography. But as a humble Midwestern farmer spending what little time he has left with his infected daughter, there was never a moment where I questioned your commitment to the role. It&amp;#39;s a very sad and introspective performance, and reveals just as much through body language as dialogue. And there’s some heavy stuff to deal with; your character, Wade, must come to terms not only with the fact that his daughter is dying, but that he may have to be the one to end her suffering before she can become a danger to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your co-star Abigail Breslin really knocks it out of the park, as well. As Maggie, she brings a real sense of tragedy and pathos to the role. Even as the infection worsens, her humanity always shines through, and, just like Wade, we never see her as the monster others fear her to be. The chemistry you two share is wonderfully genuine, and even though there’s a certain degree of inevitability to how a story like this can end, it doesn&amp;#39;t make the actual moment any less gut-wrenching when it finally comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a move I wish more action stars of your calibre (and age) would take: act in smaller parts that offer greater opportunity to flex dramatic muscles (you know, instead of attempting to relive the high-octane days of yore).  It’s the reason I&amp;#39;ve never thought twice about &lt;em&gt;The Expendables&lt;/em&gt; and its sequels; seeing someone step outside their comfort zone is far more exciting than watching them rehash what made them famous in the first place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why I’m hoping that I can look forward to seeing you in similar roles in the future. Just think of the dramatic muscles as yet another part of your physical form that needs to be pumped up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/12/maggie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/12/maggie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ex Machina</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy to replicate human movement. There’s a non-mathematical rhythm to people’s physical motion that reflects their inner emotions – from nervous ticks, to sloppy posture, to general social awkwardness. It’s what makes us human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An actor’s job is to master these subconscious tells, and in &lt;em&gt;Ex Machina&lt;/em&gt;, you’re one of the many digital artists responsible tracking those very calculated movements. By compositing a mechanical structure to actress Alicia Vikander’s body, your mission is to make her character, Ava, look both real and distinctly… not. You’re creating a reverse &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_test&quot;&gt;Turing test&lt;/a&gt; on the audience. When you succeed, it’s a thing of beauty. But nowadays, that’s the easy part. The failure is that I had to spend so much time, both during and after the film, trying to understand the basic story logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a scientific experiment, it might sound fascinating for an eccentric tech billionaire to bring an unsuspecting employee to a remote location to determine if his latest invention possesses true artificial intelligence. But as a film treatment, it’s sorely lacking a dramatic thesis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know the robot was reverse engineered from an actor’s performance. Her face is completely recognizable, and her movements are that of a flesh-and-blood woman. So while we might initially spend some time admiring your digital effects work on the legs, arms and abdomen, we never actually question the humanity on display. Our journey is inverse from that of the protagonists – do we buy her as a robot? But while the characters are looking for the intangible elements that would reveal true emotional and developed intelligence (rather than programmed responses), we have time to ponder banal questions like – how could one solitary man ever create such an elaborate and secretive replica of the human eye (for example), complete with reds in the corners and veins? You know, the stuff you didn’t bother to touch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I ask myself, why is true A.I. so much more impressive than whatever this nearly-A.I. being is that we’re seeing? Based on Domhnall Gleeson’s reactions, it’s clearly an unparalleled feat in-and-of itself. So even if the story takes place in the near future (it never specifies), Oscar Isaac’s character would be the equivalent of Henry Ford withholding the release of the Model T until it could run on pure oxygen and emit zero emissions. And that’s where the film becomes too mechanical in its execution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen a few female characters (usually played by Scarlett Johansson) in the last year going on this same journey to discover what it means to be human. The novelty has become ho-hum from an audience perspective. But what works about the film is when writer and director Alex Garland contrasts clinical art direction with a seemingly laid-back mystery man at the center. It tells us something is off. Cracked glass in a window, and excessive drinking provide the types of flaws that makes surroundings and characters compelling.  But finding flashes of life in the human characters is far less interesting than what we might have seen in a robot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/8/ex-machina.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/8/ex-machina.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Superhero Craze Isn&#39;t Superficial</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most prevalent (and lazy) criticisms of the current spate of superhero themed movies is that they aren’t really about anything. At least anything other than filling sacks of cash for Disney or Warner or Sony or whoever else wants to throw a couple of hundred million dollars at Joss Whedon and his ilk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this particular criticism is that it is demonstrably wrong. It is so clearly incorrect that I am often baffled at how people who seem perceptive and well intentioned become so vexed that they lose the use of their critical faculties &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/04/are-the-avengers-really-saving-the-world-if-the-sequels-are-inevitable&quot;&gt;(like this guy)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-avengers-age-of-ultron.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/4/captain-america-the-winter-soldier.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain America: The Winter Soldier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or any of the other colon-ridden movies are not (a.) great art or (b.) without strong profit motive. But then again you could say that about almost all of culture since we first decided to tell stories around a campfire. You can, however, make distinctions about good and bad, and those distinctions have nothing to do with the box office returns a particular movie, or set of movies, generates (if they did then Michael Bay would be considered an auteur, and no one wants to live in that universe).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re talking about the MCU (Marvel Comics Universe) one of the reasons that some miss the forest for the trees has to do with the cross-pollination of sequential comics with traditional filmmaking. Most movies, even when you’re dealing with trilogies and sequels, are hermetically sealed. It is one of the defining features of mainstream cinema—a complete story is told in ninety or one hundred and twenty minutes. Comics work in a slightly different way. And that difference is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the comic book movies do differently, on a structural level, is that the main plot carries through several different films. Think of them as chapters rather than whole novels. Each chapter carries the narrative forward toward an eventual endpoint. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious caveat to be made here: some people do not want to spend the time, money, and energy necessary to engage with this kind of storytelling. For instance, I have never watched the entirety of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin_Alexanderplatz_(miniseries)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berlin Alexanderplatz&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, despite its universal acclaim. But my lack of interest says absolutely nothing about its intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who read, or have read, comics understand this kind of story telling intuitively because it is in the DNA of the form; broad, sprawling mythologies that often span several different titles and can take years to play out. Sometimes it is well done (see: Neil Gaiman’s &lt;em&gt;Sandman&lt;/em&gt; or Marvel’s &lt;em&gt;Civil War&lt;/em&gt; series). Other times, not so well (Marvel’s &lt;em&gt;The Ultimates&lt;/em&gt;). But when executed properly, they manage to tell a big, rambunctious story with some pretty interesting themes and a depth of character that can surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those responsible for the Marvel films, like Joss Whedon and Kevin Feige, understand this kind of structure intuitively. Whedon in particular wields enormous creative influence and has managed to do something I would have considered impossible even five years ago—he invested these movies with a pretty interesting through-line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What these movies are really exploring—from the beginning with the first &lt;em&gt;Iron Man&lt;/em&gt; through to the current &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; and beyond—is the inherent tension between the desire for security and personal liberty. Oddly enough, the strongest advocate for this chaotic and often-dangerous kind of freedom is the character that could have been the most banal and jingoistic: Chris Evan’s Captain America. This split becomes explicit in &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; and will play out in the coming Civil War storyline. And if the Russo Bros. do it justice, as I suspect they will, it will be a fascinating ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shield versus The Sword. The difference between preemptive paranoia and the idea that life is inherently dangerous and a certain amount of risk has to be accepted. In short, everyone eventually dies and the thing that matters is the quality of your life, not its length (even if death is an elastic concept in the MCU). This is the central conflict of these films and you don’t have to look very hard at any of them to see these two viewpoints banging up against one another. The idea that saving the world over and over again is the singular theme of these films is missing the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if this all sounds a little hyperbolic, that’s because it is. There isn’t much nuance here. However, the best of these movies carry an earnest power that subverts a certain tendency, in some quarters, to see the uncomplicated as something that lacks value. But like most entertainments worth that label, these films have an undercurrent that touches on things we all care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also drawbacks to this kind of narrative strategy. It risks sprawl. It risks commerce subverting the creative aspect so that some movies become nothing but placeholders (&lt;em&gt;Iron Man 2&lt;/em&gt;, I’m pointing in your direction). There is also an unevenness that is inevitable because no matter strong the central planning is, some directors and screenwriters are just more adept than others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well—and this is perhaps where the rubber hits the road—some of this critical contempt is less about the films themselves and more about how their fans engage with them. The idea of sweaty nerdlings losing their minds about men and women in costume puts some people off. An attitude which, while perhaps understandable, really has nothing to do with the films as creative enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On balance, the people at the helm of this particular Juggernaut have managed to smooth out most of the rough edges and create a body of work that holds up over time. These are thoroughly enjoyable films. They don’t speak to everyone, but what does (other than the truly banal).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best of them—&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Iron Man,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/3/iron-man-3.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iron Man 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Captain America: Winter Soldier&lt;/em&gt;—are quality works of genre fiction. They are well-written, well-executed, beautiful to look at, and emotionally compelling. More importantly, they move the whole story towards something that might be truly special. Fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am sure of is that the pointless hand-wringing over these films and their supposed lack of depth is misplaced. They are primarily entertainments, in the same way that most Broadway musicals are—or any kind of music, or most books, or any piece of cultural ephemera we consume. They are worth exactly as much time, energy, and attention as you want to give them. And if you prefer other things one of the very great features of middlebrow culture (at this point in history) is that you can never see a Marvel film as long as you live and still not lose a minute of sleep or lack any number of quality alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-superhero-craze-isnt-superficial.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-superhero-craze-isnt-superficial.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Avengers: Age of Ultron</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ll indulge me for a moment, I’m going to do a little reminiscing of my own. Something along the lines of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;letter you penned to your younger self&lt;/a&gt; when you first saw 2012’s &lt;em&gt;The Avengers.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what stage of superhero worship you would have found yourself in during the spring of 1984 – you’d have been what, 4 years old? – but it was probably deeper than mine. I was 11-years old, and more of a &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;G.I. JOE&lt;/em&gt; comic guy. Like &lt;em&gt;The Avengers,&lt;/em&gt; they were published by Marvel, but even back then I knew the truth: they were monthly, 30-page advertisements for toys. Superheroes just weren’t my thing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that day in May when I wandered into Checkers Convenience and saw &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars&lt;/em&gt; #1 on the spinner rack, even my Hasbro-addled brain knew it something special, something &lt;em&gt;big.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I wasn’t quite up-to-speed with the convoluted mythologies behind Iron Man, The Hulk, Captain America, Spider-Man, The X-Men didn’t matter—I wanted in. I ate up all 12 issues of the miniseries as fast as I could. And as a marketing vehicle, &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars&lt;/em&gt; achieved its purpose: it drew me into the larger Marvel Universe: &lt;em&gt;Peter Parker:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spectacular&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Uncanny X-Men&lt;/em&gt; became regular reading for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the following year, &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II&lt;/em&gt; came out. And in the very first issue – which managed to cross-reference &lt;em&gt;every single&lt;/em&gt; Marvel title being published at the time –I checked out. Making sense of it all was just too much damn work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be worried about where I’m going with this. You probably think that I’m going to say that &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; is the Marvel Cinematic Universe’s &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II;&lt;/em&gt; it buckles under the burden of too much baggage from past filmsand too many future plot-threads to establish; that it too obviously exists only to propagate more Marvel films. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; worry me going into the film. And I’ve levelled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/4/captain-america-the-winter-soldier.html&quot;&gt;similar complaints&lt;/a&gt; against the the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html&quot;&gt;ever-expanding&lt;/a&gt; Marvel Universe before (no one wants to have to do homework just to watch a summer blockbuster).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t worry. I come from the future to tell you to rest easy, slightly-younger Jared. For in the end, &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; is … fine. Your endlessly optimistic twelve-year-old-self might find &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; a huge disappointment, but now that you’re old enough to know that all things are not, in fact, possible, and that recreating past triumphs is mostly a fool’s errand, and that very few things in life are as fun the second time round, then...you’ll probably like this movie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, not love. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I was looking forward to this second instalment – even with my misgivings, I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; excited – I did feel a little bit of disappointment when Captain America, Thor, Iron Man, The Hulk, Black Widow, and Hawkeye reassembled on screen. Not disappointment in what I saw onscreen, but disappointment in my visceral reaction to it. Everything is executed as well as it was the first time around, but this time around it all felt kind of...well, expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, yes, you might argue that this is the curse of any sequel. About &lt;em&gt;Jurassic Park: The Lost World&lt;/em&gt;, Roger Ebert asked: where is the awe, the sense of wonder? (Answer: in the first movie.) I get it. I myself am always quick to point out that you should never review any film – even a sequel – by comparing it to another. But expectations are fair game. Expectations that, in these past three years – as Marvel schools other studios and publishers on how to build the ultimate interlocking franchise – have grown impossibly big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; certainly wastes no time in trying to meet those expectations. It opens with an extended action sequence, the scale of which any regular-sized movie would save for its climax. It’s way too long, sure, but it does immediately give us what we came for: The Avengers at their ass-kicking best. It also serves to introduce a new super-powered duo: the twins Pietro and Wanda Maximoff (of the two, Elizabeth Olsen’s Wanda makes much more of an impression, even if I still don’t understand exactly what her powers were supposed to be). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Olsen stands out is no small feat. This playing field is crowded with big personalities. While &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; might not have the same reverence for the characters you found in the original, Joss Whedon is determined to use his second outing as writer and director to give each of them their due—almost to a fault (the one exception is Thor, who is reduced to a walking joke delivery system when he’s not smashing things with his hammer). One thing that can be said for Whedon: he loves his character-building, and things get pretty Whedon-y in &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt;. For the most part, this is good: Jeremy Renner’s Hawkeye is an actual character this time around, and the action slows down enough to explore budding relationships and tensions within the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to give you a point-by-point plot summary here. The amount of footnotes I’d need to explain everything would make this the &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II&lt;/em&gt; of reviews. So I’ll itemize what you, so recently in love with Whedon’s first installment, will want to know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes: the show-stopping fight between The Hulk and Iron Man is just that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: as the movie’s big bad, James Spader’s Ultron is no match for Loki. Spader does admirable voice work, and Whedon makes him an interesting screen presence, but when you’re forwarding the story by cutting away from the goddamned Avengers, you better have something on-screen with hell of a lot of charisma. Charisma that the sleek, all-CGI Ultron just doesn’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: the plot is not particularly tight. Wanda Maximoff’s ill-defined powers left me confused about who was affected by what and for how long. And, not to pick on Thor again, but his particular arc seems to exist only to set up future installments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: the climactic action scene is not any more sensible this time around. Which is a shame, given that it’s the exact same urban destructathon.* Ultron’s army of indistinguishable robots is almost as indistinguishable as the armoured Chitari in &lt;em&gt;The Avengers&lt;/em&gt;. When this much pyrotechnic skill is on display the last thing I need to be thinking is, “I don’t know where anyone is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, yes: Marvel has shoehorned as many extra characters into this film as it possibly could, all in the interest of franchise building. War Machine, The Falcon, and The Vision (a brand new character introduced in the film’s last act) add very little, story-wise, but provide a way forward for more adventures. It’s here that you will see where Whedon’s idiosyncrasies come up against the behemoth that is Marvel. The mechanics of world building push Whedon’s interests out of the picture, quite literally. The side effect of this tension is that &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; feels more like a product than an entertainment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, hey, don’t let me ruin the 2012 afterglow. I still enjoyed the movie. Whedon’s dialogue and attention to (and love for) the characters goes a long way in overcoming the larger business interests of Marvel. And look on the bright side: when it came time for your childhood heroes to be turned into movies, the reigns were handed to Joss Whedon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1046173/&quot;&gt;Steven Sommers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0418279/?ref_=nv_sr_2&quot;&gt;Michael Bay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/avengers-age-of-ultron.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/avengers-age-of-ultron.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
