<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Babadook</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The best genre films are never by-the-numbers. They employ the comfort of convention as a way to explore deeper issues. Sci-fi, for example, is always richer as allegory. The most piercing comedy is often the simple result of tragedy plus time. Yet horror films are too often satisfied with immediate, visceral thrills—the kind of generic cinematic experience a “casual” director might be satisfied delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Babadook&lt;/em&gt; proves that Jennifer Kent is no casual director. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny, then, that she hired two “casual” ADs for this film. That word, both in North American and Australia (where &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Babadook&lt;/em&gt; was shot) can of course have multiple meanings. Perhaps you were only there on a part-time basis. After all, the film doesn’t feature any big international stars and was made for a modest 2 Million. But “casual” also has more negative connotations: from unplanned, to superficial, to indifferent. None of which apply to the filmmaking I witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Babadook&lt;/em&gt; is a careful and considered entry into the crowded supernatural thriller genre. It can “casually” be described like a thousand other films: a mother tries to convince her child that the monster he is seeing in their house isn’t real—until, of course, the sinister force becomes too powerful to deny. As an entry point, that might be all the audience needs, but you realized that the premise is actually an excellent way to explore PTSD, grappling with grief, and the pressures of being a single parent. None of that sounds too sexy for the poster, but in the same way the Babadook monster is explained through a hand-made pop-up kids book, the very menacing truth behind the message is what makes the film so haunting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also must have taken note, even in your cursory position, that Kent had structured her screenplay like an exorcism film, but secularized, and, ultimately, internalized. This evil-within-us approach is much more chilling, and brilliantly reinforced by one of those inexplicable news reports about a mother’s murder-suicide with her children. That simple injection of a familiar real-world horror story makes the fear very personal and much less outlandish that it could have been. In fact, the slow-burn of the film’s first act, devoid of any scares (earned or cheated), establishes believable characters in a recognizable world, all of which enhances the more fantastical events of the the following acts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two central performances by Essie Davis and the seven-year-old Noah Wiseman are easily the most memorable aspects of the film. But they’re also serviced by the perfectly atmospheric low-light cinematography, the rigorous art direction (with a strict adherence to moody colour palettes), and the subdued sound design that never once gives us cat-jumping false alarm jitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe your position makes sense. I can see how, after making a short film based on the same story almost a decade ago, Jennifer Kent might hire a couple young aspiring directors for her first feature film, sit back, and casually say: “Don’t worry. I got this shit.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Corner Gas: The Movie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Executive producers are usually one of two things: a dude or dudette with a bag full of money and lots of notes (often about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vgYhLIThTvk&quot;&gt;the necessity of giant spiders&lt;/a&gt;), or someone spiritually invested in the project. I absolutely believe you are more the latter than the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously a labor of love for you. A project that you care deeply about. The affection among the returning cast and the sheer exuberance of the performances are impossible to deny. And if good intentions and a willingness to mug endlessly for the camera are enough to bring to life a film that feels like it was based from a rejected Gilligan’s Island spec script, I would happily accept it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m old enough to have watched a lot of two camera sitcoms during the 70s and 80s. You must remember them as well, because &lt;em&gt;Corner Gas: The Movie&lt;/em&gt; feels like one of those “very special episodes” that often portended the cancellation of one of those shows. And no amount of crane shots or wide angle fades of Saskatchewan sunsets will change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know the episodes I’m talking about. The ones where little Kirk Cameron discovers he’s just a bit different than everyone else, or where Todd Bridges is confronted with – and defeats! – the demons of drug abuse. That kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This movie runs for ninety minutes, though it might have been put to better use as the last three episodes of your long running series. When your oft-repeated cultural reference is Ted Danson – even when the anachronism of that reference is ostensibly the joke – you should realize that the well you’re plumbing has run pretty dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also – this is going to read as bitchy – but &lt;em&gt;for the love of God&lt;/em&gt; if you’re shooting in HD in mid-summer Saskatchewan sunlight, please no close-ups. Even watching on my computer monitor, I was horrified. I can’t imagine what it would look like on the big screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though one of the few redeeming features of the series is that everyone is, to put it politely, one of us – Brangelina need not apply – combining poor cinematography with layers of stage makeup that looks like it was intended for a red carpet and not for unforgiving natural light actually made me turn away from the screen a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a reason it is called magic hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things just don’t translate. Some TV shows were meant for the small screen and nothing else. I don’t doubt that the whole cast and crew are charming, funny people, but none of that is evident in this big screen version. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d very much like my ninety minutes back. Or you could just send me the grant money set aside for &lt;em&gt;Corner Gas: The Movie 2&lt;/em&gt; and I’ll make a doc about grain elevators—which, sensibly, I’ll only shoot only between the hours of 7:30 and 8:30 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/5/corner-gas-the-movie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/5/corner-gas-the-movie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Serena</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Logging is dangerous business. You’ve no doubt heard (or even seen) your fair share of logging horror stories. It would seem that the people who are able to make a successful career in the industry are aware of the risks, and can anticipate a potentially hazardous situation by taking the proper precautions. But hiring an experienced crew and choosing a reliable base of operations isn’t always enough. Sometimes, despite the best efforts, the unthinkable happens, and it leaves everyone wondering how things could go so wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Serena&lt;/em&gt; is just that kind of tragedy. One that could have been prevented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s 1929, and George Pemberton is in danger of losing his Smoky Mountain timber empire after the Black Tuesday stock market crash. While back home in Boston, he meets and marries the mysterious Serena, the daughter of a late lumber baron. Together they return to the Smoky Mountains and must resort to desperate measures to keep from losing their company and their marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the Czech mountains stand in for the Smoky Mountains of the American Carolinas. But I can’t imagine that early twentieth century logging camps differed that much from one another: a few hastily built cabins for operations, barracks to house the men, some stables, long dirt roads that lead to the cutting sites. Your particular area of expertise involves cableway extraction, where winches and cranes are used to move the massive logs down the mountain. Early in &lt;em&gt;Serena&lt;/em&gt;, one of these cranes fails, gravely injuring a worker. George leaps into action to save another worker. If this is meant to demonstrate his heroism, it doesn’t quite square with the same man who summons a young woman from the cookhouse to his quarters for some after hours logjammin’. Endemic throughout the film are George’s conflicting traits, which are meant to add dimension, but instead lead to exasperation—and, ultimately, indifference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serena herself first appears astride a white horse. To say Jennifer Lawrence is perfectly cast to play Lady Macbeth-lite gives the film too much credit. She is just so frighteningly talented that at this point audiences would probably accept her playing Batman. And she would kill it. When she arrives at the basecamp on George’s arm, they’re greeted by a very pregnant cookhouse girl. Serena sums up the situation and coolly dismisses her. She very quickly proves herself equal to any man in the camp, training an eagle to catch snakes, showing the men how to properly angle a cut, and saving the life of the camp scout. It’s easy to see why Buchanan, George’s right hand man, feels edged out and plots to give up the cooked accounting books to the sheriff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I bet you’d welcome such a remarkable woman at your logging operation, wouldn’t you? It’s too bad, then, that Serena devolves from a confident and complicated female lead into a film trope generator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she has a miscarriage, then learns that George has been supporting his illegitimate child, she becomes unhinged. She convinces George they need to dispatch of anyone that might destroy what they’ve built (you know, because women are crazy). But this is probably because, as a child, she lost her whole family  (you know, because orphan women are even crazier). The last act of the film sees characters confessing, running from peril, and sustaining brutal acts of violence. There’s also a government land-grab subplot and a panther-as-hunter/prey metaphor to fill in the blank spaces on the narrative-device bingo card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J-Law’s tween fans will likely be put off by &lt;em&gt;Serena&lt;/em&gt;’s dreary pacing and unrelenting doom. Director Susanne Bier’s fans will be especially disappointed by the story’s lack of focus and abrupt character development, flaws absent in her far superior films like &lt;em&gt;After The Wedding&lt;/em&gt;, and In &lt;em&gt;A Better World&lt;/em&gt;. The look of the film is typical Bier, though: moody and sparse, with faces shot like landscapes, gorgeously lit by moonlight and candles. The score is particularly haunting and evocative. The cast – Bradley Cooper, Toby Jones and Rhys Ifans, and, of course, Lawrence – is exceptional.  That’s why it’s so frustrating that the film’s core elements, though carefully conceived, are undermined by the anemic script adapted from Ron Rash’s novel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just a shame we couldn’t see the forest for the trees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/4/serena.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/4/serena.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Penguins of Madagascar</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your career trajectory sort of came out of left field, didn’t it? Not only are you the voice actor for Skipper the penguin in &lt;em&gt;The Penguins of Madagascar&lt;/em&gt;, the latest spin-off of the Madagascar franchise, but you’re also the writer of the original film. It’s certainly not every day that the folks who toil on the screenplay get to voice characters in the movie they’re working on! And, even if they do, so far as I can tell it has never before been the case that their minor characters became so popular that they got their own movie and TV series. Kudos must also go to Chris Miller, Christopher Knights, and Conrad Vernon — the voices of the other penguins — who have likewise contributed in very different ways: as story artist, first assistant editor, and creative consultant on the original film, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how you all accomplished this achievement, aside from the fact that the penguins in the Madagascar movies are truly entertaining, not least of all because of your voice work. So, congratulations (even if every actor who has studied the craft of voice performance for years might secretly fantasize about squishing your head for achieving success by such a sideways path)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re lucky, too; this movie is actually far better than the last entry in the franchise, &lt;em&gt;Madagascar 3: Europe’s Most Wanted&lt;/em&gt;, which featured returning stars Ben Stiller, Jada Pinkett Smith, Chris Rock, and David Schwimmer (my apologies: I know you co-directed that one). What was a major weakness in that film — its randomness and lack of a solid story structure — actually works in the favour of such madcap characters as the penguins. It may have been a highly implausible story, but it nonetheless elicited a continuous chorus of giggles from the children surrounding me in the theatre (and from myself, let’s be honest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, go forth and enjoy the creation of &lt;em&gt;Madagascar 4&lt;/em&gt;, which I see is already in the works for 2018. Maybe next time, you can find a best boy or a grip to add to the voice cast? I’m sure they’d appreciate it (though I’m sure they’ll never be abled to top Werner Herzog’s delivery of “bumbum” in the opening narration).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diane Carol Harder&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/3/the-penguins-of-madagascar.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/3/the-penguins-of-madagascar.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Theory of Everything</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Synopsizing an entire life isn’t easy. That’s why biopics tend to focus on either a definitive period (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/16/lincoln.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lincoln&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, Walk the Line&lt;/em&gt;) or take the skipping-stone approach to key milestones (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/2/mandela-long-walk-to-freedom.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mandela: Long Walk to Freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, Ali&lt;/em&gt;). The right choice is always relative to the story you want to tell. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_The Theory of Everything doesn’t focus on a single period in Stephen Hawking’s life, nor does it hang a narrative on his famous scientific achievements. Rather, it tells a complicated love story that spans decades, all of which is perfectly summarized in your final sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, your job was pretty straightforward. By creating a montage that reverses both the chronology and speed of the film, you had the enviable task of cherry-picking all the most touching moments. And there are plenty to choose from. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warm, lush cinematography perfectly compliments this twirling romance, and barrels us back to a moment when everything was much simpler (in theory, anyway). We get to experience some wish fulfillment, watching Hawking’s degenerative ALS disease reverse itself until he’s spinning freely on his feet rather than in his electric wheelchair. It’s a beautiful and bittersweet ending that helps us re-experience and re-examine everything that comes before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes the performances. By using a distinctly cinematic technique, my attention was temporarily fixated on the filmmaking itself. Specifically, the stand-out performance by Eddie Redmayne. He captures more emotion in a pained smile than most impressionistic biopic performances manage altogether—which is equally a compliment to the film’s script by Anthony McCarten and the direction by James Marsh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t want to overlook what Felicity Jones brings to the role of Hawking’s wife, Jane. As far as the film is concerned, Hawking’s existence effectively begins on the night they meet. Which makes sense, considering Jane Hawking authored the book on which the film is based. But more importantly, the “Big Bang” sparks that occur that night are, in quantum terms, the singularity that brought this story into existence. But the film itself only pays passing interest to those theories; instead of chronicling Hawking’s noble pursuit for a simple equation to define the universe, &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt; looks at love as the only rational reason for being. Even if the formula can’t be proven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s how Stephen Hawking made a name for himself: by creating brilliant theories, then being their biggest critic. And looking back, love was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/1/the-theory-of-everything.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/1/the-theory-of-everything.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Horrible Bosses 2</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roar&lt;/em&gt; is the kind of song that gets you up in the morning.  You charge around the house, hairbrush microphone in-hand, making mirrored eye contact with yourself while mumbling 90% of the lyrics, but really belting out that chorus. At precisely 8:15 you rush out the door and catch the bus to work, where you sit silently, and avoid eye contact at all costs. &lt;em&gt;Horrible Bosses 2&lt;/em&gt; follows the same trajectory — moments of ambitious fantasy spoiled by harsh reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s still worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we rejoin Nick Hendrick, Kurt Buckman, and Dale Arbus, they’ve successfully moved on from their previous employers (in that they don’t have jobs) and have started a business. They’ve created the Shower Buddy, an all-in-one shower system designed to shave minutes off your morning routine. It’s pretty much a shopping channel dream. But they fumble their first promotional opportunity on a popular morning show thanks to minor product failure, overt sexual innuendo, and unintended racism. Afterwards, Nick, Kurt, and Dale commiserate in a bar, pondering their return to the cubicle. But that’s when they get the call. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what better ringtone to set the tone for what happens next?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Bert and Rex Hanson, a father-son team whose company, Boulder Stream, specializes in the manufacture of things that no one thought they needed. Bert, the patriarch of Boulder Stream, admires the boys’pull-themselves-up-by-the-boot-straps attitude and fuels their American Dream with a massive order. Cue&lt;em&gt;Roar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that dream ends with all the subtlety of a bucket of cold water to the face when Bert cancels the order with the intent of bankrupting their company, &lt;em&gt;Nick-Kurt-Dale&lt;/em&gt; (say it fast), and picking it up for pennies on the dollar. Not ones to settle conflict in traditional ways, Nick, Kurt, and Dale devise a plan to kidnap the younger Hanson for ransom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, as they discovered the first time around, they’re just not killers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, they’re not really kidnappers either and the whole plan goes sideways with a nitrous-oxide incident that results in Rex Hanson taking advantage of the situation and effectively kidnapping himself.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, things don’t go smoothly from this point but their plan is as entertaining as it is ineffective.  The film does try and touch on some of the bigger issues of a class system, but never too seriously, or too critically, so don’t expect to come out with a greater understanding of workforce empowerment in America. But let’s be honest, if you’re going to see this movie, you’d probably be disappointed if they brought you down with reality. This is the movie equivalent of your song; so grab a hairbrush microphone, suspend your disbelief for a bit, and enjoy your time in front of the mirror before you have to rush out the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cue &lt;em&gt;Roar&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Smart&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/28/horrible-bosses-2.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/28/horrible-bosses-2.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Laggies</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve wrangled many animals in the past, mainly dogs, and mainly on kid’s movies. All of which, I’m sure, requires a level of patience as a job prerequisite. But director Lynn Shelton’s latest mumblecore musing, &lt;em&gt;Laggies&lt;/em&gt;, ambles along at a deliberate pace. Shelley, the tortoise in your charge, moves so slowly that sometimes it must have seemed like she wasn’t going anywhere—but to Shelley, it probably felt like everything was blurring past at warp speed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28 year-old Megan is overeducated and underemployed. She lives with her high school sweetheart Anthony while working sporadically for her dad. Megan is content to stand on the sidelines as her high school besties tick off the wedding and baby boxes on their checklists. When Anthony suddenly proposes, Megan pretends she has a week-long seminar to attend, but instead hides out with her teen friend Annika. During that week, Megan vicariously relives her high school years and makes some serious decisions about her future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While other animal actors need constant grooming and PETA-approved trailers, it must have been refreshing to work with an actor and a director who are so low maintenance. Shelton often shoots in her native Seattle, which gives &lt;em&gt;Laggies&lt;/em&gt; an unobtrusive, organic quality. She does away with the glamourizing that plagues many quarter-life crisis films. Keira Knightley’s Megan looks less like a Chanel spokesmodel and more like the poster child for an Old Navy factory outlet. The homes and cars are unapologetically suburban, and instead of fancy coffee shops or nightclubs, the characters visit drive-thrus and strip mall restaurants. Megan doesn’t want the same cookie-cutter life as her friends, and it’s easy to see why it’s taken her so long to admit to herself that she’s outgrown them; their lives are comfortably bland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cast – Shelley The Tortoise included – is the best kind of understated. Chloe Grace Moretz plays Annika’s sadness about her mother’s absence matter-of-factly rather in the mode of a default Hollywood emotion. When Annika’s dad discovers Megan in the house, he sits her down for a friendly but guarded chat. Sam Rockwell possesses a rare, innate charm that can convince an audience he would let a strange woman stay at his house and not hit on her, while simultaneously making us wish he would. Knightley’s recognition of her untenable stasis is never forced, nor does her evolution feel artificial. She tells her sensitive new-age fiancée that her power animal is a tortoise, and it’s easy to see why he believes her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shelton has a knack for filming the literal and figurative spaces between people, and Andrea Seigel’s contrived (albeit likeable) script is at home in Shelton’s navel-gazing universe. She balances the self-analytical tone without allowing it become too precious or too cynical. The turtle-as-power-animal metaphor might have been a bit too facile if it wasn’t for the cast’s sincere delivery of Seigel’s unironically witty dialogue. It doesn’t take a tortoise wrangler to know that their shell protects a fragile soul. What’s less obvious (and perhaps more cumbersome) is the weight of our lives and how we owe it to ourselves to build ones worth carrying around for the long haul. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As every famous tortoise knows, life is a long distance race, not a sprint to the finish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/27/laggies.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/27/laggies.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Town That Dreaded Sundown</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The real-life events that occurred in the town of Texarkana in the late 1940s – an unidentified killer terrorizing the local populace – inspired filmmaker Charles B. Pierce to release &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; in 1976 (a pretty darn solid film in its own right, if memory serves). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remake, which you worked on, takes place in a universe where Pierce’s film is screened annually on Halloween, much to the chagrin of those old enough to remember the murders. Texarkana feels as if it never progressed past the 70s, with everybody possessing a wicked cool vintage car, popped collars, and era-appropriate feathered hair. But it’s primarily your excellent production design makes the town feel inexorably trapped in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe calling it a remake is a bit of a misnomer. On the one hand, some of the more iconic moments from the original are recreated – including the (in)famous trombone murder – and the present day investigation has intriguing parallels with the 1976 film. But this new version feels more like a sequel than anything else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constant references to Pierce’s original movie, even going so far as to have the director’s son appear as a total weirdo and potential suspect, could have lead to some truly unbearable meta-wankery. How fortunate then, that the writer and director are (for the most part) as capable as you are at balancing the ironic and sincere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a truly harrowing opening kill sequence, the premise for this reveals itself to be kinda brilliant: the heroine determines that the key to unmaking the modern day killer lies in getting to the truth of what happened half a century ago. Along with some impeccably orchestrated set-pieces – most notably a chase scene taking place in what appears to be a graveyard for used billboards (no idea how you thought this up, but it’s amazing) – we get a genuinely compelling mystery to tie it all together. It’s very welcome. I mean, there are some hiccups along the way, like the hilariously unbelievable romance between the Final Girl and a guy working at the town’s archive, but these are petty complaints in light of everything that works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then we get to a final act, which is so lackluster that it very nearly derails everything that came before it. I mean, I don’t think it’s fair to compare every self-referential movie to &lt;em&gt;Scream&lt;/em&gt;, but when the killer’s mask comes off and they explain their actions, the script seems to have borrowed liberally from the preeminent 90s meta-slashfest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy oh boy, is it ever lousy. Not just because it’s a reveal that any astute viewer can see coming from a country mile away. To be fair, there is a kind of cool secondary twist on the heels of this (non-)revelation, but it makes so little sense that the movie itself has to acknowledges how illogical it is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really hoping this would be a homerun, as your production work definitely suggested that this wasn’t simply going to be a remake/sequel/reimagining that would be content to go through the motions. And for the most part it isn’t. But that ending is such a goodwill-killer, which is a damn shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully we’ll be seeing more of your vision in future horror movies, as you bring a freshness sorely lacking in most of today’s genre output.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/26/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/26/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>God&#39;s Pocket</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’re best known as Joan Harris, the chilly office manager at the fictional ad agency in &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;. Joan is the proud figurehead of the Good Ship &lt;em&gt;Sterling Cooper &amp;amp; Partners&lt;/em&gt;, and not just because of her bombshell appearance. She’s the confident queen bee, feared, respected. But beneath the facade she’s a complicated, vulnerable woman. Joan is a character that comes along once in an actor’s lifetime. The kind of role that really showcases your gifts, and, no doubt, the kind of role that spoils you for future work. Especially roles like &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, in which your character is a literal figurehead: sculpted, wooden, and designed to lead men into a storm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; is the passion project of your &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; co-star John Slattery. It’s not only his feature directorial debut—he also co-wrote the script (adapted from Peter Dexter’s novel) and produced. You’re part of a dream cast of character actors he has assembled to tell the story of God’s Pocket, a gritty neighbourhood in the late-70s full of losers and crooks. Slattery, who has directed several &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; episodes, is obviously comfortable filming detailed period pieces; the art direction in &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; excels in capturing the colours, designs, and setting of the era while still managing to give the film a sense of timelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film’s problem isn’t style, its substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, of course, have no problem drifting through this bygone world. You play Jeanie, the mother of sociopathic loud-mouth Leon, who gets killed at his blue-collar job. You beg your husband Mickey to find out what really happened to Leon, while ensuring that he gets a proper funeral. Problem is, Mickey, a low-level crook, has no cash, and his boss, Arthur, is into the local loan shark for 20-Large. Meanwhile, local newspaper columnist Richard Shelburne, an alcoholic has-been and third-rate celebrity, gets involved in your case. But, of course, he ends up falling in love with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do you do? You sob, you sleep, you glare, you sashay around in too-tight house coats—talents perhaps better-suited to your torpid &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; co-star January Jones. This left me wondering why Slattery didn’t cast &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; in this lifeless role. But at least you didn’t have to suffer alone. Philip Seymour Hoffman plays Mickey as a schlubby Philip Seymour Hoffman-type, drifting through scenes covered in flop sweat and self-loathing. And there must have been a surplus of flop-sweat and self-loathing in the make-up trailer, because it’s doused liberally all over Richard Jenkins newspaperman and Eddie Marsan’s slimy funeral home director. What’s left is spritzed over the denizens of the local watering hole, where inveterate drunks get cut off and respond with things like: “You can’t cut off the truth!” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bet you were missing Matthew Weiner right about then. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery of your son’s death is just one of many unsatisfying threads that unravel into oblivion. There are horse races, dead bodies in meat trucks, unfulfilling sex scenes, and the occasional brutal act of violence—all of which are apparently essential to the ambling plot, though none are particularly intriguing. You only have about fifteen lines in the whole film, and half of them are, “I know something happened to Leon, I just &lt;em&gt;know!&lt;/em&gt;” Your job is to pose with laundry, in dirty kitchens, while being alternately avoided and pursued. This may be &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s still a man’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; feels like three separate movies. And none of them moved me. Particularly because in their attempt to combine unflinching, urban drama and dry humour, they succeeded at neither. This must have been particularly frustrating for you, since you’re so used to balancing both as the acid-tongued Joan. It’s even more unfortunate since &lt;a href=&quot;http://on.aol.com/video/roger-sterlings-best-one-liners-517732993&quot;&gt;John Slattery’s Roger Sterling is legendary&lt;/a&gt; for delivering some of &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;’s best lines while having arguably the most surprising character evolution on the show. It’s obvious, though, that his strengths as a director lie in visual storytelling. The writing of copy is a skill best left to somebody else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just sorry that 
you have to go back to the 60s to play a female character who is more than just a pretty face. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/25/gods-pocket.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/25/gods-pocket.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Virunga</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding ungracious, your work on &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; hurt my enjoyment of the film. Not because it was sub-par. Quite the opposite. The fact is, the sonic gloss you applied to Orland von Einsiedel’s documentary was so perfectly polished that it seemed at times to work against the very nature of the film and its intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your imprint is everywhere. From slow-motion shots of water droplets to ear-ringing gun shots and bombs, your hyper-realistic sound effects actually disengaged me from the material—albeit subconsciously. I felt like I was watching a Hollywood film. That says a lot, considering &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/change/2010/10/christopher-redmond.html&quot;&gt;my ongoing relationship&lt;/a&gt; with East Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the privilege of visiting the volcanic Virunga region of the Democratic Republic of Congo, and even spent time at Dian Fossey’s Gorilla Rehabilitation and Conservation Education (GRACE) center. Much of &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; plays out there, telling the story of a similar gorilla orphanage and the rangers tasked with protecting the surrounding national park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by protecting, I do mean with AK-47s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand firsthand the shock of seeing soldiers brandish their weapons so freely— and I understand the temptation to play that up. I’m guilty of the same dramatics when I recount my experiences travelling with mountain trackers and guides who are armed with guns to protect us not from the gorillas, but from the &lt;em&gt;guerillas&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is no doubt why the director indulges in a few dramatic point-of-view shots down the barrel of a gun. In that sense, your work is only complimenting his vision. Which isn’t entirely unjustified. The DRC is a ridiculously dangerous place. More people have been killed in the Congolese Civil War than in any other conflict since WWII. So when the story of &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; quickly turns from being that of a safari to surviving an armed take-over by M23 rebels, I know why you went full-clip on the sound effects. A simple shaky camera (in huge contrast to the film’s otherwise beautiful cinematography) is energized tenfold by the overwhelming echo of shelling and gunshots. But by laying that continuous sound bed over so many cuts, the danger felt almost manufactured. I felt manipulated, like you were trying to give me what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I wanted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not so different from my experience with the gorillas themselves. With only 800 in the world, seeing a majestic Silverback in the wild has truly been one of the highlights of my life.  In contrast, seeing a baby gorilla in one of those concrete rehab centers was one of the most depressing. It’s hard to articulate the profound nature of that difference, but it repeatedly came to mind watching the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is, while I’m spending a disproportionate amount of time fixating on your amplification of the drama, real drama does occur in this film. I hope that more people spend the money to visit these parks and support their preservation. I just hope you haven’t scared them away (I guess we’ll just have to remind them that entering the park from the Rwandan and Ugandan side is much, much safer).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/24/virunga.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/24/virunga.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
