<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Will a Female Comedian Ever Be a Movie Star?</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Sometime around the year 2000, I had a sad epiphany. While talking movies with some friends, I realized there was no female equivalent to the big comedy stars of the day: Jim Carrey, Mike Myers, Adam Sandler, Eddie Murphy, etc. The only counterexample we could think of was Cameron Diaz. But other than &lt;em&gt;There’s Something About Mary,&lt;/em&gt; there wasn’t much to base that argument on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I had no answer as to why a woman hadn’t broken through with the same success as so many men. But I figured it was only a matter of time. A new century was upon us, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to last weekend: another epiphany. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently three sitcoms  in my weekly must-watch TV schedule: &lt;em&gt;Girls&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Broad City&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt&lt;/em&gt;. Three shows that don’t just feature female leads, but each boast deep rosters of hilarious female characters and creators. And this is on top of other shows chalk full of great female leads like &lt;em&gt;Veep&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Mindy Project&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Parks and Rec,&lt;/em&gt; and easily a dozen others.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I tried to think of equivalent female &lt;em&gt;movie&lt;/em&gt; stars. Women who are performing in comedy films with the same success as their small-screen counterparts. Needless to say, I couldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What gives? Why is it that television has long been, and is now (perhaps more than ever) filled with funny female actors and rich characters, while female film stars are always one-and-done when it comes to big comedy successes? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first instinct is to blame Kristen Wiig. Who can forget the fervor that surrounded &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids&lt;/em&gt;, and the countless think-pieces that heralded the coming of an exciting new world of female-driven comedies? The film’s wild crossover success (evidenced, for me, by the fact my 81-year-old grandma also loved the film) resulted in a critical and financial bonanza, including two Academy Award nominations (Best Original Screenplay for Wiig and Annie Mumolo, and a Supporting Actress nod for Melissa McCarthy). But Wiig seemingly took all that goodwill and burned it with a string of low-energy indie films (&lt;em&gt;Girl Most Likely&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hateship Loveship,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/30/friends-with-kids.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Friends With Kids&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, The Skeleton Twins&lt;/em&gt;). Maybe it was a conscious reaction to the pressure, but, so far, it certainly feels like a squandered opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the four years since &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids&lt;/em&gt;, I don’t feel like we’re much further ahead. There are exceptions, of course. &lt;em&gt;The Heat&lt;/em&gt; made almost as much money as &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids,&lt;/em&gt; and co-starred McCarthy, who has made a valiant effort to be crowned the queen of comedy. Her crude clowning can kick ass, but her big test at solo stardom was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/24/tammy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tammy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which failed to generate significant business (or laughs). Her co-star, Sandra Bullock, also bucked the one-off comedy curse (&lt;em&gt;Miss Congeniality&lt;/em&gt;’s lackluster sequel, notwithstanding), but no one will ever consider the Academy Award-winner a comedy-first movie star. Same goes for Reese Witherspoon, Barbara Streisand, and Diane Keaton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiig still seems to be the Great White Hope for female comedy superstardom. Her campaign got a serious boostthis January when she was announced as one of the leads in the upcoming, all-female &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/ghosts-of-ghostbusters.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; reboot (along with McCarthy, Kate McKinnon, and Leslie Jones). But any excitement generated by that bold decision was quickly deflated by the seemingly knee-jerk follow-up announcement telling us not to worry because, of course, there will  be an all-male &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; remake as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I’m so relieved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who’s to blame here? Is it the writers who can’t generate funny female-driven scripts? Is it the studios? Can they really be &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; entrenched in sexism when audience demand is so obvious? From &lt;em&gt;Clueless&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/10/3/pitch-perfect.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pitch Perfect&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, people buy tickets when something good is in theaters. And the talent pool for funny female performers has never been deeper: Emma Stone, Aubrey Plaza, Zooey Deschanel, Amy Schumer, Rose Byrne, Kat Dennings—all of them are talented enough toone day wear the crown. Even Rebel Wilson has a shot (even if she&amp;#39;s destined to always be the Josh Gad to McCarthy’s Jonah Hill). Then there’s Sarah Silverman, Tina Fey, Amy Poehler, Queen Latifa, Leslie Mann, Elizabeth Banks, and Jennifer Aniston, all of whom are proven comedic talents, but seem to have only a fleeting interest at headlining rom-less coms. Or maybe they’ve just never had the right chance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I know is that we need more of what we’re seeing on TV every single week. It’s not hard for women to be funny. Or for them to be movie stars. So why can’t they be both?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/18/will-a-female-comedian-ever-be-a-movie-star.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/18/will-a-female-comedian-ever-be-a-movie-star.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Run All Night</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Genre films always walk a slippery slope. On the one hand, they offer the comfort of the familiar: the audience and filmmakers enter into an unspoken contract that dictates certain simple expectations will be met. On the other, simply meeting expectations isn’t enough; that familiar stuff must be expertly executed, and, in the very best cases, shown to us in a unique light. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering why I’ve opened my letter to you with this Genre 101 lesson. It’s pretty simple, really: your new movie, &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt;, is very much a film ruled by genre conventions. Yet I get the feeling that director Jaume Collet-Sera and writer Brad Ingelsby might have seen your character as the convention-breaker. Because every time you show up, &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt; suddenly goes from being predictable and uninspired to flat out ridiculous. And, well, pretty stupid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everything about &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt; is cookie-cutter. Stop me if you’ve heard any of this before: an aging mob boss who has gone (mostly) straight has a hot-headed son who may undo what he’s tried to achieve; another aging ex-enforcer (the boss’s longtime friend, natch) has become a drunk, and has become estranged from his own straight-arrow son; through a series of plot contrivances, the two sons have a run-in that eventually leaves the old-timers gunning for each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may come as a shock, but regret, revenge, and betrayal are not the most unique themes to bring to the mob genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this all sounds facetious, but I’m being a little bit sincere. The way it plays out, Collet-Sera and Ingelsby seem to think they’ve invented these tragic mob archetypes from whole cloth. They want to play at the level of tragic opera. Structuring the film as a flashback from what appears to be our hero’s final minutes tips their hand: they want events to feel predetermined. But instead they’re merely predictable (see above re: the knife’s edge of genre picture). Their true intentions are revealed in the casting. When you cast Liam Neeson as the rundown killer forced back into action to protect his son, we all know the movie they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wanted to make: the Liam-Neeson-disposes-of-bad-men-with-ruthless-efficiency movie. The new twist here is that he feels, I don’t know, a little sadder about being such an efficient killer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe it was your character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filmmakers play it mostly straight, trying heir damnedest to convince us that everything is &lt;em&gt;really heavy.&lt;/em&gt; Lord knows Harry Gregson-Williams’s score attempts to portray the crushing moral weight behind every plot point. Sure there’s a lot actions scenes that use a shaky camera in place of actual choreography, but it’s a very sad shaky cam. The less said about the silly 3D computer effects that move us from one location to another, the better (okay, I’ll say this much: at least it’s abandoned early.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then you show up as the highly-skilled contract killer, Price. And you look – and act – like a cross between The Terminator and Brother Mouzone form &lt;em&gt;The Wire.&lt;/em&gt; Seriously, you’re just as ruthless, unstoppable, and even more impervious to pain. You’re even given a laser-sight pistol that shines through smoke, finding targets before they know you’re there (though no one specifies if it‘s actually a “phased plasma rifle with a 20 watt range”). Your character is imagined only in references to other, better characters. The most incongruous of these is your &lt;em&gt;Bullit&lt;/em&gt;-inspired trench coat—a better reference to that movie could have been made by filming coherent car chases. As you walked though corridors, killing policemen and mobsters with robot-like determination, the hollowness of &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#39;s pretensions are given harsh relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you disappeared for a while, and the movie continued on as if nothing out of the ordinary had happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It probably sounds like the ridiculous over-the-top-ness of your character was a welcome relief from the mediocrity of the rest of the movie – even rereading my own description of it strikes me that way – but it merely annoyed me. It was like eating at a restaurant that has reached beyond its abilities, then fed candy corn between courses: a bland meal made unpalatable by the addition of something that’s terrible even on its own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong—I don’t blame &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; for this. The conception and execution of your character speaks to the video game aesthetic Collet-Sera can’t quite escape. Like the movie itself, your character is a bunch of influences from better movies sloppily thrown together in the hope that their sum will some how create a better whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/16/run-all-night.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/16/run-all-night.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Cinderella</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your track record is pretty impressive. &lt;em&gt;Hugo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Shutter Island&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Other Boleyn Girl&lt;/em&gt;—not only are you a master of period films, you’ve also had the pleasure of measuring Leonardo DiCaprio’s inseam more than a few times (yeah, I’m jealous—who wouldn’t be?). But even with all of those films on your resume, bringing a fairy tale like Cinderella to life must feel like one of the biggest feats of your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might think that adapting a classic like this would make your job easier. But, boy, would they be wrong. Crafting a revival like this is hard work. You have to get it exactly right. Especially with a story as familiar as Cinderella: she’s the innocent girl with a pure heart forced to serve her stepmom and stepsisters, only to be transformed into a princess by her fairy godmother so she can meet her prince. Stroke of midnight, glass slippers—you know, Disney 101.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, you didn’t let the expectations stifle you. You met the challenge and managed to perfectly capture the magic and flamboyance of the story through the wardrobe you created, from duotone slim-cut jackets that make princes charming to the the fluid movement of Victorian-era gowns that turn lonely country girls into the belle of the ball. Later, when the wicked stepsisters showed up, they didn’t need to say a word to reveal their idiocy—the loud, jewel-encrusted clothing they wore told me everything I needed to know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s during ballroom scene, when the men and maidens hit the dance floor, that your strategic use of colour is most striking. Draping all the other guests in warm tones while Cinderella is wrapped in striking light blue fabric kept my eyes locked on her as she drifted through the sea of revellers was brilliant. No spotlight needed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and director Kenneth Branagh clearly used the 1950 version as a template for this live-action adaptation, but you managed to avoid turning it into yet another reimagining basted in unnecessary grittiness. I’ll admit, after &lt;em&gt;Alice in Wonderland&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oz: The Great and Powerful&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Maleficent&lt;/em&gt;, it was refreshing to see a retelling that relied on the storybook enchantment that made the story popular in the first place. I don’t need to see Prince Charming riding a Harley and blasting fools with a sawed-off (or do I?). With live-action versions of &lt;em&gt;The Jungle Book&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Beauty and the Beast,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dumbo&lt;/em&gt; recently announced, I suspect there will be a creative tug-o’-war about which approach to take. If you happen to be involved in any of these upcoming movies, please do your best to steer them down the lighter path. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, this film is good. Not great, but good. Hell, all I know is that it’s been years since I’ve seen the old animated version, and you made me remember what it was like to feel the bippity, the boppity, and most definitely the boo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have Courage and Be Kind,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ankit&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/CInderella.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/CInderella.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>&#39;71</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It is films like &lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt; that remind all of us why cinema can be called an art form. There is no commercial rationale for this film, no real clamor for an intimate picture about one English soldier and his harrowing experiences in Northern Ireland during the height of the unrest in 1971. In fact, without you and your support it is unlikely &lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt; would have seen the light of day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an extraordinary film. Affecting and subtly peppered with the kind of bucolic tragedy that occupies sectarian conflicts across the world, &lt;em&gt;‘71&lt;/em&gt; honors the ideals you champion: developing young talent and helping to tell stories that are aesthetically rigorous while still remaining approachable to a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt; is a straightforward thriller. A young British soldier gets separated from his unit during a daytime raid on a Catholic block in Belfast, and then the rest of the film is occupied with his struggle to find his way back to his barracks. The depth of the work comes from the young soldier’s interactions with the various factions (and the individuals that comprise them) as he makes his fraught journey back to what he believes is safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filmmaking is remarkably assured for any director but especially for someone making their feature film debut. Yann Demange is, not incidentally, someone you (and other privately and publicly funded institutions) have helped nurture throughout his career. This is a fine example of how properly funded and supported infrastructure can lead to some extraordinary work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cinematography is top notch, the editing is fluid and clear, and the story bangs along at a pitch perfect clip. The performances are uniformly solid. The only real standout—aside from the lead performance by Jack O’Connell—is Corey McKinley, a young actor playing an unnamed Loyalist youth. He owns the screen for a seven-minute stretch that pivots the whole film. McKinley manages to be both precociously assertive and somehow tragic as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a visual artistry to the film that comes close to overshadowing the narrative but Demange ultimately exercises shrewd judgment in where he puts his camera. Thrillers seem to work best, for me at least, when they remain restrained and understated. This film never forgets that dramatic tension derives from humans having to make decisions in a fundamentally clouded moral universe. For each character there are no good options, just ones that are more, or less, evil and self-serving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘71&lt;/em&gt; contains useful echoes of Sydney Pollack’s &lt;em&gt;Three Days of The Condor&lt;/em&gt;. It features a protagonist who is resourceful and capable trying to work through a byzantine and largely inscrutable political maze. Ultimately though, he is at the mercy of the people he encounters along the way, and it is how those interactions play out that determine his fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘71&lt;/em&gt; also has echoes of some of the best of the American films made in the late sixties and early seventies. It seems that a lot of modern filmmakers (JC Chandor and now Demange, just to name two) are taking their cues from people like Lumet, Scorsese and even Friedkin–producing muscular, spare dramas with a strong emphasis on good scripts and interesting characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for whatever part you have in encouraging this kind of good work I cannot thank you enough, BFI. This was an unlooked for gem in what seems to be a bit of a renaissance for films made for adults.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/71.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/71.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Housebound</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s astonishing how easy you make it look, man. Blending horror and comedy in a manner that keeps one from overpowering the other is always a tricky feat. Frankly, it&amp;#39;s difficult to think of any recent films that have successfully managed it. That’s why your whip-smart script for &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; is so special—it brings the funny and the scary together beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with your strong handling of the characters. A question that inevitably comes up during the course of a haunted house flick is: &amp;quot;Why don&amp;#39;t they just leave?&amp;quot; Sure, you have your &lt;em&gt;Insidious&lt;/em&gt;es and your &lt;em&gt;Paranormal Activitie&lt;/em&gt;s which explain it away by revealing that the supernatural activity is bound to a person instead of a location. But I quite dig your practical solution: because of the electronic monitoring device around her ankle, petty criminal Kylie is forced to deal with sinister goings-on, lest she violate the terms of her house arrest.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neat and simple. Yet you provide us with a nice about-face later on when Kylie is given an opportunity to escape, only to stay for purely altruistic reasons. The more she learns about the house&amp;#39;s bloody past, as well as a killer who has escaped justice, the more her motivations evolve. She undergoes genuine moments of growth, and doesn’t just make decisions solely to benefit the script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to share a brief thought or two about Amos, the security guard tasked with monitoring our protagonist: you so easily could have made him the stock asshole who scoffs when evidence of the supernatural first rears its head, but his boyish enthusiasm and immediate willingness to help is incredibly charming. He’s yet another great character that elevates this already great movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit back to what I was saying before: it&amp;#39;s impressive how carefully you tread the line between comedic and full-on horror elements. There&amp;#39;s a great bit with dial-up internet, terrific banter between Kylie and Amos, and some outrageously zany gore gags that bring to mind the early work of Peter Jackson. But there is also genuine tension when there needs to be, and we never lose sight of just how high the stakes are for our protagonists. What best exemplifies this balancing of contrasting tones is the climax. It features one of the best extended showdown-with-a-killer sequences I&amp;#39;ve seen in recent memory, it manages to be gut-bustingly funny one second and hand-wringingly intense the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit that I felt a slight twinge of disappointment when the movie shifted gears and the nature of what&amp;#39;s was truly on at the house was cast in a different light. But that speaks more to my personal expectations, and it was certainly a clever and unexpected direction to take the story. It hit some unexpectedly emotional beats as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m guessing you&amp;#39;ve heard the news that &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; is already being optioned for an American remake. It’s so bafflingly unnecessary that I can&amp;#39;t even put it in words (maybe just a series of inarticulate noises). It seems a safe bet that we can save ourselves a little time and write it off as being inferior.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years from now, if &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#39;t mentioned in the same breath as other horror-comedy classics like &lt;em&gt;Dead Alive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Evil Dead II&lt;/em&gt;, than I&amp;#39;ll be sure to eat my hat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/11/housebound.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/11/housebound.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Chappie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When making a big budget, dystopian flick like Neill Blomkamp’s &lt;em&gt;Chappie,&lt;/em&gt; your robots truly matter. How they look and whether or not their appearance reflects the mood you are trying to convey is essential to the film’s success or failure. This is especially true if one of the robots is the title character of the aforementioned multi-million dollar extravaganza. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine if the &lt;em&gt;Terminator&lt;/em&gt; (once it shed it’s Schwarzenegger) looked liked the robot in a Bugs Bunny cartoon. James Cameron would now be directing the line at McDonalds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did a man’s work in helping to develop the visual aesthetic of this particular robot. Chappie is perfectly modulated to allow Sharlto Copley’s motion capture performance to shine through. However, it is a significant problem when a motion capture performance is by far the best part of a film that has a number of actual humans as featured players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chappie—&lt;/em&gt;the film as opposed to the robot—is a godawful mess, narratively as well as conceptually. The casting ranges from poor (Hugh Jackman, paradoxically both wasted and ill-chosen) to ballsy (Die Antwoord’s Ninja and Yolandi Visser) to curiously misused (Sigourney Weaver and Dev Patel).  But they all recede into the background whenever the titular character is on the screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chappie&lt;/em&gt; is both derivative and an homage to several films including &lt;em&gt;Short Circuit,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Robocop&lt;/em&gt; and even makes a more than a cursory nod to Blomkamp’s own &lt;em&gt;District 9&lt;/em&gt;. What it doesn’t do, however, is find its own voice. It lurches wildly in tone from gritty to comic to maudlin to occasionally effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of that is the script. Too often it relies on what seem to be improvisational moments between Chappie and his adoptive parents—Ninja and Visser—as they try to gangsta Chappie up in order to aid them with their comically ineffective schemes. There is a throwaway plot involving Jackman and his rivalry with Patel. Sigourney Weaver, again wasted in a largely throwaway role, plays a weak echo of her Queen Bitch from &lt;em&gt;Working Girl.&lt;/em&gt; At no point in the film do any of these disparate threads cohere in a way that is at all convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single compelling moment comes early on in the film when Chappie is abandoned to the streets of Johannesburg; it is in this sequence that you see most clearly where Blomkamp can create moments of real human pathos. It is a stark, unrelenting five minutes that stayed with me long after the film ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason why this sequence succeeds—where most of the film fails—is because it focuses on Chappie’s awakening to the harsh realities of the world he has been born into. It also works because it is uncluttered by any of the cardboard characters that usually fill Blomkamp’s South African landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copley’s MoCap performance is effective because the robot design evokes a human in form but is still non-specific enough for anyone to identify with—it is the perfect blank slate for the audience to project themselves upon. Chappie also has rudimentary facial expressions that work in ways that are a little surprising, given such a limited palette. He is a creation that deserves, as do you, a far better film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Blomkamp might be better served by adapting other people’s work. Maybe then he could find a way to incorporate the magic you helped him create into a film that compliments that magic—instead of muting it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/10/chappie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/10/chappie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Unfinished Business</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Of all the crew members listed in Ken Scott’s &lt;em&gt;Unfinished Business&lt;/em&gt;, you have the coolest credit. I have no idea what exactly it means, but it has earned you this letter because...well, why the hell not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the film, Dan, Timothy, and Mike have one last chance to save their fledgling mineral sales company. They chase a big client all the way to Berlin for a seal-the-deal handshake, and they need to deliver a presentation that blows away their competition (and former boss). If they don’t, Timothy can’t divorce his wife and Dan can’t send his angsty kids to private school. So there’s a quest. And a ticking clock. But unfortunately there’s no real sense of urgency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I forgot to mention: Dan’s company sells swarf, which is basically manufacturing waste. This film is also &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swarf&quot;&gt;swarf&lt;/a&gt;: probably important to those who need to sell it, but I can’t be arsed to get too enthused. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I usually find the American-in-Europe culture clash set-up very funny. Language barriers, weird food, European permissiveness versus American prudishness—the ingredients are all there. The film sets itself up as a road trip/caper/fish out of water comedy, but doesn’t embrace any of the tropes or conventions that make those subgenres funny. It holds the promise of some potentially hilarious running gags, but none of them pay off. The German GPS bit should have been milked for all it was worth, and, as always, there’s a giant pile of kinky German sex jokes that could have been plundered. But these opportunities are brushed aside in favour of a family/bullying subplot that feels shoehorned in, and endless scenes of the guys “going over the presentation just &lt;em&gt;one more time&lt;/em&gt;.” Their arrival in Berlin coincides with the Folsom Europe festival, a huge marathon, and a G8 summit, but instead we get to watch Dan pore over his slides for the umpteenth time. Which brings me to my next gripe: none of the film’s obstacles are very obstacle-y. I feel like it should take more than a few paint pellets to the torso to sneak into a G8 summit. None of the calamities that befall the protagonists seem to last more than a couple of scenes before being neatly resolved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it feels way too phoned-in. The filmmakers seemed too indifferent for me to care about the exploits (such as they are) of Dan, Timothy, and Mike, or for me to want them to succeed. Maybe if I knew how ‘Master of the Sword’ fit into the endeavour, I might have been more impressed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait, it had something to do with the scene in the bathroom of the leather club, didn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/9/unfinished-business.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/9/unfinished-business.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Second Best Exotic Marigold Hotel</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When you’ve watched films for close to fifty years, you occasionally get to see a performer’s entire career play out in front of you. Sometimes it’s painful (Jon Voight), sometimes it’s funny (Jack Nicholson), and every once in a while it’s a privilege (you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear &lt;em&gt;The Second Best Exotic Marigold Hotel&lt;/em&gt; is hardly the best showcase for your work. A meandering, often incoherent mess, it is a film that lurches from moment to moment without a whole lot of intention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a trifling contrivance about the necessity of obtaining a second hotel (ostensibly to house the incipient hordes of adventurous, elderly British ex-pats of reduced circumstance) to compliment the first hotel, but the title kind of says it all. This is definitely the second best Exotic Marigold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first film—simply titled &lt;em&gt;The Best Exotic Marigold Hotel&lt;/em&gt;—was a clever, engaging piece of entertainment. But in this iteration Dev Patel is carrying far too much narrative weight and screen time for a character that is so thinly drawn. Nor is Patel is good enough to transcend the material. As for most of the rest of the cast—which includes Richard Gere and David Strathairn—they seem happy just to collect their paychecks and wander around Jaipur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when either you, Maggie Smith or Bill Nighy are on screen something truly alchemical happens; lead is in fact turned to gold. It really is magical to see. I think it has something to do with simple professionalism as well as talent. There is never a moment of sloppiness or mugging for the camera. I believe absolutely everything you and you fellow Brits say. And given the thinness of this script, that is high praise indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a glance at your resume is enough to see how varied and challenging your career has been. Those choices also speak to a fundamental strength that many UK actors possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theatre actors, especially Shakespearean theatre actors, cannot take a moment off. That continual awareness is often painfully apparent, especially in contrast with people who turn off the moment the camera pivots away from them. There are several moments throughout &lt;em&gt;The Second Best Exotic Marigold Hotel&lt;/em&gt; when you seem to be acting in an entirely different film than most of the rest of the cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The few scenes where you and Maggie Smith get to share the screen together are particularly worthwhile. Not for any De Niro-Pacino type pyrotechnics but simply for the joy of watching two absolute masters make a silk purse out of a sow’s ear. Perhaps this is one of the reasons the film is so uneven and directionless. It is as if the Director John Madden and screenwriter Ol Parker figured: we’ve got all of these great people together again—what can go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, quite a bit. Since your long-budding romance with Nighy is reduced to an awkward sub-plot and the rest of the film is filled with far lesser lights, I kept bouncing back and forth between being engaged and then utterly disinterested. Not exactly a great rhythm. This is a film you watch on a lazy Sunday, not something you spend money and time going to a theatre to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perverse way you, Maggie Smith and Nighy made this film worse, simply by showing how much better it may have been had you all featured more prominently. In particular your performance was a pointed reminder of why you have endured and flourished—while lesser lights have long since faded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for a lifetime of beautiful poetry, Dame Judi. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/8/the-second-best-exotic-marigold-hotel.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/8/the-second-best-exotic-marigold-hotel.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Valley Below</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Drumheller is a tourist trap town in the middle of the Alberta badlands, guarded by the “World’s Largest Dinosaur” and a giant plaster Jesus. It already &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like a movie set—just not the droll, Tim Burton type. In &lt;em&gt;The Valley Below&lt;/em&gt;, you managed to capture the suffocating timelessness of Drumheller – with its dusty, old-timey main street and desolate highway stretches and strip malls – and turn it into a place from a Larry McMurtry novel, where the inhabitants are restless and stuck. Even the colourful fibreglass dinosaurs dotting the town seem forlorn. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Valley Below&lt;/em&gt; follows four loosely connected characters over the course of a year: Kate, a pregnant teen about to go to university; Warren, an alcoholic Zamboni driver and songwriter; Kate’s dad Gordon, a taxidermist trying to save his marriage; and Barry, a cop and local radio DJ with a sensitive streak. The world these characters inhabit is one of breathtaking vistas and desolate futures. It’s a place literally surrounded by skeletons. It’s the kind of world that is easy to get wrong—or, worse, to accidentally condescend to. Thankfully, your unpretentious art direction and design manages to avoid hollow imitation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writer/Director/Producer Kyle Thomas understands this world. The assured, natural performances serve the spare style beautifully. There is an unaffectedness here that is rare for a Canadian film. None of it reeks of try-too-hard. Just like your modest design, which is always present, yet never obvious. When Kate picks up her goofy boyfriend on the morning after a house party, we see a pig’s head floating in a kiddy pool on the front lawn. Warren’s bungalow is strewn with just enough empty bottles and dirty dishes to make it seem like it wasn’t set-decorated. You’ve &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; to that house party. You’ve &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; to that bungalow. You know these people. But more importantly, &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; know these people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You filled Gordon’s small workshop with every manner of awls, furs, and tools. Before he begins assembling a deer’s head trophy, he takes off his wedding ring and hangs it on a pair of antlers behind him. It’s a small, thoughtful action that tells us volumes about this man and his situation. As he works at making the deer look as lifelike as possible - stitching the fur and choosing from a selection of glass eyes - we realize he’s done the same with his seemingly perfect marriage. Barry has a model train set in his basement that resembles a miniature Drumheller: plastic Jesus, dinos, and all. It’s more than just a symbol of how he watches over his town. It’s a metaphor about perspective. The town may be small, but it is dwarfed by the character’s desires. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overlapping nature of the narrative structure never feels contrived the way most multi-narrative films often do. Thomas holds shots for exactly the right time, only lingering when it serves the story. His edits are confident and deliberate. There is a hint of Altman’s &lt;em&gt;Nashville&lt;/em&gt; in his method, both in the music and in the film’s episodic nature. There are shades of Alexander Payne’s &lt;em&gt;Nebraska&lt;/em&gt; in your visual style, from the depressing motel rooms, to the dark and desperate taverns. Somewhere in between, you found the Drumheller of &lt;em&gt;The Valley Below&lt;/em&gt;, a place that is ageless yet eerily recognizable. A place where nothing – and everything – happens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for letting this tourist hang with the locals for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/6/the-valley-below.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/6/the-valley-below.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Revolution is Upon Us</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Not so long ago you could always tell the difference between a movie made in Hollywood and just about anywhere else. It was like they carried a watermark. No matter how banal the content, how utterly derivative the plot, how wooden the acting, the one thing you could pretty much say about any studio film made in Hollywood was that they looked really good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was because Hollywood had accumulated, over the course of several decades, an almost complete monopoly on the mechanics of film production. It wasn’t just about huge budgets, it was about support infrastructure, technical know how and the means of production: cinematography, editing, sound production and even sound stages, color separation, film processing and finally distribution networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To match that kind of out of the gate firepower would require the resources of a national government. So, with a few exceptions, most films that were produced outside of Hollywood were, whatever their latent artistic qualities, working at a huge disadvantage. They just weren’t as shiny as what Hollywood was pounding out year after year. To compete on the world stage required both money and technical resources that were inordinately concentrated in the southern end of the State of California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And listening to the some of the doomsayers from the last awards season you would think almost nothing has changed over the last twenty years. Just lately there has been a constant lament amongst many in the industry about how the death of small and medium budget films made for people over twenty-five is upon us. That we were doomed to two binary choices—artistically ambitious but technically constrained micro-budget films (a kind of perpetual dogme 95, not by choice but by necessity) and a never-ending barrage of Hollywood summer bombast, beginning in March and ending sometime in late October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t seem to be the case at all, as it turns out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filmmaking has quietly entered a renaissance of unequalled quality and diversity. Independently produced movies have never been more interesting, beautiful, varied, and accessible. The voices that are being heard are more distinct in ethnicity, as well as class and geography, even gender, than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even a partial list of non-Hollywood films from just the last year: &lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/4/leviathan.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leviathan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Timbuktu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/9/ida.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under The Skin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Girlhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Force Majeure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/2/a-girl-walks-home-alone-at-night.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as independently produced North American films like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;NightCrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; or straight up entertainments like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; put lie to the idea that small to medium budget films of exceptional quality are somehow disappearing from the landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filmmakers themselves are Korean, Mauritanian, Russian, Iranian, British, French, men, women, and transgendered, outsiders, neophytes, mavericks, political radicals and absolutely beholden to no one. And you know what the best part is? We all can see these films pretty much at the click of a mouse and for a couple of bucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point is often lost in the mountains of snark generated by people who often have, at most, a passing familiarity with any film that isn’t on a constant loop in their feeds. And the declinists in the room—with their moaning about how films for adults are so vanishingly rare—expose themselves for the culturally myopic whiners and curmudgeons that they are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem for them seems to be that the center of gravity for this renaissance isn’t located in Southern California. It isn’t even on the North American continent. If you had to assign a geographic ground zero it would probably be somewhere in North Africa, or perhaps Eastern Europe, depending on the particular year. And from people who often mouth platitudes about diversity and the Hollywood monoculture I too often hear the words: ‘I haven’t seen that yet’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that a lack of access was a pretty valid defense. If Hollywood didn’t pay it didn’t play but that is a red herring at this point in the game. If you’re not seeing the diversity in film that you would like to, you probably aren’t looking very hard. Just off of the top of my head, some of the most interesting films from last year were from women directors: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Babadook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Girlhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Beyond the Lights&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone at Night&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And finding these films usually requires less work than making a sandwich. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single greatest thing about the technological change that has occurred around filmmaking in the last twenty-five years is simply this: the means of production are now firmly in the hands of the content creators. Hollywood’s monopoly on production is broken and the grip it currently still enjoys on distribution is soon to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it isn’t much of a stretch these days to find all kinds of films for all sorts of tastes. More to the point, most of the cinema being produced outside of Hollywood isn’t what used to be considered art house fare: with their low budget productions and often impenetrable and esoteric narratives. And if you were lucky you might find these rare gems playing on one screen in NYC at 12:00 AM on a Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, for me to see &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt;—the Academy Award winner for best foreign language film—I had to open up iTunes on my computer and pay $5.99.  To see &lt;em&gt;Timbuktu&lt;/em&gt; I had to walk a few blocks to TIFF and see one of the most beautiful and unsettling films I have ever experienced up on a big screen—but I have no doubt that it will be available on any number of legitimate venues in the near future, as well as old school DVD and Blu-Ray. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days the strength of much of non-Hollywood film is in its middlebrow aesthetic and its capacity to speak coherently to mass audiences while managing to avoid simply existing as product. Timbuktu is set in a foreign land that few North Americans would recognize yet it is perfectly comprehensible to even my wretchedly tarnished sensibilities—as well as beautifully shot and conventional in its narrative arcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, I tend to think this can be nothing but good for Hollywood itself. Challenged and often aesthetically overtaken these days, it will be interesting to see how the Monolith responds. My money is on a resurgence of the kind of dynamic filmmaking the major studios haven’t had much to do with since the mid to late seventies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t always a curse, as it turns out, to live in interesting times.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/4/the-revolution-is-upon-us.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/4/the-revolution-is-upon-us.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
