<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Avengers: Age of Ultron</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ll indulge me for a moment, I’m going to do a little reminiscing of my own. Something along the lines of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;letter you penned to your younger self&lt;/a&gt; when you first saw 2012’s &lt;em&gt;The Avengers.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what stage of superhero worship you would have found yourself in during the spring of 1984 – you’d have been what, 4 years old? – but it was probably deeper than mine. I was 11-years old, and more of a &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;G.I. JOE&lt;/em&gt; comic guy. Like &lt;em&gt;The Avengers,&lt;/em&gt; they were published by Marvel, but even back then I knew the truth: they were monthly, 30-page advertisements for toys. Superheroes just weren’t my thing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that day in May when I wandered into Checkers Convenience and saw &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars&lt;/em&gt; #1 on the spinner rack, even my Hasbro-addled brain knew it something special, something &lt;em&gt;big.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I wasn’t quite up-to-speed with the convoluted mythologies behind Iron Man, The Hulk, Captain America, Spider-Man, The X-Men didn’t matter—I wanted in. I ate up all 12 issues of the miniseries as fast as I could. And as a marketing vehicle, &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars&lt;/em&gt; achieved its purpose: it drew me into the larger Marvel Universe: &lt;em&gt;Peter Parker:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spectacular&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Uncanny X-Men&lt;/em&gt; became regular reading for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the following year, &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II&lt;/em&gt; came out. And in the very first issue – which managed to cross-reference &lt;em&gt;every single&lt;/em&gt; Marvel title being published at the time –I checked out. Making sense of it all was just too much damn work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be worried about where I’m going with this. You probably think that I’m going to say that &lt;em&gt;Avengers: _Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; is the Marvel Cinematic Universe’s &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II;&lt;/em&gt; it buckles under the burden of too much baggage from past filmsand too many future plot-threads to establish; that it too obviously exists only to propagate more Marvel films. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; worry me going into the film. And I’ve levelled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/4/captain-america-the-winter-soldier.html&quot;&gt;similar complaints&lt;/a&gt; against the the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html&quot;&gt;ever-expanding&lt;/a&gt; Marvel Universe before (no one wants to have to do homework just to watch a summer blockbuster).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t worry. I come from the future to tell you to rest easy, slightly-younger Jared. For in the end, &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; is … fine. Your endlessly optimistic twelve-year-old-self might find &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; a huge disappointment, but now that you’re old enough to know that all things are not, in fact, possible, and that recreating past triumphs is mostly a fool’s errand, and that very few things in life are as fun the second time round, then...you’ll probably like this movie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, not love. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I was looking forward to this second instalment – even with my misgivings, I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; excited – I did feel a little bit of disappointment when Captain America, Thor, Iron Man, The Hulk, Black Widow, and Hawkeye reassembled on screen. Not disappointment in what I saw onscreen, but disappointment in my visceral reaction to it. Everything is executed as well as it was the first time around, but this time around it all felt kind of...well, expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, yes, you might argue that this is the curse of any sequel. About &lt;em&gt;Jurassic Park: The Lost World&lt;/em&gt;, Roger Ebert asked: where is the awe, the sense of wonder? (Answer: in the first movie.) I get it. I myself am always quick to point out that you should never review any film – even a sequel – by comparing it to another. But expectations are fair game. Expectations that, in these past three years – as Marvel schools other studios and publishers on how to build the ultimate interlocking franchise – have grown impossibly big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; certainly wastes no time in trying to meet those expectations. It opens with an extended action sequence, the scale of which any regular-sized movie would save for its climax. It’s way too long, sure, but it does immediately give us what we came for: The Avengers at their ass-kicking best. It also serves to introduce a new super-powered duo: the twins Pietro and Wanda Maximoff (of the two, Elizabeth Olsen’s Wanda makes much more of an impression, even if I still don’t understand exactly what her powers were supposed to be). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Olsen stands out is no small feat. This playing field is crowded with big personalities. While &lt;em&gt;Age of&lt;/em&gt; Ultron might not have the same reverence for the characters you found in the original, Joss Whedon is determined to use his second outing as writer and director to give each of them their due—almost to a fault (the one exception is Thor, who is reduced to a walking joke delivery system when he’s not smashing things with his hammer). One thing that can be said for Whedon: he loves his character-building, and things get pretty Whedon-y in &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt;. For the most part, this is good: Jeremy Renner’s Hawkeye is an actual character this time around, and the action slows down enough to explore budding relationships and tensions within the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to give you a point-by-point plot summary here. The amount of footnotes I’d need to explain everything would make this the &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II&lt;/em&gt; of reviews. So I’ll itemize what you, so recently in love with Whedon’s first installment, will want to know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes: the show-stopping fight between The Hulk and Iron Man is just that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: as the movie’s big bad, James Spader’s Ultron is no match for Loki. Spader does admirable voice work, and Whedon makes him an interesting screen presence, but when you’re forwarding the story by cutting away from the goddamned Avengers, you better have something on-screen with hell of a lot of charisma. Charisma that the sleek, all-CGI Ultron just doesn’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: the plot is not particularly tight. Wanda Maximoff’s ill-defined powers left me confused about who was affected by what and for how long. And, not to pick on Thor again, but his particular arc seems to exist only to set up future installments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: the climactic action scene is not any more sensible this time around. Which is a shame, given that it’s the exact same urban destructathon.* Ultron’s army of indistinguishable robots is almost as indistinguishable as the armoured Chitari in &lt;em&gt;The Avengers&lt;/em&gt;. When this much pyrotechnic skill is on display the last thing I need to be thinking is, “I don’t know where anyone is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, yes: Marvel has shoehorned as many extra characters into this film as it possibly could, all in the interest of franchise building. War Machine, The Falcon, and The Vision (a brand new character introduced in the film’s last act) add very little, story-wise, but provide a way forward for more adventures. It’s here that you will see where Whedon’s idiosyncrasies come up against the behemoth that is Marvel. The mechanics of world building push Whedon’s interests out of the picture, quite literally. The side effect of this tension is that &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; feels more like a product than an entertainment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, hey, don’t let me ruin the 2012 afterglow. I still enjoyed the movie. Whedon’s dialogue and attention to (and love for) the characters goes a long way in overcoming the larger business interests of Marvel. And look on the bright side: when it came time for your childhood heroes to be turned into movies, the reigns were handed to Joss Whedon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1046173/&quot;&gt;Steven Sommers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0418279/?ref_=nv_sr_2&quot;&gt;Michael Bay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-avengers-age-of-ultron.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-avengers-age-of-ultron.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Going Clear: Scientology and the Prison of Belief</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Without you Alex Gibney’s &lt;em&gt;Going Clear: Scientology and the Prison of Belief&lt;/em&gt; probably never gets made. This isn’t just because you are the Pulitzer Prize winning author whose 2013 non-fiction book prompted Gibney to make the film in the first place. The most important contribution you made to this film was your professional integrity and the rigor of your work. Because if you are going to go after Scientology you had better be sure all the I’s are dotted and T’s are crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the early revelations of the film is this pertinent fact: in 1993 Scientology succeeded in strong-arming the I.R.S. into granting them &lt;a href=&quot;file://localhost/Users/Timothy001/Desktop/www.nytimes.com:.webloc&quot;&gt;tax-exempt status&lt;/a&gt; (as a religious non-profit). This means they managed to coerce—by means both litigious and extra-legal—the single most powerful non-military U.S. government agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson here is: if you are going to take a swing at these guys you had better be prepared for a long, protracted and bloody war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That your book managed to clear all the legal hurdles required set the stage for Gibney to make his film. And what a film it turned out to be. &lt;em&gt;Going Clear: Scientology and the Prison of Belief&lt;/em&gt; manages to balance tone and content in a way that treats the subject with the gravity it deserves without ever losing sight of the more surreal and absurd aspects of the whole sordid mess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gibney also removed the word &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; when adapting the title of your book for his project. He seems to have decided that while there is some salacious value in the antics of people like Tom Cruise and John Travolta, they aren’t really the story here. The film exclusively concerns itself with how people allow themselves—gradually and through a toxic stew of self-deception, wishful thinking and a lack of critical attention—to be lured into a pyramid scheme of the most puerile sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structurally the film quickly dispenses with the necessary, but cartoonishly absurd, origin story of Scientology—and a short bio of its founder, L. Ron Hubbard. After that the narrative moves into more interesting territory. In a series of interviews intercut with low-key re-enactments and unsettling archival footage (of both LRH and the current leader David Miscavige), Gibney examines both the development of the church and, in parallel, the methods used to ensnare and retain its adherents. The interviews with various former members of the Church are persuasive in their frank descriptions of the kind of surreal behavior they participated in—and were subject to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost as an afterthought you see clips of Cruise and Travolta, but mostly as object examples of how the church achieves their ends by leveraging people’s own vanity and need for absolution. At various times both men were considering leaving the Church and the strong implication seems to be that their own personal confessions were used to discourage that particular course of action. These personal revelations were obtained during what Scientology describes as ‘auditing’. A process that is essentially a melding of the Catholic confessional and talk therapy—without any of the institutional prohibitions on disclosure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most affecting is the story of Paul Haggis, a producer and filmmaker that was a member of the Church for over thirty years. He left Scientology in 2009—ostensibly after a disagreement with the Church hierarchy over their support of Prop 8 in California. His story is a template for all of the stories in the film. A man looking to make some improvements in his life finds himself ensnared—after decades of slow ascension through the ranks—in an enterprise that proves to be, at its core, a ludicrous fabrication. A fabrication invented by a man (LRH) that was likely a victimof his ownprofound mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that you enter the story, Lawrence. In 2011 you published your 25,000 word essay in the New Yorker called &lt;a href=&quot;file://localhost/Users/Timothy001/Desktop/www.newyorker.com:.webloc&quot;&gt;‘The Apostate”&lt;/a&gt;. It is a brilliant piece about Haggis and his 34-year relationship with the church—and how the scales finally fell from his eyes.  From that article came the book—and eventually, Gibney’s film. After that, the threats of lawsuits, intimidation and generally bad behavior that were the inevitable consequence of exposing the Emperor’s junk to the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for taking all of that on, we owe you a real debt, Lawrence. A couple of beers at the absolute minimum. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/5/going-clear-scientology-and-the-prison-of-belief.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/5/going-clear-scientology-and-the-prison-of-belief.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Age of Adaline</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a fan of wildlife programs? You know, the kind where a herd of gazelles lazily sips at a watering hole while a lioness prepares to pounce, all while David Attenborough’s soothing voice runs a play-by-play of the grisly proceedings? &lt;em&gt;Age of Adaline&lt;/em&gt; shares a few similarities with those classic zoological telecasts: it’s expertly photographed, the creatures and landscapes are gorgeous, and your sonorous voice provides context to the action. And like those nature programs, &lt;em&gt;Age of Adaline&lt;/em&gt; provides very little in the way of character development or dramatic tension. The difference is, we usually have more of a reason to root for the gazelle than the simple fact that she’s pleasing to look at. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Blake Lively is most certainly easy on the eyes. As Adaline, Lively isn’t just ageless—she’s &lt;em&gt;timeless&lt;/em&gt;. She emanates old Hollywood glamour, completely at ease in every era in which the film takes place. Unfortunately, she is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in a vintage Chanel ad, where being aloof, chilly and opaque are acceptable qualities. She’s supposed to be in a modern romantic fairy tale. But it’s unfair to lay all the blame at Blake’s lovely feet. For a movie about a woman who has lived for more than a hundred years, it’s disappointing – and more than a little bit baffling – that Adaline is so lacking in dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in 1906, Adaline led a normal life...until the age of 29 when her car plunged into a frigid river and was then struck by lightning. She survived, but she was unable to age. In present day San Francisco, she falls for a man named Ellis, who turns out to be the son of William, a man she had a fling with in London in the Sixties. She now must face the truth about her circumstances or risk losing yet another chance at love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn about Adaline’s backstory through the three laziest screenplay devices available: old newsreel footage (that she watches because she works at a library), flashbacks, and narration (no offense). This is when we’re introduced to your authoritative voice. You describe Adaline’s first few years in a historical context: a newspaper declaring her as the first baby born on New Year’s Day 1906, the Great San Francisco earthquake and fire, the building of the Golden Gate Bridge where she meets her husband, an engineer who perishes during construction, leaving her a young widowed mother. And then you continue Adaline’s curious backstory ten months after the death of her husband when she drives her car off a snowy road and into the river. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an external narrator is used well, it gives the audience a sense of remove, an objectivity (think &lt;em&gt;Magnolia&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Little Children&lt;/em&gt;). In &lt;em&gt;Age of Adaline&lt;/em&gt;, your job is purely expository. Instead of allowing Adaline to tell her own life story (and in the process, provide the opportunity for some much needed character development), the filmmakers instead decide to give you the task of explaining her preposterous plight. As Adaline plunges into the chilly water, you explain the pathology of anoxic shock, combined with head injury and the defibrillating properties of being struck by lightning which, when combined, leads to agelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You then go on to tell us how Adeline spent years trying to make sense of her medical predicament, while making up excuses for her inability to age. In the Fifties a traffic cop questions Adeline’s age, and then the FBI gets involved (because, &lt;em&gt;communism!)&lt;/em&gt;, and she goes on the run, leaving behind her now college-aged daughter. Flash-forward to present day and she’s fallen for Ellis, a quasi-stalker with scruffy hair, who loves history and drives a late-model Saab despite the fact he’s a millionaire (which is apparently shorthand for “endearing Mr. Right-type”). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get a break when the film is turned over to the veterans. Ellen Burstyn as Adaline’s daughter Flemming, Harrison Ford as William, and Kathy Baker as his wife. They manage to navigate the stray plot threads gamely and elevate the script’s sappiness. Ford seems more invested than he has in years, and he and Baker provide most of the film’s genuine laughs. A special mention should go to newcomer Anthony Ingruber for his uncanny portrayal of young William. With his adorably spot-on grimacing, he almost manages to out-curmudgeon Harrison Ford. But it’s Ellen Burstyn who steals every scene she’s in, believably playing “younger” than Lively’s Adaline. She’s so convincing that it’s a shame the writer’s didn’t give &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; the narration job (again, no offense). That might have given the film the depth and warmth that your bystander perspective just couldn’t provide (no offense, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you return in the third act, you’re describing another car careening on a slippery road in a snow storm. But at this point we’re expecting it. Unfortunately, since we’ve never learned about Adaline’s hopes or desires, or who she really is beyond the obvious, your narration might as well have been done by Charlie Brown’s teacher, because by that point, all I could hear was, “wha, wha, wha, wha, wha, wha…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, seriously, no offense.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/1/age-of-adaline.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/1/age-of-adaline.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>We Need to Talk About Adam</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you are a 13-year-old-boy, ignore this letter. Carry on with your Xboxing and your YouTubing or whatever it is you kids are into these days. But if you have pubes, and a fully developed prefrontal cortex, you also have some explaining to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who the hell are you, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to figure you out for years. When I picture you in my head it’s not pretty. I see monobrows, Cheeto-dusted sweatpants, and Crocs. I imagine too many digits and not enough teeth. I realize this sounds horribly condescending, especially because I was once one of you. But that was a long time ago. Clinton was president. Napster was a thing. Adam Sandler was funny. I was high. Pretty much all the time. But even now, when the most mind-altering substance I imbibe is Tazo Calm tea, I still think &lt;em&gt;The Wedding Singer&lt;/em&gt; is funny. Everything he’s done since then would require me to ingest Chris Farley-levels of recreational pharmaceuticals to find even mildly amusing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So really, who are you? I’ve asked around and no one will readily admit to being an Adam Sandler fan. But you must be out there. It’s kind of like how everyone likes to hate on U2, yet their massive stadium shows sell out in minutes. Someone’s going, but nobody wants to cop to it. Like that barbed wire tattoo you thought was cool for twelve minutes in ‘99, if you can hide it now why wouldn’t you? And I can’t say I blame you. Admitting you like Adam Sandler’s films means admitting to yourself what you know deep inside must be true: Adam Sandler thinks you’re stupid. He thinks you’re sexist, and racist and borderline sociopathic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least it seems that way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why else would he continue to make sophomoric drivel set in a Hooters, or in an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.citypress.co.za/entertainment/movie-review-tired-offensive/&quot;&gt;Africa rendered so insulting and full of stereotypes&lt;/a&gt; that he might as well have just shot it at The Rainforest Cafe? Why would he keep playing the same sad-sack Everyman with a bullying streak and an uncontrollable temper? It’s because he thinks you’re a bunch of mouth-breathing rubes who will happily pay to see whatever insipid dreck he deigns to shart out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the topic of sharting, Adam Sandler movies can best be compared to the McRib; they both come around about once a year surrounded by inflated hype, they’re molded into a pre-formed shape with the cheapest material, are completely devoid of nutritional value, and they cover you in shame sweat immediately following consumption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also make an inexplicably obscene amount of money. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast food chains don’t make food as much as they sell &lt;em&gt;product&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/the-three-types-of-adam-sandler-movies/&quot;&gt;Sandler operates in much the same way.&lt;/a&gt; To him, comedy isn’t art, it’s commerce. Like McD’s, he succeeds because he keeps operating costs low thus ensuring a high return on investment. His movies aren’t movies, they are units sold. Quantity versus quality. His goal isn’t to make millions of people laugh, it’s to make a few people rich. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Sandler stopped trying years ago. He admits as much himself. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.avclub.com/article/adam-sandler-confirms-his-movies-are-just-paid-vac-204952&quot;&gt;His films are an excuse for him and his friends to get a paid vacation&lt;/a&gt;. Which wouldn’t be so sad if his movies were even marginally funny. Instead they take aim at the marginalized. His style of comedy isn’t just lazy, it’s mean. And it’s mean &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; it’s lazy. The easiest, cheapest laughs are the ones you get from punching down, from harvesting the lowest hanging fruit. They aren’t effortless, they are effort-free. There is no subtext, no hidden metaphors, no subtlety whatsoever. Chicago Tribune’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2015/04/adam-sandler-has-finally-hit-the-limit-of-satire/391550/&quot;&gt;Michael Phillips nailed it&lt;/a&gt; when he said, &amp;quot;People of color, to say nothing of women, who have been marginalized, patronized or humiliated by a stupid joke in an Adam Sandler movie over the last few years constitute the biggest club in modern Hollywood.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for some reason, you’re all still laughing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, a group of Native American actors walked off the set of Sandler’s latest cinematic abortion, &lt;em&gt;Ridiculous 6&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/2015/04/23/native-actors-walk-set-adam-sandler-movie-after-insults-women-elders-160110&quot;&gt;They had been told the movie wasn’t racist, and that the production had hired a Native consultant.&lt;/a&gt; They went ahead in good faith that their culture would be represented respectfully. But once on set, they raised several concerns (inappropriate character names and costumes to name a few) which were summarily dismissed. It would have been bad enough if they &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; had to endure a bunch of people “whitesplaining” what should and shouldn’t offend them. They were then told by producers, “If you’re overly sensitive, you should leave.” Netflix, the company behind the film, released an overly defensive statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;The movie has ridiculous in the title for a reason: because it is ridiculous. It is a broad satire of Western movies and the stereotypes they popularized, featuring a diverse cast that is not only part of — but in on — the joke.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make one thing crystal clear: Adam Sandler wouldn’t recognize satire if it shat in his mouth. But it’s no surprise Netflix is going to stand firm. Last fall they inked a four (!) picture deal with Sandler (who approved of the union, saying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/netflix-signs-adam-sandler-to-a-4-year-movie-deal-2014-10&quot;&gt;Netflix rhymes with “wet chicks”&lt;/a&gt;), and they aren’t necessarily in the same financial position that bigger studios like Disney and Sony are to weather the kind of box-office stinker that &lt;em&gt;Ridiculous 6&lt;/em&gt; is destined to be, let alone endure three more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, Sandler himself has remained mum on the incident. But his co-star &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rollingstone.com/movies/news/vanilla-ice-on-ridiculous-6-this-movie-isnt-dances-with-wolves-20150427&quot;&gt;Vanilla Ice has leaped to the film’s defense&lt;/a&gt; stating, “I’m part Chocktaw Indian” which is the Native equivalent of saying “I can’t be racist, I have a black friend.” If this was Sandler’s idea, maybe he does have a sense of humour after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, you have a few options, you can admit you’re a horrible person who has helped to line the pockets of a self-loathing, man-child because you also think poking fun at the disenfranchised is the height of comedy. You can admit you’re a stupid person, because you think jokes like, &lt;a href=&quot;http://defamer.gawker.com/these-are-the-jokes-that-caused-actors-to-walk-off-adam-1699990455&quot;&gt;“Say honey, how about after this, we go some place and I put my pee-pee in your tee-pee?”&lt;/a&gt; are funny and you just can’t be bothered to try harder because thinking hurts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can admit that admiring an entitled 48 year-old millionaire doofus who wears cargo shorts and ballcaps is embarrassing, grow the fuck up, and finally make an appointment to get that barbed wire tattoo lasered off. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Unfriended</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Remember that gag in &lt;em&gt;The Simpsons&lt;/em&gt; with Luke Perry analogue Kyle Darren, as a teen heartthrob whose face transforms into a sea of wrinkles when he smiles?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tip my hat to you for being able to avoid the embarrassing spectacle of an actor desperately trying to convince the audience they&amp;#39;re years younger than they appear by casting people who actually resemble high school students. It adds a nice feeling of authenticity, and if there&amp;#39;s one thing I can give &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt; major props for it&amp;#39;s the use of actual search engines and social media sites; nothing ridiculous like FaceParty or YouSearch. Since the entirety of the action unfolds within a teenage girl&amp;#39;s computer monitor as she juggles a Skype group chat with her friends while scouring the internet for advice on how to deal with the vengeance-minded spirit of a former classmate, it&amp;#39;s important that everything feels as real world as possible.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a pretty novel and cool twist on the incredibly tiresome found-footage conceit, and I&amp;#39;ll be honest by saying I was actually kinda anticipating this. Unfortunately, once you take away the flashy window dressing, almost nothing about&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt; works at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, I&amp;#39;m a sucker for revenge stories. Few things satisfy me more than seeing the baddest of the bad receive their much deserved comeuppance. The idea of a girl driven to suicide only to return and punish her tormentors is a pretty solid one, but the way the film executes it feels incredibly confused and problematic. For better and (mostly) worse, you were able to find actors who could hit all the requisite levels of superficiality, despicability, and selfishness I imagine are present amongst many in that age bracket. However, even though it is revealed that our protagonists were somewhat complicit in the events leading up to Laura&amp;#39;s death, nothing about their systematic bumping-off holds any real emotional resonance. They aren&amp;#39;t callous enough for their deaths to feel justified and satisfying, yet on the flipside they don&amp;#39;t even come close to being likeable enough for us to feel sad about what&amp;#39;s happening to them. It all feels pretty hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing as the shenanigans are kicked off by a humiliating video of Laura being posted online, I must commend the filmmakers for having the good taste not to adopt a ripped-from-the-headlines approach and have the footage contain a sexual assault. That said, the video basically amounts to nothing more than Laura getting blackout drunk and having an accident. Embarrassing to be sure, but going on to torment her friends feels oddly unearned. Even more eyebrow raising are the implications that in life Laura may have herself been a bully and her conduct could have been far more egregious than those of her victims&amp;#39;, despite her near endless moral postulating (&amp;quot;You all deserve this, you&amp;#39;re all terrible people&amp;quot;, etc). Other than a minor twist or so towards the end, we have people being punished for basically leaving mean comments on YouTube, and an antagonist whose righteousness completely falls apart under the slightest scrutiny, despite the way the film handles her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, what about the scares, you may ask? I must admit that some of the death scenes are well done and even a little disturbing due to how unexpectedly graphic they are, but even then they&amp;#39;re severely undercut by the ludicrousness that follows. For instance, after witnessing the horrifying death of one of their friends, the survivors proceed to spend what feels like an eternity screaming, &lt;em&gt;screaming&lt;/em&gt; at each other over relatively minor secrets the ghost forces out of them. C&amp;#39;mon guys, big picture. You can argue over who totalled whose truck later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate horror that tries to address real life issues, but &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt; is just a mess on nearly every level. That said, you do have a good eye for age-appropriate casting so hopefully your services will be called upon for the next teen-centric horror exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/28/unfriended.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/28/unfriended.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Far From The Madding Crowd</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In some ways your book &lt;em&gt;Far From The Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; could stand as a proto-feminist manifesto. In other ways, important ways, it is an antecedent to some of the worst melodrama know to humanity. That the two things come together so artlessly in the 2015 film adaptation of your novel is unfortunate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This iteration of &lt;em&gt;Far From The Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; begins well. Your awkwardly named protagonist, Bathsheba Everdene, is fiercely independent and, thanks to a timely inheritance from a doting uncle, beholden to no one. For a woman to be propertied and untethered to any man was a rare circumstance at the end of the 19th Century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the rest of the story is a tangled web of contrivance involving three different Harlequin Romance archetypes. The quiet, self assured cowboy (in this case a shepherd played by Matthias Schoenaerts) the moneyed but damaged bachelor—Michael Sheen, of course—and even a faithless cad of a soldier, played by Tom Sturridge. As the story progresses it becomes hopelessly, and pointlessly, labyrinthine. A film that could have been a fascinating examination of class and gender in Victorian England devolves into a series of romantic mishaps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The names of Bathsheba’s suitors betray a kind of on-the-noseness that is present throughout the narrative: Gabriel Oak as the Shepherd, William Boldwood (I’ll bet it is) as the aging bachelor and Sergeant Troy as the philandering gambler in soldier’s clothing. Even the date of the original publication doesn’t excuse this clumsy wordplay, since there are far too many novels that come from the same period—&lt;em&gt;Jane Eyre&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;War and Peace&lt;/em&gt; just to name two—that rise far above this kind of genre laziness. I have also seen adaptations of &lt;em&gt;Far From the Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; where the tone and the melodrama were circumvented in useful ways—&lt;em&gt;Tamara Drewe&lt;/em&gt; most recently. But this particular version, helmed by director Tomas Vinterberg, is entirely too self-important and earnest to finesse the more leaden aspects of the plot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the performances are uniformly competent, the film itself is beautifully shot and the source material is rich enough that it might have been used to create something far more interesting. But the film falls apart in the last two acts. By choosing to focus on the Bathsheba’s inept management of her personal relationships, Vinterberg undercuts the moments that could have elevated this beyond a high-end gothic romance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are glimpses of what would have been (at the time) seditious egalitarianism as Bathsheba mucks it up with her various employees, literally getting covered in shite—thereby confounding the Monty Python method of identifying the ruling classes. But these become throwaway moments as more and more of the film occupies itself with describing the ungainly four way relationship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a way to make all of this work, I’m sure. But in this instance at least part of the problem is there is far too much story packed into too little time. Either this should have been a mini-series or there should have been some editorial decisions about what the film was going to focus on, because as it exists it is neither beast nor fowl—and that confusion is fatal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adaptations always carry a certain peril—lose the thread and you will be crucified by the fans. Or stick too closely and you run the risk of being hamstrung by the limitations of the original text. In this case a more liberal interpretation of your source material may well have served everyone better. As it stands &lt;em&gt;Far From The Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; is a film that is weighed down by a story that once must have felt revolutionary, but now seems trite.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/27/far-from-the-madding-crowd.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/27/far-from-the-madding-crowd.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Superman v Star Wars: The Blockbuster Awakens</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Two movie trailers set the internet ablaze last week. At the annual Star Wars Celebration festival in Anaheim, director J.J. Abrams debuted the second &lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; trailer to an auditorium full of eager fans. Earlier that same afternoon, in what you might call a teaser for the teaser of the trailer, Zack Snyder offered a few quick (and rather feckless) clips from &lt;em&gt;Batman&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;v Superman: Dawn of Justice&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this pageantry and playing coy is considered best practice for film marketers; trailer releases have become almost as important as the actual release of the film—and probably &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; important to those opening weekend numbers than the actual quality of the film. But these two particular trailers –in the aesthetics they purport to represent and the manner in which they were debuted – are indicative of two very different attitudes towards the contemporary Hollywood blockbuster. One approach  has exhausted critics, seems to be on the brink of exhausting fans, and may soon exhaust its momentum at the box office. The other approach, rooted in the not-so-distant past, might revive the diminishing artistic returns of the major studios’ tent-pole popcorn flicks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, the two trailers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ngElkyQ6Rhs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; bets heavily on nostalgia: we begin with a panoramic view of a familiar desert planetscape (&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; Tattooine, but a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; arid, windswept world); we get X-Wings and tie fighters; and, most notably, a Luke Skywalker voice-over and our first glimpse of retirement-age Han Solo. If you’re not a &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; devotee (and no mystical energy field controls &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; destiny), much of this won’t matter to you. But if you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; a fan, the swell of John Williams’ melodic strings and winds likely dried your throat, and the glimpses of your old pals Artoo and Chewie may have brought tears to your eyes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IwfUnkBfdZ4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Batman&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;v Superman&lt;/em&gt; is a much different trailer. After Snyder’s flirtatious tweets, it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ew.com/article/2015/04/17/batman-v-superman-trailer-leak&quot;&gt;“leaked” a week early&lt;/a&gt; (who can say whether the marketing team at Warner Bros. is just incompetent, or so incompetent that they’re brilliant). It begins with the standard throb of ominous ambient noise, then gives us a little Charlie Rose voice-over (which isn’t quite as affecting as hearing Mark Hamill); then a slow tracking shot towards a shadowed statue that is revealed to be, yes, a monument to Superman with, yes, graffiti scrawled across the chest that reads: False God. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zack Snyder has never been one for subtlety. Whatever hope there had been that the influence of Christopher Nolan (who produced &lt;em&gt;Man Of Steel&lt;/em&gt;, as well as this quasi-sequel) might quell his instinct for misanthropic self-seriousness was crushed by the arrival of his misanthropic, self-serious Superman film. The &lt;em&gt;Dawn of Justice&lt;/em&gt; trailer suggests that his follow-up is exactly what you might expect from the much-maligned pop-artist: beautiful, hyper-real CGI shots that seem like moving Rubens paintings, and laughable, hyper-dramatic dialogue (“this is how it starts...the fear, the rage...the feeling of powerlessness...”). This sneak peek at this latest superhero crossover – with which DC Comics and Warner Bros. is hoping to establish an &lt;em&gt;Avengers&lt;/em&gt;-style cinematic continuity – is more of the same: lots of shadows, sneering, heavy weaponry and political metaphors so broad that not even the Last Son of Krypton could leap them in a single bound. But let’s be frank: more of the same isn’t a bad thing for the bottom line. Despite being a critical disappointment, Superman’s big screen comeback grossed $668 Million worldwide. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zack Snyder may not be seeking redemption (he’s admirably unapologetic), and neither is J.J. Abrams (though some people think he should be). But Abrams faces a different challenge with his new flick—perhaps no filmmakers in the history of filmmaking has ever faced higher expectations than Abrams does as the heir to the Holy Trilogy. Online reaction to the very first &lt;em&gt;SW:FA&lt;/em&gt; teaser is proof. A pitch perfect capsule of images and sounds that elicited every good feeling about the original trilogy that the prequels supposedly forgot, and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; the naysayers found something to complain about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this new &lt;em&gt;SW:FA&lt;/em&gt; trailer suggest about Abrams’ approach? And how does it differ, in its foundational approach to big-budget cinema, from the &lt;em&gt;BvS&lt;/em&gt; trailer? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it’s important to understand why it makes sense to compare these two pictures. What makes them relative variables is the simple fact that they &lt;em&gt;exist&lt;/em&gt;. As recently as a decade ago, the notion of a big-budget superhero film featuring both of DC Comics’ two most iconic characters (along with Wonder Woman &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Aquaman, who are featured in a series of promotional posters, and therefore, one supposes, appear in the film—once again WB’s genius/incompetent marketing at work) would have been preposterous. Likewise, the possibility of new &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; films – featuring the original cast, no less! – seemed utterly implausible even just a few short years ago. George Lucas’s prequels had seemed to annihilate the franchise’s big screen ambitions (animated properties like &lt;em&gt;Clone Wars&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rebels&lt;/em&gt; have thrived on television and in toy aisles). That these two films are being released within a few months of each other suggests that we are reaching the crest of the sea change that began when Marvel began intermingling its characters and bundling them into blockbuster franchises. The narrative continuity that is so important to sci-fi and comic book superfans now exists in theaters. What seemed impossible is now possible. More than possible, actually. &lt;em&gt;Profitable&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about Abrams? He’s already rebooted one beloved sci-fi franchise, and, while he didn’t always get the ratio of fan service to storytelling right (says one of the fans he serviced), he resurrected the Enterprise and its crew fairly well. &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; will require a defter touch, though, and if this latest trailer is any indication, Abrams may have gotten it right. And he gets it right in direct opposition to the approach Snyder takes. Optimism, positivity, clarity and, most significantly–– a palpable sense of &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; something that Hollywood seems to have completely forgotten when it comes to these types of films. What made Abrams’ second &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; flick such a disappointment was how much it felt like every other recent mega-action film: incomprehensible action, overwhelming effects, the sound and fury signifying nothing, and, worst of all, an obscenely high body count paired with imagery suggestive (almost offensively) of 9/11. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You might say he Zack Snyder-ed it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of this is speculation (and no small amount of barely-suppressed fanboy hope), which is precisely what trailers of this kind are meant to provoke. Maybe &lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; will be dark and gloomy and replete with the kind of slick CGI that contradicts the gritty Old-West aesthetic of the very first film. Maybe  &lt;em&gt;Batman&lt;/em&gt; v Superman will embrace the absurdity of a superpowered alien fighting a rich old white guy with an underground armory and a taste for cosplay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the trailers don’t suggest so. And while these little two-minute commercials the marketing department cuts together are rarely indicative of the &lt;em&gt;quality&lt;/em&gt; of the film, they tend to pretty accurately predict a film’s mood and tenor.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s little doubt that &lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; will top the list of 2015’s biggest films (and with a Christmas release, might just end up being 2016’s box office champion, too). And there’s also little doubt that Abrams has made it a priority to recapture a bit of the innocence and wonder that made Lucas’ space adventures more than just films. The question is, will this return to a simpler, lighter, more positive approach to the blockbuster reverse the trend that started a decade ago with the Nolan’s first Batman film? Has the gritty reboot run its course? And is that necessarily a good thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good or not, it will be, in the meantime, a relief.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/22/superman-v-star-wars-the-blockbuster-awakens.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/22/superman-v-star-wars-the-blockbuster-awakens.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>True Story</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have never believed you. On a deep, molecular level I find you utterly unconvincing. No matter what character you may be playing I find it almost impossible to accept you as anything other than Jonah Hill pretending to be some guy. So the fact that you are the deeply flawed protagonist of a film called &lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; is kind of problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jonah Hill Effect is far less of a barrier for me in movies like &lt;em&gt;21 Jump Street&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;This is The End&lt;/em&gt; because you are not playing a character that requires much of a stretch—either on my part or yours. All I have to do is accept the premise of you as helpless schlub (and, in the case of &lt;em&gt;This is The End,&lt;/em&gt; demon spawn) and I’m in. In &lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; though, your singular capacity to undermine my suspension of disbelief is reflective of the films most glaring weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; is an account of the relationship between a journalist and an accused murderer. It is the kind of true crime story (like NPR’s &lt;em&gt;Serial&lt;/em&gt; or HBO’s &lt;em&gt;The Jinx: The Life and Deaths of Robert Durst&lt;/em&gt;) that demonstrates a reality that ethicist Janet Malcolm delineates in her book, &lt;em&gt;The Journalist and the Murderer:&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Every journalist who is not too stupid or too full of himself to notice what is going on knows that what he does is morally indefensible.&amp;quot;  It is the kind of work that—if it is to be successful at all, and not simply exploitative and inherently parasitic—requires the finest sort of calibrations regarding tone and presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; feels most thin when dealing with its central theme—what is the space between people’s stated intentions and their actions—largely because the two central characters are not presented credibly. I don’t believe James Franco’s portrayal as accused murderer Christian Longo and I certainly do not believe you in the role of disgraced NYT journalist Michael Finkel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your performance is arid, disengaged. Your scenes with Franco feel like a table read or a workshop, completely devoid of emotional content. The performance is so mechanical and workmanlike that I feel like I am watching particularly well rehearsed community theatre, competent enough but devoid of any real emotional truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt;’s problems do not begin and end with casting. The choice to break the film into vignettes that are so clearly delineated make the whole exercise feel dispassionate and removed. The point of making a fictional film based on true events would seem to be about reaching some deeper truths, something that lies behind a straightforward recitation of events. But the film’s structure undermines that goal, leaving it feeling emotionally sterile and disconnected from its subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; certainly strives for a kind of authenticity—using natural light and low-key performances, long takes and a general reserve in the story telling. The pallet is cold and often muted and nothing about the visual presentation is over the top. Normally these would all be points in the film’s favor but in this case they tend to underline the vacuity of the central performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are the only way into this film for the audience but you are an unreadable cipher. The character you portray is the linchpin of the whole story and you just don’t give us enough to hang onto—despite the fact that, as a narrator, your character is inherently unreliable. I don’t even believe the truth of your lies, as it were. So at the end of the film all I could think was how interesting this story might have been if it had been a documentary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/20/true-story.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/20/true-story.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Conversation With Director Denis Villeneuve</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;On the day &lt;em&gt;Sicario&lt;/em&gt; was announced as part of the 2015 Festival de Cannes’ official competition, C. Redmond speaks with the incredible French-Canadian director about his chances of winning, maintaining his signature in Hollywood, and the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; sequel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean to you to be accepted into Cannes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the biggest honour – it’s a massive honour for me to be part of the competition this year. Cannes is the Mecca of cinema. To see the lineup, I go there with humility because just to be part of that lineup I’m already very proud, and grateful for the invitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You kind of got your start at Cannes. You worked your way from the Director’s Fortnight, and then Un Certain Regard. Did you feel it was almost inevitable that you would someday have a film in competition, or are you surprised?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my dream but sometimes you feel like dreams are fading because more and more I was making movies in America. So I thought I was going away from that world of film festivals, and right now this movie that was produced in Los Angeles is a nice compliment because it’s very important for me to keep my identity as a filmmaker when I’m shooting abroad. Just to be able to keep my point of view, to stay myself. And the fact that they are inviting me, they recognize the fact that I was able to protect my identity as a filmmaker in another system of production. That for me is a big compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Coen Brothers are going to be leading the jury. Do you think that will help your odds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, strangely, I’m feeling that because we share Roger Deakins as a cinematographer, I think it makes things tougher (laughs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you talk to me about working with Roger&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Deakins? Tell me what the difference was between working with him the first time and working with him a second time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second time I was much, much more comfortable with Roger. The first time I was always a bit impressed. I was feeling like a student and he’s the teacher. The second time it was more collaborative, the communication was much better. Stylistically we get along pretty well. The first experience was beautiful, but the second was better. Working with Roger, honestly, it’s rare in your lifetime that you will have a chance to work with a master. And he’s someone, even if I’m on set with him and I have to direct him, or nourish him so he’s able to create, I always feel like I’m in a learning process, because I’m learning all the time with Roger. Every shot, I’m learning something. It’s a massive privilege for me to get to work two times with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there someone you worked with on your most recent film &lt;em&gt;Sicario&lt;/em&gt;  that stood out to you as great, but might never get any media attention?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh boy. Yeah, I’ll give you one right now: the dolly pusher, his name is Bruce Hamme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve got to be kidding! I did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/10/prisoners.html&quot;&gt;review of &lt;em&gt;Prisoners&lt;/em&gt; and I wrote to Bruce Hamme &lt;/a&gt;. That’s too funny. I noticed his work.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the man. That guy is an artist. He’s the dolly grip and he’s the extension of Roger, the one who will create the dance of the camera, the one who will find the right rhythm. He’s the most precise, the way he pushes the camera is just an art form. I feel he is also the most lovely human being. Roger is using a specific crane in almost every shot, which means in almost every shot we have to build that crane, a little crane that is so precise and so delicate and Bruce is dancing with that crane all day long, and working and he never complains. And he’s the nicest human being. Bruce is definitely the one I will make an homage to, a tribute to Bruce. I could talk about him for hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s perfect. I met you at the Genie Awards four years ago, and you told me your friends were making fun of you saying, “Denis, when are you going to stop making these pretentious art films and make a sci-fi film, because you know that’s what you really love”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(laughs) Exactly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And now you’ve got two sci-fi films coming. Tell me how that finally happened.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I arrived in LA with &lt;em&gt;Incendies&lt;/em&gt;, all the studios were asking me, “What will you do? What would be your dream?”  And my only answer was always sci-fi, because I knew that if there was something that I could do in Hollywood that I couldn’t do at home it was sci-fi. With sci-fi you need a certain amount of resources. So I kept on saying this and at one point two young producers came with a fantastic little short story called &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt;. It was one of the best things that I’d read and I was like “Whoa!” this is poetic, beautiful and strong and exactly the kind of project that I would dream to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep saying I want to do sci-fi for adults, so like &lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt;. That was always the two examples I would give that I would want to do. Or &lt;em&gt;Close Encounters&lt;/em&gt;. So with 21 Laps, a company set in LA, I developed this little sci-fi project called &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt;. I’m going to shoot in next June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And now you’re going to work with Bradford Young as a cinematographer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I’m going to work with Bradford Young because Roger Deakins wasn’t available this summer. He wanted to do the project but there was a scheduling conflict. So I made a long research and came into contact with that cinematographer. He’s young but he already has a strong signature. I was very impressed. I fell in love with his work quite quickly, and to my great pleasure he agreed to get on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Would you consider working with (cinematographer) Nicolas Bolduc again?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to because I love Nico. Yeah, of course! But when you cast a DP, you cast a specific sensibility, and for &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt; I needed someone like Bradford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt;? That doesn’t seem like it would be in Roger Deakins’ normal palate of what he does. Would you consider him for that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot answer that, but I can tell you you have the wrong instincts (laughs). It would be a dream for me to do that with Roger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(laughs) Good to know!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Are you able to talk about at all what you want to do, how you want to put your stamp on revisiting that story?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a creative point of view unfortunately I can say nothing, other than that the script is pretty powerful and that it was a long decision for me to make. It was too much of a dream for me to participate on such a project and I’m aware of the massive pressure. The original &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; is one of my favourite movies of all time. I saw that movie maybe fifty times in my life. I will do my homework and I am uber excited. I wake up every morning pinching myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think there are any lessons to be taken from&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prometheus&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be very disappointed because unfortunately I can say nothing.  All I can say is that the script was written by Hampton Fancher, Ridley Scott and Michael Green and the three of them did very impressive work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any scripts that you’re writing that you want to do in the future?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest I cannot make a lineup of projects. For now I’m just concentrating on &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt; and the possibility of &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; right after is enough for me (laughs). After that, I will sleep for three weeks, or three months maybe. I feel that I lined up a lot of projects one after the other and after that I will probably take a break. Just for a few months and go back on to screenwriting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just promise it’s not going to be as long as the break you had between  &lt;em&gt;Maelstrom&lt;/em&gt; (2000) and &lt;em&gt;Polytechnique&lt;/em&gt; (2009). We need you too much.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(laughs) Don’t worry, that’s not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Last Knights</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The vocal style you use, singing the same syllable over several notes, is called “&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melisma&quot;&gt;melisma&lt;/a&gt;”. Its intended purpose is to provide a hypnotic, or trance-like effect. You’ve found incredible success by blending this style with electronica, hip-hop and French torch songs and yet have always managed to sound completely original. &lt;em&gt;Last Knights&lt;/em&gt; repeats so many worn out tropes, visuals, and stock characters that it too induced a trance-like effect. A kind of deja-vu that nearly sent me into a deep sleep for its seemingly seven-plus hour duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen &lt;em&gt;47 Ronin&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;King Arthur&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;Robin Hood: Men&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;In&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Tights&lt;/em&gt; then you won’t see anything that hasn’t already been done better (and blessedly faster) than &lt;em&gt;Last Knights.&lt;/em&gt; I could try to elaborate on the plot, but the one-sentence IMDb description is vague and unfulfilling enough that I figured I’d follow in &lt;em&gt;Last Knight&lt;/em&gt;s’ phoned-in footsteps and just copy/paste it here. “A fallen warrior rises against a corrupt and sadistic ruler to avenge his dishonored master.” In fact, part of me is tempted to just write this review by cribbing sentences from reviews of better sword and sandal epics. But unlike the makers of &lt;em&gt;Last Knights&lt;/em&gt;, I’m at least half interested in creating something new. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clive Owen plays Raiden, who is part of an elite group of warriors in what I can only assume is some kind of alternate universe. According to Morgan Freeman’s voice over, this group was formed “during the long dark period of the Great War” and is made up of “all races, colours and creeds”, (but not all genders, unsurprisingly). These fierce fighters are sworn to protect their masters, who in Raiden’s case is Morgan Freeman’s Lord Bartok. When Gezza Mott, the fey, sociopathic Minister to the Emperor has Bartok killed and his people evicted, Raiden and his fellow warriors spend the next seven, or maybe it was eight hours of screen time trying to avenge his death.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sound is considered part of the nebulous “world music” genre, which encompasses everything from reggae, to Inuit throat singing, and Buddhist chanting. Your inclusion as a vocalist in this film was most likely meant to lend a trans-cultural vibe, since not once do we ever really know where the film is set. Describing it sounds like I’m trying to recall details of my own kidnapping while under hypnosis: it’s mostly snowy, and grey, there are mountains and forests, and the capital looks like a heavily CGI’d Medieval Times. Perhaps the film’s pedigree (it’s a Czech/South Korea co-production helmed by Japanese director Kazukai Kiriya) contributed to its identity crisis. Or perhaps by trying to be all things to all audiences it simply collapsed under the weight of its own hubris, and no one knew which country was legally bound to put it out of its misery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first heard your clear and powerful voice I thought it was my own inner monologue moaning “Anhhhhhhhh...anhhh...annnnnnnhhh” in agony from hearing dialogue desperately searching for gravitas, seeing characters so flimsily drawn I could have seen right through them if the sets weren’t so poorly lit, and watching bland fight scenes so tension-free they could have been choreographed by the WWE. The only thing that might have saved this film from being a complete snooze-fest would have been some unintentional humour, but &lt;em&gt;Last Knights&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t even have the decency to be camp. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Knights&lt;/em&gt; is a retrograde throwback celebrating “manly men doing manly things” that takes itself far too seriously. But through it all, your voice remains steady and true, and I welcomed it, since the only other women in the film were either crying, or whoring it up at the local tavern. I think Clive Owen’s wife might have been a twig vendor but I also might have imagined it when I went into one of the fugue states this film induced. Or maybe Clive Owen’s real life wife &lt;em&gt;really is&lt;/em&gt; a twig vendor and that’s why had to make this movie. I hope that’s the case, or else I’m going to have to get a band of rogue warriors together to avenge his honour. Any chance you’re interested in being our minstrel?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/16/last-nights.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/16/last-nights.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
