<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>American Sniper&#39;s Magic Bullet Theory</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Readers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Sniper&lt;/em&gt; is a big fat box-office hit. It has become a must-see movie, not just for star-spangled flag-wavers, Oscar completionists and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-snipers-fake-baby-mocked-764702&quot;&gt;plastic baby fetishists&lt;/a&gt;, but general audiences, too. Yes, the film is a legitimately well-made drama, and can be twisted to fit all sorts of personal and political agendas. But it’s also surprisingly subversive. How? Because the filmmakers suggest that Chris Kyle is a bit of a fraud.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many journalists, critics, and pundits have dissected Chris Kyle’s actions; whether he was motivated by patriotism, racism, or deeper psychology problems. But no one seems to be talking about how he may have made a lot of this stuff up. Or at least the film allows for that interpretation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screenwriter Jason Hall takes a bit of creative license and introduces a fictional character – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/16/american-sniper.html&quot;&gt;a rival sniper&lt;/a&gt; – who helps balance out Kyle’s unfair superiority over the enemy, but also weakens what could have been a much more powerful allegory about the unjustness of the American invasion of Iraq. It’s an effective (if not generic) dramatic addition, and justifies Kyle’s need to return, time and time again, to a foreign country that poses no real threat to him or America. But it’s also the narrative device that questions Kyle’s self-identification as a sure-shot protector of the innocent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film doesn’t try to completely discredit Kyle’s kill count. But in the way it handles the enemy sniper storyline, the film does offer a subtle refutation of his heroic claims. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to buy Kyle’s account of events as they&amp;#39;re dramatized in &lt;em&gt;American Sniper&lt;/em&gt;. In the final battle sequence, director Clint Eastwood shows us the al-Qaeda sniper being shot, and then lingers on the sniper’s dead body. On paper, it sounds like a simple indulgence; an incredulous victory that elevates Kyle to superhero status. He’s a man who can perform the impossible. But look carefully at the sober reactions of the supporting characters and the filming techniques used in this sequence. It&amp;#39;s easy to conclude that Kyle doesn’t actually kill the enemy sniper. He made it up. It was a fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s plenty of evidence. When Kyle is being briefed for his last mission, he’s told about a sniper picking off construction engineers on a building downtown. Kyle excitedly asks: “Is it Mustafa?”. But the commander answers with deference: “It can be whoever the fuck you need him to be.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the audience, like Kyle, are craving a final confrontation. So of course we believe the sniper is Mustafa. But why the mystery? Why not have his commander at least acknowledge the possibility, or agree with the likelihood, of it being Kyle’s proto-antagonist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trucks roll out and we get a beautiful aerial shot of Baghdad, trailing behind a drone that flies with dream-like ease. Once above the target building, however, the camera twists, a suspended musical note plays—a signal that things are about to take a turn for the worse. We get the feeling we’re entering a nightmare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon Kyle is on a rooftop, trying to figure out the enemy’s location. Another U.S. soldier is shot. Kyle, realizing he’s made a wrong assumption, scrambles to a new position. The filmmakers aren’t just telling us that Kyle is fallible in his choices, but letting us know that Kyle is literally looking at this situation the wrong way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastwood, however, cuts in close to assure the audience that, yes, of course it’s Mustafa. Phew, right? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle repositions to a convenient clearing in the roof. Over a mile away from his target, Kyle looks through his scope at the enemy’s probable position. Even through a magnified sight, no one is visible at the other end. Kyle’s commander points this out, and a point-of-view perspective shot reinforces this claim. It’s impossible to see anyone at that distance. When asked for confirmation, we get an even closer view: still, no one is visible. Yet when asked, Kyle confirms, confidently asserting: “Oh, it’s him.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle fires, and for the first time in the film Eastwood indulges in a bit of stylized slow-motion. This signals a departure from the grounded, realistic perspective he employs throughout the rest of the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watch the bullet fly into the vast city. Crystal clear. Almost supernatural. But this is because we’re now seeing things through Kyle’s imagined perspective. The camera cuts to Mustafa in profile – also in dream-like slow motion – then we cut back to see the bullet disappear into the distance, out of Kyle’s imagined sight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few shot-reverse-shot close-ups provide the imaginary face-to-face confrontation Kyle craves. Then blood explodes onto a shawl behind the enemy’s head. Kyle, looking into the distance, breathes a sign of relief. A moment later, his satisfaction is interrupted by the reality that he has given away their position to the insurgents below. His commander spells it out: “You just fucked us, Legend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Kyle relaxes, a fellow solider (turned in the opposite direction as Kyle) responds with President Bush’s famously assertive – and premature (ie. wrong) – Iraq War declaration: “Mission accomplished!” The forced enthusiasm stings with irony. Kyle’s magic bullet would make Lee Harvey Oswald jealous. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the film goes into full nightmare mode. A sandstorm rages over the final battle, completely obstructing the enemy and obscuring all clarity. This pathetic fallacy is used to muddy the visual palette and reflect a confused state of mind—one that comes from knowing that closure isn’t simply a target you can hit. Especially when you&amp;#39;re lying to yourself about the truth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But would Eastwood really rely on such misdirection without introducing the idea of an unreliable protagonist sooner? Of course not. The dolly shot when Kyle is at home, staring blankly at a television that isn’t turned on, is another clue that what he sees and what’s happening aren’t always the same thing. We hear the cacophony of a gun battle, but it’s only the echoes in his head. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the film, when Kyle has supposedly transformed into a perfect father, he walks into the kitchen with a cocked hand-gun pointed as his wife. She might not sense the danger, but we sure as hell do. This isn’t just foreshadowing of what’s about to happen to Kyle, but a blatant reminder that he’s still unhinged. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more telling is the sequence right &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the sniper showdown. Look at the way Kyle is framed during the most emotionally charged scene in the film, when a small child picks up an RPG and aims it at U.S. troops. Kyle&amp;#39;s spotter is also in the frame, but sitting back, staring blankly into the sky. This comes, oddly, right &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Kyle has killed a man on the street. The spotter doesn’t even sit up straight and look over the ledge to confirm the kill. Are we supposed to assume that Kyle is so prolific in killing that his fellow soldiers don’t even react anymore? Is this second solider simply bored by war? Or are the filmmakers suggesting another imaginary battle being waged in Kyle’s mind? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies with the viewer. And that&amp;#39;s the real reason&lt;em&gt;American Sniper&lt;/em&gt; is connecting with so many people. If you look close enough,  Chris Kyle can be “whoever the fuck you need him to be.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/1/american-snipers-magic-bullet-theory.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/1/american-snipers-magic-bullet-theory.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Whiplash</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A bravura performance is, by its very nature, exhilarating to behold. And J.K. Simmons, as the despotic music instructor Terrence Fletcher in &lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt;, indeed gives a bravura performance. He spits verbal abuse like a beatnik R. Lee Ermey, demonstrates a Hannibal Lecter-like capacity for psychological torture, and even attempts to decapitate a student by hurling a cymbal discus-style at the kid’s head. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely, though, does a bravura performance by a member of the post-production crew take center stage the way it does in &lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt;. From the very first frames, your virtuosic editing asserts itself as a core component of writer/director Damien Chazelle’s aesthetic—and, as the film progresses, it seems to take on a life of its own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analogy is almost too easy: the editor as drummer, keeping time, setting pace. But in this film, it’s particularly apt. You never rush, never lag. You’re always right on tempo, even when that tempo is completely syncopated. Like the great jazz musicians around whom &lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt; builds much of its mythology (to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2014/10/11/whiplash_charlie_parker_and_the_cymbal_what_the_movie_gets_wrong_about_genius.html&quot;&gt;misguided objections&lt;/a&gt; of some critics), you seem to be improvising a visual solo that runs in phrases and melodies above and beneath and through the raw material provided by writer/director Damien Chazelle and cinematographer Sharone Meir. As Fletcher puts his studio band through the paces, the countless hours of practice are compressed into little mini-montages of close-cropped images: instrument cases are opened and closed, reeds are drained, callouses drip blood. The unease before a big performance is further constricted by similarly disorienting bursts: sheet music is marked, drum keys crank on tension rods, a pair of lips exhales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, these are stylistic (perhaps superfluous) embellishments. But in a jazz performance, no one begrudges such flourishes; it’s what the art form is all about. It’s those unexpected notes that make a thing sublime, unique. Likewise, in &lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt;, the edits occur where you don’t expect them, and it’s in this polyrhythmic interplay between the images – close and wide, dark and light, fast- and slow-motion – that the film elevates itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you don’t just express your proficiency by showing off in those big moments. Early in the film, when drumming prodigy Andrew Neimann finds himself on an awkward first date, we get a quick glimpse beneath the table as his companion gently brushes her foot against his. For all the bombast elsewhere, this cut is almost invisible; you can hardly believe you weren’t looking at their shoes the whole time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film itself is about bravura performances, and, as you might expect, it culminates with one (the way it unfolds, though, is quite unexpected, so that’s not quite a spoiler). What makes &lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt; unique in the genre (if one can indeed call the journey-of-the-arts-prodigy narrative its own genre) is the honesty with which it addresses the messy (sometimes bloody) process by which greatness is achieved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was there to push people beyond what&amp;#39;s expected of them,” Fletcher tells Neimann. “There are no two words in the English language more harmful than &lt;em&gt;good job&lt;/em&gt;.” I wonder if you had a similar relationship with any of the mentors you worked with early in your career. Maybe David Milch during your time on &lt;em&gt;Deadwood&lt;/em&gt;. Or maybe John Axelrad, who you’ve assisted on numerous films, including two James Gray pictures. Was it one of them who pushed you beyond what was expected of you as an editor? Have either of them ever chucked a hard drive of raw footage at your head? Whatever the case, you’ve certainly found a way to push yourself. And the result is a singular achievement that even a chronically dissatisfied psychopath like Terrence Fletcher could be proud of. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/28/whiplash.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/28/whiplash.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Is it #OscarsSoWhite or just #OscarsSoWrong?</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear America,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Since the Oscar nominations were announced last week, the noticeable lack of diversity among the high profile nominees has become a huge controversy. “The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/oscars/oscar-nominations-2015-academy-criticised-for-allwhite-nominees-in-acting-categories-9980457.html&quot;&gt;whitest year&lt;/a&gt; since 1998!” has become a familiar lament. “Selma gets snubbed!” was a headline or sub-head in almost every single Oscar news item of the day. Hands were wrung—not just in self-righteous protest, but in disappointment over the dismissal of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html&quot;&gt;beautifully accomplished film&lt;/a&gt; that could have used the boost in profile.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selma being overlooked, however, feels less like an institutional crime than one of poor taste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one will deny that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_of_Motion_Picture_Arts_and_Sciences&quot;&gt;Academy’s demographics&lt;/a&gt; don’t reflect the diversity of America. Neither do most of the films that Hollywood makes (not by a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2014/12/11/these-charts-prove-hollywood-still-has-a-huge-racial-gap/&quot;&gt;long shot&lt;/a&gt;). Clearly that needs to change. However, in nearly two decades, this is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/oscars-acting-nominees-all-white-764018&quot;&gt;only the second time&lt;/a&gt; acting nominations went exclusively to white actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disappointment of film fans seems to be focused on David Oyelowo and Ava DuVerany (two relative unknowns), neither of whom received one of the five slots coveted by every film actor and director in the world. It’s a missed opportunity, sure. Especially with such a legitimate chance to nominate (deservedly) the first female Black director. But when the nominees were announced last week, barely anyone had seen &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;. Yet everyone in the media (social and traditional) wasted no time in crying foul. The road to progress seems to lead, once again, to &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;—but maybe not in the way that most people think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact the film was nominated in fewer categories than most of us would have liked might paradoxically be a positive sign. This feels like true equal-opportunity outrage, the kind everyone feels when their favorite film is ignored. But it doesn’t feel like an outrage about a &lt;em&gt;lack&lt;/em&gt; of equal opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, the unflinching drama &lt;em&gt;12 Years a Slave&lt;/em&gt; – directed by a Black Brit – took home Best Picture. And for the most part, black movie stars have been fairly represented at the Oscars for the better part of a decade. Jamie Foxx, Forrest Whittaker, Morgan Freeman, Lupita N’yongo, Octvia Spencer, Mo’Nique Imes-Jackson, Jennifer Hudson—all major winners in the last decade (representing 7 of the past 40 acting awards). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an outsider’s perspective, things don’t necessarily look so grim. At the same time, however, it&amp;#39;s understandable how it might feel like a step backward. Particularly in a year when racial inequality has led to some truly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomberg.com/politics/articles/2014-12-07/bloomberg-politics-poll-finds-most-americans-see-race-relations-worsening-since-obamas-election&quot;&gt;ugly moments&lt;/a&gt;. Especially when &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; felt so timely, so worthy. But isn’t it possible that accusations of institutional racism are overblown in the exact same way that accusations were of quota-filling from last year? Isn’t the odd all-white year of actors (say, once a decade) kind of statistically inevitable? Is DuVernay really so unique in being excluded? Remember all the flack about Affleck&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Argo&lt;/em&gt; snub from a few years ago? Great directors of great films are often overlooked, from Fritz Lang to Christopher Nolan. Not to mention scores of worthy actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the first biopic about Martin Luther King Jr. &lt;em&gt;seemed&lt;/em&gt; to check all the Oscar boxes. Yet it only received a check in two categories. The Academy, apparently, isn’t as predictable as we think. That said, &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is nominated for Best Picture in a year where only eight films got that distinction (out of a possible 10). That’s an accomplishment that shouldn’t be diminished. If we’re going to bemoan the short-changing of &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;, why aren’t we also talking about some of the other minority exclusions? Like Chadwick Boseman’s incredible performance as James Brown in &lt;em&gt;Get On Up&lt;/em&gt;. Or lauding that film’s similar subversion of the biopic formula (just try to watch the first 10 minutes and not be hooked). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that spirit,, why not share some upset over the fact Jake Gyllenhaal wasn’t nominated for &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;. There are no easy answers to explain that blatant omission, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the case, it’s clear that America has reached a point where a great film by a black director, about a great black man, with great performances by great black actors can be overlooked—not because of race, or politics, but because the Academy’s usual poor taste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s something akin to progress, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerley,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Cast &amp;amp; Crew&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2015 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/26/is-it-oscarssowhite-or-just-oscarssowrong.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/26/is-it-oscarssowhite-or-just-oscarssowrong.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Boxtrolls</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You have always been a favorite of mine, Sir Ben. But this performance? Unbelievable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Boxtrolls&lt;/em&gt; is the most complete genre film I have seen in a very long time. And that includes &lt;em&gt;Zero Dark 30, Birdman, Raid: Redemption&lt;/em&gt; and even &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt;. While those films hold a special place in my heart, &lt;em&gt;Box Trolls&lt;/em&gt; stands head and shoulders above them in a particular way. The only other films that come immediately to mind that are as carefully realized are Kurosawa’s &lt;em&gt;Seven Samurai&lt;/em&gt; and Huston’s &lt;em&gt;The Maltese Falcon&lt;/em&gt;. Both of which are examples of the kind of films that feel utterly true to themselves. Yes, just like &lt;em&gt;The Boxtrolls&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a bit of that magnificence is owed to you, Sir Ben. Your ecstatically unhinged portrayal of the aptly-named social climber, Archibald Snatcher/Madame Frou Frou. You are not alone in your excellence. Voice acting is an often overlooked art, but it can really make a good film better and a mediocre film unwatchable. In this case, Simon Pegg and Nick Frost, along with Jared Harris, Richard Ayoade (and even Tracy Morgan for god’s sake) add to a heady mix of world building and joyously unconventional chaos that is unmatched in any film I have seen this year, animated or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be difficult to do justice to the depth and detail of the world &lt;em&gt;The Boxtrolls&lt;/em&gt;creates. Every behavioral and visual cue of its occupants and their environment reinforces a sense of place, a world that is fully contained and articulated. A small but telling example is how the Box Trolls demonstrate their non-verbal approval; it’s a gesture so simple, yet so poignant, that it serves to cement their reality. The film is filled from top to bottom with these kinds of moments—but you have to give this film the attention it deserves to catch them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is adapted from the YA book &lt;em&gt;Here Be Monsters&lt;/em&gt; by Alan Snow. Certainly this film is not a verbatim retelling of the book, but it does retain a particular anarchic undercurrent. A more effective and pointed deconstruction of the idiocy of rigid class barriers would be difficult to imagine. The kind of distortions and lack of perspective such systems engender is exposed, in the film, with metaphors like the implied importance of a thing as banal as the color of a hat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snatcher – desperately grasping, alternately fawning and threatening, wholly consumed with the trappings of power – is an example of what kind of citizen these sort of barriers create. But the flair, my god. You can chew scenery even when you’re a stop-motion grotesque. Despite your overwhelming presence, the film still perfectly integrates Snatcher and his nasty anima, Madame Frou Frou, into its pantheon of distinctive and memorable characters. It all works phenomenally well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated films have become the gold standard for narrative construction. They are almost always remarkably well-crafted when it comes to the basics of storytelling. And while some have argued that the plot of &lt;em&gt;The Boxtrolls&lt;/em&gt; is too thin, I think that misses what’s important: so much of the story resides in the lived details of the characters rather than the exposition; cheese as a status symbol; the unarticulated but overt class barriers; the parallels between the Box Trolls and Europe’s historically demonized ethnic under classes. All these details add a subtle narrative richness that is essential in making the world of the story feel real. I also now understand why the &lt;em&gt;Lego Movie&lt;/em&gt; didn’t make the cut. &lt;em&gt;The Boxtrolls&lt;/em&gt; makes it look like the basement project of a couple well-equipped, smart-assed university kids. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Ben for contributing to this minor masterpiece. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I feel like it would be alright to call you Ben.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 19:00:01 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/25/the-boxtrolls.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/25/the-boxtrolls.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Foxcatcher</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever watched a movie that, by all accounts, you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; like, but for whatever reason the pieces never quite click into place and you’re left cold? For me, &lt;em&gt;Foxcatcher&lt;/em&gt; fits that description perfectly. It&amp;#39;s admirable in many respects; handsomely put together with some standout performances from Channing Tatum and Mark Ruffalo. Unfortunately, your weirdly one-note portrayal of the wealthy and eccentric John du Pont is one of those cold, out-of-place pieces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is, from the very moment he’s introduced, you play him as slightly off. Actually, no, that isn&amp;#39;t quite right. “Slightly off” better describes Tatum&amp;#39;s Mark Schultz, the socially awkward striver prone to startling episodes of self harm. What you did, instead, was borrow a page from the Jack Nicholson playbook and go big right from the start (see &lt;em&gt;The Shining&lt;/em&gt;), turning up the dial on Du Pont’s jarring bizarreness rather than mapping a more gradual descent into madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, this makes Du Pont so markedly different from anyone he interacts with that it raises the question as to what exactly he&amp;#39;s capable of, and some of the early scenes are indeed filled with an uneasy tension. But it becomes evident the longer the film goes on that there will be little nuance or variation to your performance, and what started out as aberrant and unsettling quickly becomes tedious. I went into the film knowing little of the real life du Pont, and once the credits began to roll I was just as uninformed. The screenplay grasps at explaining his psychology, but it’s all fairly shallow and uninteresting (he has mommy issues, surprise surprise). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#39;m not going to lay all the blame entirely on your shoulders. Far from it.  &lt;em&gt;Foxcatcher&lt;/em&gt;, as a whole, is flat. There&amp;#39;s little spark to the wrestling scenes, which is surprising given that so much of the film&amp;#39;s narrative revolves around Schultz and his team training for the 1998 Olympics. Additionally, the relationship between Mark Schultz and Du Pont, complete with blurry sexual subtext, is never truly engaging. The grand moment of tragedy, towards which the whole film builds, feels oddly mishandled. Not just because your performance makes it clear, from the very moment you appear onscreen, that Du Pont is capable of doing terrible things (we’re basically waiting for it to happen for two interminable hours), but because the other character involved spends almost no screen time with you. The stakes feel low. If it wasn’t based on true events, the ending would feel like a cheap, easy way to add a jolt to the otherwise uneventful narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hard to not be intrigued by the prospect of seeing you in a fully dramatic role, and I hope you continue taking on such projects in the future. Maybe next time choose one that offers you a better chance to flex your dramatic muscles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/25/foxcatcher.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/25/foxcatcher.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mortdecai</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There was a time when I would have been envious of your position above Johnny Depp’s lip. He was the dark, brooding bad boy to all the cookie-cutter, L.A. heartthrobs manufactured in the 80s. Depp made me actually hope a hot narc would show up at my high school. But as I followed his career, it was his film choices that made me a real admirer. &lt;em&gt;What’s Eating Gilbert Grape, Ed Wood,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dead Man&lt;/em&gt; set him apart from his contemporaries who seemed to be chasing blockbuster stardom. The zenith of Depp’s oddball sensibility was &lt;em&gt;Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas&lt;/em&gt;. Depp, Hunter S. Thompson and Terry Gilliam - three fearless creative geniuses and their collective madness represented in one filthy, Rube Goldberg-device of a film. I was in movie nerd-vana. Depp was the undisputed King of Quirk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But every empire must fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must know you weren’t Depp’s first faux facial hair. Since the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Caribbean&lt;/em&gt; phenomenon, Depp has increasingly made a habit of taking on roles that require him to wear makeup, wigs, and any number of piercings, contact lenses, and false probosci. It’s as if he’s purposely seeking out films that will put him in the makeup chair for at least five hours. There used to be a time when Depp merely being in a film would be the defining reason for me to see it. That Black Pearl has sailed. If I wanted to see a guy who used to make my labes sweat, poncing around in a garish costume and affecting a ludicrous accent, I’d go to my ex-boyfriend’s annual Halloween party. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this a &lt;em&gt;Dear John’s Moustache&lt;/em&gt; letter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not enough for Depp to merely wear these ridiculous get-ups, now they have to be written into the script. Depp is the titular Lord Charlie Mortdecai in &lt;em&gt;Mortdecai.&lt;/em&gt; A self-described part-time rogue (?), Charlie is in danger of losing Mortdecai Manor to back-taxes. His expertise as an art dealer makes him the unwilling partner of the MI5 in trying to retrieve a stolen painting that may have the code to a Swiss bank account containing lost Nazi gold. Charlie must work with Inspector Martland, a former schoolmate, who just happens to be desperately in love with Charlie’s wife Johanna, played by a glowing Gwynneth Paltrow. Johanna, who has just returned from a trip abroad, is confronted by you, the moustache Charlie has proudly cultivated in her absence. But Johanna refuses all intimacy with Charlie unless he gets rid of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have nothing against you personally. I love silly disguises and madcap romps. &lt;em&gt;The Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt; series, the &lt;em&gt;Austin Powers&lt;/em&gt; trilogy, the &lt;em&gt;Carry-On&lt;/em&gt; movies all celebrate stupidity yet somehow manage to be clever despite themselves. No one could accuse these caper comedies of delivering the sly wit of Oscar Wilde, but they at least aspire to some measure of winking camp. _Mortdecai is a movie for Adam Sandler fans who lift their pinkies when they sip their Bud. Double-entendres are too high-falootin’ for this crowd. Johanna and Charlie argue about whether you make his mouth look like a vagina, or like the hair above a vagina. A literal running gag involves you making Johanna gag when she gets close to you which in turn engages Charlie’s sympathetic gag reflex. A-List actors saying vagina! And gagging! Trenchant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit it was hard for me to take my eyes off of you. In some scenes it looked as though you were fuller on one side, and then sometimes that side seemed thinner. But I never would have noticed had the droning exposition—often coming from right beneath you—not been delivered so blandly. Most caper comedies understand the need to pepper their expository scenes with sight gags. Nothing brings what should be a fun heist flick to a dead halt like two poorly lit actors sitting opposite each other reading out the plot scenario. Instead, Depp’s ersatz British patois (“Righto, old bean!”), and incessant warblings are supposed to be enough to engage us. After the fifth time, I stopped counting how often I checked my watch. If someone only had two hours to live, I’d recommend watching &lt;em&gt;Mortdecai&lt;/em&gt;. It would feel like an eternity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the vomit scenes, spit-takes and an unnecessary erection visual, &lt;em&gt;Mortdecai&lt;/em&gt; is harmless buffoonery with a couple of bright spots. Paul Bettany as Charlie’s valet, Jock is a slightly kinder, gentler version of the sociopath he played so deliciously in &lt;em&gt;Gangster No. 1&lt;/em&gt;. He seems to know he’s too good for this drivel but mugs gamely anyway. A scene when you are in an elevator with a bunch of L.A. hipsters is decidedly on the nose, and every so often, the script offers up a crackerjack line that made me sad that the rest of the film couldn’t rise up to meet it, even halfway, for more than a minute or two. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could see Depp’s unadorned face more often. I miss the days when he was more enamoured with building strange characters from the inside out, rather than from the outside in. I’m glad, though, that you got second billing in all of &lt;em&gt;Mortdecai&lt;/em&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2015/01/19/what_is_mortdecai_investigating_the_secrecy_behind_johnny_depp_s_latest.html&quot;&gt;confounding promotional material&lt;/a&gt;. You deserve the recognition. Depp may have carried you, but you carried the movie, and it must have been exhausting. Now it’s time for you to relax in the comfort of your home, aka the box that Mr.Potato Head came in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/24/mortdecai.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/24/mortdecai.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Escobar: Paradise Lost</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think you’re good at your job. I really would. As you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0892255/fullcredits?ref_=tt_cl_sm&quot;&gt;already&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0374569/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm&quot;&gt;know&lt;/a&gt;, Benicio Del Toro is known for disappearing into his roles, and portraying real-life drug kingpin Pablo Escobar in &lt;em&gt;Escobar: Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt; must have meant many long hours of research for you. At least, I think it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there’s not a whole lot of your work on display in Andrea Di Stefano’s debut feature film. Even though Escobar’s name is in the title, Di Stefano has instead chosen to focus on the fictionalized love story of a Canadian ex-pat who falls for Escobar’s niece and becomes caught up in the chaos surrounding the final days of the infamous Colombian’s drug empire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nick, Josh Hutcherson continues the long, sad tradition of fictional white characters tasked with helping a white audience acclimate to an unfamiliar foreign world. This decision is a little depressing in that it perpetuates the notion that an audience can only relate to characters that look like them. But it’s made worse by the fact that Hutcherson brings exactly two notes to his performance: lovestruck (happy) and worried (less happy). To be fair, I can’t lay all the fault at his feet, as Di Stefano’s script doesn’t give him much to do beyond that. The theme Di Stefano is trying to establish is one of blind love; a man unwittingly pulled into terrible events. The actual result is character who just seems sort of stupid. While attending a lavish birthday party for Escobar, NIck asks his true love where all the money comes from. She answers simply, cheerfully, “Cocaine!” Hutcherson expresses brief worry, but quickly shifts back to his puppy-love face. Not long after, he tells his brother that Escobar is “not as bad as everyone says.” You start feeling that whatever Hutcherson’s character has coming is his own damn fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a plot structure, that isn’t necessarily a bad thing. If the young lovers burned brightly enough, we’d believe that he’d ignore all the warning signs just to be with her. But it doesn’t. Claudia Traisac, as Nick’s beloved Maria, is about as broadly sketched as he is: pretty and nice and selfless (she works with the poor!). Did I mention pretty? As a screen couple, they do a lot of talking about being in love without ever actually showing it. If Di Stefano wants us to see them as as a drug-era Jack and Rose heading towards a Pablo Escobar-shaped iceberg, he plotted his course all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the idea was that you and Del Toro would create such a magnetic presence in Escobar that everyone, including the audience, would be drawn to him. I can’t say for sure, because little of that ended up onscreen. Like the romance, there’s a lot of talk about how beloved Escobar is – he’s referred to as “Papa Escobar” by the poor – but we don’t get much evidence beyond that. An early speech given by Escobar hints at his charisma, but the camera is more interested in focusing on the dopey white boy scanning the crowd for the sexy Latina. He looks everywhere &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the stage. This scene might as well play as a metaphor for the experience of watching &lt;em&gt;Escobar: Paradise Lost.&lt;/em&gt; Hutcherson is that too-tall concert-goer standing right in front of you, blocking your view of the performer you actually want to see. If he’d just move out of the way, you might enjoy yourself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s s shame, because there’s an early scene that shows how the work you did with Del Toro might have brought the film to life. After Escobar’s birthday party, Nick is paid a late-night visit by the man himself. Escobar is basically feeling him out to see if he’s a worthy suitor for his niece, but in the course of their conversation, the young man mentions some local thugs giving him and his brother a hard time. Silently, Escobar takes a pen out of his pocket and jots a note on his palm. Nothing is said, but we all know it’s bad news for those thugs. It’s a small moment, but it demonstrates, powerfully, the way fates are decided in the smallest of moments. As the talk winds down, Escobar says, “This was good conversation.” He’s right: it’s a genuinely interesting scene. I just wish that when Escobar left the room, the camera had followed him instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/23/escobar-paradise-lost.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/23/escobar-paradise-lost.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Song of the Sea</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;First off, my congratulations to you and the entire production team of &lt;em&gt;Song of the Sea&lt;/em&gt;. It’s been a few years since Tomm Moore’s Academy Award nomination for &lt;em&gt;The Secret of Kells&lt;/em&gt;, and I’m so glad to see him back on the list of nominees for Best Animated Feature. In a field now completely saturated with mind-melting 3D and geeky-cool, I appreciate the occasional return to an elegant, hand-drawn 2D look and a story that is enchantingly simple and sweet. No cheeseburgers flying out of the screen at your head here – just a wee tale of love, loss, and magic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben lives in a lighthouse and spends his days with his dog, Cù. He misses his mother, and loves remembering the stories she used to tell. He has neither the time nor the patience for his adoring little sister, Saoirse, who is painfully cute and has never spoken a word. Neglected by their father, who is still wracked with grief over the loss of his wife, Ben and Saoirse are bundled off to live in the city with their Granny, who takes no guff from anyone. Far away from their home by the sea, Saoirse falls ill. She is revealed to be the last of the Selkies, mysterious half-seal-half-humans of Irish myth. And so Ben must race to save his sister, and other various fairies, witches, and elves kicking around the Irish countryside.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All animated films walk the line between art appreciation and entertainment, usually dipping more towards one or the other. There were moments during the film when I wondered if this one was perhaps more for the grown-ups, given its softer, more meditative pacing compared to – well – fast food flying at one’s head. But the littlest filmgoers in the theatre were drawn right in, all saucer eyes and slack jaws. I think it had something to do with the wonderful use of contrast. I loved the powdery watercolour backgrounds blending together the ‘normal’ world with the world of magical beings. Eye-catching on their own, they are the perfect backdrop to the sharper, more vivid character designs, like that of Granny, who somehow looks wonderfully round and pinched at the same time. The visual contrasts in the artwork complement the thematic contrasts between ancient and present-day, ordinary and magic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much to take away from the film, depending on your outlook. I saw it as a cautionary tale against helicopter parenting and exerting too much control on a child’s behaviour (basically don’t tell your kids to calm down or behave or they will literally shrivel up and turn grey). My companion saw a surprisingly dark tale of grief and emotional repression, and also came away with a sense of guilt over all the times he was ‘a shitty big brother’. The soft pacing and lilting lullaby soundtrack allow for a degree of contemplation you just don’t get with giant 3D ice-cream sundaes, or lemurs who like to move it-move it. I’m a huge fan of the aforementioned lemur, but I could definitely go for more of this sort of quieter, gentler animated offering. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/22/song-of-the-sea.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/22/song-of-the-sea.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Selma</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve had a rough week. Since the 2015 Oscar nominations were announced, you’ve been accused of racism, sexism, and even Lego-ism. It’s enough to make you throw your nine-iron into a sand trap and listen to some Jimmy Buffet to calm down, isn’t it? Sorry, I know not all of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2014/03/oscar-voters-94-white-76-men-and-an-average-of-63-years-old/284163/&quot;&gt;you are old, white men&lt;/a&gt;. Only 76% of you are men, and only 94% of you are white. And on average you’re 63 years old. But to assume you all listen to Jimmy Buffett was mean. I’m sure some of you listen to Coldplay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; ticks off all the boxes on the Oscar-bait Bingo Card. It’s historically significant, features a Great Man righting Great Wrongs, and is full of British actors affecting American accents. There’s even an explosion. But &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is not a spectacle, and the Academy loves spectacle. It loves sweeping sentimentality and chewed scenery, but above all, it loves triumph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is not a triumphant movie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of you are old enough to have firsthand memories of hearing Dr. Martin Luther King Jr deliver his iconic ‘I Have A Dream’ speech. Perhaps you remember seeing footage of Civil Rights activists getting sprayed by fire hoses or being beaten with billy clubs in places like Selma, or Mobile or Birmingham. Witnessing these dramatic highs and lows at such an impressionable age may or may not have influenced how you make and watch movies. But it certainly seems to have influenced the way you judge them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, the bone I have to pick is with specific branches of the Academy – namely the Actor’s branch and the Director’s branch. The entire Academy only votes after all the nominations are made by the specific branches. That vital distinction is missing in a lot of Oscar coverage. The Academy as a whole actually nominated &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;, and its Best Picture nomination is indeed a huge honour, but in this case it feels like a consolation prize. To nominate &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; and overlook the the two people who are overwhelmingly responsible for its distinction as a great film borders on the absurd. But I think I know how this happened. You didn’t snub &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; director Ava DuVernay and its star David Oyelowo because you’re racist or sexist. You snubbed them because you’re restraint-ist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1965, Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and his supporters planned a march from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama in order to secure equal voting rights for African Americans in the South. &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; chronicles the public and private struggles that Dr. King had with President Johnson, Alabama Governor George Wallace, his wife Coretta Scott King, and other leaders and members of the Civil Rights movement leading up to this historic march. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were expecting &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; to be a biopic you must have been confused. We never see MLK as a child, or witness that pivotal moment that defined his life’s work. There is no clever framing device that drives the narrative from flashback to present time. There are no flashbacks. The film deals with a specific and strategic battleground in the Civil Rights struggle, and with MLK’s relationships within that timeline. There is a lot more talking than marching in &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;, but those conversations are fraught with tension. The one device DuVernay employs to great effect are the FBI communiques that tap across the screen like teletype. It’s a reminder that despite the spirit of cooperation that President Johnson publicly extended to MLK, he continued, albeit begrudgingly, to allow Hoover and his men to spy on and attempt to smear the Reverend Doctor’s name and undermine his efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were you disappointed that in their portrayal of MLK, DuVernay and Oyelowo chose not to indulge in hero worship? Or were you hoping that a portrayal of MLK would expose greater flaws and a more profound sense of his humanity? Oyelowo plays a man who is constantly on the brink of failure – in his movement and in his marriage – who must remain calm and composed, not because he wants to, but because he knows it is what’s required of him. This strain is especially palpable in the scenes between him and his wife Coretta (played with painful dignity by Carmen Ejogo). MLK’s transgressions are only hinted at, yet DuVernay’s framing of the shots of husband and wife allow the spaces between them to tell us all we need to know. Oyelowo’s performance of a man who can’t show the incredible pressure he&amp;#39;s under is riveting. It’s exactly the type of complex and nuanced performance that you should reward, but never do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must have been frustrating to expect a capital ‘I’ important film and then realize that it bears none of the hallmarks you typically celebrate. &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; is decidedly matter-of-fact and yet it bursts with emotion. When confronted with scenes of shocking brutality, DuVernay knows exactly when to turn the camera away. She understands the power of moderation and the balance between show and tell. When the heroes claim their prize there is no exultation, no glorious swell of music, no single tear slowly tracing down a humble, black face. Because there is no victory in finally getting something you were owed all along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know others will continue to chide you for your lack of diversity this year, and for choosing to recognize films and performances that predominantly represent the white, male experience. But your inability to see beyond convention is just as disheartening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selma is triumphant only in its restraint. Unfortunately that’s not the kind of triumph the Academy rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Most Violent Year</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;1981 was a year I would like to forget. I was 19, badly dressed, and listening to some of the worst music the Western world has ever created. But thanks to you and director J.C. Chandor—as well as art director Doug Huszti—I now will never be able to erase those stains from my memory. You have etched that year and its sensibilities into my brain forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forgive you that unwanted imposition because &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt; is note perfect in tone. The fidelity of its depiction of a particular period is only one of the things that make this film close to flawless. Choosing Oscar Isaac as the almost impossibly stubborn Small Business Owner/ Protagonist (of an oil distribution company no less), Jessica Chastain as his wife and business partner, and Albert Brooks—in a role originally intended for Stanley Tucci—as their family lawyer was also touched with a quiet genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in New York, it also evokes a period that was formative for me in my love of films. This is the dirty, knockabout New York of &lt;em&gt;The French Connection,&lt;/em&gt; a time before the whole city was castrated by Disney and it adherents. Smoky back rooms filled with a remarkably diverse cast of players, engaged in the some of the most Machiavellian examples of business relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world that these people inhabit is made seamless and utterly believable by the maturity of the script, the nuanced and incredibly competent direction, as well as a cast that never takes a wrong step. It is also a cast that has a Guatemalan/Cuban lead, features an African man as an incorruptible authority figure, and a woman who is not only the equal of her husband in every way but also the spine of their shared business. All of these components simply exist, they are never underlined or trumpeted but are simply part of the tapestry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there is your contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the clothes to the cars to the architecture to the choice of locations, you managed to capture a New York made of rusting steel, wood paneling and slightly ludicrous wardrobes. The tans and washed-out polyester tones, the overly styled hair and nouveau riche sensibilities contrasting with the stripped down aesthetic of an industrial park were pitch perfect. This is a New York in transition, spiritually, economically and demographically. And it is a painful transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been some comparison of this film to Coppola’s &lt;em&gt;Godfather&lt;/em&gt; pictures, largely because of the themes of dynasty and violence that permeate &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt;. But I think a better point of reference is Sidney Lumet. His films so often had as their central theme a struggle between expedience and doing what was right. Think &lt;em&gt;Serpico&lt;/em&gt; or even 1981’s &lt;em&gt;Prince of the City.&lt;/em&gt; Set in this New York with these kind of ethical quandaries at their centre, they were mature, thoughtful films filled with real characters, facing the often mundane complexities of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt; is simply pastiche, but the pedigree is far more Lumet than it is Coppola. There is something distinctly un-operatic and kitchen-sink to this film that makes it more realist than impressionistic. It is a film about people first and then it engages its larger themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you and Chandor decided that, like Japanese artists who create an intentional flaw in their work, you needed to remain humble. That is the only reason I can fathom for the clunky, tacked on nature of the epilogue. It stood out like cotton in a disco and came close to unraveling all you had built. I hope against hope it simply disappears in the DVD version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, this was a film that is otherwise a masterpiece of what I hope cinema is moving towards again—a balance between the tentpole Gotterdammerung of the summer and quietly brilliant character studies like &lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year.&lt;/em&gt; That would be the best of all possible worlds. And I truly appreciate your efforts in trying to make that a real place we can all inhabit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
