<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Housebound</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s astonishing how easy you make it look, man. Blending horror and comedy in a manner that keeps one from overpowering the other is always a tricky feat. Frankly, it&amp;#39;s difficult to think of any recent films that have successfully managed it. That’s why your whip-smart script for &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; is so special—it brings the funny and the scary together beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with your strong handling of the characters. A question that inevitably comes up during the course of a haunted house flick is: &amp;quot;Why don&amp;#39;t they just leave?&amp;quot; Sure, you have your &lt;em&gt;Insidious&lt;/em&gt;es and your &lt;em&gt;Paranormal Activitie&lt;/em&gt;s which explain it away by revealing that the supernatural activity is bound to a person instead of a location. But I quite dig your practical solution: because of the electronic monitoring device around her ankle, petty criminal Kylie is forced to deal with sinister goings-on, lest she violate the terms of her house arrest.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neat and simple. Yet you provide us with a nice about-face later on when Kylie is given an opportunity to escape, only to stay for purely altruistic reasons. The more she learns about the house&amp;#39;s bloody past, as well as a killer who has escaped justice, the more her motivations evolve. She undergoes genuine moments of growth, and doesn’t just make decisions solely to benefit the script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to share a brief thought or two about Amos, the security guard tasked with monitoring our protagonist: you so easily could have made him the stock asshole who scoffs when evidence of the supernatural first rears its head, but his boyish enthusiasm and immediate willingness to help is incredibly charming. He’s yet another great character that elevates this already great movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit back to what I was saying before: it&amp;#39;s impressive how carefully you tread the line between comedic and full-on horror elements. There&amp;#39;s a great bit with dial-up internet, terrific banter between Kylie and Amos, and some outrageously zany gore gags that bring to mind the early work of Peter Jackson. But there is also genuine tension when there needs to be, and we never lose sight of just how high the stakes are for our protagonists. What best exemplifies this balancing of contrasting tones is the climax. It features one of the best extended showdown-with-a-killer sequences I&amp;#39;ve seen in recent memory, it manages to be gut-bustingly funny one second and hand-wringingly intense the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit that I felt a slight twinge of disappointment when the movie shifted gears and the nature of what&amp;#39;s was truly on at the house was cast in a different light. But that speaks more to my personal expectations, and it was certainly a clever and unexpected direction to take the story. It hit some unexpectedly emotional beats as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m guessing you&amp;#39;ve heard the news that &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; is already being optioned for an American remake. It’s so bafflingly unnecessary that I can&amp;#39;t even put it in words (maybe just a series of inarticulate noises). It seems a safe bet that we can save ourselves a little time and write it off as being inferior.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years from now, if &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#39;t mentioned in the same breath as other horror-comedy classics like &lt;em&gt;Dead Alive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Evil Dead II&lt;/em&gt;, than I&amp;#39;ll be sure to eat my hat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/11/housebound.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/11/housebound.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Chappie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When making a big budget, dystopian flick like Neill Blomkamp’s &lt;em&gt;Chappie,&lt;/em&gt; your robots truly matter. How they look and whether or not their appearance reflects the mood you are trying to convey is essential to the film’s success or failure. This is especially true if one of the robots is the title character of the aforementioned multi-million dollar extravaganza. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine if the &lt;em&gt;Terminator&lt;/em&gt; (once it shed it’s Schwarzenegger) looked liked the robot in a Bugs Bunny cartoon. James Cameron would now be directing the line at McDonalds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did a man’s work in helping to develop the visual aesthetic of this particular robot. Chappie is perfectly modulated to allow Sharlto Copley’s motion capture performance to shine through. However, it is a significant problem when a motion capture performance is by far the best part of a film that has a number of actual humans as featured players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chappie—&lt;/em&gt;the film as opposed to the robot—is a godawful mess, narratively as well as conceptually. The casting ranges from poor (Hugh Jackman, paradoxically both wasted and ill-chosen) to ballsy (Die Antwoord’s Ninja and Yolandi Visser) to curiously misused (Sigourney Weaver and Dev Patel).  But they all recede into the background whenever the titular character is on the screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chappie&lt;/em&gt; is both derivative and an homage to several films including &lt;em&gt;Short Circuit,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Robocop&lt;/em&gt; and even makes a more than a cursory nod to Blomkamp’s own &lt;em&gt;District 9&lt;/em&gt;. What it doesn’t do, however, is find its own voice. It lurches wildly in tone from gritty to comic to maudlin to occasionally effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of that is the script. Too often it relies on what seem to be improvisational moments between Chappie and his adoptive parents—Ninja and Visser—as they try to gangsta Chappie up in order to aid them with their comically ineffective schemes. There is a throwaway plot involving Jackman and his rivalry with Patel. Sigourney Weaver, again wasted in a largely throwaway role, plays a weak echo of her Queen Bitch from &lt;em&gt;Working Girl.&lt;/em&gt; At no point in the film do any of these disparate threads cohere in a way that is at all convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single compelling moment comes early on in the film when Chappie is abandoned to the streets of Johannesburg; it is in this sequence that you see most clearly where Blomkamp can create moments of real human pathos. It is a stark, unrelenting five minutes that stayed with me long after the film ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason why this sequence succeeds—where most of the film fails—is because it focuses on Chappie’s awakening to the harsh realities of the world he has been born into. It also works because it is uncluttered by any of the cardboard characters that usually fill Blomkamp’s South African landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copley’s MoCap performance is effective because the robot design evokes a human in form but is still non-specific enough for anyone to identify with—it is the perfect blank slate for the audience to project themselves upon. Chappie also has rudimentary facial expressions that work in ways that are a little surprising, given such a limited palette. He is a creation that deserves, as do you, a far better film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Blomkamp might be better served by adapting other people’s work. Maybe then he could find a way to incorporate the magic you helped him create into a film that compliments that magic—instead of muting it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/10/chappie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/10/chappie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Unfinished Business</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Of all the crew members listed in Ken Scott’s &lt;em&gt;Unfinished Business&lt;/em&gt;, you have the coolest credit. I have no idea what exactly it means, but it has earned you this letter because...well, why the hell not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the film, Dan, Timothy, and Mike have one last chance to save their fledgling mineral sales company. They chase a big client all the way to Berlin for a seal-the-deal handshake, and they need to deliver a presentation that blows away their competition (and former boss). If they don’t, Timothy can’t divorce his wife and Dan can’t send his angsty kids to private school. So there’s a quest. And a ticking clock. But unfortunately there’s no real sense of urgency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I forgot to mention: Dan’s company sells swarf, which is basically manufacturing waste. This film is also &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swarf&quot;&gt;swarf&lt;/a&gt;: probably important to those who need to sell it, but I can’t be arsed to get too enthused. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I usually find the American-in-Europe culture clash set-up very funny. Language barriers, weird food, European permissiveness versus American prudishness—the ingredients are all there. The film sets itself up as a road trip/caper/fish out of water comedy, but doesn’t embrace any of the tropes or conventions that make those subgenres funny. It holds the promise of some potentially hilarious running gags, but none of them pay off. The German GPS bit should have been milked for all it was worth, and, as always, there’s a giant pile of kinky German sex jokes that could have been plundered. But these opportunities are brushed aside in favour of a family/bullying subplot that feels shoehorned in, and endless scenes of the guys “going over the presentation just &lt;em&gt;one more time&lt;/em&gt;.” Their arrival in Berlin coincides with the Folsom Europe festival, a huge marathon, and a G8 summit, but instead we get to watch Dan pore over his slides for the umpteenth time. Which brings me to my next gripe: none of the film’s obstacles are very obstacle-y. I feel like it should take more than a few paint pellets to the torso to sneak into a G8 summit. None of the calamities that befall the protagonists seem to last more than a couple of scenes before being neatly resolved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it feels way too phoned-in. The filmmakers seemed too indifferent for me to care about the exploits (such as they are) of Dan, Timothy, and Mike, or for me to want them to succeed. Maybe if I knew how ‘Master of the Sword’ fit into the endeavour, I might have been more impressed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait, it had something to do with the scene in the bathroom of the leather club, didn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/9/unfinished-business.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/9/unfinished-business.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Second Best Exotic Marigold Hotel</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When you’ve watched films for close to fifty years, you occasionally get to see a performer’s entire career play out in front of you. Sometimes it’s painful (Jon Voight), sometimes it’s funny (Jack Nicholson), and every once in a while it’s a privilege (you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear &lt;em&gt;The Second Best Exotic Marigold Hotel&lt;/em&gt; is hardly the best showcase for your work. A meandering, often incoherent mess, it is a film that lurches from moment to moment without a whole lot of intention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a trifling contrivance about the necessity of obtaining a second hotel (ostensibly to house the incipient hordes of adventurous, elderly British ex-pats of reduced circumstance) to compliment the first hotel, but the title kind of says it all. This is definitely the second best Exotic Marigold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first film—simply titled &lt;em&gt;The Best Exotic Marigold Hotel&lt;/em&gt;—was a clever, engaging piece of entertainment. But in this iteration Dev Patel is carrying far too much narrative weight and screen time for a character that is so thinly drawn. Nor is Patel is good enough to transcend the material. As for most of the rest of the cast—which includes Richard Gere and David Strathairn—they seem happy just to collect their paychecks and wander around Jaipur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when either you, Maggie Smith or Bill Nighy are on screen something truly alchemical happens; lead is in fact turned to gold. It really is magical to see. I think it has something to do with simple professionalism as well as talent. There is never a moment of sloppiness or mugging for the camera. I believe absolutely everything you and you fellow Brits say. And given the thinness of this script, that is high praise indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a glance at your resume is enough to see how varied and challenging your career has been. Those choices also speak to a fundamental strength that many UK actors possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theatre actors, especially Shakespearean theatre actors, cannot take a moment off. That continual awareness is often painfully apparent, especially in contrast with people who turn off the moment the camera pivots away from them. There are several moments throughout &lt;em&gt;The Second Best Exotic Marigold Hotel&lt;/em&gt; when you seem to be acting in an entirely different film than most of the rest of the cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The few scenes where you and Maggie Smith get to share the screen together are particularly worthwhile. Not for any De Niro-Pacino type pyrotechnics but simply for the joy of watching two absolute masters make a silk purse out of a sow’s ear. Perhaps this is one of the reasons the film is so uneven and directionless. It is as if the Director John Madden and screenwriter Ol Parker figured: we’ve got all of these great people together again—what can go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, quite a bit. Since your long-budding romance with Nighy is reduced to an awkward sub-plot and the rest of the film is filled with far lesser lights, I kept bouncing back and forth between being engaged and then utterly disinterested. Not exactly a great rhythm. This is a film you watch on a lazy Sunday, not something you spend money and time going to a theatre to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perverse way you, Maggie Smith and Nighy made this film worse, simply by showing how much better it may have been had you all featured more prominently. In particular your performance was a pointed reminder of why you have endured and flourished—while lesser lights have long since faded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for a lifetime of beautiful poetry, Dame Judi. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/8/the-second-best-exotic-marigold-hotel.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/8/the-second-best-exotic-marigold-hotel.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Valley Below</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Drumheller is a tourist trap town in the middle of the Alberta badlands, guarded by the “World’s Largest Dinosaur” and a giant plaster Jesus. It already &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like a movie set—just not the droll, Tim Burton type. In &lt;em&gt;The Valley Below&lt;/em&gt;, you managed to capture the suffocating timelessness of Drumheller – with its dusty, old-timey main street and desolate highway stretches and strip malls – and turn it into a place from a Larry McMurtry novel, where the inhabitants are restless and stuck. Even the colourful fibreglass dinosaurs dotting the town seem forlorn. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Valley Below&lt;/em&gt; follows four loosely connected characters over the course of a year: Kate, a pregnant teen about to go to university; Warren, an alcoholic Zamboni driver and songwriter; Kate’s dad Gordon, a taxidermist trying to save his marriage; and Barry, a cop and local radio DJ with a sensitive streak. The world these characters inhabit is one of breathtaking vistas and desolate futures. It’s a place literally surrounded by skeletons. It’s the kind of world that is easy to get wrong—or, worse, to accidentally condescend to. Thankfully, your unpretentious art direction and design manages to avoid hollow imitation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writer/Director/Producer Kyle Thomas understands this world. The assured, natural performances serve the spare style beautifully. There is an unaffectedness here that is rare for a Canadian film. None of it reeks of try-too-hard. Just like your modest design, which is always present, yet never obvious. When Kate picks up her goofy boyfriend on the morning after a house party, we see a pig’s head floating in a kiddy pool on the front lawn. Warren’s bungalow is strewn with just enough empty bottles and dirty dishes to make it seem like it wasn’t set-decorated. You’ve &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; to that house party. You’ve &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; to that bungalow. You know these people. But more importantly, &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; know these people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You filled Gordon’s small workshop with every manner of awls, furs, and tools. Before he begins assembling a deer’s head trophy, he takes off his wedding ring and hangs it on a pair of antlers behind him. It’s a small, thoughtful action that tells us volumes about this man and his situation. As he works at making the deer look as lifelike as possible - stitching the fur and choosing from a selection of glass eyes - we realize he’s done the same with his seemingly perfect marriage. Barry has a model train set in his basement that resembles a miniature Drumheller: plastic Jesus, dinos, and all. It’s more than just a symbol of how he watches over his town. It’s a metaphor about perspective. The town may be small, but it is dwarfed by the character’s desires. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overlapping nature of the narrative structure never feels contrived the way most multi-narrative films often do. Thomas holds shots for exactly the right time, only lingering when it serves the story. His edits are confident and deliberate. There is a hint of Altman’s &lt;em&gt;Nashville&lt;/em&gt; in his method, both in the music and in the film’s episodic nature. There are shades of Alexander Payne’s &lt;em&gt;Nebraska&lt;/em&gt; in your visual style, from the depressing motel rooms, to the dark and desperate taverns. Somewhere in between, you found the Drumheller of &lt;em&gt;The Valley Below&lt;/em&gt;, a place that is ageless yet eerily recognizable. A place where nothing – and everything – happens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for letting this tourist hang with the locals for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/6/the-valley-below.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/6/the-valley-below.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Revolution is Upon Us</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Not so long ago you could always tell the difference between a movie made in Hollywood and just about anywhere else. It was like they carried a watermark. No matter how banal the content, how utterly derivative the plot, how wooden the acting, the one thing you could pretty much say about any studio film made in Hollywood was that they looked really good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was because Hollywood had accumulated, over the course of several decades, an almost complete monopoly on the mechanics of film production. It wasn’t just about huge budgets, it was about support infrastructure, technical know how and the means of production: cinematography, editing, sound production and even sound stages, color separation, film processing and finally distribution networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To match that kind of out of the gate firepower would require the resources of a national government. So, with a few exceptions, most films that were produced outside of Hollywood were, whatever their latent artistic qualities, working at a huge disadvantage. They just weren’t as shiny as what Hollywood was pounding out year after year. To compete on the world stage required both money and technical resources that were inordinately concentrated in the southern end of the State of California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And listening to the some of the doomsayers from the last awards season you would think almost nothing has changed over the last twenty years. Just lately there has been a constant lament amongst many in the industry about how the death of small and medium budget films made for people over twenty-five is upon us. That we were doomed to two binary choices—artistically ambitious but technically constrained micro-budget films (a kind of perpetual dogme 95, not by choice but by necessity) and a never-ending barrage of Hollywood summer bombast, beginning in March and ending sometime in late October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t seem to be the case at all, as it turns out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filmmaking has quietly entered a renaissance of unequalled quality and diversity. Independently produced movies have never been more interesting, beautiful, varied, and accessible. The voices that are being heard are more distinct in ethnicity, as well as class and geography, even gender, than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even a partial list of non-Hollywood films from just the last year: &lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/4/leviathan.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leviathan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Timbuktu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/9/ida.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under The Skin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Girlhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Force Majeure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/2/a-girl-walks-home-alone-at-night.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as independently produced North American films like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;NightCrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Most Violent Year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; or straight up entertainments like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; put lie to the idea that small to medium budget films of exceptional quality are somehow disappearing from the landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filmmakers themselves are Korean, Mauritanian, Russian, Iranian, British, French, men, women, and transgendered, outsiders, neophytes, mavericks, political radicals and absolutely beholden to no one. And you know what the best part is? We all can see these films pretty much at the click of a mouse and for a couple of bucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point is often lost in the mountains of snark generated by people who often have, at most, a passing familiarity with any film that isn’t on a constant loop in their feeds. And the declinists in the room—with their moaning about how films for adults are so vanishingly rare—expose themselves for the culturally myopic whiners and curmudgeons that they are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem for them seems to be that the center of gravity for this renaissance isn’t located in Southern California. It isn’t even on the North American continent. If you had to assign a geographic ground zero it would probably be somewhere in North Africa, or perhaps Eastern Europe, depending on the particular year. And from people who often mouth platitudes about diversity and the Hollywood monoculture I too often hear the words: ‘I haven’t seen that yet’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that a lack of access was a pretty valid defense. If Hollywood didn’t pay it didn’t play but that is a red herring at this point in the game. If you’re not seeing the diversity in film that you would like to, you probably aren’t looking very hard. Just off of the top of my head, some of the most interesting films from last year were from women directors: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Babadook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Girlhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Beyond the Lights&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone at Night&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/21/selma.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And finding these films usually requires less work than making a sandwich. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single greatest thing about the technological change that has occurred around filmmaking in the last twenty-five years is simply this: the means of production are now firmly in the hands of the content creators. Hollywood’s monopoly on production is broken and the grip it currently still enjoys on distribution is soon to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it isn’t much of a stretch these days to find all kinds of films for all sorts of tastes. More to the point, most of the cinema being produced outside of Hollywood isn’t what used to be considered art house fare: with their low budget productions and often impenetrable and esoteric narratives. And if you were lucky you might find these rare gems playing on one screen in NYC at 12:00 AM on a Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, for me to see &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt;—the Academy Award winner for best foreign language film—I had to open up iTunes on my computer and pay $5.99.  To see &lt;em&gt;Timbuktu&lt;/em&gt; I had to walk a few blocks to TIFF and see one of the most beautiful and unsettling films I have ever experienced up on a big screen—but I have no doubt that it will be available on any number of legitimate venues in the near future, as well as old school DVD and Blu-Ray. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days the strength of much of non-Hollywood film is in its middlebrow aesthetic and its capacity to speak coherently to mass audiences while managing to avoid simply existing as product. Timbuktu is set in a foreign land that few North Americans would recognize yet it is perfectly comprehensible to even my wretchedly tarnished sensibilities—as well as beautifully shot and conventional in its narrative arcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, I tend to think this can be nothing but good for Hollywood itself. Challenged and often aesthetically overtaken these days, it will be interesting to see how the Monolith responds. My money is on a resurgence of the kind of dynamic filmmaking the major studios haven’t had much to do with since the mid to late seventies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t always a curse, as it turns out, to live in interesting times.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/4/the-revolution-is-upon-us.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/4/the-revolution-is-upon-us.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;While on the surface &lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night&lt;/em&gt; is a vampire story, it seems far more interested in conveying atmosphere and emotion than it does in giving us a traditional narrative experience, and you set up a wonderful shot near the halfway mark of the film that perfectly encapsulates this mission statement. In a completely dialogue free scene, the titular &lt;em&gt;Girl&lt;/em&gt; stands facing away from co-lead Arash as he approaches, then ever-so-slowly turns around and relaxes her head against his chest. It&amp;#39;s a lovely bit of visual storytelling, and says so much more about these characters and what they&amp;#39;re feeling than words could. This one shot makes it perfectly clear that this is a movie about two lonely people finding a connection, however improbable it may be.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have taken the easy route and lent this a film a drab visual style to mirror the despair of living in Bad City, a heavily industrialized wasteland whose residents enjoy varying states of isolation and suffering, choosing either to slip into drug abuse or seek companionship from the wrong sort of people. Though it must be said that the movie isn&amp;#39;t nearly as heavy as all that; it certainly never exploits its characters. Instead, your evocative black-and-white cinematography makes even the mundane and ugly appear beautiful. Which is quite an achievement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curiously absent are the visceral thrills typically associated with this type of genre picture; outside of dispatching one of Bad City&amp;#39;s more loathsome inhabitants, writer/director Ana-Lily Amirpour doesn’t rely on violence to give her story momentum, which, in an age when cinematic thrills come cheaper than ever, is a classy decision that reflects an intent to make &lt;em&gt;Girl&lt;/em&gt; more of a mood piece than a full on horror film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coupled with ingenious costume design that has the Girl&amp;#39;s chador double as both traditional garb and billowing cloak, you work wonders when it comes to lending The Girl a screen presence that feels truly unique and iconic.  Whether it’s a hooded figure slipping in and out of the city&amp;#39;s all-encompassing shadows while stalking her prey, or, in what might be my favourite shot in the film, riding a skateboard down the street with the edges of her chador billowing around her like  a bat’s wings.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I&amp;#39;d be remiss without mentioning how agreeable your camera finds lead actress Sheila Vand. Her remarkable performance runs the gambit from palpable vulnerability to great savagery. She promises to inflict grave harm upon a child if he were to ever stop being a &amp;quot;good little boy&amp;quot;—and we believe her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breathing a new life into a stale sub-genre, &lt;em&gt;A Girl Walks Home Alone At Night&lt;/em&gt; is being sold as &amp;quot;the first Iranian vampire-western.”  Here&amp;#39;s hoping it won&amp;#39;t be the last.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/2/a-girl-walks-home-alone-at-night.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/2/a-girl-walks-home-alone-at-night.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Focus</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Do you think the &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; production office sent out a secret call sheet on the day you arrived on set reminding the cast and crew to leave their valuables at home? You call yourself a “gentleman thief,” but one can never be too careful. A con artist must cultivate a certain kind of sociopathic charm in order to be successful; a talent for knowing what people secretly want and then giving it to them—or at least delivering the illusion. Pickpocketing, it seems, requires a different set of skills: the ability to blend in, to be simultaneously seen and not seen. You came to fame by pickpocketing President Jimmy Carter’s Secret Service agents, relieving them of the keys to his motorcade. You must have talked a pretty good game, because instead of ending up behind bars, you became a consultant for law enforcement and security agencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that 
the Secret Service and the makers of &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; can agree on at least one thing; clever and charming criminals are a lot of fun to be around. At least for a while. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot of &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; is typically convoluted: veteran con-man Nicky takes neophyte pickpocket Jess under his wing for a multi-million dollar operation during the Super Bowl in New Orleans. Three years later, after hearts and trust have been broken, they meet again in Buenos Aires where Nicky is helping a billionaire Formula One race-car team owner (and Jess’ new boyfriend) cheat his way to a win. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After meeting-cute in a failed “jealous husband” scam, Jess begs Nicky to show her some of his tricks (which are actually yours). As he casually chats with her about the art of pickpocketing, he relieves her of various belongings – a ring, a watch, a wallet – and returns them to her while she watches, dumbfounded. He tells her that the trick is in diverting a mark’s focus, making them see what they want to see. &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; takes this advice to heart. Con/Heist films are best when they (a) don’t take themselves too seriously, and (b) give the audience lots of beautiful things and people to pay attention to. Will Smith’s Nicky is all brooding suaveness in dark bespoke suits, and Margot Robbie’s Jess pops like bubblegum with bright pink dresses and wide-eyed enthusiasm. Their chemistry is palpable, their romance inevitable, but we’re always anticipating the bait and switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve given TED talks on the science behind awareness manipulation and why we’re psychologically wired to want to believe what we see. The pickpocket design you delivered for &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; – specifically the one protracted scene in New Orleans – is certainly exciting to watch. As Nicky’s team introduces Jess to their system, the camera follows a series of expertly executed lifts and boosts as it skims through a crowd of revelers gathered in the streets. Post-scam, the loot is displayed in a satisfying sequence reminiscent of that ode to excess, &lt;em&gt;Lifestyles of the Rich and Famous&lt;/em&gt;: hundreds of Piagets and Rolexes, jeweled rings and necklaces, and piles of money laid out in velvet lined cases. A high-stakes gambling scam during the Super Bowl involving the goofily creeptastic B.D. Wong is particularly nerve-wracking. This pace is exhilarating. But, unfortunately, isn’t sustained throughout this otherwise perfectly fun and funny con-man flick. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the film changes locales to Buenos Aires, it loses some of its lustre, despite the dizzyingly sumptuous backdrop of brightly coloured cars, buildings, and women. It’s only a matter of time before alliances are broken and double-crosses are double-crossed. Up until now, the film could have lifted whatever it wanted from my purse, but, by the end, with only the obvious love story left to hold our attention, my focus was wandering. With some hilarious supporting performances by Gerald McRaney, Adrian Martinez, and the aforementioned Wong, &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt; does it’s best to divert our attention from its barely-better-than-average plot twists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left feeling like many of the audience members you’ve amused with your theatrical pickpocketing: it was a harmless good time, and I didn’t mind feeling a little bit cheated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/1/focus.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/1/focus.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Tale Of Princess Kaguya</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It must be a thankless task to try and translate a work so thoroughly drenched in the folklore of a specific culture; because no matter how well you perform, something will be inevitably lost. There is no way to transmit the fundamental conceits that underpin the whole of the narrative. To do that would require a lifetime of work for both you and the audience. However, even if what you managed is a lesser work than the original, it still shines very brightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Tale Of Princess Kaguya,&lt;/em&gt; an animated film from Studio Ghibli, is a beautiful, meandering film. Like much of traditional Japanese cinema, it is least troubled with pacing and plot. Tone and mood are the primary concerns here. The animation is loose and seemingly naturalistic, the score is haunting and subtle and the dialogue is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inherently pastoral film &lt;em&gt;The Tale of Princess Kaguya&lt;/em&gt; expresses a love of nature and a thoughtful examination of the cycles of birth and death. The sometimes misguided aspirations that parents force on their children is also one of the central themes, as well as a lot of gentle nudging about greed and social posturing and the often ridiculous pomp that props up rigidly defined class systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choices that director Isao Takahata makes (he also directed &lt;em&gt;Grave of the Fireflies&lt;/em&gt;, one of the most appallingly effective anti-war films I have ever seen) to tell a story so filled with myth and the supernatural are at the heart of its effectiveness. Compared to almost any animated film these days &lt;em&gt;The Tale Of Princess Kaguya&lt;/em&gt; is noteworthy for it’s complete lack of visual pyrotechnics. This is a simple story told simply. The magic is in how that becomes so affecting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole film is less a fable and more a series of metaphoric observations about some pretty universal concerns. What is truly valuable in life? Is it possible to be yourself as a young person and not disappoint your parents? Mostly though there is no lesson other than we are all variable creatures with many flaws and some strengths. Life is often filled with meaningless obligation and trivial strife so the moments of joy are inevitably tinged with melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that seems trite it is only because I am failing in the translation. How the film evokes these sweeping, universal themes is earthy and quiet and utterly lacking in pretension. There is both a quiet joy and a pervasive sadness that every frame of this film somehow transmits. Part of this comes from the animation. The figures are simple and expressive and move with grace and elegance (except when they shouldn’t). The background art is exquisite, seamlessly reinforcing or contrasting whatever is happening in the foreground without drawing attention to itself. That it seems hand drawn is not just a stubborn adherence to tradition but a calculated, aesthetic choice that underlines the rustic slant of the whole project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Tale Of Princess Kaguya&lt;/em&gt; is an art house film in the best sense of the word. It requires engagement on the part of the audience and the capacity to let go of your preconceptions about what a story is and how it can be told, but it rewards those efforts with a film that was truly beautiful and moving. Long-winded and meandering in a very Japanese way, the payoff is nonetheless extraordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite what must be countless moments that simply don’t line up with my Western sensibilities and background this film and your translation of it connected with something fundamental in me. Studio Ghibli is perhaps the single most able advocate of a kind of honest reverence for the natural world that I can think of, and you captured that reverence beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/26/the-tale-of-princess-kaguya.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/26/the-tale-of-princess-kaguya.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The DUFF</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed since I was in high school. Back in 2000, my “unique” ability to use editing software packed a real punch to my student campaign videos. With the help of a few spinning graphics – KAPOW! I was Batman. I even had a Robin: that slightly awkward friend recruited to make me seem cool. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, a DUFF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term isn’t mainstream and probably never will be. As an acronym (Designated Ugly Fat Friend), it’s far too front-and-center in all the film’s marketing to ever gain true cultural traction (or a pornographic sub-genre) the way MILF did after &lt;em&gt;American Pie&lt;/em&gt;. But damn if you and the filmmakers don’t try. Through playful graphics, you literally spell out the word (and countless other things) for people throughout the film. Everything is given the early iMovie treatment, with tweets, texts, and imaginary fireworks splashed all over the screen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder I dug it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mae Whitman also helps, completely owning her starring role as the sub-sexy, totally approachable, literal girl-next-door. Her chiseled neighbour, played by Robbie Amell, is a jackass jock and childhood friend who gets recruited to give her the &lt;em&gt;She’s All That&lt;/em&gt; hair-shake transformation. The story and stock characters continue to evoke every teen comedy ever made since the 80s, right up to the advertising that tells us &lt;em&gt;The DUFF&lt;/em&gt; is this generation’s &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; (as your graphics stress). And yeah, it might be. Not by redefining anything, but simply by being funny, confident, and accessible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the DUFF of teen movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in a world where geeks and geek-culture &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;does rule the world, that’s not an insult. The more Whitman’s character gets humiliated throughout the film, the more we love her. The “attack ad” videos created by the resident school hottie are complete with auto-tuning and slow-motion – the special sauce of many embarrassment-enhancing viral videos. But it’s the moments when the film doesn’t try to be era-specific that really work. We know exactly where everything is going (the prom), what’s going to happen (a big kiss), and who’s going to end up with who (duh), but be damned if I wasn’t rooting for it all to happen anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flare you added was nice, but it’s not what makes the film shine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/25/the-duff.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/25/the-duff.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
