<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Action Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-action.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Action Fans, <br />
  				<p>For us, the action is the juice. And this video is JUICY! </p>

<p>Maybe we’re high on all the gunfire and roundhouse kicks, but this feels like the best video yet in our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>. Every movie just rocks. But enough talk, time for action!</p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yJxODCQkOqs?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. It also made for some heated debates, which only barely avoided becoming all-out fights.</p>

<p>(Don’t worry. Cooler heads prevailed. Even if that goes against the spirit of the genre.)</p>

<p>So here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. For the first time ever we included some of these in the video itself. But here’s some more detail:</p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM ACTION A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-action/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 2000s</strong><br />
        The Bourne trilogy, Daniel Craig’s James Bond, Ip Man… fucking IP MAN! It was a good decade for sure, but Q, V, and X also won with virtually no competition. The most impressive decade was the 80s thanks to Hong Kong. And the 90s were shockingly under-represented.  
      </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-action/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: F</strong><br />
          Holy F! Not only are there a lot of options for this letter, with the entire Fast &amp; Furious franchise, but you’ve got a great variety of options: from classic action-thrillers like <em>The French Connection</em> and <em>The Fugitive</em>, to beloved shoot-em-ups like <em>Face/Off</em> and <em>First Blood</em>, to one one of the best Bond movies - <em>From Russia With Love</em>. But in the end, peak Fast and Furious - <em>Fast 5</em> - won this quarter mile.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-action/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>Mission: Impossible</em> - all of them</strong><br />
        What a crime that all six Mission: Impossible movies were up against <em>Mad Mad Fury Road</em>. Picking one M:I film would have been its own major challenge (probably the original or <em>Ghost Protocol</em>, right?), but I guess we were spared that agony. Still, it feels like the franchise got cheated. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-action/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Eastern Condors</em> vs <em>Enter the Dragon</em></strong><br />
    If you think Bruce Lee should be on this list, go rewatch those movies and put the action up against any of his Hong Kong contemporaries. Hell, just watch the fight with Sammo Hung in <em>Enter the Dragon</em> and then ANY action scene with Sammo Hung in <em>Eastern Condors</em> to prove the point. More proof that a little body fat is actually a <em>good</em> thing.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-action/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>North by Northwest</em></strong><br />
         When you search “action” movies on Wikipedia, they don’t even bother listing anything before the 1960s. But <em>North by Northwest</em> is a type of proto-action movie that helped define what the genre would become. Also, how fun is the transition we did from Fury Road into this film? Come on! 
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/5/10/a-z-action.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/5/10/a-z-action.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Rom-Com Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-rom-com.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Rom-Com  Fans, <br />
  				<p>We’re just some boys, posting in front of some girls, asking them (and everyone else!) to love our choices. </p>

<p>As we continued our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, we couldn&#39;t neglect Romantic Comedies. This video, along with Musicals, is being posted on their MsMojo page, which we hope is a match made in heaven. Enjoy.</p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IG3DsMNeAhs?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. We also strived for balance. Hence why Julia Roberts only has a couple movies on the list - and why there’s only one Tom Hanks/Meg Ryan selection. We threw Drew Barrymore a bone instead of going with <em>Notting Hill</em> – so sue us! </p>

<p>Anyway, here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM ROM-COM A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-rom-com/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1990s</strong><br />
        Rom Coms had a huge resurgence in the 90s, minting new movie stars left-right-and-center in a time when even <em>Runaway Bride</em> could run away with over $300 million at the box office (for a middling Julia Roberts film). Oh, how times have changed. We did, however, still manage to pull a lot of great picks from the 00s, and even some from the last few years with big hit movies that have made the genre refreshingly less bridal white. Nothing from the 60s though, and the summer of love. Go figure.  
      </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-rom-com/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: S</strong><br />
          <em>Sleepless in Seattle</em> is not only a huge film for Nora Efron, but for the genre as a whole. It cemented Tom Hanks and Meg Ryan as America’s sweetheart couple (though it didn’t introduce us to them - don’t forget about <em>Joe vs the Volcano</em>!), and Hanks also made the fantasy classic <em>Splash!</em> a decade earlier. Then there’s the proto Rom Com film <em>The Shop Around the Corner</em>, later remade as <em>You’ve Got Mail</em>. We could also add Cameron Crowe’s <em>Say Anything</em> as a contender. So because we had most of those stories and stars covered in Y, we went with the impossible-to-hate pairing of Bradley Cooper and Jennier Lawrence. An Oscar win and that many noms for a Rom Com is hard to ignore, too. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-rom-com/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>Enchanted</em></strong><br />
        We’re going to go out on a limb and guess that <em>Enchanted</em> has a lot more fans than <em>Enough Said</em>. Well, you’re in luck! <em>Enchanted</em> made our best Musicals video, so we opted for a bit of an adult alternative for this one. Also, Julia Louis-Dreyfuss. Enough said.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-rom-com/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Moonstruck</em> vs <em>My Best Friend’s Wedding</em></strong><br />
        <em>Moonstruck</em> doesn’t seem to have the fan legacy as <em>My Best Friend’s Wedding</em>, but it certainly has a more impressive resume. Three Oscar wins, another three nominations (including Best Picture and Best Director), and it arguably re-ignited the whole new Rom Com wave even before <em>When Harry Met Sally</em>. But peak Julia Roberts is something to behold, so we said a little prayer for you and went with a fan favourite. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-rom-com/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Think Like a Man</em></strong><br />
         The big loser for this letter is <em>There’s Something About Mary</em>, but that movie feels a little more at home in the gross-out comedy genre, even if there’s no denying its bonafides as a Rom Com. So instead, we wanted to highlight a movie that was a huge hit and reminded Hollywood that a diverse cast could sell tickets and sexy jokes. And just look at that cast - damn! 
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/5/4/a-z-rom-com.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/5/4/a-z-rom-com.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Musical Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-musical.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Musical Fans, <br />
  				<p>Get ready to either sing our praises, or start singing the blues. </p>

<p>As we continued our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, we had to do a Musical video. It’s being posted on their MsMojo page, where we hope to get a standing ovation for our choices. Enjoy. </p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tZSH0NASKRE?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. And it’s also worth remembering that these are best <em>movie</em> musicals, not broadway musicals. So lackluster adaptations into the new medium won’t make the grade (sorry, <em>Rent</em>). </p>

<p>Anyway, here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM MUSICAL A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-musical/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1970s</strong><br />
        When you think Musicals, you probably think of the golden age of Hollywood, which pretty much died in the late 60s. And yet, the musical lived on - dare we say thrived - through the counterculture era of the 70s. It certainly had a revival in the 2000s after nearly going extinct in the 90s, and still manages to put out big hits every year today. 
      </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-musical/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: M</strong><br />
          You’ve got <em>My Fair Lady,</em> which won eight Oscars. <em>Mama Mia!</em>, the most successful musical movie of all-time. <em>Les Misérables</em>, which was a huge critical and commercial hit of the most beloved broadway musical of all-time. And then there’s Moulin Rouge, which single-handedly revived the entire Musical genre in the 90s. But in the end, there’s just no toppin’ Poppins. Hopefully a spoonful of sugar will help that medicine go down. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-musical/cheated-in.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED IN: <em>Quartet</em></strong><br />
        Initially, qwe had The Who’s <em>Quadrophenia</em> here. Perfect, we thought! Then we actually watched it… and it’s not a musical. It’s based on an album by The Who, and only later got turned into a musical. So we emergency switched in <em>Quartet</em>. Which is about music and features singing, but not exactly in the spirit of a true musical (we know).
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-musical/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>West Side Story</em> vs <em>The Wizard of Oz</em></strong><br />
        Two titans of the genre. And if you’re voting for the best movie, you’re going with <em>The Wizard of Oz</em>. But for the best musical movie… we snapped our fingers and went to the other (possibly wrong) side of the tracks. It’s just too influential of a musical movie not to make the list. And we have another video coming soon that Dorothy will land in, not to worry.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-musical/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Purple Rain</em></strong><br />
         The only other real option here was <em>Pennies From Heaven</em>. That might fit the mold a bit more cleanly of a true musical, but we aren’t being purists with the inclusion of Quartet anyway. And let’s be honest, we can all use a little more Prince in our lives. Always. 
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/27/a-z-musical.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/27/a-z-musical.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Superhero Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-superhero.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Superhero Fans, <br />
  				<p>Not all heroes wear capes. But in this case, it definitely helps. </p>

<p>As you’ll see, we wanted to include superheroes in our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>. But pulling it off required some creativity. Did we save your favourite movie?  </p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2CYaxeY3Sgw?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>As you see, we played by the same set of rules as all the other videos:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>In this case, that last point meant not making this video an unofficial extension of the Marvel Cinematic Universe. So not every Avenger made the cut, especially when there was a solid alternative. </p>

<p>The bigger question here was what makes something a superhero movie? We didn’t create hard-and-fast rules like we did for sci-fi. But it’s safe to say these films all at least take place in a “superhero” world, even if the hero isn’t the protagonist. </p>

<p>Now here’s what we learned, and why we ultimately decided to make a couple jokes rather than actually cheat. </p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM SUPERHERO A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-superhero/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 2010s</strong><br />
        Obviously. Half the movies in this video are from the last 10 years. The oldest movie on here is from 1989. You’re welcome, Internet. </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-superhero/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: B</strong><br />
          <em>Black Panther</em> fans probably have a right to be mad. The movie was nominated for Best Picture and is the highest grossing solo superhero film. Not to mention what it means to have a black superhero. Which also made it hard for <em>Blade 2</em> to compete. In the end, we went with another man in black, because you can’t deny what Tim Burton’s original movie did for the genre.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-superhero/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>The New Mutants</em></strong><br />
        Thanks to COVID-19, we haven’t had a chance to see <em>The New Mutants</em> yet. So <em>No Ordinary Hero</em> wins on a technicality. A big technicality. <em>No Ordinary Hero</em> is technically about superheroes, but not a “real” superhero. It’s about a <em>real</em> superhero. Or at least a guy who plays a superhero on TV but then has to become one, of sorts. Anyway, take your victory lap <em>No Ordinary Hero</em>! We could have done a third freeze-frame with the wrong <em>Nightcrawler</em>, but if there was a movie that qualified, we had to use it.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-superhero/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Spider-Man 2</em> vs <em>Superman</em></strong><br />
        I mean, we know who would win in a real fight, but when it comes to movies? Damn, it was close. Having a movie from the 70s sure would have felt good - especially something as beloved as the original <em>Superman</em>. But no Spidey?? We couldn’t do it. And Ebert agreed Spider-Man was the best superhero movie of all-time, so there. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-superhero/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Joker</em></strong><br />
         Don’t get up our asses and say that <em>Joker</em> isn’t really a superhero movie. It’s the story of a villain in a superhero world. And considering the competition - <em>Justice League</em> and <em>Jonah Hex</em> - any arguments against <em>Joker</em> are going to feel pretty petty. But go ahead, we’re ready for it.
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/26/a-z-superhero.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/26/a-z-superhero.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Sci-fi Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-sci-fi.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Sci-Fi Fans, <br />
  				<p>We’re hoping the hardcore among you will come to our rescue when people see what we’ve done to this list.</p>

<p>This instalment of the <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a> includes ground rules for what we call “sci-fi”. We’re taking the “science” term more literally than some, trying to seperate space fantasy from true visions of the future, or science run amok. Take a look, and let’s talk. </p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_v4ZiuN7BeU?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>As you see, we had two sets of rules this time. One that applies to all videos:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>And one that’s unique to defining the genre of Sci-Fi:</p>

<ol>
<li>Humans come from Earth</li>
<li>Earth-based monsters are created by scientists</li>
<li>No ghosts or magic</li>
</ol>

<p>Why did we do it? Well, for one, we have a lot of videos coming out. Tomorrow is Superheroes, and so we didn’t want to deal with Marvel movies in this one. And by actually defining sci-fi, <em>Star Wars</em> became a casualty. An even worse “offender” of hardcore sci-fi rules, in some cases. Most humans in Marvel movies are from earth, but not all. Earth doesn’t even exist in <em>Star Wars</em>. The next rule helps us differentiate between Frankenstein and Dracula, or King Kong and (the original) Godzilla. There are important distinctions that give those characters different meanings, even if they can lazily all be called “monsters”. And the last rule basically takes us away from the supernatural, even when science is involved (sorry,<em>Ghostbusters</em>). But also, it reinforces why the Star Wars universe (with the force) and Marvel movies (with mystics) aren’t truly sci-fi films.</p>

<p>Got it? Good! Now here’s some take-aways from the rest of our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission.</p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM SCI-FI A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-sci-fi/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1980s</strong><br />
        A little surprising, but that’s definitely the way it shook out. New technology introduced in the 70s definitely gave the genre increased legitimacy, leading to a lot of classic films that still set the gold standard today - from visionary epics (<em>Blade Runner</em>), to beloved family films (<em>E.T.</em> and <em>Honey, I Shrunk the Kids</em>), to critical darlings (<em>The Fly</em>) and franchise peaks (_Star Trek II_… and, just for good measure, consider that other franchise peak that didn’t qualify).
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-sci-fi/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: C</strong><br />
          K was actually the hardest for the wrong reasons (<em>horrible</em> options), but in terms of being spoiled with choice, C was probably the biggest doozy. We actually jumped on board pretty quick once we agreed <em>A Clockwork Orange</em> qualified, but it came at the expense of <em>Close Encounters of the Third Kind</em>, <em>Contact</em>, <em>Children of Men</em>, <em>Cube</em>... all movies more readily considered classic sci-fi. But we cut Kubrick from horror, and <em>2001: A Space Odyssey</em> doesn’t start with a letter, so be damned if we were going to deny him here. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-sci-fi/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>The Road Warrior</em></strong><br />
         Obviously we should say <em>Star Wars</em> was the real movie cheated out (or <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em>), but we explained that choice earlier. For <em>Mad Max 2:</em> <em>The Road Warrior</em>, we first debated if it would be M or R, since the movie was first released in the U.S. simply as <em>The Road Warrior</em>. If we went with R (where we were leaning), it was up against another cult classic from the same era. But we ultimately plan to represent the Mad Max series in another genre, so when that video eventually comes, we will finally sleep at night. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-sci-fi/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Alien</em> vs <em>Aliens</em></strong><br />
        We did this to ourselves. Had we used <em>Alien</em> in horror, we could have put <em>Aliens</em> in sci-fi and called it a day. But we didn’t, and it has been ripping us from the inside out ever since. We’ll find a way to make-good with a future video. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-sci-fi/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Honey, I Shrunk the Kids</em></strong><br />
         Most serious critics would have gone with <em>Her</em> here, but not us. No sir. We took a stand against all those depressed and depraved visions of technology to reflect the good, clean fun you can have with the genre. 
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/25/a-z-sci-fi.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/25/a-z-sci-fi.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Crime Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-crime.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Crime Fans, <br />
  				<p>It may not have the same rabid following as Horror, Sci-Fi and Animation, but the crime genre does have one thing going for it - some of the best movies ever made. </p>

<p>In doing this <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, it would have been a crime to skip the genre responsible for so much incredible and important cinema. Some movies ended up getting whacked we would have never expected, but you can’t go against the family - or the rules of the alphabet. Enjoy. </p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F_P3LFGi47U?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. We also, as always, strived for balance when it came down to a pissing contest over what film was the “best”.</p>

<p>So here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM CRIME A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-crime/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1990s</strong><br />
        Your gut probably tells you it will be the 70s. Based on this list, it’s almost the 50s. But in the end the 90s proved the most prolific decade for greatest crime movies. And it’s not like they claimed easy letters. We dare you to disagree with any of those 90s spots.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-crime/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: T</strong><br />
          <em>Taxi Driver</em> is not on this list. Neither is <em>Touch of Evil</em>. Nor <em>Traffic.</em> Scorsese got M instead (taking it away from <em>The Maltese Falcon</em>, <em>Memento,</em> and even Fritz Lang’s <em>M</em>) since he really couldn’t expect to take G - even if <em>Goodfellas</em> is hellagood. It’s a deal with the devil, but we played by eye-for-an-eye rules (or, in this case, T-for-a-G)
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-crime/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>The Departed</em></strong><br />
        We went with <em>Infernal Affairs</em>, the Hong Kong movie it’s based on, instead. Yes it helped us make the list less American-centric, but it’s also pretty defensible if you’ve seen that original trilogy. We kind of double-screwed Scorsese though, since it meant we also didn’t give him <em>The Irishman</em>. That’s the real I-for-an-I!
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-crime/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>The Night Hunter</em> vs <em>No Country for Old Men</em></strong><br />
        Just brutal, we know. We might as well have flipped a coin. But Anton Chigurh bit the dust. What’s the most you ever lost on a coin toss?
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-crime/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Uncut Gems</em></strong><br />
         We were thrilled that <em>Queen and Slim</em> not only gave us a 2019 movie, but a good one. U was not as straightforward. The 90s were already very well represented, but we easily could have gone with <em>The Usual Suspects</em>. Or even <em>The Untouchables</em>. But in the end, we went with the greatest trick Adam Sandler ever pulled - convincing us he deserves to exist (as a serious actor).
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/24/a-z-crime.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/24/a-z-crime.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: War Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-war.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear War Fans, <br />
  				<p>No one is really a fan of war itself, but films <em>about</em> war? That&#39;s another story.</p>

<p>This is the second video in our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, and it opens with a bang. Many of the other films are less obvious, but equally glorious (and/or horrifying), so strap in.</p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/B5XQYYw-44w?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. It also made for some heated debates, which only barely avoided becoming all-out fights. </p>

<p>(Don’t worry. Cooler heads prevailed. Even if that goes against the spirit of the genre.)</p>

<p>So here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission.</p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM WAR A-Z</p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-war/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1960s</strong><br />
        Objectively, the 1960s just have the most films on our list (even if <em>X-15</em> is more about test pilots and the space race than actual war). But most of the others are iconic and run the full spectrum of the war genre, from terrifying, to rousing, to epics, to even a musical. The decade redefined the genre. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-war/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: B</strong><br />
        Depending on your age, the first “B” movie you probably think of in the war genre is <em>The</em> <em>Bridge on the River Kwai</em> or <em>Black Hawk Down</em>. Or you could definitely argue for <em>Braveheart</em> (we stuck to modern war, even if we didn’t state that as a rule). They’re all A+ movies (not B-movies!) for different reasons. But <em>The Battle of Algiers</em> is still one of the most impressive films ever made. The White House actually screened it for Generals before invading Iraq to help them understand modern warfare. If you haven’t seen it, go watch it. Now!<br />
        <br />
        (Also, P and D were bloodbaths to argue between in their own right)
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-war/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>Valkyrie</em></strong><br />
        It probably should be on the list. It’s definitely more classically a “war” movie than <em>Victory</em>. The only reason it isn’t here, honestly, is because we used it on our very first <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C6vHljlgQsU"><em>Action Movies A-Z</em></a> before we changed the format of the videos. We didn’t want to repeat ourselves. But if this new series goes well, we'll probably redo Action anyway, and then really seem like fools. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-war/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>The Great Escape</em> <strong>vs</strong> <em>Grand Illusion</em></strong><br />
        This one hurt. <em>Grand Illusion</em> was the first-ever release of the Criterion Collection. It’s a renowned piece of humanist anti-war filmmaking, which continues to age incredibly well. But it’s not Steve McQueen on a motorbike, and our dads would never speak to us again if it wasn’t included.  
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-war/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Come and See</em></strong><br />
         It’s here because it’s devastating and underseen. Know what’s <em>not</em> underseen or on this list? <em>Casablanca</em>. Plenty of people will call it a war film, but come on. That’s not the shelf you’re going to find <em>Casablanca</em> on at the video store. You still go to the video store, right?
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/23/a-z-war.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/23/a-z-war.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Animated Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-animation.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Animation Fans, <br />
  				<p>Who knew debates over the best animated films of all-time would get so…. animated?</p>

<p>As we continue our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, we made sure to draw from a long history of classic animation feature films. EWven though for this first season we are focusing on genres, and animation is a medium, it’s a category we just couldn’t ignore. Enjoy. </p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gPBwj6mD-Qg?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. We also had to ignore certain “outdated cultural stereotypes” at times to focus instead on the larger cultural impact. </p>

<p>So here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM ANIMATION A-Z</p>

<p>Now that this first video is out, here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-animation/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 00s</strong><br />
        It makes sense that the decade which saw the introduction of an Oscar category for Best Animated Feature is when the medium really started to flourish. Pixar changed the game, taking the shine off Disney’s new golden era (until Disney gobbled Pixar up, too), while Anime surged in popularity. DOn’t sleep on the 90sl of course. And ‘88 alone gave us three Toho masterpieces - how does that happen??
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-animation/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: S</strong><br />
        The default here would have been to go with the O.G. Disney classic <em>Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs</em>. Recency bias would put <em>Spider-man: Into the Spiderverse</em> ahead of the pack. And nostalgia could have carried <em>Shrek</em> right to the top. Hell, even <em>South Park: Bigger, Longer, Uncut</em> would compete in almost any other letter. Instead, we had to go with what many consider Hayao Miyazaki’s masterpiece, <em>Spirited Away</em>.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-animation/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>Fantastic Mr. Fox</em></strong><br />
        They probably won’t be the most vocal corner of the Internet, but it’s impossible to deny the _Frozen-_heads and what that film did for Disney’s 20-year drought of creating a true animated classic. Sorry, Wes.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-animation/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Toy Story</em> <strong>vs</strong> <em>Toy Story 3</em></strong><br />
        If you accept that one of the Toy Story movies has to make the list (and yes, accept it!), then it really comes down to which one. You could easily argue any of the four films, but <em>Toy Story 3</em> has the most convincing track-record to compete (between box-office, Oscar nominations, and general love). Still, we went with the original. Not only is it a great film, but it made computer animation acceptable - beloved, even. Those kind of innovations are a nice tie-breaker. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-animation/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Persepolis</em></strong><br />
    Anime junkies will argue for <em>Princess Mononoke</em> here, while Disney die-hards often consider <em>Pinocchio</em> to be Walt’s early-era masterpiece. But <em>Persepolis</em> is an excellent and important film not made by the two titans of animation that definitely deserves a place in the conversation of greatest animated films of all-time.
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/22/a-z-animation.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/22/a-z-animation.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Comedy Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-comedy.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Comedy Fans, <br />
  				<p>Making a video about the greatest comedies of all time is serious stuff. Well, we took it seriously, anyway. </p>

<p>This is the second instalment in our <strong>Greatest Movies A-Z</strong> series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, and it might have been the hardest of all. As tempting as it is to just stick to Will Farrell movies that make us laugh, we had the whole history of cinema to contend with. A rich, hilarious history which we hope this video serves as a nice reminder. Enjoy. </p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe width="624" height="351" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WQYfRc0aYoA?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Again, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. Sometimes you have to go with beloved movies even if you don’t personally love them (looking at you, <em>Caddyshack</em>). </p>

<p>So here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission.</p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM COMEDY A-Z</p>

<p>Now that this first video is out, here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-comedy/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1980s</strong><br />
        The 1980s have the most films on the list, suggesting some generational bias. The 70s and 90s are also well represented. The last 20 years have it rough: there’s not a single movie here from the 2010s. They just don’t make ‘em like they used to! And by that, we mean in the 20s and 30s (it’s not nostalgia - those movies we included are <em>still</em> great).
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-comedy/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: G</strong><br />
        G, didn’t expect that! If a Charlie Chaplin vs Buster Keaton face-off wasn’t enough (<em>The Great Dictator</em> vs <em>The General</em>), what about the 1-2 punch of Bill Murray’s all-time classics <em>Groundhog Day</em> and <em>Ghostbusters</em>? Or maybe we meet halfway in the timeline with <em>Gentlemen Prefer Blondes</em>? Instead, we played some politics, giving Keaton the G film and pushing <em>Groundhog Day</em> to another genre, and having Marilyn Monroe “settle” for the still pitch perfect comedy <em>Some Like it Hot</em>. <em>Ghostbusters</em> just didn’t make the call of a pure comedy - it’s so much more.<br />
        <br />
        <strong>Runner-up: A</strong>. <em>Anchorman</em> vs <em>Ace Ventura</em> vs <em>Austin Powers</em> - come on!<br />
        <br />
        <strong>2nd Runner-up: B.</strong> <em>Blazing Saddles</em> vs <em>The Big Lebowski</em> vs _Bridesmaids_… see why we said this genre was the hardest??</p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-comedy/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>Lost in America</em></strong><br />
        It’s a Criterion Collection comedy (which is pretty rare), and just a hell of a funny ride. But the video was getting a little bro-centric. Even though Reese Witherspoon double dips with <em>Election</em>, <em>Legally Blonde</em> was just too big and beloved not to recognize.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-comedy/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Wayne’s World</em> <strong>vs</strong> <em>What’s Up, Doc?</em></strong><br />
        Wayne and Garth would probably claim they aren’t worthy of taking out screen queen Barbara Streisand in <em>What’s Up, Doc?</em>, but _Wayne’s World_really holds up. Still, we banged our heads against the wall for a while, then just went with our gut. Asphinctersayswhat?
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-comedy/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>Dumb and Dumber</em></strong><br />
        You’re either thinking <em>hell yes!</em> this movie made the cut, or <em>what the hell</em>? The film snob in us definitely fought for <em>Dr. Strangelove or How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb</em>. The film historian part of our brain mounted a solid argument for the Marx Brothers’ <em>Duck Soup</em>. But at the risk of our pets losing their heads, we just had to respect the biggest comedy star of the 90s in one of the dumbest, funniest movies of a generation
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/21/a-z-comedy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/21/a-z-comedy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Horror Movies: A-Z</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/a-z-horror.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Horror Fans, <br />
  				<p>You know what’s really scary? Committing to a list of the all-time best horror films. </p>

<p>As the first video in our new Greatest Movies A-Z series with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaWd5_7JhbQBe4dknZhsHJg">WatchMojo</a>, we knew it wouldn’t be easy. That doesn’t mean we knew it would be so hard. But here it is:</p>

<div class="video-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TsZ1naZczHc?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>As you can see, we gave ourselves some guidelines:</p>

<ol>
<li>One film per letter</li>
<li>Articles don’t count (the, an, a, etc.)</li>
<li>Final list should encapsulate the genre</li>
</ol>

<p>The last rule dictated a lot of our hardest decisions. And we’re confident with where we ended up - especially after a last minute change to replace <em>Killer Klowns from Outer Space</em> with <em>King Kong</em>. </p>

<p>(Seriously. We almost forgot <em>King Kong</em> was a horror movie. That would have gotten ugly).</p>

<p class="intro" style="margin-top:4rem">LESSONS FROM HORROR A-Z</p>

<p>Now that this first video is out, here’s some take-aways from our decision-making process. If your favorite movie isn’t in our final video, there’s a very good chance it’s a decision, and not an omission. </p>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-horror/top-decade.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>TOP DECADE: 1970s</strong><br />
        Nine of our choices come from the 70s. Every one of them has a sequel and/or remake. The decade really set the template for modern horror. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-horror/hardest-letter.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>HARDEST LETTER: P</strong><br />
        <em>Paranormal Activity</em>. <em>Poltergeist</em>. <em>The Purge<em>. </em>Pet Cemetary</em>.  All extremely successful and important to the genre, but they ultimately have to bow down to the mother of mainstream horror: <em>Psycho</em>.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-horror/cheated-out.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>CHEATED OUT: <em>Alien</em></strong><br />
        Is <em>Alien</em> a horror movie? Sure. But it fit better in another genre, so we didn’t even consider it here. Don’t worry, we can hear you scream. 
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix" style="margin-top:4rem;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-horror/best-battle.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>BEST BATTLE: <em>Scream</em> vs <em>The Shining</em></strong><br />
        If you think we’re crazy for not going with Kubrick, trust us, we know. <em>The Shining</em> is a bona fide classic, and has had a real cultural resurgence since <em><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/9/room-237.html">Room 237</a></em>, <em><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/4/3/ready-player-one.html">Ready Player One</a></em>, and <em><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2019/11/12/doctor-sleep.html">Doctor Sleep</a></em>. But <em>Scream</em> single-handedly rejuvenated the horror genre in the mid 90s. It spawned three sequels, countless imitators, and even a spoof series (<em>Scary Movie</em>) that got all the way to a fifth instalment. Not to mention how the original <em>Scream</em> still totally slaps as a horror movie. The best argument against it might be that we already have a Wes Craven film in <em>Nightmare on Elm Street</em>. But like <em>Scream</em>, we just had to play with the rules here.
    </p>
</div>

<div class="clearfix"  style="margin:4rem 0;width:100%;">
    <div style="height:100%;float:left;width:40%;">
        <img style="vertical-align: top;display: inline-block;" src="/assets/img/features/inline/a-z-horror/special-consideration.jpg"> 
    </div>
    <p style="margin-top:0;float:left;width:60%;padding-left: 20px;">
        <strong>SPECIAL CONSIDERATION: <em>The Wizard of Gore</em></strong><br />
        Is it really better than <em><a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/2/19/the-witch.html
">The Witch</a></em>? Probably not, but we had to throw some love at the buckets-of-blood king Herschell Gordon Lewis. Helped us round out the style of horror films on the list, too. 
    </p>
</div>

<p>Think your list would be better? More balanced? Less heart-breaking? Let us know.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/20/a-z-horror.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2020/4/20/a-z-horror.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
