<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Imitation Game‎</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This is The Important British film with a capital WWII that everyone at the festival has been waiting for. And wow, it delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of mathematician/code-cracking genius Alan Turing was Oscar-bait the moment it was conceived as a screenplay. But what&amp;#39;s amazing is how well everything is actually handled. The non-chronological structure helps to not only keep the pacing strong, the plot twists engaging, and the character turns more dynamic, but also ensures that the climax is properly chilling without a sagging denouement. It&amp;#39;s an exceptional story told exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cast is also in fine form, even if &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&amp;#39;s&lt;/em&gt; Benedict Cumberbatch was the too-obvious choice to play another brilliant, socially awkward techno wiz. Consider it his redemption for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/22/the-fifth-estate.html&quot;&gt;another similar role&lt;/a&gt; in a film that opened your fest last year. This time, he&amp;#39;s given real heart and a full character arc, which finds a great dramatic ally in the film&amp;#39;s already monumental historical stakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If enough people see the film, it&amp;#39;s easily the most obvious (and maybe appropriate) choice for winning this year&amp;#39;s famous Audience Award.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Good Kill</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Good actors. Good script. Good director. Good timing. Good job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Good Kill&lt;/em&gt; is the kind of film that slides nicely into your programming. Though there&amp;#39;s some anticipation in seeing Ethan Hawk reteam with writer/director Andrew Niccol, any expectations are tempered by the fact both men have made some less than stellar projects since &lt;em&gt;Gattaca&lt;/em&gt; (the Ford Mustang that Hawk&amp;#39;s character drives throughout this film was a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/4/getaway.html&quot;&gt;good reminder of that&lt;/a&gt;). Yet the story of a U.S. drone pilot feels rich for commentary, and Niccol doesn&amp;#39;t waste the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of delivering an over-written thriller, Niccol is more interested in exploring the malaise and disconnect between drone pilots and their targets. He creates some nice visual parallels between the battlefields of Afghanistan and the dusty Nevada base of operations that lies just outside the wild nightlife of Vegas. All the best lines go to Bruce Greenwood as the commanding officer, who rattles off catchy acronyms and golden military nuggets (like &amp;quot;get your revenge in first.&amp;quot;). But it&amp;#39;s the lines like &amp;quot;Don&amp;#39;t ask me if this is a just war. To us, it&amp;#39;s just war,&amp;quot; that give the film a conscience and prove the script isn&amp;#39;t operating on autopilot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-1-good-kill.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-1-good-kill.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Eight</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Thursday, September 11.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-2014-day-eight.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-2014-day-eight.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Captive</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have one big question for you: was the use of flashbacks and flash-forwards in &lt;em&gt;The Captive&lt;/em&gt; your idea? Or was it director Atom Egoyan&amp;#39;s? I&amp;#39;m curious to know whether this was part of the screenplay&amp;#39;s original structure, or if it was a choice made during post-production, mainly because it seems to be the most divisive aspect of the film. I can&amp;#39;t decide how I feel about it, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that telling the story this way forced me to think a little harder about what I was watching. This is not a criticism in and of itself, except that I&amp;#39;m not sure it was always necessary. Sometimes the temporal shifts felt like &amp;quot;a gimmick, a trick you didn&amp;#39;t need&amp;quot; (like Ryan Reynolds and his young daughter so aptly discuss during the scene right before she disappears).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet there&amp;#39;s also serious confusion surrounding important plot points and when they actually take place. &lt;em&gt;(SPOILER ALERT!)&lt;/em&gt; It takes a long time, for instance, to reveal &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; Nicole, the detective played by Rosario Dawson, was actually kidnapped. This is the focus of the first scene of the film, but only actually happens last, chronologically - and this reveal feels anticlimactic after all the tension of trying to place it within the correct sequence of events, especially since it&amp;#39;s only a subplot to Cassandra&amp;#39;s disappearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, after I&amp;#39;d finished the film, when I really thought about it, this story device reminded me of the way my mind works when I obsess about something, thinking about it to the point of being overwhelmed, jumping from detail to memory to detail in no specific order while trying to figure out why something bad happened, something over which I ultimately had no control. So if that&amp;#39;s the feeling you were going for - a feeling of tense, OCD-like worry - then kudos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I enjoyed the film, but can&amp;#39;t quite figure out how I feel about this method of storytelling. Was it a gimmick you didn&amp;#39;t need, or a great trick for helping us empathize with the characters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diane Carol Harder&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/the-captive.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/the-captive.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Look of Silence</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Few documentaries warrant a sequel. Then again, few documentaries are landmark cinematic achievements like &lt;em&gt;The Act of Killing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joshua Oppenheimer&amp;#39;s new film, &lt;em&gt;The Look of Silence&lt;/em&gt;, once against takes us into the dark and disgraceful period of Indonesian history, face-to-face with the genocidal madmen who still hold political power 40 years after their crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living up to &lt;em&gt;The Act of Killing&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#39;s innovative and subversive storytelling tactics might not be possible, but &lt;em&gt;The Look of Silence&lt;/em&gt; breaks new ground by actually confronting the killers about their crimes. Once again risking his life, along with dozens of others who helped make the film (as before, many are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/13/the-act-of-killing.html&quot;&gt;credited as &amp;quot;Anonymous&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;), Oppenheimer gives us a brave central character to get behind: Adi, a man whose brother was brutally slaughtered by the paramilitary death squads.It&amp;#39;s as shocking and provocative as its predecessor, while still standing alone as an artistic and activist triumph.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-4-the-look-of-silence.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-4-the-look-of-silence.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Rosewater</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;So you didn&amp;#39;t land the world premiere of &lt;em&gt;Rosewater&lt;/em&gt;. Not even the North American premiere, actually. So what if the story is about an Iranian-Canadian journalist. And big deal that everyone is curious about what Jon Stewart brings to his first film as writer and director.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a super sarcastic set-up from &lt;em&gt;The Daily Show&lt;/em&gt; (those can be extremely dangerous, after all). After seeing the picture, there&amp;#39;s no sense losing sleep over the fact that you made us thesecond (gasp!) audience to see this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won&amp;#39;t be hard for journalists to get excited about the tale of Mazir Bahari. The film does a great job of lauding the dangerous risks that the press faces abroad. Especially since the film does so without ever becoming saccharine or sanctimonious. On the other hand, there isn&amp;#39;t enough going on at a plot level to warrant such a big production (a good metaphor for the Bahari&amp;#39;s imprisonment, actually). Because footage from &lt;em&gt;The Daily Show&lt;/em&gt; was used to accuse Bahari of being a U.S. spy, I understand why Stewart felt a need to make the film. I&amp;#39;m just not sure many other&amp;#39;s will feel the need to see it—especially once the novelty wares off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-3-rosewater.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-3-rosewater.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>&#39;71</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not usually a fan of war movies (don&amp;#39;t tell anyone, but still haven&amp;#39;t seen&lt;em&gt;Saving Private Ryan&lt;/em&gt;), but you definitely got my attention with this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in the early days of The Troubles in Belfast, a rookie British soldier finds himself lost and alone in IRA-controlled territory. I was on the edge of my seat as he dodged through alleyways, attempting to find his way back to his barracks while trying to avoid getting shot by zealots. And I sincerely appreciated how complicated the politics were—and that no one in this battle was wholly innocent (except, maybe, our protagonist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If more combat films could be like this – tense thrillers that are more about survival than destruction – I might just become a convert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diane Carol Harder&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-2-71.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-2-71.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Corbo</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The October Crisis has inspired some of Canada&amp;#39;s finest films. Michel Brault&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Les ordres&lt;/em&gt; and Pierre Falardeau&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Octobre&lt;/em&gt; are the most notable, and despite their propaganda-like levels of sympathy for the FLQ and Quebec sovereignty movement, they&amp;#39;re undeniably great cinematic experiences. &lt;em&gt;Corbo&lt;/em&gt; may not achieve such heights, but it&amp;#39;s certainly worthy of being grouped in this elite class of &amp;quot;distinctly&amp;quot; Quebec cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film canonizes teenagers in the 1960s who were willing to kill complete strangers to promote the separatist movement. This makes the film&amp;#39;s inclusion in Canada&amp;#39;s premiere film festival sound strange on paper, but adding &lt;em&gt;Corbo&lt;/em&gt; to the line-up is far from a political statement. It&amp;#39;s a well-crafted period film that takes its characters and politics dead serious. I haven&amp;#39;t seen (or even heard of) writer and director Mathieu Denis&amp;#39; only other feature film, Laurentie. But after seeing &lt;em&gt;Corbo&lt;/em&gt;, he&amp;#39;s one to watch out for. In a good way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-1-corbo.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-1-corbo.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Seven</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Wednesday, September 10.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-2014-day-seven.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-2014-day-seven.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Nightcrawler</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;That first clap you heard when the screening was over? That was me. And the sigh of relief right afterwards? That was me, too. I was waiting to find the film at this year&amp;#39;s festival that I&amp;#39;d flip over, and I finally did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearless and fascinating characters, a gripping plot, biting satire, a wicked sense of humor—&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; almost feels like this year&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Spring Breakers&lt;/em&gt; ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/28/spring-breakers.html&quot;&gt;high praise, indeed&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the opening scene, Dan Gilroy, in his directorial debut, makes a statement that anything can and will happen. Jake Gyllenhaal takes his creepiness to just the right places in this film about a man who&amp;#39;s looking for a job – any job, really – that will suit his yet-to-be-defined skills and bald-faced ambition. Needless to say, he finds something he&amp;#39;s rather perfect for. My spoiler-phobic instincts allowed me to experience every moment with complete surprise, and I was swept away by the excitement. Now I&amp;#39;m turning all my enthusiasm into word-of-mouth buzz, so people can hopefully avoid the terribly revealing trailer for a film that goes way-too-deep into the third act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People should just trust me – and you – and check out this film. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-4-nightcrawler.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-4-nightcrawler.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
