<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Dope</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/dope.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear McGuffin, Plot Mechanism, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dope&lt;/em&gt; is as much a cultural artifact as it is a story. An artifact because it often only makes sense in relationship to the films that it depends on to first inform, and prop up, its central premise—movies like &lt;em&gt;Juice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Boys N’ The Hood&lt;/em&gt; and especially &lt;em&gt;Menace II Society.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These movies all dealt with the limited number of choices that inner city youth face. In the 1990’s the cinematic response to this dearth of choices usually took the shape of nihilistic acceptance, or sometimes defiance followed quickly by tragic consequences. &lt;em&gt;Dope&lt;/em&gt; tries to sketch a third option. Bur that new option only makes sense, in this case, when contrasted with what came before. This is not necessarily an ineffectual strategy, but it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; depend upon a prior knowledge of the genre, which is a risky approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dope&lt;/em&gt; certainly begins with real promise. The main characters—a 90’s throwback nerd, a lesbian and a bro-y stick figure who all live in present day Inglewood CA.—aren’t types that conventionally populate the urban youth genre. Not to mention their single unifying principle—membership in the only new wave/thrash band in their zip code. It gave me hope that this might be a different take on an otherwise well-worn premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this trio of high school kids becomes unwittingly embroiled in a drug transaction gone wrong is the moment when you make your first appearance (in this case as a knapsack full of MDMA) and also where the film goes a little off-track. Because McGuffins like yourself (as Hitchcock once described you—the &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; that the spy’s are all concerned with but the audience doesn’t really care about) are only useful in very small doses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case you trigger a convoluted narrative involving competing drug gangs, bit-coins, corrupt city officials and some pretty retrograde gender politics. This unnecessary baggage muddies what had begun as a pretty interesting—and sometimes funny—meditation on what it is like to be an outsider in a very specific set of circumstances.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;Dope&lt;/em&gt; seems intent on repudiating the underlining despair present in the films that it structurally mimics, it often falls into the very tropes it wants to undermine. It is, in some significant ways, a prisoner to the kind of inexorable logic that made the earlier films so powerful. They were expressing what seemed to be an unanswerable dilemma for the young men at the center of these stories, and one that also seemed to lack a win/win option. Caine in &lt;em&gt;Menace II Society&lt;/em&gt;, Bishop in &lt;em&gt;Juice&lt;/em&gt;, Doughboy in &lt;em&gt;Boyz N’ The Hood&lt;/em&gt; all end up dead, caught up in lives that are circumscribed by mostly terrible options.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when this film starts to lean more heavily on the standards of the genre, especially in the second and third act, those conventions tend to step on the more nuanced approach of the first act. Characters become much less three-dimensional as the story mechanics flatten them out. Plot starts to drive character and the film becomes less organic, more by the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a lot to like here. Good central performances by a young cast, more than a few sharply observed moments that establish a strong sense of place, and a script that is ambitious and often surprising. Unfortunately, that promise fades away when you, Mr. McGuffin, take centre stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly you’re useful as an entry point, a reason for the characters to engage and act. But when you become the focal point of the story, you’re revealed for what you are—a mechanism and nothing more. That kind of exposure means the rest of the film becomes an exercise of moving from a to b to c. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGuffins, as is true of so many other aspects of cinema (like editing, or the soundtrack, or even the performances), are best when they go unnoticed. Sadly, in &lt;em&gt;Dope&lt;/em&gt;, you draw far too much attention to yourself and what could have been a pretty good film is instead reduced to a self-defeating exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/19/dope.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/19/dope.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Jurassic World</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/jurassic-world.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Jack Horner, Palaeontology Consultant, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;You’re the most famous palaeontologist since Ross from &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt;. Which is kind of sad because you’re &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; a palaeontologist with years of study under your belt. Your behind-the-scenes presence in all the &lt;em&gt;Jurassic Park&lt;/em&gt; releases has helped provide a realistic-ish portrayal of what would happen if humans faced off against dinosaurs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say realistic-&lt;em&gt;ish&lt;/em&gt; because you yourself admitted that you had to curb your expertise for the sake of entertainment, which is admirable. It’s one thing to be a consultant about dinosaurs, but it’s another to consciously suppress your knowledge for the betterment of the movie. Although, you have to agree, velociraptors are scarier without the feathers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong; your most recent project, &lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt;, was entertaining as hell. It isn’t every day you get to see an alpha standoff between a genetically altered mega-dinosaur and a T-rex. My inner child pretty much passed out from excitement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as entertaining as it was, this showdown is part of the problem. &lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt; strayed too far away from being a movie about dinosaurs to being a summer blockbuster about “monsters.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your input in the original trilogy was based on fact, but &lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt; had a new twist involving humans tampering with gene-modification to create a new, enhanced species of dinosaur. The film shows us what would happen if that dinosaur was raised in captivity only to escape and wreak havoc on unsuspecting tourists in a prehistoric-themed amusement park (same thing happened when I played &lt;em&gt;Zoo Tycoon: Dinosaur Digs&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the type of ideal scenario for a classic Hollywood monster mash. When our mega dinosaur is loose in the forest and an elite team of soldiers goes in to contain it, the bloodbath that follows closely resembles something out of &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt;: lots of screaming and people being flung around. What’s the best way to show this creature is a force to be reckoned with? Throw some collateral damage its way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That type of arc opens doors for even more clichés, blatant and excessive foreshadowing, and inappropriate moments of comedy and romance that strip away realism and predictable character growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I for one enjoyed the minor details you helped provide: the velociraptors, using their hind legs to aggressively climb their prey (similar to hungry hyenas), or the rotting teeth that can be seen when our antagonist dino sniffs out Chris Pratt. I would have liked to see more of that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt; is definitely entertaining. It’s a summer blockbuster. I get that. And as far as summer blockbusters go, it hit the mark. I had fun watching it, as did my girlfriend (who was there for Chris Pratt). I laughed, felt tense, and even jumped out of my seat a couple of times. If this is the trend that any sequel will follow, I’d be okay with it. I just hope if you are to be attached again, that you’ll have more of a say with the how the movie pans out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure the success of &lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt; will help finance your goal to bring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/paleontologist-jack-horner-is-hard-at-work-trying-to-turn-a-chicken-into-a-dinosaur/2014/11/10/cb35e46e-4e59-11e4-babe-e91da079cb8a_story.html&quot;&gt;Chickenosaurus&lt;/a&gt; to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ankit&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/12/jurassic-world.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/12/jurassic-world.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Entourage</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/entourage.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Doug Ellin, Writer/Creator/Director, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;Eight seasons and a movie. That’s a long run for any creative endeavour. Just keeping up the energy is a feat in and of itself—especially for something as fundamentally empty as &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt;. The Hollywood adventures of Vinnie Chase and his gang of charisma-free bros—brother and fellow actor Johnny Drama, his manager E, and driver Turtle (I’d name the actors, but let’s not pretend they’ll have any kind of career outside this)—felt like something that warranted three, maybe four seasons. It was always a trifle of a show, and the longer it went on it was obvious that there never was any &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; there. Nothing. At all. How could you keep returning to mine something that emptied its reserves so long ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What became clear to me while watching your movie version of &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt;, though, was that the eight season run is actually the key. In what I can only assume may be the first known instance of cinematic Stockholm Syndrome, at some point you stopped being any kind of observer of your subjects. Instead of viewing them objectively, you started to admire them. You wanted to be them; your own creations became your aspiration. That has to be it. It’s certainly the best way to explain why &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt; is as lazy—and as dumb—as its characters. It takes the easy way out of, well, everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, I suppose, we do have a bit of a field guide for the lazy auteur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we finally have an answer to the age old problem of what to do when a writer needs his character to spout exposition, but can’t be bothered to make it in any way a natural part of dialogue: make them non-sequitors! It leads to awesome exchanges like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great Vinnie invited us to is yacht in Ibiza!”&lt;br&gt;
“Yeah. I can’t believe he split up with his wife on their honeymoon!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need to introduce a sort-of celebrity that may not be instantly recognizable with an audience whose head isn&amp;#39;t up the ass of Hollywood? Just have Turtle and E engage in call-and-response until the relevant information has been explained in a way that would embarrass the author of an &lt;em&gt;I Can Read&lt;/em&gt; book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hey, look!&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;Who&amp;#39;s that?&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s Ronda Rousey!&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;The MMA fighter?&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;Yeah!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I get it. Writing is hard. And if anything, &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt; is and always was about things coming easy. I&amp;#39;m not the first one to point this out to you, Doug, but &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt; may be the most conflict-free series to ever grace television and the big screen. HBO&amp;#39;s comedy successors to your time slot, &lt;em&gt;Veep&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Silicon Valley&lt;/em&gt; both know that there&amp;#39;s little—drama &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; comedy—in watching characters constantly win at life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, Doug, you do seem to understand this on some basic level. In &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt;, you make the most token of gestures towards some sort of conflict: the supposed dramatic crux set up pre-credits is that Vinnie demands to direct the next movie in which he stars. I was willing to ride along; there’s something to be made from the proposal that Vinnie’s hubris will destroy his reputation and take his agent Ari down with him. But then the opening credit sequence concluded with the title “Eight months later.” You skipped over the entire production of the film to get back to … more parties, more luxury porn, and—worst of all—more bro-humour. Like the loathsome depiction of every female character in this movie, I guess I only have myself to blame for thinking things would be different this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did let me watch &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt; in a different light, though. Instead of seeing it only as the not-funny, up-its-own-ass piece of misogynous dreck it most assuredly is, I could also see the self-reflecting prison you had built around yourself. When Vinnie asks Ari (Jeremy Piven, being the one reliable bright spot on the show, returning to erase any good will that remained for his character) for another 10 or so million dollars to finish the film, everyone worries that the movie is in trouble. Maybe it will reveal that, much like Adrienne Grenier, there’s absolutely nothing to Vinnie Chase. And then you go and make the biggest of bone-headed decisions: you show a scene from the actual movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That movie is some sort sci-fi reimagining of &lt;em&gt;Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde&lt;/em&gt; called, naturally, &lt;em&gt;Hyde&lt;/em&gt;. As Ari sits though a rough cut, terrified that he’s about to witness a megaflop, we are treated to &lt;em&gt;Hyde&lt;/em&gt;’s opening credits: Vinnie dressed a hooded, kind of Jedi-Knight-cyborg-DJ overseeing what looks to be the rave scene from &lt;em&gt;The Matrix Reloaded&lt;/em&gt;. For real. And the thing is, I couldn’t tell if I was supposed to read this as amazing or laughably ridiculous. Okay, I knew it was the latter, but I wasn’t sure what side everyone in &lt;em&gt;Entourage&lt;/em&gt; was on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, Doug, you came to the rescue as always with your dialogue designed to explain the scene for all levels of learning impairments. “It’s a masterpiece!” “It’s the best thing he’s ever done!” “This will win at the Golden Globes!” I might have bought this just a little if you hadn’t shown me something that has all the artistic merit of a cut Uwe Boll scene. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Ari steps up as the champion for &lt;em&gt;Hyde&lt;/em&gt;, willing to risk everything to protect its vision, I’m fairly certain I’m not supposed to be siding with the &lt;em&gt;Entourage’s&lt;/em&gt; villain, the investor’s son, who wants to reedit &lt;em&gt;Hyde&lt;/em&gt; himself purely out of spite because Vinnie stole a girl from him. Anything he does can’t be worse than what we’ve already seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had a brief-but-actual dilemma: was I watching a movie made by people so blinded by their own reflection that they can no longer tell when they’ve crossed the line into self-parody? Or was I watching a satire &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; those very people that was so razor sharp, so pitch perfect, that maybe I was the one too dense to be in on the joke? Maybe there were some signifiers that I just didn’t get - maybe the possibility of winning a Golden Globe &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; supposed to come off as the joke we all know it is. And then I remembered, in perhaps the biggest irony of all, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/26/pain-gain.html&quot;&gt;Michael Bay already made that movie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You actually believe what you’re shovelling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 19:43:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/entourage.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/entourage.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Requiem for an Underdog</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/requiem-for-an-underdog.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear 1985, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;1985 was the year I escaped into movies. And it was a good year to escape from. I was eleven, and there were only two things I was scared of: nuclear war, and losing one of my parents. In 1985, one of those things happened. And since I’m not writing to you from an underground bunker filled with powdered water and assault rifles (although that &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be pretty cool), you can probably guess which of the two I’m talking about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dad was almost fifty when I was born. He’d served in the army during World War II. He was part of that Greatest Generation of men who smoked two packs a day, drank liberally at the Legion, and never saw a doctor. On my 11th birthday he went to the hospital because he couldn’t breathe. By the fall, he was back home. He was dying. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to be at home during that time, too, with a case of mono so bad my whole body was swollen and I was delirious with fever. Over the next six weeks, as I recovered, Dad and I propped ourselves up on couches in the den and binge-watched movies on Pay TV. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the youngest child by so many years that my family treated me like another adult. Nothing was dumbed down for me, nothing was kept from me. I had no bedtime, and no restrictions on what I could read or watch. I know that my family did this out of love, and out of respect for my intelligence and curiosity. But an unfortunate side effect of having no little-kid filter was that, while I was fully aware of what was going on in the world, I had no tools with which to process it. I had a visceral, almost debilitating fear of what would happen if the U.S. and Russia launched their nuclear missiles. Sure, I knew that if I needed clarity on something I could go to one of the many adults in my life, but, in the case of the Cold War, no one could adequately explain what was going on because so much of it was completely absurd. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-80s, Cold War tensions were high. Not a week went by when we didn’t hear about nuclear testing, or have a regularly-scheduled program interrupted by Peter Jennings, who would somberly describe yet another plane hijacking or hostage taking. When Reagan, Thatcher, and Gorbachev weren’t busy playing chicken with warheads, they were metaphorically whipping out their junk to see whose was biggest (unsurprisingly, it was Maggie’s). Every once in a while, Gaddafi or Khomeini would do something crazy—you know, just to keep things interesting. Then there was Apartheid. And acid rain. And the recession, and famine in Ethiopia, and random mass shootings, and the AIDS epidemic. It’s no wonder coke was the drug of choice in the 80s; we were running out of time and there was &lt;em&gt;soooo&lt;/em&gt; much to talk about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Dad was a burly, barrel-chested guy. He’d been an amateur boxer and hockey player before he met my mother. But, sitting there on the couch beside me, he was sunken and grey. His favourite actors were John Wayne, Clint Eastwood, and Charles Bronson. Manly men. His favourite movie was &lt;em&gt;Gunga Din&lt;/em&gt;, a 1939 war movie about three unruly British sergeants holding back a murderous horde of thugs in 1880s India. Fighting alongside them is their water boy, Gunga Din, who dreams of making a better life for himself. Dad loved watching underdog movies. It’s the only time he ever cried. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I spent that fall watching movies with my father, there were three films that had profoundly affected me: &lt;em&gt;Testament, The Day After,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Big Chill&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two are about people trying to survive the fallout of nuclear war. The third is a yuppie classic about a bunch of affluent white people who get together after a friend’s suicide to figure out what happened to their stupid hippie idealism. &lt;em&gt;The Big Chill&lt;/em&gt; appealed to me because I took some weird satisfaction in seeing a group of adults struggling with their collective existential angst the same way I did. The other two were training films of sorts. &lt;em&gt;Testament&lt;/em&gt; was a remarkably subtle portrait of a woman trying to keep her family and sanity intact after nuclear war upends her comfortable suburban existence. &lt;em&gt;The Day After&lt;/em&gt; is an explicit play by play of a nuclear attack on a small American town. It was so terrifying that after it was shown on TV my school held an assembly to calm down all the kids who were freaked the fuck out (and it wasn’t just us fragile children; the network had 1-800 phone lines set up with counsellors to talk down hysterical viewers). After seeing those films, I didn’t feel so alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that didn’t last long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dad died on February 11, 1985. At home, right there in the room where we’d watched all those movies together. Which movies? I couldn’t even say. There’s a lot that I don’t remember about that time. And other things I recall as clearly as if they happened yesterday. I remember Dad’s Legion buddies filing past his coffin to place poppies inside. I remember bagpipes. I didn’t cry. Not once. I remember all the adults telling me to “take care of your mother.” I was left on my own to find a way to take care of myself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t bother familiarizing you with the &lt;em&gt;Rocky&lt;/em&gt; franchise—the first five minutes of every &lt;em&gt;Rocky&lt;/em&gt; film does that for you. &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; is “the one with the Russian” (as it is colloquially known). Rocky is retired, but agrees to coach his best friend Apollo Creed in a friendly exhibition fight against Ivan Drago, a giant hunk of Caucasian granite and the pride of the Soviet athletic training system. After being stunned by the spectacle of James Brown singing &lt;em&gt;Living In America&lt;/em&gt;, Drago recovers and proceeds to pummel Apollo. Rocky has an opportunity to throw in the towel, to save Apollo’s life, but he doesn’t do it, and Apollo is killed. After a requisite period of mourning and soul-searching (which involves driving his Bugatti around town to Robert Tepper’s synth-heavy song &lt;em&gt;No Easy Way Out&lt;/em&gt;) Rocky decides to fight Drago himself...&lt;em&gt;in Russia&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will defend &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt;. To the death. I once came close to throwing down fisticuffs with someone who dared to say that &lt;em&gt;Rocky V&lt;/em&gt; (the Voldemort of the &lt;em&gt;Rocky&lt;/em&gt; franchise) was better than &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt;. I had to be physically restrained and removed from the room (please note: this was sober, and at a child’s birthday party). I don’t labor under any delusions that &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; is a “good” movie. It’s not. I know this objectively. I knew it in the fall of ’85, when my brother took me to see it at the small movie theatre in our hometown. I knew it when I begged him to take me several more times. I knew it wasn’t good in the way I knew &lt;em&gt;Amadeus&lt;/em&gt; was good, or that &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; was good. But I didn’t need &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; to be good. I needed it to make me &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; good. I needed it to give me some hope, however contrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; was an antidote to &lt;em&gt;Testament&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Day After&lt;/em&gt; (and even to &lt;em&gt;The Big Chill&lt;/em&gt;). I wasn’t worried about trying to survive radiation poisoning anymore, or about whether or not adults would get their heads out of their asses long enough to keep the world from imploding. The Italian Stallion gave me back my power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My love for &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; is, at its essence, very simple. It’s about wish fulfillment. Rocky didn’t just win the fight—he managed to capture the hearts and minds of our Godless communist enemies. And on &lt;em&gt;Christmas Day&lt;/em&gt; no less! He didn’t just show up and win, either. He had to work hard, without his family, with the KGB on his ass. He trained in a goddamned barn! No one believed in him, no one thought he could win. But he did. Of course he did. And at the end of his triumphant victory, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MsJnxlXepsY&quot;&gt;his world-changing speech&lt;/a&gt; concludes, he gives a shout out to his kid, and tells him he loves him, and his kid mouths back the words: “I love you.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waterworks. Every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter that &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; is rife with cliché, full of cartoonish stereotypes, and laced with horrible (and somehow unforgettable) dialogue. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cxs1MHw2_Ds&quot;&gt;It features the granddaddy of all sports montages&lt;/a&gt;, set to the jingoistic fist-pumper &lt;em&gt;Burning Heart&lt;/em&gt;. It has one of the cheesiest slo-mo sequences in film history, where Duke shouts “Noooooooo!” as Apollo falls to the floor. It has a creepy love story between Adrian’s ingrate brother Paulie and a sexy robot. The acting is almost as embarrassing as the blatant product placement. It even features a fake Gorbachev! But I don’t care. I love it—not in spite of those shortcomings, but &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a freedom that comes from facing your biggest fear and living through it. Especially at a young age. 1985 was the year that I realized no one - kids or adults – knows &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;, and I took a perverse comfort in that. Things that mattered before my Dad died suddenly seemed petty or insignificant. Other things became more important. The impact of it changed my emotional DNA. I became guarded. I refused to let anyone see me hurting. Movies got me through that year, though—and through subsequent years that weren’t much easier. Like my Dad, I don’t cry unless I’m watching a movie. And like my Dad I’m a sucker for underdog movies. It’s the only time I let myself indulge in unapologetic sentimentality. I’m a natural born cynic, and those movies taught me that my cynicism is borne from hope. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt;’s earnestness. I sincerely think Sylvester Stallone was as frustrated and frightened as the rest of us, and that he genuinely wanted to make a difference. So he tried. The only way he knew how: by making a movie about punching people while listening to &lt;em&gt;Survivor&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe Stallone hoped &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt; would change the world. Maybe it did, maybe it didn’t. But it sure changed mine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 07:43:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/11/requiem-for-an-underdog.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Spy</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/spy.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear ‘Homophobic Aunt’ Wig, Costume, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;The ‘Melissa McCarthy movie’ has almost become a sub-sub-genre in itself; Packaged as comedy but somehow more horrifying than funny. The premise of any Melissa McCarthy movie seems to be ‘How obnoxious, dirty, and pathetic can we make her look? How deeply can we degrade and humiliate her character before people stop laughing?” It has often bugged me that all we seem to get is more &lt;em&gt;Tammy&lt;/em&gt;, when all I want is to see her play the President in a remake of &lt;em&gt;Air Force One&lt;/em&gt; (come on, you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; how hard that movie would bring it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll probably be waiting for a while for that particular wish to come true, but in the meantime I’m happy to report that &lt;em&gt;Spy&lt;/em&gt; is a welcome step in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spy genre has been spoofed many times with mixed results, and I was starting to feel like it was losing steam. But McCarthy’s turn as a dowdy CIA desk jockey-turned field agent is hysterically funny. Her Susan Cooper might just be an even bigger badass than James Bond (I actually think James Bond is a lousy spy, but that’s a conversation for another day). Spy flick tropes are used as launch pads for gags that are over the top, but never overplayed (I’m looking at you, Austin Powers).There is also some heavy gender politicking at play here; Susan’s boss, her sidekick, and the villain are all women. Male characters, be they good guys or bad guys, make for excellent eye candy, but are pretty well useless beyond that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the conversation surrounding &lt;em&gt;Spy&lt;/em&gt; will probably be about another traditionally male-oriented genre being ‘overwhelmed by estrogen’ or some such nonsense. But what appealed to me most was the Feig-McCarthy &lt;em&gt;cri de&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;coeur&lt;/em&gt; against the now common tropes of the Melissa McCarthy movie, the &lt;em&gt;Tammy&lt;/em&gt;s and &lt;em&gt;Identity&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thief&lt;/em&gt;s of this world. Susan’s various cover identities created for her by the CIA - frumpy single mom, unemployed call centre associate, etc. - are variations on many of the sad, fat mess characters she has played in the past. Her frustrated reaction to the pathetic back stories and cringe-worthy disguises (like you) echoed my own feelings of being fed-up to the teeth with this shit. Rather than waiting for the excruciatingly embarrassing splatter onto rock bottom for the eventual makeover where everyone is supposed to go, “Oh, look! She’s actually like, really pretty!” Susan ditches the sadsack cover and takes it upon herself to glam up. Her rage has as much to do with other people’s bullshit perceptions of her as it does with the arms dealers and assassins she encounters, something to which many other unassuming, desk job-working women out there will relate (holla’!), but minus the arms dealer and assassin part (I’m assuming).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spy&lt;/em&gt; delivers a good, swift kick to the idea that women carrying ‘traditionally male’ films have to be demeaned and (sometimes literally) dragged through mud in appliqué cat sweaters and ugly wigs, but I doubt it will have the last word on the matter. Indeed, I expect the upcoming ‘male&lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; remake vs. female &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; remake’ furor to reach near-Culloden proportions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my sincere hope - and don’t take this the wrong way - that you and other disguises of your kind will no longer be considered necessary in the women-can-be-‘dude-funny’-too debate that I can’t even believe is still a thing. I’m sure there’s an Adam Sandler project in production that could use you, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/4/spy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/4/spy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: San Andreas</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/san-andreas.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Jeanne Bautista, Disaster Victim, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;The term “blockbuster” has always been rooted in violence. Originating from aerial bombs dropped during World War II, the word was officially adopted by the media in the 70s (after &lt;em&gt;Jaws&lt;/em&gt;) to describe a massive “hit” at the box-office. But the “blockbuster” has now become quite literal. Studios decided at some point in the past few years that the secret formula for what sells has been hiding in plain sight all along: bust the block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s just one problem. A tiny moral quandary that filmmakers need to deal with when creating earth-shattering images at the center of a city: 9/11.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reverence to that day, it has become &lt;em&gt;de rigueur&lt;/em&gt; to complain about the dismissive way innocent bystanders, like you, are killed in blockbusters. As each new superhero movie grows in scale, so too does the collateral damage. Buildings and entire cities are frequently leveled with little or no consequence. The epidemic arguably reached an apex in 2013 with &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/16/star-trek-into-darkness.html&quot;&gt;Star Trek Into Darkness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/14/man-of-steel.html&quot;&gt;Man of Steel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  That’s when the accusations of appropriating images from September 11th really started to fly. How could they? What a cheap way to entertain an audience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, movies like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/16/godzilla.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/7/11/pacific-rim.html&quot;&gt;Pacific Rim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/avengers-age-of-ultron.html&quot;&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; have at least &lt;em&gt;tried&lt;/em&gt; to appease movie-goers with references to how and where the public could hide during the super-sized battles. This gives the audience license to enjoy the wild destruction without that pang of guilt from worrying that someone might actually get hurt. And I won’t lie – it did help me enjoy those films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then along comes &lt;em&gt;San Andreas&lt;/em&gt;. An earthquake that rocks the entire West Coast of California, and there’s nowhere to hide. No one is safe. And even more interestingly, there’s also no one to blame. In a dark and thrilling way, it’s actually a thing of beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m tired of every big blockbuster being held hostage by the memory “that day”.  And most importantly, when I watch all the people like you being killed in wild and disturbing ways (crushed by debris, falling off buildings, swept away by gushing waters), I’m actually reminded of the countless times this has happened around the word – from Haiti to Nepal to Indonesia. Natural disasters are becoming the wars of our times. It’s a fight where there is no tangible villain and everyone is a victim. There’s something powerful and unifying about that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on about &lt;em&gt;San Andreas&lt;/em&gt;’ horribly on-the-nose dialogue, or the eye-rolling shots of sexy eye candy, or underused side-stories. But I would be lying to say that I wasn’t sufficiently enraptured by the massive spectacle on display (no, not just “The Rock”) to overlook these minor grievances. In fact, I was surprised at just how little Dwayne Johnson is given a chance to flex his muscles in the film. He spends much of his time in a cockpit rather than in the trenches. But scaling down his heroics somehow helped ground the film, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, is it insensitive of me to have taken so much pleasure in your nameless demise? Does my seeing you as a stand in for thousands of people who have suffered around the world make the film more moving, more relevant, or more shamelessly entertaining? I’m not entirely sure, but seeing average people die did make me feel closer to the action. And that’s all I want really want in a blockbuster.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/3/san-andreas.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/3/san-andreas.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Aloha</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/aloha.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Cameron Crowe, Writer/Director/Producer, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;We need to have a word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, with less-than-supportive leaked emails and delayed press screenings, as well as a terrible first weekend, much of the world suspects that &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt;  isn’t a very good film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not bad in the sense that there are laughable continuity errors or boom mics in the shot. Production values aren’t the problem. And the concept isn’t necessarily a bad one to bring to life (unlike, say, Gus Van Sant’s recent bad-buzz release, &lt;em&gt;Sea of Trees&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow you have managed to take a number of potentially interesting elements—a beautiful location (Hawaii), a great cast (Bill Murray, Emma Stone, Bradley Cooper, Rachel McAdams) as well as some intriguing geopolitics—and turned it all into something so ponderous that I’m surprised it didn’t drag the whole chain of volcanic islands back down to the bottom of the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; begins with an examination of a fairly new phenomenon—private enterprise and their increasing investment in the exploration and exploitation of space—and then promptly left turns into a cartoonish romcom. After that the tone, and the focus of the story, shift four or five times, until the film finally sputters to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are the performances. &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; really falls apart just twelve minutes in when, of all people, Bill Murray appears. I think he was caricaturing some awful hybrid of Richard Branson and Elon Musk. But, to be honest, it was hard to tell—his character was all over the map. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know you’ve gone terribly wrong when Bill Murray is a net negative in your film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention Emma Stone, who I usually quite like. But she was tied to a character so one dimensional that I began to dread every moment that she appeared on screen. It felt like watching a singularly unfunny friend do a twelve-minute bit on open mic night. Bradley Cooper’s character, a disgraced and ostensibly disabled veteran who’s injury comes and goes the same way Keanu Reeves’ accent did in Coppola’s &lt;em&gt;Dracula,&lt;/em&gt; was so poorly articulated that it was never clear if we were meant to hope for his redemption or his comeuppance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to lie, Cameron. I’ve always found your films to be, at best, powder-puff entertainments laced with the kind of earnest, American exceptionalism that makes my teeth grind. But &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; is irredeemable. Especially your contrived and awkward attempt to cover this film with a patina of Hawaiian spiritualism. That’s just fucking embarrassing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel bad for everyone involved in this nonsense. Except for you. Because you should really know better. That you don’t, given how long you’ve been around, speaks to a kind of willful ignorance that I consider inexcusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally I try hard to find good things to say about every film I see but this thing stymied me at every turn. It is the crystallization of everything that is wrong with big studio filmmaking. &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; is both cynical and manipulative, yet somehow also naïve and completely convinced of its own moral authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is my unsolicited advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop. Just stop.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/2/aloha.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/2/aloha.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Me and Earl and the Dying Girl</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/me-and-earl-and-the-dying-girl.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Gerald Sullivan, Production Designer, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;When you are seventeen, one of the most useful clues to who you are is your bedroom. If I were a psychologist and I wanted to understand exactly what made someone tick at that point in their lives, I wouldn’t interrogate them, I would go through their stuff. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me and Earl and the Dying Girl&lt;/em&gt; is a film about exactly that. The Me in this case is the requisite awkward teenage boy—Greg—played by Thomas Mann. He is both the self-avowed unreliable narrator and that rarest of things—a quirky teen who doesn’t immediately put me to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is primarily concerned with Greg and his interaction with both Earl (CJ Cyler, Greg’s film making partner and much less angst-ridden confidant) and the Dying Girl, Rachel (Olivia Cook). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a year or so in the life of Greg, &lt;em&gt;Me and Earl and the Dying Girl&lt;/em&gt; begins with his first awkward interaction with Rachel. It also depicts Greg’s mostly unsuccessfully attempt to navigate the transition between the end of his prison term in the worst of all institutions, high school, and the wide unknown world to come. But the heart of the film is the short relationship between a miserable, self-absorbed asshole (Greg, representing every sixteen year old boy everywhere) and an afflicted young woman. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olivia Cook as Rachel, a young women suffering from leukemia, manages to avoid melodrama in an impressively authentic, lived in performance. As well as that solid central performance, the filmmakers also managed to circumvent all of the usual tropes usually found at the centre of this genre. Clichés like the doomed romance, ageless wisdom from a person without any real life experience, the almost painfully stoic forbearance of a ridiculously cruel fate—are either subverted or ignored altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the film takes place in Rachel’s bedroom as she progresses through the various stages of her disease. This is a film that spends a lot of its time in rooms that are filled with the ephemera of their owners, and it is the reason why you are so important to the success or failure of this film, Gerald.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believed this movie. I believed the people, the places, the minute detail that informed each room—the little visual details that make up someone’s life as they grope toward some kind of understanding of who they are, and what they care about. Those details were all up there, on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an interesting nod to Michael Gondry (especially his &lt;em&gt;Be Kind, Rewind&lt;/em&gt;) that anchored the film and these characters for me. It implied a particular sensibility and gave the audience a through line that smartly managed to connect almost all of the characters. It is those kinds of touches, along with some strong supporting performances (especially Molly Shannon and Nick Offerman) and a good script. These, plus quiet and assured direction from first timer Alfonso Gomez-Rejon, all raise this film far above what could’ve been just a hackneyed tear-jerker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was the closing scene and a discovery that Greg makes in one of your rooms, a moment whose seed was planted in such a clever way early in the film, a moment so well executed and thoughtful that it elevated this film from good to memorable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was one of those small details, hiding in plain sight, that only means something if you bother to look.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice work, Gerald.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/1/me-and-earl-and-the-dying-girl.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/6/1/me-and-earl-and-the-dying-girl.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Poltergeist</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/poltergeist</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Steven Spielberg, “Story By” Credit, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;This is a milestone in your career – the first time one of your films has ever been re-made. The proposition must have felt… otherworldly. Someone comes along and tells you they can reconnect with a long deceased property and bring it back to life. You were probably confused and skeptical. Could it really be done? Surely these hucksters were only looking to make a buck. But your confusion probably gave way to curiosity, then suspense, culminating with: “Sure, why not give it a try. It can’t hurt, right?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it can. It can hurt a lot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director Gil Kenan’s &lt;em&gt;Poltergeist&lt;/em&gt; almost makes the first film worse by association. That said, I’m not someone who holds the original film from 1982 on a pedestal. I saw it for the first time three or four years ago, well past its best-before date, though I enjoyed the film’s attention to small character detail and world-building, not to mention the patience in storytelling. You can certainly take credit for that. Even your original inspiration – the now all-too-familiar image of a young child being demonically seduced by a television screen, which has almost spawned its own horror sub-genre – is something I could still appreciate. Not to mentionthe film having some great in-camera effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But stacked kitchen chairs don’t pack the same punch they used to. So it’s understandable that a studio would want to capitalize on the name and “update” the story and effects for a new generation.  But they couldn’t have done so in a more half-assed way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First to blame might be the lead casting. Sam Rockwell is a fine actor in many roles, but his sarcastic and detached persona is completely at odds with the film’s tone once the plasma hits the fan. If his father character can’t get visibly worked up about his daughter being sucked into a television, why the hell should I? Rockwell probably behaves as the script requires – we’ve all seen this story before, so let’s just get past it to the all-important action beats – but the film is infinitely worse as a result. His jump from dismissive doubter to “well okay, time to just deal with it” feels like it mirrors the way you probably approached the remake in the first place. No wonder you came to mind so much watching the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s surely not because of any of the film’s technical accomplishments. Once we go into the parallel universe (well before that, actually), I had completely checked out of the story. Trees attack, dolls jump on faces, and arms reach out of gunk in the floor - but none of it is handled with an ounce of conviction. Making the film competent-looking just isn’t enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you didn’t direct the original, but you did you did come up with the original concept, plus you have a screenwriting and producing credit. So I assume you had some control over this new film’s existence. You were smart enough not to take another producer credit, lest you shoulder some responsibility for the mess that’s now on screen, but still I lay the blame for this insulting resurrection at your feet. You nuked the TV – even at arm’s length.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/26/poltergeist.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/26/poltergeist.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Tomorrowland</title>
				<image>
  				<url>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/tomorrowland.jpg</url>
        </image>
				<description>Dear Brad Bird and Damon Lindelof, Writers, &lt;br /&gt;
  				&lt;p&gt;When your primary intention in making a film is advocating for a specific political viewpoint, you’re no longer making art, you’re making a piece of propaganda. That isn’t necessarily a negative. There is some Soviet-era cinema chock full of overt political intentions that works just fine. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland,&lt;/em&gt;  however, it is a poisonous way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your film concerns itself with our species’ impending, self-inflicted, apocalypse. More specifically, it is about how that apocalypse might be averted, if only those of us who still remember how to dream can find common cause. As an elevator pitch I have heard worse, but during the trip from the elevator to the screen it seems that the movie got “Lindeloffed”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Clooney and Britt Robertson (he is a broken, cranky, inventor genius, she is a young, cranky, inventor genius) don’t ever connect with each other, or the audience. And the story itself is poorly told, relying on hackneyed plot devices and almost cartoonishly one-dimensional character types. These are just the most obvious indications of how &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland&lt;/em&gt; was influenced by a man who once wrote &lt;em&gt;Nash Bridges&lt;/em&gt; episodes. (I’m looking at you Damon.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also true—at least for you, Brad—that most of your earlier movies were already teetering on the edge of this kind of polemic scolding. &lt;em&gt;Iron Giant&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Incredibles&lt;/em&gt; especially weren’t particularly subtle about their political leanings—a weird mix of exceptionalism and finger wagging about the dangers of the Military Industrial Complex. They were redeemed by their charm and an earnest commitment to story that muted some of the more irritating evangelizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most egregious example of &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland&lt;/em&gt;’s failure as an entertainment is how transparent its creator’s intentions are. Every beat of the story is telegraphed in a way that makes the whole project inevitable, and in the dullest way possible. It’s a tricky enough thing to lace a story with ‘meaning’, but when half the writing team is someone responsible for things like &lt;a href=&quot;/content/2012/6/12/prometheus.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prometheus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cowboys and Aliens&lt;/em&gt; it becomes an impossible task. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another irritating byproduct of this kind of clunky narrative is that the characters flatten out and become gossamer thin. What comes out of their mouths is driven by expositional need. There is no depth to their portrayal because they are just mouthpieces, rather than people with their own inherent contradictions and idiosyncrasies. Even Tomorrowland itself is less an aspirational destination than it is a leaden and uni-dimensional MacGuffin that drives the plot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Laurie is the only one of the cast that manages to imbue his character with something resembling complexity and that is because, like all British actors, he can say one thing while very clearly meaning something else entirely. Every other character is little more than a wind-up automaton. Except the robot—who is, oddly, the most unpredictable character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland’s&lt;/em&gt; failure may have been inevitable in some ways. I remember reading one critique of &lt;em&gt;The Incredibles&lt;/em&gt; that pointed out its could be read as a little authoritarian and elitist. I scoffed but it was a scoff that secretly lacked conviction. Unfortunately, in this film those minor themes have become pre-eminent. In fact, &lt;em&gt;Tomorrowland&lt;/em&gt; is so weirdly upside down that Hugh Laurie gives a lengthy speech in the third act of the film—a monologue that is supposed to be his manifesto of E.V.I.L.—that turns out to be the most heartfelt, genuine, and true moment in the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the movie concludes with an overtly manipulative visual that looks like a mash-up of a Socialist Realist Poster and a Benetton ad from the early 2000s. It felt like a moment born in a boardroom much more than an earnest expression of hope. And there is nothing worse than subverting genuine hopefulness in the aid of cynical ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a lot of splainin’ to do, Mr. Lindelof and Mr. Bird&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/22/tomorrowland.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/22/tomorrowland.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
