<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Captive</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have one big question for you: was the use of flashbacks and flash-forwards in &lt;em&gt;The Captive&lt;/em&gt; your idea? Or was it director Atom Egoyan&amp;#39;s? I&amp;#39;m curious to know whether this was part of the screenplay&amp;#39;s original structure, or if it was a choice made during post-production, mainly because it seems to be the most divisive aspect of the film. I can&amp;#39;t decide how I feel about it, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that telling the story this way forced me to think a little harder about what I was watching. This is not a criticism in and of itself, except that I&amp;#39;m not sure it was always necessary. Sometimes the temporal shifts felt like &amp;quot;a gimmick, a trick you didn&amp;#39;t need&amp;quot; (like Ryan Reynolds and his young daughter so aptly discuss during the scene right before she disappears).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet there&amp;#39;s also serious confusion surrounding important plot points and when they actually take place. &lt;em&gt;(SPOILER ALERT!)&lt;/em&gt; It takes a long time, for instance, to reveal &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; Nicole, the detective played by Rosario Dawson, was actually kidnapped. This is the focus of the first scene of the film, but only actually happens last, chronologically - and this reveal feels anticlimactic after all the tension of trying to place it within the correct sequence of events, especially since it&amp;#39;s only a subplot to Cassandra&amp;#39;s disappearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, after I&amp;#39;d finished the film, when I really thought about it, this story device reminded me of the way my mind works when I obsess about something, thinking about it to the point of being overwhelmed, jumping from detail to memory to detail in no specific order while trying to figure out why something bad happened, something over which I ultimately had no control. So if that&amp;#39;s the feeling you were going for - a feeling of tense, OCD-like worry - then kudos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I enjoyed the film, but can&amp;#39;t quite figure out how I feel about this method of storytelling. Was it a gimmick you didn&amp;#39;t need, or a great trick for helping us empathize with the characters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diane Carol Harder&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/the-captive.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/the-captive.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Nightcrawler</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;That first clap you heard when the screening was over? That was me. And the sigh of relief right afterwards? That was me, too. I was waiting to find the film at this year&amp;#39;s festival that I&amp;#39;d flip over, and I finally did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearless and fascinating characters, a gripping plot, biting satire, a wicked sense of humor—&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; almost feels like this year&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Spring Breakers&lt;/em&gt; ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/28/spring-breakers.html&quot;&gt;high praise, indeed&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the opening scene, Dan Gilroy, in his directorial debut, makes a statement that anything can and will happen. Jake Gyllenhaal takes his creepiness to just the right places in this film about a man who&amp;#39;s looking for a job – any job, really – that will suit his yet-to-be-defined skills and bald-faced ambition. Needless to say, he finds something he&amp;#39;s rather perfect for. My spoiler-phobic instincts allowed me to experience every moment with complete surprise, and I was swept away by the excitement. Now I&amp;#39;m turning all my enthusiasm into word-of-mouth buzz, so people can hopefully avoid the terribly revealing trailer for a film that goes way-too-deep into the third act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People should just trust me – and you – and check out this film. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-4-nightcrawler.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-4-nightcrawler.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Manglehorn</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This might not be fair, but I&amp;#39;m getting a bit tired of all the gloomy character dramas dominating this year&amp;#39;s line-up. I understand why actors are drawn to stories that prioritize the &amp;quot;who&amp;quot; of a story over the &amp;quot;what&amp;quot;, but as an audience member, I&amp;#39;m starting to crave a good, juicy, vigorous plot. Sadly, that&amp;#39;s not the case with &lt;em&gt;Manglehorn&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Gordon Green has made a return to the serious side of things with a movie about an old curmudgeon forced to soften up in his twilight years ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-2014-day-two.html#st-vincent&quot;&gt;sound familiar&lt;/a&gt;?). He&amp;#39;s a romantic who can&amp;#39;t get over a lost love. So much so that he&amp;#39;s completely oblivious to the charms of the new woman in his life, played by Holly Hunter. The film is small in scale, but not without some charming moments (like a spontaneous musical outburst in a bank), and one strangely ambitious transition shot of a highway traffic pile-up (which probably cost the film half its budget). But aside from these nice flourishes, there&amp;#39;s not a whole lot to get excited about—with the exception of Holly Hunter, of course, who the festival (and the world) can always use a little more of.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-3-manglehorn.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-3-manglehorn.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Kahlil Gibran&#39;s The Prophet</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The idea of an animated feature based on &lt;em&gt;The Prophet&lt;/em&gt;, Kahlil Gibran&amp;#39;s collection of poetic essays, was enough to spark my curiosity while selecting my festival fare this year. Though a few lines and passages from the book have stayed with me over the years, I&amp;#39;m not really one for poetry. It doesn&amp;#39;t &amp;#39;come alive&amp;#39; for me very easily. But today was the exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part poetry reading, part art gallery tour, part Yo Yo Ma concert, the film compiles chapters from the book into animated segments, each rendered by different artists. All of this is framed around the central narrative of a young girl who befriends a poet and political prisoner. That said poet is voiced by Liam Neeson was, admittedly, another huge draw for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gibran&amp;#39;s text leaps to life in vivid colour, and my concern of too many things being attempted at once was soon forgotten. I realized it was best to simply succumb to the film&amp;#39;s interweaving elements, absorb the richness of the imagery and sound, and process it all afterwards. Although the main narrative is initially weak compared to the individual segments, it builds into a thoroughly moving conclusion, leaving me, admittedly, a little teary-eyed as I emerged from the theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if you happen to know who I need bribe to get Liam Neeson to come to my house and read me poetry, please, hook a girl up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-2-kahlil-gibrans-the-prophet.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-2-kahlil-gibrans-the-prophet.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Second Chance</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Susanne Bier&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;A Second Chance&lt;/em&gt; was perhaps a bleak choice to kick off my TIFF 2014 selections, but it set the bar pretty high. Nikolaj Coster-Waldau plays a policeman who does something drastic and inadvisable when tragedy strikes at home. Though my viewing companion was desperate for even a few moments of levity, I was waiting for the film to veer off into overwrought melodrama which, thankfully, it didn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any story centered upon the endangerment or harming of children elicits an intensely visceral response, with little room or patience for nuance. Care is taken to present the character&amp;#39;s actions while underscoring their vulnerabilities, commanding compassion from the viewer rather than revulsion. Full credit goes to Bier for the restraint and sensitivity with which she treats the subject and her characters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-1-a-second-chance.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-1-a-second-chance.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Six</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Tuesday, September 9.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-2014-day-six.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-2014-day-six.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>An Eye for Beauty</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a bad sign when Canadian icon Denys Arcand has a new film at your festival and it&amp;#39;s a) not being talked about, and b) playing here after already having a theatrical run in Quebec. Considering this is only his second film since the Oscar-winning &lt;em&gt;The Barbarian Invasions&lt;/em&gt;, it seems crazy that Arcand has been relegated to an afterthought on the festival circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an idea why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Eye For Beauty&lt;/em&gt; covers many of the same themes that Arcand explored so well in &lt;em&gt;The Decline of the American Empire&lt;/em&gt; - young intellectuals sitting around tables and freely discussing their outlook on art and debauchery - only this time, he&amp;#39;s a generation removed from his subjects. It&amp;#39;s missing real insight on what young professionals experience today, and displays none of the energy or pathos from his earlier work. The film largely comes across as a loveless and detached effort, and apart from the stilted English-speaking scenes, where the actors struggle to find a natural rhythm, it&amp;#39;s not without some merit. But it&amp;#39;s a film that fits in the lower half of Arcand&amp;#39;s work, and one that reveals he may be less a great filmmaker than a filmmaker who has made a few great films. Though that&amp;#39;s the case for many auteurs – especially in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-postcard-3-an-eye-for-beauty%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-postcard-3-an-eye-for-beauty%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Foxcatcher</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Some films feel important from the very first frame. &lt;em&gt;Foxcatcher&lt;/em&gt;, with its dreamy slow motion historical footage, and sparse soundtrack, is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After winning best director at the Cannes Film Festival, Bennett Miller&amp;#39;s new film was an obvious choice for this year&amp;#39;s line-up. It doesn&amp;#39;t hurt that it packs some diverse star power with Channing Tatum, Mark Ruffalo and Steve Carrell. The story of Olympic gold medal wrestler Mark Schultz&amp;#39;s relationship with billionaire John du Pont gets a treatment closer to &lt;em&gt;Capote&lt;/em&gt; than _Moneyball _(Miller&amp;#39;s two other directorial efforts, also based on true stories). The film is less interested in giving us information than atmosphere, with cold colours and restrained dialogue.The only real flourish is Carrell&amp;#39;s elongated nose, but even that quickly feels of service to the bigger story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an accomplished film that&amp;#39;s worthy of the hype, but the buzz is more about meeting (fairly high) expectations than delivering a real showstopper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-postcard-2-foxcatcher.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-postcard-2-foxcatcher.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mommy</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I love you for showcasing films like this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I get jealous because Xavier Dolan is only 25, and already has 5 feature films to his name (all of which have been at TIFF). It makes me question what I&amp;#39;ve been doing with my life so far, but at the same time, he also makes me incredibly proud to be Canadian.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dolan is brilliant because he does not try to imitate Hollywood, or try to tell traditional 3-act stories. Instead, he creates worlds that are slightly different than our own, then sets very real, three-dimensional characters within them to see what will happen.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can hardly wait to see what kind of work he&amp;#39;ll be doing in ten years&amp;#39; time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diane Carol Harder&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-postcard-1-mommy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-postcard-1-mommy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Five</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Monday, September 8.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-2014-day-five%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/8/tiff-2014-day-five%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
