<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
<<<<<<< HEAD
				<title>Yes, Nightcrawler is the Best Film of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Fellow Critics,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This letter is addressed to you, but, admittedly, it’s an attempt to validate my own convictions. I wish I could have leaned back, stretched out my arms in self-satisfied comfort, and submitted my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/31/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;Top Films of 2014&lt;/a&gt; with the same confidence &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/1/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2013.html&quot;&gt;(and perfect photo) as I did in 2013&lt;/a&gt;. But that hasn’t been the case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I knew &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/13/the-act-of-killing.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Act of Killing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was unequivocally the most impressive, entertaining, and important cinematic accomplishment of the year. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has garnered similar praise from many of you this year, yet I can’t comply in calling it the best of the best. True, Richard Linklater’s 12-year character study is brilliant, poignant, and deceivingly simple, but I left the theatre without that instant appreciation. It took a few days for the film’s lackadaisical rhythm and fleeting preciousness worked me over. My own son is quickly growing before my eyes, so the film certainly has a special place in my heart—but it’s only second place on my list. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I almost didn’t trust &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/9/tiff-postcard-4-nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;my initial reaction to &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Toronto International Film Festival. I was giddy when the credits rolled, both thrilled and relieved to have found a film I could enthusiastically champion. The experience was all the more surprising since I walked in to the theater knowing only two things: the title and the star. The only promotional still frame I saw of Jake Gyllenhaal – eyes bulging, arm carefully outstretched with a flashlight fixed on the door of a van – was enough to get me curious about what awaited. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my spoilerphobic delight, that particular frame comes in first scene of the film. As Gyllenhaal’s Lou Bloom is caught sneaking around an industrial compound by a security guard, we get the first of many strange, stilted interactions with authority figures. Appearing to acquiesce to the man’s demands, he suddenly notices the guard’s wristwatch and pounces on him like a wild animal. He becomes a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Force Majeure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; more revealing than a controlled avalanche. And in that moment, the rules of the universe are established immediately: if you want something, take it. Consequences are a burden of the weak. And, in the case of the guard’s fate, never even revealed. Within the first five minutes, I felt a rush of excitement. Anything could happen in this film. It’s a thrill I rarely receive in today’s sequel-heavy, reboot-filled, regurgitation-plagued movie landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a master class of narrative clarity and character ambiguity. As a seasoned Hollywood scriptwriter, Gilroy knows all the beats of a studio script and gleefully undermines them at every turn. There’s no clashing of what the hero wants vs. what he needs. No sympathetic background to get us invested in his character. No mid-point turn or all-is-lost moment of self-doubt. Gilroy doesn’t&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savethecat.com/&quot;&gt;save the cat&lt;/a&gt;—he strangles it, and doesn’t sacrifice a thing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we need to know about Lou Bloom is revealed through action or inference. His dialogue is all lifted from corporate HR manuals and every human interaction is purely transactional. He’s the living embodiment of &lt;em&gt;The Corporation&lt;/em&gt;. Not even Jordan Belfort in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/7/wolf-of-wall-street.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; could outmaneuver this coyote of the Sunset Strip. The biggest difference between the two men, in fact, is not their occupations, but rather the decade in which they exist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/28/spring-breakers.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spring Breakers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2013, &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; is the 2014 film that best taps into the Millennial experience. The pursuit of happiness is exaggerated to expose the depraved benchmarks of those ideals. There are no shades of grey along the way to success, only neon signs, black lights, and hot red cars. Lie, steal, cheat, sabotage, kill—just don’t lose focus. It’s the only way to get ahead. You will be justified and rewarded. The audience will even be on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sure as hell was. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My unexpected support for Bloom’s sociopathic drive came, in part, from 2014 marking my first year as a full-time freelancer. The otherwise abstract notion of the “Economy” has had a very real effect on my quality of life. The deck always feels stacked against you, and working for almost nothing in order to “establish a business relationship” (as Bloom agrees to when selling stolen copper piping), is not an introductory step, but a &lt;em&gt;Groundhog Day&lt;/em&gt; reality in an industry that’s struggling to survive. Not just in creating media content, but the very spirit of entrepreneurialism. &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedissolve.com/reviews/1181-nightcrawler/&quot;&gt;just a modern version of &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; satirizing local journalism. It’s a critique of the entire capitalist system. Lou is a wired intelligence playing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with the human race; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/the-imitation-game.html&quot;&gt;an enigma&lt;/a&gt; of the free market cracked by the Axis of Evil. To take a quote from Ridley’s Scott’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/12/exodus-gods-and-kings.html&quot;&gt;undeservingly derided &lt;em&gt;Exodus: Gods and Kings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: “That’s the irony, isn’t it? The people most suited to attaining power are the least suiting to having it.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most films, Rick the Intern (played to perfection by Riz Ahmed) would have served as an audience surrogate to help us see through the madness; a Bud Fox to Bloom’s Gordon Gekko. Instead, Rick is a disposable partner whose pink slip is a meager handful of blood-covered cash. But in the business world, them’s the breaks (or the lack-thereof, in the case of Lou’s rival). The high gear the film reaches in the third act gave me &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whiplash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It felt both earned and appropriate. The implausibilities that &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.indiewire.com/criticwire/nightcrawler-reviews-taxi-driver-meets-network-20140906&quot;&gt;many argued&lt;/a&gt; over were completely irrelevant to me because the allegory was so strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what makes &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; so poignant. Lou Bloom is not a hero, he’s a victor. A tribute who not only survives the contemporary &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but learns to control them. The incongruous musical score by James Newton Howard underscores this triumph with synthesized fervor, playing more like a soundtrack in Bloom’s mind than a cue for tension to the audience. I never felt inspired by his amoral actions—but I did understand them. And that’s a mighty tall order for someone as contemptible as Lou Bloom. No film has used black comedy and biting social commentary to to such an effect since &lt;em&gt;A Clockwork Orange&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again I say, with bolstered confidence: yes, &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt; is the best film of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/yes-nightcrawler-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/yes-nightcrawler-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
=======
>>>>>>> FETCH_HEAD
				<title>The Interview</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Deep down, you knew that &lt;em&gt;The Interview&lt;/em&gt; would eventually be released. You had to. Sure, you illegally leaked embarrassing emails, financial statements, and several upcoming Sony Pictures films, but even when victory seemed possible, it wasn’t. Your disgusting bluff about attacking cinemas that screened &lt;em&gt;The Interview&lt;/em&gt; was mercifully undermined by an arthouse alliance of 300+ independent theatres that stepped up at the last minute. And since the film’s on-schedule release at Christmas, all talk about you has disappeared. Thank fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to focus on the real fart fest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth Rogan and Evan Goldberg are no strangers to scorn. However, it’s usually from middle-aged critics and jaded Gen Xers who maxed out on the pair’s bromance humour after &lt;em&gt;Superbad&lt;/em&gt;. Although the two Canadian ex-pats have written some horrible comedies (&lt;em&gt;Drillbit Taylor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Watch&lt;/em&gt;), their co-directorial debut &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/12/this-is-the-end.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This Is The End&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was very well-received. So penning a politically relevant end-of-the-world showdown in &lt;em&gt;The Interview&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t the ambitious leap it may have initially seemed. It was the plot about a TV host and his producer being recruited by the CIA to assassinate North Korea’s leader Kim Jong-un, that ignited a real-life global incident that no one expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that, assholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully now we can forget the unnecessary democratic importance you gave the film. By bringing more attention to the title than it could have ever earned on it’s own, many people patriotically paid to download the film, only to realize that it was just another comedy, packed with far more homoeroticism than activism. This seemed to skew a lot of the early reviews, but personally, I thought it was pretty much right on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the film, of course, contains drug montages, naked chicks and poop jokes, it does at least qualify as a beginners guide to dictatorship. A Potemkin village turns James DeFranco’s character into a Dennis Rodman-esque apologist for the regime. Myth’s about Jong-un’s divine right to rule are used as the butt (hole-less) of jokes but paint him as a pitiful man rather than powerful monster. And in a late confrontation, actual stats are used about the millions of people starving in the country and living without basic human rights. Nothing you can’t find from the first few paragraphs of the country’s Wikipedia page, but still – it’s in there. And the film is better for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving at a solid clip, the film manages more than a few laughs from its (apparently) brazen premise. Even the aforementioned tropes – especially the drug sequences – are kept mercifully short and used to energize the film rather than indulge in tired psychedelic imagery. But here’s the real kicker – Kim Jong-un, or rather Randall Park’s portrayal of the man, is the real star of the show. By making the man more adorable than abhorrent, the filmmakers imbue a humanity that the real leader probably doesn’t deserve. Which makes the final confrontation all the more impactful and satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But alas, it’s only a stupid movie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/the-interview.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/the-interview.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Wild</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You make your mark early, as &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt; opens on a craggy California slope. A young woman, her skin burnished by the sun and streaked with dirt, sits beside her oversized backpack . She pulls off her boots and socks to reveal blistered, bloody feet, skin rubbed raw, toenails barely attached. What happens next informs the tone of the film. For anyone who thought they were coming to see a glamourously windblown actress trekking across a softly focused vista, the first scene issues a harsh warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ain’t gonna be pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the four years since the death of her mother, Cheryl Strayed goes from promising college student to a heroin and sex addict who effectively drives away those closest to her. In the summer of 1995, she sets out to hike 1100 miles of the Pacific Crest Trail, which stretches across several mountain ranges from Mexico to Canada. A novice hiker alone on the PCT, Cheryl will encounter physical and emotional obstacles unlike anything she has ever faced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the first time you’ve had to ugly up an A-list actor, nor is this the first time you’ve worked with &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;’s Canadian director, Jean-Marc Vallée. You won an Oscar for convincing audiences that Matthew McConnaughey and Jared Leto were wasting away from AIDS in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/19/dallas-buyers-club.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dallas Buyer’s Club.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This isn’t even the first time you worked on a movie about someone walking alone in the wilderness. On &lt;em&gt;Into The Wild&lt;/em&gt; you made Emile Hirsch’s Christopher McCandless’ malnutrition seem painfully real. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/articles/arts/culturebox/2014/12/wild_and_into_the_wild_cheryl_strayed_and_christopher_mccandless_compared.single.html&quot;&gt;The comparisons between &lt;em&gt;Into The Wild&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are inevitable and not altogether unwarranted. But the idealistic McCandless was trying to find himself. Cheryl just wants to be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What brings Cheryl to the PCT isn’t initially clear. Even she isn’t entirely sure why she’s there. The trail isn’t a metaphor for her life. It’s not redemption. But for almost a hundred days it is her closest friend and fiercest enemy. Cinematographer Yves Bélanger films it as such, equal parts stunning and humbling, serene and relentless. When Cheryl dreads each monotonous footstep, so do we. When she takes a moment to appreciate the majesty of the Sierras, we do too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheryl’s past haunts her throughout her journey. Vallée uses razor-sharp cuts as flashbacks - Cheryl having sex, injecting heroin, fighting with a man - which eventually become whole scenes as she gets further into the trail. He saves the tenderness for the flashbacks of Cheryl watching her mother singing and dancing, or driving her and her brother away from their abusive father. One is a set of memories Cheryl hopes to exorcise, the other she is desperate to hold onto. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your job was to believably transition Cheryl from college kid to junkie to weary traveller, and luckily Reese Witherspoon was your canvas. Witherspoon (who also produced) carries this film like her “Monster” – the enormous backpack Cheryl hauls across the backcountry. This is the kind of role that screams “Oscar bait!” but thankfully Reese’s performance never does. Though Cheryl was 26 when she hiked the PCT, Witherspoon delivers a cynical vulnerability that perhaps younger actresses might not have done as convincingly. Witherspoon’s Cheryl is the kind of complicated female lead we rarely see onscreen; a frustrating and reckless mess with nothing to lose. She is not easy to root for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vallée is careful enough to maintain the film’s vast scope without sacrificing intimacy, and smart enough to trust that an actor of Witherspoon’s talent doesn’t need much accoutrement. He uses the Simon &amp;amp; Garfunkel song “El Condor Paso” as a powerful yet unobtrusive leitmotif, its lyrics “If I could” perfectly echo Cheryl’s inner monologue. She could quit, she could keep going. She - and the audience - is never quite sure what she will do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through you, Cheryl’s face and body tell her story. Dark under-eye circles, dried blood and fading bruises fill in the blanks that Nick Hornby’s mercifully underwritten script omits. The patches of inflamed skin on Cheryl’s back and hips, rubbed raw from the weight of Monster, scab and toughen as she adjusts to carrying her burden. Facing demons and making amends is painful and it isn’t pretty, but when stripped to the bone, there’s beauty to be found in the fight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Into the Woods</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0589174/?ref_=ttfc_fc_cr497&quot;&gt;CV is amazing&lt;/a&gt;. You’ve brought lions, tigers, bears, and pretty much every other man-eating predator to Hollywood’s biggest film sets (which explains your upcoming consultant role on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0369610/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jurassic World&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Yet that’s not why you were hired on &lt;em&gt;Into the Woods&lt;/em&gt;. Rather than actually bringing something authentic to the screen, it seems the filmmakers wanted you to create a passable facsimile of an authentically powerful auditory experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Now I get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t waste time critiquing the singing voices of the stars, which, by-and-large, are perfectly passable. Rob Marshall’s film adaptation of the Broadway classic (of which I confess, I’m not a fan) is lacking in much more egregious ways. Still, the stage origins are painfully obvious: from the clumsy staging of actors (always “accidentally” running into each other), to the confined framing of the physical environment itself (padded constantly by budget-saving fog and shadows). All of this is expected and forgiven in live theatre. On screen it felt like one big cheat after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the giants. And the wolf sequence. And a certain death scene off a cliff.  None of which embraced the power of cinema to immerse, impress or enhance the storytelling experience. All Marshall does is repeat the stage beats while keeping his camera at the same disadvantage as a seated audience member. There are occasional exceptions, but none of the ingenuity that Marshall employed to elevate &lt;em&gt;Chicago&lt;/em&gt; from hit theatre to Oscar-winner is apparent here – especially when you consider the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, let’s talk about that material. When Stephen Sondheim penned &lt;em&gt;Into the Woods&lt;/em&gt;, the concept of what happens after happily-ever-after was considered nothing short of brilliant. Today, reviving fairy tales has become as tired as rebooting superhero franchises. Every princess story is getting a rethink, so saving that twist for the last half of the film means the narrative feels like it’s on auto-pilot for the first half. Had the film treatment been interpreted as joyously campy, or self-consciously satirical, that might have been okay. But instead, all we have to carry us through the familiar story beats are Sondheim’s quirky music and his aversion to catchy melodies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the man is considered nothing short of a musical messiah in the theatre community. But I can’t help feel as though his musicals are for people who are sick of musicals. That might explain why not a single song was stuck in my head after leaving the theatre, other than my trying to rationalize the tacky instances of rhyming the same word with itself (&lt;em&gt;Witches can be right. Giants can be good. You decide what’s right. You decide what’s good&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fault may be mine for wanting &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/1/2/les-miserables.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Les Misérables&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gravitas in a story that was never designed as such, but I still found myself vastly preferring the mediocre remake of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/20/annie.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; over this. I would have much preferred the money going into better effects than bigger stars. Nobody needed to see Johnny Depp’s knee-jerk interpretation of The Wolf – that kind of casting is about as obvious and lazy as, well, rhyming a word with itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, those crashing tree sounds you created were as crackling as we would expect in any film. But as the old saying goes – if I hadn’t been there to here it, I could have believed it all never happened.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/2/into-the-woods.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/2/into-the-woods.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>C. Redmond&#39;s Top Films of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you read the site frequently, you’ll know that we are home to B-movie aficionados, superhero apologists, and film school theorists alike. Read a few reviews and you’ll quickly get to know who has a soft spot for everything Canadian, and who refuses to bestow perfect praise on anything &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet we did attempt to create an authoritative Dear Cast and Crew list of the year’s top films. We thought of everything: democratic voting, socialistic slotting, even secret autocracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of it worked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each review is written from the perspective of an individual critic, and subject to their own personal criteria for what it worth seeing (and what isn’t). My list is no different. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing just over 200 films this year, here are the highlights. You can judge me accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Top 14 Films of 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;Boyhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html&quot;&gt;Whiplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html&quot;&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html&quot;&gt;Force Majeure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/6/edge-of-tomorrow.html&quot;&gt;Edge of Tomorrow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mistaken for Strangers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/7/mommy.html&quot;&gt;Mommy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/3/the-overnighters.html&quot;&gt;The Overnighters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;Under The Skin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/20/blue-ruin.html&quot;&gt;Blue Ruin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/28/nymphomanic-vol-1-and-2.html&quot;&gt;Nymphomaniac Parts 1 and 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Ida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/1/only-lovers-left-alive.html&quot;&gt;Only Lovers Left Alive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Ten Favorite Canadian Films&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Mommy&lt;/em&gt; memorial list)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/12/afflicted.html&quot;&gt;Afflicted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-postcard-2-tu-dors-nicole.html&quot;&gt;Tu dors Nicole&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/11/enemy.html&quot;&gt;Enemy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/10/tiff-postcard-1-corbo.html&quot;&gt;Corbo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bang Bang Baby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/the-f-word.html&quot;&gt;The F Word&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trailer Park Boys: Don’t Legalize It&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloody Knuckles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/the-captive%20copy.html&quot;&gt;The Captive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Special mention – Had &lt;em&gt;The Dirties&lt;/em&gt; (2013) been eligible (I didn’t catch it until this year), the film would have topped this list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Surprisingly Good&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/10/locke.html&quot;&gt;Locke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/12/robocop.html&quot;&gt;Robocop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/7/the-lego-movie.html&quot;&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Superior Sequels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/19/22-jump-street.html&quot;&gt;22 Jump Street&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/12/dawn-of-the-planet-of-the-apes.html&quot;&gt;Dawn of the Planet of the Apes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/21/planes-fire-rescue.html&quot;&gt;Planes: Fire &amp;amp; Rescue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unapologetically Awesome&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/16/godzilla.html&quot;&gt;Godzilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;The Raid 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overrated Everywhere Else&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/24/birdman-or-the-unexpected-virtue-of-ignorance.html&quot;&gt;Birdman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/12/life-itself.html&quot;&gt;Life Itself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Immigrant&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Didn’t Disappoint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/13/how-to-train-your-dragon-2.html&quot;&gt;How to Train Your Dragon 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html&quot;&gt;Dumb and Dumber To&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/9/gone-girl.html&quot;&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/a&gt;*&lt;br&gt;
*Yes, I acknowledge &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html&quot;&gt;the irony&lt;/a&gt; of listing the film here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extra Special Indies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/4/obvious-child.html&quot;&gt;Obvious Child&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Guest&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html&quot;&gt;The Babadook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid at All Costs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin City: A Dame to Kill For&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/9/a-million-ways-to-die-in-the-west.html&quot;&gt;A Million Ways to Die in the West&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-3-revenge-of-the-green-dragons.html&quot;&gt;Revenge of the Dragons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/20/open-windows.html&quot;&gt;Open Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
They Came Together&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/19/devils-knot.html&quot;&gt;Devil’s Knot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 20:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Jared Young&#39;s Top Films of 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s true. Our attempts to compile a comprehensive, democratic list of Dear Cast and Crew’s favorite films of 2014 was scrapped after an epic email thread replete with name-calling and threats of physical harm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is to be expected. The disagreements between our staff of writers has expressed itself in all &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/13/the-cabin-in-the-woods-1.html&quot;&gt;sorts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/4/13/the-cabin-in-the-woods-2.html&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/16/star-trek-into-darkness.html&quot;&gt;wonderfully&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/6/out-of-darkness-revisiting-the-wrath-of-khan.html&quot;&gt;passive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/9/skyfall.html&quot;&gt;aggressive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/17/five-reasons-skyfall-fell-flat.html&quot;&gt;ways&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/summer-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;over&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html&quot;&gt;the years&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the spirit of healthy rhetorical debate (and petty one-upsmanship), here is an alternative to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/31/c-redmonds-top-films-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;C. Redmond’s Top Films of 2014&lt;/a&gt;. While I haven’t seen quite as many films this year, the ones that resonated represent a broad range of genres, budgets, and artistic ambitions. From an indie thriller that channels early John Carpenter, to a blockbuster animated flick adapted from a building toy, the year’s best flicks were as diverse (and satisfying) as any in recent memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(But let’s be honest. Christopher and I agree on a lot of these films. Ultimately, this alternate list is just an excuse to lavish more praise on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/a&gt;, which was the catalyst of the aforementioned slander and abuse).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Top 10 Films of 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol reversed&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;Interstellar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;The Raid 2: Berendal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html&quot;&gt;The Babadook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;Boyhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/20/blue-ruin.html&quot;&gt; Blue Ruin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;Under The Skin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/7/the-lego-movie.html&quot;&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Guest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 19:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/jared-youngs-top-films-of-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/jared-youngs-top-films-of-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Imitation Game</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In your lifetime, you were as impenetrable and enigmatic as the oracular machine you are most famous for reverse engineering. &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt; is a relentlessly competent attempt to understand you as a person while also deconstructing that pivotal moment in history when you managed to break Nazi Germany’s most important code machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There it is, though—“relentlessly competent” sounds like half a compliment. And it is. There was something lacking in this film. It felt like a compromise between subjects: the endlessly fascinating story of how Enigma was cracked, and your very personal trials and tribulations. Both are worth an hour and fifty-four minutes of screen time, and both are certainly well-represented. But neither felt like they were investigated and explained in a way that was anything more than perfunctory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the manner that some biopics feel shallow despite the lead character eating-up all the available screen time, I felt cheated in some fundamental way at the end of this film. Here is one of the pivotal characters of the twentieth century, a singular person of real significance, yet I feel I know little more about him than if I had read a moderately competent 3000-word essay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s far too easy to second-guess something as fragile and complex as a feature film – especially one that takes on such a heady mix of subjects – however, I really feel like something essential was lacking, some connection to who you were as a person, something more than just the tortured genius or shunned deviant. Part of the difficulty in adapting a story like yours is figuring out where to begin. Your history is essential to what you did as an adult, but that’s always a fraught exercise onscreen; flashbacks are too easily expressed as clunky backlighting. So often with historical biopics, we essentially get a highlight reel: names, dates, significant moments and interactions. To really succeed in the time allotted, a film requires a level of nuance that &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, while exquisitely shaped, doesn’t ascend to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more than most people, you deserve the cinematic equivalent of a long form essay. You are someone worthy of six-plus hours of screen-time. You require that depth of characterization and backstory. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html&quot;&gt;Strong cases have been made&lt;/a&gt; for how some subjects beg for the kind of depth you can only achieve with a mini-series, and I can’t think of a better example than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly the performances were adept, the cinematography lush but restrained. And there was little to complain about onscreen. I suppose it was what &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; there that irked me. I would have liked to have seen more of the essential you and your life and less of the highlight reel. Ultimately this was a safe, competent rendition of a life that deserved more than that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/the-imitation-game.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/30/the-imitation-game.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Unbroken</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Ideally, when navigating uncharted waters, there’s a team of experts guiding your every move. Otherwise, a seemingly routine mission can spiral out of control and set in motion a life-changing sequence of events. That’s what happened to Louis Zamperini during a rescue effort off the Pacific Coast in the Second World War. It could also have happened to second-time director Angelina Jolie, but she was smart (and lucky) enough to surround herself with some of the best in the business. People like you, Sean, who were looking out for her safety. &lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; for the safety of the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wise choice. And while you’re at it, why not bring in the Coen Brothers to write your script? And Roger Deakins to shoot your film? And William Goldenberg to edit it? That’s more than just “the safe thing to do”—in this case, it helped save the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zamperini was an unlikely hero before he went to war. As the child of non-English speaking Italian immigrants, he scrapped his way through small town bigotry before representing the United States as a long-distance runner at the 1936 Berlin Olympics. His incredible finish in the 5,000 meter race won him worldwide attention—and even a personal meeting with Adolf Hitler (though that scene is omitted from the film; Jolie must have decided it was safer to not have her hero seen shaking hands with the world’s vilest villain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the opening aerial shots – filmed with Deakins’ trademark confidence and perspective realism – we immediately get a sense of the scale and import of the story. The dialogue is sparse, never cute, and dials back much of the bravado that might have crept in (think &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/9/lone-survivor.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lone Survivor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Jolie herself has said that she would have never been drawn to that type of macho storytelling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shark attacks, on the other hand? Well, she dove right in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the film is at its best during the lost-at-sea storyline. The danger is more desperate and lonely, and there’s a cosmic cruelty that is detached from any political commentary. As a result, it amplifies every injustice suffered in the latter half of the film.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony, of course, might be that this is a very safe film for mainstream audiences to enjoy over the Christmas break. But, hey, the words “safe” and “cinema” are allowed to go together sometimes, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/29/unbroken.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/29/unbroken.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Night at the Museum: Secret of the Tomb</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Did you know? Could you see the fatigue? Did you spend more time than usual on set? Because from where I was sitting all I could see was a man who seemed emptied out. The word “bereft” and all that it implies was at the forefront of my mind every time he was onscreen. I didn’t love Robin Williams the same way &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/12/dear-robin.html&quot;&gt;many people seemed to&lt;/a&gt;. But I found myself getting pretty upset as I sat and watched his light going out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Night at the Museum: Secret of the Tomb&lt;/em&gt; is most notable for the fact that it’s one of the last films Robin Williams made before ending his life. Otherwise it is a pretty forgettable return to a franchise that is largely...well, forgettable. The whole gang (plus a Neanderthal version of Ben Stiller—don’t ask how that happens) head off to England to...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...never mind. It really isn’t important. There’s a MacGuffin about the moon and Ben Kingsley as Pharaoh and a tablet that looks like an Egyptian iPad, but that’s all just an excuse to change locations to the British Museum in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did the set feel different? In an industry that often eats its young as a matter of course, I sometimes wonder how reptilian you must become to manage. You might actually know, eh, Hugh? You’ve spent a lot of time as the invisible man on set. Your IMDB page reads like the CV of a Ricky Gervais character: Fair Goer (uncredited) &lt;em&gt;Philomena,&lt;/em&gt; Wealthy Gentleman (uncredited) &lt;em&gt;Parks and Recreation,&lt;/em&gt; Hospital visitor (uncredited) &lt;em&gt;Gangsta Granny.&lt;/em&gt; I can’t imagine the bad behavior and prima donna tantrums you must have witnessed (especially on &lt;em&gt;Gangsta Granny&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching this film, for me, was mostly an exercise in trying not to choke up every time Robin Williams appeared onscreen. It felt faintly ghoulish, to be honest; watching a person recently dead struggle through threadbare dialogue while trying to project anything but pathos. The kids in the theatre seemed to enjoy what was in front of them. So there’s that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a moment late in the film when Robin Williams, in the guise of Theodore Roosevelt, turns to Ben Stiller and gives him some advice about the best way to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment is so bursting with sad irony that both my wife and I actually started crying. Yet the children who surrounded us were happily unaware that anything other than a pause in the action was occurring. It was a surreal way to spend two hour so if you’re a parent who has any connection to Robin Williams as a performer, maybe it would be better to take the kids to &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6,&lt;/em&gt; or wait for &lt;em&gt;Into The Woods.&lt;/em&gt; I doubt anyone except the producers of _Night at the Museum: Secret of the Tomb will suffer for your choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for you Hugh, I hope you got to spend a little time with the man Robin Williams used to be—because the Robin Williams I saw up on the screen was the ghost of a person who has yet to pass.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/22/night-at-the-museum-secret-of-the-tomb.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/22/night-at-the-museum-secret-of-the-tomb.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Annie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was nine years old in 1982 when the original film adaptation of &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; came out. For girls my age, this was our &lt;em&gt;Frozen.&lt;/em&gt; We bought the books, the toys, and the cassette tapes. We drove our parents insane shout-singing “Hard-Knock Life” and “Tomorrow” in the backs of station wagons. No one owned VCRs yet – they were ridiculously expensive and roughly the size of a Datsun B210 – so we waited many months to finally see the movie again when it was released on Pay TV. Betamax? No—the one family that owned a Betamax was unceremoniously shunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry for my little nostalgic digression. I hope you were able to follow along despite my ancient technological references. I also hope that a few years from now, when the graphics you designed for the 2014 re-imagining of &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; are hilariously dated, that the story itself will still hold up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wouldn’t bet my vintage Swatch on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 21st Century Annie is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an orphan, as she reminds us throughout the film. She’s a foster kid. She lives in Harlem with her mean foster mom, Miss Hannigan, and five foster sisters, but continues to hold out hope that her real parents will come back for her someday. Annie is saved from an oncoming car by gruff telecom billionaire Will Stacks, who is lagging behind in the city’s mayoral race. Stacks’ handlers convince him to “foster” Annie to help improve his image with voters. While the arrangement starts out as a publicity stunt, Annie and Stacks eventually realize they’ve found the only family either of them has ever known. Their bond is tested when Annie’s supposed parents reappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is a major plot point in &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt;. Stacks’ campaign manager and Girl Friday are perpetually scanning websites to assess how their boss is being portrayed online. When a visit to a soup kitchen goes horribly wrong, the moment is re-played on screens large and small, and is even auto-tuned into a pop song on YouTube. Events happen at lightning speed, and you had to design a constant stream of graphics for Twitter, Google and major news sites. Of course, someone manages to film Stacks saving Annie and it “goes viral.”. In Stacks’ penthouse, a never-ending stream information and images is displayed on floor-to-ceiling screens. Annie can change the graphics in her room from unicorns and glitter to puppies and moonbeams. She chooses to sleep under a desk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say I blame her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1982 &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; is set in New York City during Prohibition, and the film embraces this era completely. The musical numbers reflect that golden age of Hollywood with Busby Berkeley-esque dance routines and over-the-top orchestration. The sheer number of grinning children, adults, and animals crammed into each scene could have only been managed by a director like John Huston. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; is contemporary and urban but feels strangely small—and not in an intimate way. Director Will Gluck missed many opportunities to scale up the song and dance sequences, opting to fill the empty spaces with your dizzying graphics (instead of actual people). Or maybe he thought repeating a flash-mob – like the one he staged for &lt;em&gt;Friends With Benefits&lt;/em&gt; – was just &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The updated songs – and even the originals – capture the film’s saccharine tone perfectly. What Quvenzhane Wallis lacks in vocal chops she makes up for with sheer positivity and charm. She’s the perfect choice for Annie. It would seem the entire cast was chosen less for their singing prowess and more for their bankability. Jamie Foxx can sing, but the fact that he sounds a little too much like R. Kelly doesn’t make his relationship with a young girl any less icky. Poor Cameron Diaz has the toughest shoes to fill. Carol Burnett was a force of nature as the original Miss Hannigan (for a master class in drunk singing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDkEXszYtdo&quot;&gt;see her version of “Little Girls”&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, Cameron isn’t a good enough singer or comedienne to inject the villainous Miss Hannigan with enough malice or pathos to make her as cartoonishly menacing as she needs be. For some reason her backstory involves being bitter at having been kicked out of C+C Music Factory before their first appearance on Arsenio—two references that aren’t getting any fresher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is to imply that you didn’t do a good job. On the contrary.Your detail-rich work is an accurate reflection of the ever-connected world we live in. But that world and its technology is evolving daily, and for a tech-heavy film that can be a liability. The best musicals don’t always have the most intricate librettos or the most elaborate art direction, but they do share one important quality: they’re timeless. &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; has some fun and clever moments – especially a scene involving a movie premiere and its product tie-ins – but it’s probably not going to be the kind of repeat-viewing hit that Sony was hoping for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, parents of &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/28/frozen.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-addicted kids. You’ll have to wait for a better musical to come along before your kids will finally Let It Go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/20/annie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/20/annie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
<<<<<<< HEAD
=======
			<item>
				<title>2014 Silver Stamps</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Readers,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chasing awards is a fool’s errand. Just when you think AIDS is the new cool, ALS comes along and throws a bucket of ice water (and quantum physics) on your head. The lesson? Keep it fresh. Up the ante. No one wants to be last year’s disease. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s our motto for the Silver Stamps. We can’t keep beating on the same ol’ &lt;em&gt;Man of Steel&lt;/em&gt; drum every year (though we would if we could). So here’s a brand-spanking-new list of winners and losers who helped define the last year in cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 2014 Awards&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Based on Good, Hard Science&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/19/particle-fever.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Particle Fever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Based on Good, Hard Fantasy&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/1/guardians-of-the-galaxy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Inspired by Cosmology&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/1/the-theory-of-everything.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Endorsed by Cosmologists&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Example of Why Chivalry is Dead&lt;/strong&gt; – Wes Bentley in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interstallar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Example of Why Sexism is Alive&lt;/strong&gt; – Every Character in &lt;em&gt;Sin City 2: A Dame to Kill For&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Unintentionally Meta Film in The Unofficial Year of Meta Films –&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/20/open-windows.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Windows&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trailer of the Year, Sponsored by Spoilerphobes Anonymous&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Red Band version)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Breakers Award for Most Conflicted Boner&lt;/strong&gt; – tie: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/28/nymphomanic-vol-1-and-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nymphomaniac&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under the Skin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Overlooked, Underseen, and Confusingly Marketed Film of the Year&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/6/edge-of-tomorrow.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edge of Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (aka. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Live. Die. Repeat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Man-Crush 2014&lt;/strong&gt; – Jake Gyllenhall for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/11/enemy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enemy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Inspiring Return to Form&lt;/strong&gt; – Jim Carrey in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dumb and Dumber To&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Runner Up: Keanu Reeves in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Depressing Return to Form&lt;/strong&gt; – Arnold Schwarzenegger in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/15/sabotage.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Runner Up: Michael Bay for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/27/transformers-age-of-extinction.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transformers: Age of Distinction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proving that Franchises Can Actually End:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/content/2014/12/17/the-hobbit-the-battle-of-the-five-armies.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hobbit: The Battle of the Five Armies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proving that Everything is Now a Franchise:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Inexplicably Improved Franchise&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/21/planes-fire-rescue.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planes: Fire &amp;amp; Rescue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Incongruous Musical Score&lt;/strong&gt; – James Newton Howard, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Prison Break Action Sequence:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/30/x-men-days-of-future-past.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;X-Men: Days of Future Past&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second-Best Prison Break Action Sequence&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raid 2:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Berendal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third-Best Prison Break Action Sequence:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/1/guardians-of-the-galaxy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst Sequel in a Year of Terrible Sequels:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Sequel in a Year of Great Sequels&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Jared Young: Osage County Award for Wildly Overpraising Sub-Par Cinema&lt;/strong&gt; (Presented by Christopher Redmond) – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trip To Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Man of Steel&lt;/em&gt; Award for Total Incompetence in Comic Book Adaptations:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Enjoyable Earworm:&lt;/strong&gt; “Everything is Awesome” from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/7/the-lego-movie.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Authentically Canadian Film:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/18/the-grand-seduction.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Grand Seduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst Faux-Canadian Film:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/16/tusk.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tusk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitchiest Heartthrob Performance of the Year:&lt;/strong&gt; Andrew Garfield in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Dead-Eyed Heartthrob Performance of the Year:&lt;/strong&gt; Aaron Taylor-Johnston in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/16/godzilla.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst Excuse For A Studio To Fund A Star’s Safari Vacation&lt;/strong&gt;:  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/23/blended.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blended&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Performance Of An Evil Dystopian Leader Masquerading As A Benign Mother Figure&lt;/strong&gt;: Three-way tie – Meryl Streep in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/the-giver.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Kate Winslet in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/22/divergent.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; Patricia Clarkson in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/7/the-maze-runner.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 3rd Annual Roger Deakins Award for Excellence in Being Roger Deakins&lt;/strong&gt; – Roger Deakins for &lt;em&gt;Unbroken&lt;/em&gt; (sight-unseen)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st Annual Jeff Bridges Award for Excellence In Bridgearian Acting&lt;/strong&gt;: Jeff Bridges in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/the-giver.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How’d we do? Make your own nominations below before December 31, 2014 and we’ll include some of our favourites in our official list!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 01:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/18/2014-silver-stamps.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/18/2014-silver-stamps.html</guid>
			</item>
		
>>>>>>> FETCH_HEAD
	</channel>
</rss>
