<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Breakup Buddies</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I really didn&amp;#39;t know what to expect when I saw this Chinese buddy road trip movie on the TIFFF programming list. But, recovering from a recent break-up myself, I was game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see why the stars, Bo Huang and Zheng Xu, are such a big deal in China; they&amp;#39;re both pretty hilarious, and have good chemistry (first honed when they starred together in &lt;em&gt;Lost in Thailand&lt;/em&gt;). What could have been a run-of-the-mill buddy comedy had some interesting twists, and a parallel narrative structure to make the divorce that instigates the story all the more poignant in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only real complaint is that the subtitles were too fast; there’s so much witty banter, but I was only able to catch every second or third line. Some of the story beats relayed by onscreen text (emails, text messages, etc.) weren’t translated, either. Overall, though, I found myself laughing a lot more than I thought I would, and found myself enjoying this fresh and unexpected side of Chinese cinema. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a soothing balm to my own broken heart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diane Carol Harding&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-4-breakup-buddies.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-4-breakup-buddies.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Phoenix</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of people probably roll their eyes when they hear about another Holocaust movie. Personally, I watch every single one I come across—but it&amp;#39;s definitely not new territory. Although &lt;em&gt;Phoenix&lt;/em&gt; somehow makes it feel that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the Holocaust is the setup. The main character is a survivor of Auschwitz, and the film never lets us forget it. But that’s not really what the story is about. It&amp;#39;s about the recovery, the haunting, and the feelings of betrayal survivors were forced to deal with in the midst of their normal, everyday lives. All of which is masterfully handled, both in the performances and the cinematography. Heavy stuff, but I was definitely glad that I spent my Saturday morning at the theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diane Carol Harding&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-3-phoenix.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-3-phoenix.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Red Army</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m a huge fan of Hot Docs - Toronto&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; world-renowned film festival - but it usually signals something special when you TIFF folks land a documentary premiere. And that&amp;#39;s exactly the case for Gabe Polsky&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Red Army&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a truly great sports film, and certainly the best hockey doc of all-time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polsky chronicles the Russian superstars who came to fame during the late 70s and found unstoppable dominance in the 80s. Through fantastically paced editing, striking graphical treatments, mounds of archival footage and new interviews with Vladislav Tretiak, Alexei Kasatonov and, most entertainingly, Vyacheslav Fetisov, we learn what it was really like to play for the Soviet Union&amp;#39;s powerhouse hockey club. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enlisted as actual soldiers and forced to live in barracks away from their families for 11 months a year, the film uses hockey as the perfect prism through which to examine Cold War culture. The story continues all the way to the first Russians playing in the NHL, but never stretches back far enough to even mention the &amp;#39;72 Summit Series, which Canadians believe to be the definitive international hockey showdown. Not the case. The film proves there&amp;#39;s a tonne more rich hockey history to be found in subsequent years, and that the &amp;#39;72 Summit was only one battle in a great sporting war.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-2-red-army.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-2-red-army.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Search</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Some things you just want to like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Search, Michael Hazanavicius’ follow up to his phenomenally successful &lt;em&gt;The Artist&lt;/em&gt;, must have had you salivating when you saw it on the calendar.Starring Bérénice Bejo, and Annette Bening, with a tremendous breakout performance by a young man (a child, really), named Maksim Emelyanov, &lt;em&gt;The Search&lt;/em&gt; has a multi-faceted storyline filled with the kind of war-torn pathos that send chills through the Oscar crowd while still retaining some indie cred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​I can imagine your disappointment then, when you first screened it. Despite rambling, often stilted performances from the two principal cast members, it has great cinematography and some remarkable visual storytelling that is then undercut by long-winded, hackneyed speechifying (from Bening particularly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A six dressed up as a nine is somehow more disappointing than just a six.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tim&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-1-the-search.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-postcard-1-the-search.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Four</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Sunday, September 7.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-2014-day-four.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/7/tiff-2014-day-four.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Revenge of the Green Dragons</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It’s official. You just screened my first major disappointment of the festival: &lt;em&gt;Revenge of the Green Dragons&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty hard not to come into this Martin Scorsese-produced Chinese gangster film with high hopes – especially since it’s co-directed by Wai-keung Lau (credited as Andrew Lau), who made the Infernal Affairs films that Scorsese adapted into &lt;em&gt;The Departed&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it all goes terribly, almost hilariously wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Set in 1980s New York, the film is full of English-as-a-second-language performances (or characters?), which lends itself to painfully on-the-nose dialogue and over-acting. And those are the forgivable sins. 
What makes the film slide straight into parody is the misguided attempts to make it feel like an 80s action movie; wailing guitar solo soundtrack, constant pace-killing fades to black, and strobing, slow-motion sequences meant to punctuate melodramatic deaths. Even the bang-bang intro feels like it comes from an 80s TV show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’d think that’s the point, right? Except the film takes itself deadly serious. All the visuals are desperately trying to live in the shaky-cam, off-kilter camera angle universe of the present, and end up making the whole movie laughable when I was primed to love it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-3-revenge-of-the-green-dragons.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-3-revenge-of-the-green-dragons.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Elephant Song</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You never really know which films are going to draw a crowd at this festival. I figured I was safe only showing up a few minutes early for a Canadian film by Charles Binamé that’s adapted from a play. But of course, this one features filmmaking wunderkind Xavier Dolan in a starring role. So I had to sit on the theatre floor for about 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the first walk-outs left empty seats behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, walkouts at press and industry screenings don’t mean much when you’ve crammed an unreasonable number of films into the line-up. Still, a high walkout rate never bodes well. I won’t venture to say how many left (not many more than normal), but as someone who stayed, I wasn’t all too riveted to my seat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dolan plays a mental patient who holds the secret to a doctor’s disappearance, but he never truly inhabits the character. His mannered affections came off as a Christoph Waltz imitation, and the story itself loses a lot of energy by the mid-point. Binamé knows how to move a camera in tight spaces to off-set staged exchanges, but when the mind-games grow wary, there’s little else to latch onto. 
Other than those comfortable arm rests I finally had.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-2-elephant-song.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-2-elephant-song.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Riot Club</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hot British bad boys certainly have (maybe not-so-niche) appeal. Even I was curious what female director Lone Scherfig would bring to &lt;em&gt;The Riot Club&lt;/em&gt;, which Laura Wade adapted from her own male-centric play, &lt;em&gt;Posh&lt;/em&gt;. And after the opening scene, which dives head-first into big breasts and unrepentant Renaissance debauchery through a wily sense of humour, I buckled up for a wild ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too bad the film never really went there. Despite this early filmic treatment and &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;-esque promise, the film doesn’t amount to much more than &lt;em&gt;The Skulls&lt;/em&gt; at Oxford. The play’s spatial limitation start to feel unnecessarily confined for the big screen during the climax (especially in the massive Princess of Whales Theatre, which signalled a certain importance for a press-only screening). But alas, it was all ultimately as disposable as the women the male characters talk about but rarely engage. To re-quote the them, I suppose there are films for today, and films for tomorrow. This was just a film for today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-1-the-riot-club.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-postcard-1-the-riot-club.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Three</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Saturday, September 6.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-2014-day-three.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/6/tiff-2014-day-three.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>St. Vincent</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Bill Murray has a few &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/writers/coryh/&quot;&gt;big fans&lt;/a&gt; at Dear Cast and Crew. Just last week, we had a 10-review marathon series &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/ghosts-of-ghostbusters.html&quot;&gt;dedicated to Ghostbusters&lt;/a&gt;. But today, you guys and the City of Toronto one-upped us by declaring it Bill Murray Day, screening some of his classic films and culminating in the premiere of &lt;em&gt;St. Vincent&lt;/em&gt;. All this saintly canonizing was all just a warm-up, it seems, to preparing us for the film itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;St. Vincent&lt;/em&gt; follows a familiar story between a doe-eyed boy and curmudgeon old man (like &lt;em&gt;Bad Santa, Bad Grandpa, Denis the Menace&lt;/em&gt;, etc). But it’s hard to fault a film that had me laughing multiple times before the opening credits were done. It was smart for the festival to capitalize on this assured debut by writer/director Theordore Melfi, who leverages Murray’s natural appeal without letting him rest on the usual charms—and it just might earn the comedy legend some Oscar love. The film itself doesn’t elevate much past the feel-good material, but remains enjoyable throughout due to a strong supporting cast in Naomi Watts, Melissa McCarthy and Chris O’Dowd (not to mention delightful newcomer Jaeden Lieberher).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, it’s really all about Murray. As it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-4-st-vincent.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-4-st-vincent.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
