<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Timbuktu</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I will admit I knew next to nothing about Timbuktu prior to seeing Abderrahmane Sissako’s film. For me, it was just the place the evil butler tried to send the kittens in &lt;em&gt;The Aristocats&lt;/em&gt;. I certainly had no idea about its past as a hub of Islamic language and culture. I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; remember when it was briefly taken over by the Maghreb arm of al Qaeda, which brings us to the events depicted in the film. All I knew going in was that it was about a town that gets taken over by jihadist militants. I was expecting it to be brutal and depressing. What I saw instead was a beautifully crafted portrayal of life under extremist control. I knew a bit about the Big News Story of occupation and liberation, but the film gave me a closer look at the smaller picture (which I think might be the more important one), and the ways in which people confront the loss of the smallest freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central plot follows Kidane, a guitar-strumming cattle herder and his family who live peacefully in the desert, beyond the reach of the militants. Of course, they don’t &lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt; beyond that reach for very long. While Kidane and his family are the heart of the narrative, the rest of the characters are every bit as compelling, even those who are only in one or two scenes. Though we don’t see more than a couple of brief moments in their lives, they stayed with me long after the film ended. Your long takes and frequent use of close-ups afforded the actors near-total command of my attention, from the girl glaring in sullen defiance at members of a Sharia tribunal, to the misery and regret on the face of a young jihadist as he briefly recalls his former life as an aspiring rapper. I say &lt;em&gt;near&lt;/em&gt;-total command of my attention because I can’t ignore the profound impact the film’s other visual and stylistic elements had on me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a film about people rebelling at every opportunity, from the subtlest of expressions to outright defiance, against the constraints forced upon them. I feel like you were in lock step with these many tiny rebellions. The militants in the film spend a lot of time droning on and on about everything that is forbidden, and it’s a long bloody list. But for every forbidden pleasure, we see a character indulging in it. And you aid and abet the townsfolk by infusing each shot with colour and beauty. No bright clothing allowed? Boom - voodoo priestess parading through town in vivid blues and reds with a pet chicken and zero fucks given. Football is forbidden? Cut to kids joyfully kicking an imaginary ball around. No music allowed? Secret midnight jam session captured with a sense of intimacy and romance that would most certainly not fly with the ‘Chef Djihadiste’. Not everyone gets away with their acts of defiance, and here we see the kind of cruelty of which the jihadists are capable. Mercifully, you don’t dwell on these images. We all know how brutal their ‘justice’ is. We don’t need to see it play out in any detail. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film uses a gentle yet unyielding touch in underscoring the absurdity of the jihadists’ attitudes and actions. That it also uses humour to this end was surprising, and one of the things that makes &lt;em&gt;Timbuktu&lt;/em&gt; unique. There are moments of flat-out mocking - I noticed you frequently had a donkey wander in and out of the shot whenever the jihadists approached. Well played. But there are also moments of softer derision that treat their targets with grace and empathy. ‘Jihadist doing tai chi in a trance’ isn’t something I ever thought I would see, and it makes no sense at all. It’s ridiculous and we all have a good laugh at his expense because (in the words of my companion),“fuck that guy”, but it is also one of the most serene and beautiful moments in the entire film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the film isn’t all that optimistic. French and Malian forces would drive the jihadists out within a year, but I couldn’t help thinking about all the other places and people who continue to struggle under the control of Islamist extremists. You could have easily clubbed us over the head with the mindless cruelty and destruction wrought by such groups but I, for one, am glad you chose to go with a hopeful reminder that while extremist ideology may exert control over one’s body, the spirit puts up one hell of a fight. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Two Days, One Night</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;“Too slow” is a complaint I often overhear when leaving a theatre after a film. “Nothing really &lt;em&gt;happens&lt;/em&gt;” is another. I heard both immediately after seeing Jean Pierre and Luc Dardenne’s &lt;em&gt;Two Days, One Night&lt;/em&gt;. I didn’t say anything, but had I chosen to stop and drop some film geek wisdom on that total stranger, I would have pushed my glasses up the bridge of my nose and informed him that the film’s slow pace and deceptively simple plot actually complement an ambivalent, complicated narrative that unfolds far quicker than they realized. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One Friday evening, factory worker Sandra is informed that she is to be laid off. Her boss grants her one last chance to save her job; She is given the weekend to convince her colleagues to vote for her to remain at the factory, the catch being that in doing so they must forego their own bonuses. Faced with her family’s financial ruin and battling her clinical depression with some highly inadvisable over-medicating, Sandra spends her weekend calling on each of her co-workers, pleading for their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if viewed as a simple character study, the film is well worth the price of admission. Marion Cotillard makes it impossible to take your eyes off Sandra, even when you feel compelled to look away, as though that would somehow spare her the slightest amount of shame and humiliation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as I said before, there is so much more going on. You set a pace that matches Sandra’s demeanor at the outset of the film: somnambulistic and hesitant. However, it allows us to really feel Sandra’s desperation build. Given the episodic feel to Sandra’s encounters with her co-workers, a more rapid or frenetic pacing would have made the plot feel repetitive quite quickly. Instead, there is a cushion of time in between plot points that allow the viewer to contemplate the film’s bigger questions and issues; Between Sandra and her colleagues, some in even more dire circumstances than hers, who is more deserving? What is the likelihood that Sandra keeping her job will mean someone else losing theirs? What kind of shitty boss pits his staff against each other like that?! How would &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; vote? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the heavy political concerns raised by the film, I wouldn’t have been surprised if you had gone for a more hard-hitting, crowd-stirring approach in the editing room. But this is a Dardenne Brothers film, not &lt;em&gt;Les Miserables&lt;/em&gt;. Come Monday morning, Sandra will either get to keep her job—by now a hollow victory—or be turned out by her peers. She will not find her inner Norma Rae, and there will be no “I am Spartacus” moment right before the vote. Instead, you allow the highs and lows of the plot to gently flow into an elegant and poignant conclusion, as though you shared my need to see Sandra retain or regain at least a modicum of dignity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/19/two-days-one-night.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/19/two-days-one-night.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Kingsmen: The Secret Service</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You have achieved an unenviable immortality since your ignominious passing., haven’t you? The last thing I was expecting when I walked into the theatre to watch Matthew Vaughn’s &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; was a vicious skewering of your Ubermensch John Galt. But given how much philosophical cover you have afforded the latest iteration of morally challenged free marketers I suppose I shouldn’t be entirely surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there it was, that skewering splattered across the screen—from the remote island filled with the elite movers and shakers to the class-consciousness that fills almost every frame of this movie. &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; is informed by every James Bond joint that Roger Moore ever made —coupled with a Picketty-like critique and the idea that a Gentleman (or Gentlewoman) is made, not born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all there, plus some of the old Ultraviolence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samuel L. Jackson might seem to be an odd avatar for &lt;a href=&quot;about:blank&quot;&gt;John Galt&lt;/a&gt;, with his lisp and Flavor Flav fashion sense, but in all ways that matter he is a note perfect melding of a James Bond megalomaniac and the fatuous ideal of your Objectivist ethos.  Both are equally cartoonish, in their conception and motivations, and the combination works remarkably well within the confines of Vaughn’s surreal, amped up world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaughn himself seems particularly scattershot with his chosen targets. It is a laundry list of the unpleasant and woefully mislead. Religious fundamentalists, the lads down the pub, Old Money types and Venture Capitalists as well as brutal climbers like Michael Caine, who is so eager to eradicate any trace of his humble beginnings that he gleefully subverts his life’s work to maintain the Kingsman’s class driven purity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also some confusion about what exactly is appropriate as an object of aspiration. Is it excellence? Power? Sexual Conquest? Saville Row smoothness? All of the above? But it is a glorious kind of manic confusion and Vaughn and the remarkably strong cast make it work eighty-five percent of the time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Firth was a happy surprise, a kind of Henry Higgins with a bulletproof umbrella and a remarkable facility for all sorts of ruckus. The set piece that features him annihilating an entire Jesus Camp-type Congregation was a personal favorite. Vaughn does Guy Ritchie slow motion progressions far better than Guy Ritchie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the truly retrograde artifacts of &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; is its sexual politics. Women are either the competent and emasculating nemesis, vague paragons of virtue or simply a sexual reward. Here Vaughn seems stuck in the Old Bond trope most purely. This is a film about men and their various ticks and affectations. And in the same way that the Moore Bond films were Walter Mitty-level fantasies about urbane, smoove talking killers this film seems entirely comfortable inhabiting the same conceit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film sits squarely on the shoulders of its young protagonist, played with a remarkable depth and confidence by Taron Egerton. Eggsy is a lad from a Council Estate (the British equivalent of inner city projects) the kind of Public Housing that your adherents see as ground zero for all the ills of socialist parasitism. That he is the eventual architect of the demise of the Galt-clone is both pointed and surprisingly satisfying. I usually don’t care for these kind of simplistic revenge fantasies but Vaughn managed to target most of my personal peeves so well, and with a kind of nasty wit, that I enjoyed this movie thoroughly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose in a lot of ways this is the perfect film to put the final nail in your coffin. A chimera that meanders all over the map with a kind of pyrotechnic competence anchored by the inimitable Mark Strong: a working class Scotsman who, in the end, sides with the slightly anarchic kids as they summarily execute the 1% that you fetishized so slavishly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is to ludicrous and enjoyable confections that put you in your place, Ayn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/17/kingsmen-the-secret-service.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/17/kingsmen-the-secret-service.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>5 Radical Ways to Rejuvenate the Oscars</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Academy,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look, I know the Academy Awards are not a public institution, bound by oversight committees, regulatory reforms, and never-ending calls to accountability. But they might as well be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t missed an Oscar telecast since I was 10 years old – back when I insisted Spielberg &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to “finally win for &lt;em&gt;Schindler’s List&lt;/em&gt;, dammit” (so what if I hadn’t seen the film?). Like millions of people, that unreasonable sense of ownership, outrage and interest has never changed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor, I think, would you want it to. That we the people care enough to complain is a testament to your cultural relevance (and, by extension, economic well-being). The Grammy’s only &lt;em&gt;wish&lt;/em&gt;people were passionate enough to nitpick changes to Album/Record/Song of the Year awards. So please, read on with an open mind. No one is asking you to throw out the&lt;em&gt;Million Dollar Baby&lt;/em&gt; with the bath water, but here’s a few ways you can stay on top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Eliminate Male/Female Actor Distinctions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a biggie, and it would be revolutionary. But it shouldn’t be. Like all affirmative actions, the idea of having male and female actors compete for different awards is rooted in good intentions. It’s also a sign of progress when their time has passed. Yes, women’s roles have historically been paltry compared to their male counterparts. Actually, you can (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiewire.com/article/sorry-ladies-study-on-women-in-film-and-television-confirms-the-worst-20150210?utm_campaign=sorry-ladies-study-on-women-in-film-and-television-confirms-the-worst-20150210&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=Facebook&amp;amp;utm_content=sorry-ladies-study-on-women-in-film-and-television-confirms-the-worst-20150210&quot;&gt;quite easily&lt;/a&gt;) argue that not much has changed – except each year when ten famous actresses and supporting actresses get to pretend like all is well in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt; A single Best Actor (Male or Female) award would change the conversation about how women are portrayed in films. We could finally compare characters to characters, instead of pretending that acting is like a sport where men have some sort of physiological advantage. To ease the transition, I would earmark three nomination slots for men and three for women – but only have one winner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead. Imagine it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“Men and women don’t compete for the same roles! It doesn’t make sense!”&lt;/em&gt;  Really? Tell that to Tilda Swinton (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), Angela Bassett (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/3/22/olympus-has-fallen.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Olympus Has Fallen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), Angelina Jolie (&lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jul/22/entertainment/la-et-salt-20100722&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), or any number of other actresses who have had to win roles away from men. Moreover, do you think Tom Hanks could have auditioned for &lt;em&gt;Ray&lt;/em&gt;, or Jamie Foxx was considered for &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;? Malarkey! We don’t divide awards by race, and we shouldn’t by sex. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acting is acting, period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Divide Fictional/Biographical Acting Awards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; Remember back when I said acting is acting, period? Yeah, about that... You Academy voters have an unnatural obsession with rewarding actors who portray real-life people. To wit: 7 of the past 10 male actor winners and 8 of the past 15 female actor winners have played characters based on real people. This year alone, 4 of the 5 Best (Male) Actor nominations are for biographical roles. It’s getting a bit silly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt;If nothing else, having separate character categories would keep the acting races more interesting. But it would also draw more attention to the craft of communicating human emotion rather than mimicking mannerisms. Of course that’s reductionist and not always the case. There’s a lot to be said for evoking the spirit of a real noteworthy individual – even ones who aren’t well-known to the public (like Ron Woodroof from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/19/dallas-buyers-club.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dallas Buyers Club&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). But it should be a separate category. For your sake, if not ours. Bonus: it would also fill the two empty categories (main and supporting) you’ll have when you eliminate the male/female acting distinction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“Just because a character is based on a real-life person doesn’t change the actor’s craft. And where do you draw the line with ancient historical figures?”&lt;/em&gt; Great question! As you know, it’s one that the Writer’s branch of the Academy has been dealing with forever. And that’s your answer: if writing has to be divided into “original” and “adapted” screenplays for having even a whiff of source material origins, then the same staunch logic should apply to actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Create an Award for Best Stunts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea&lt;/strong&gt;: Big budget, tent-pole films are the only thing holding Hollywood studios together. Scale of spectacle is often what justifies the theatrical experience, so it’s high time that one of the last unheralded departments of the industry – the one that often shines in these types of films – finally gets their turn in the spotlight. They’re literally putting their lives on the line to provide people a fleeting moment of entertainment. I think they’ve earned it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result&lt;/strong&gt;: Everyone has, at one point, complained about digital effects “looking fake”, which too often diminishes the emotional stakes on screen. However, people can’t get enough of the thrilling skyscraper sequences from movies like &lt;em&gt;Mission Impossible: Ghost Protocol&lt;/em&gt;, or the gritty realism of fight scenes in movies like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raid 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Great stunts are still being performed, but they’re too often eclipsed by a digital revolution that takes away as much credit as it absorbs blame. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;There’s not enough industry support for a Best Stunts category. It was voted down just&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/race/academy-votes-creating-oscar-category-202123&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;back in 2011&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt; Like outlier sports that have to earn their way into the Olympics, it’s normal for old establishments to resist change. Heck, it wasn’t until 1981 that you guys even had an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/12/12/the-make-up-of-2012-pt-1.html&quot;&gt;award for Best Make-Up&lt;/a&gt;. But it’s not too late to right an old wrong – and, at the same time, get people more excited about the art of filmmaking. That’s the point of this whole thing, isn’t it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Turn the Best Foreign Language Film Category into a World Cup-style tournament&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; This category should be a major prize, and not a clandestine sideshow. Currently, each country (via a closed committee) submits one film for consideration. Then, all the submissions (around 80) are cut down to a shortlist of nine, before five nominees are selected. That secondary step of selecting nominees from a shortlist was recently revamped, but only at a procedural level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a way to get people around the world much more involved, right from the start: borrow the format of the World Cup. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt; Dividing countries into pools who compete against one-another to advance to the next round would not only bring awareness to a greater number of films, but get the public watching more foreign content. The pools would be statistically weighted (based on previous award wins and whatever else), but a film would need to pass three or four rounds before being a nominee. The decision would still rest in the hands of the Academy, but the public could be along for the ride, and hopefully have access to screenings as the process happens, just like a sporting event.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“No way, it will only draw attention to an already contentious process – not to mention the difficulty of arranging distribution rights for all the films around the world”&lt;/em&gt;. Oh, stop it with your facts and reality. Think big: a public tournament format of narrowing down the films would go a long way for gaining exposure and interest in this award, and all the associated films (not just the winner). Sure it’s more work, but also more reward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Remodel Academy Membership&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea:&lt;/strong&gt; People have complained about your “steak eater” membership for years, and this year’s #OscarsSoWhite campaign drew enormous attention to the lack of diversity in your ranks. So how do you address this issue, without advocating tokenism or lowering the bar to membership? I can’t believe I’m saying this, but you might have to take a page from the Canadian Senate, or UN Security Council: setting term limits on appointed members and/or rotating voting powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The result:&lt;/strong&gt; It takes many people the better part of their career to be invited into the Academy, so it’s hard to begrudge its older skewing demographics. Yet begrudge we do, and this membership remodelling won’t just transform your statistics, but get you in touch with a younger audience (ie. increase TV ratings). Rather than the current opt-out policy, capping term limits and/or rotating voting years would ensure a diversity of worthy voices get a chance. Moreover, you could have an established number of permanent members in each branch (like the Security Council), but by allocating a fixed number of permanent spots, you could avoid the full-on death watch for new spots to open up in the current membership-for-life model.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The counter-argument&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“People work hard to join the Academy – it’s unfair to take that away.”&lt;/em&gt; The new focus should aim to recruit the best members in the industry, not just lifetime achievers or friends of insiders.  Fixed terms would mean people have to stay working hard to keep membership, and as a result, have one more motivation to create more great films. Change like this would add legitimacy to the Academy, not take it away. Plus, it’s not like fewer stars would show up to the Oscars – you’ve been to the Golden Globes, right? Only 90 foreign journalists vote for those, and it’s the second biggest award show in town. Your membership credibility isn’t going anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/16/5-radical-ways-to-rejuvenate-the-oscars.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/16/5-radical-ways-to-rejuvenate-the-oscars.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Fifty Shades of Grey</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I mean, really. Why even bother showing up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was no doubt  exciting when the &lt;em&gt;Fifty Shades of Grey&lt;/em&gt; filmmakers first chose you as they’re own Christian Grey – a confident, experienced man to guide them through the pain-for-pleasure world of BDSM. You probably stroked your whip, fondled your chains, and tugged your rope in anticipation. Oh, the things you were going to show them. But how soon did you realize that Hollywood is even more of a cold-clam than Anastasia Steele?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe they lead you on for a while. Even I felt slightly seduced (or at least amused) by the film initially. There was a playfulness to director Sam Taylor-Johnson’s touch – a warmth and self-awareness that forgave the cloud of naïveté wavering overhead. After all, audiences aren’t used to erotic thrillers. We know every beat of action movies and romantic comedies, but this was supposed to be different. More adult – sophisticated. As such, my wife and I guided each other through the complex and prolonged foreplay sequences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The grey pencil in her mouth represents his PENIS!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The rain represents how WET he makes her! Pathetic phallic-cy!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, making these remarks in a theatre would get us punished. But the long pauses between lines of dialogue almost invited midnight movie-ish call-outs. And we weren’t alone. Our advance screening was packed with over 300 women (and 27 men, the security guard told me) buzzing before and during the film. The teenage lip-bitters to our left and fifty shades of grey hairs in front of us were all working through a serious case of the vapors. It almost felt warranted for a while, as the film gently asserts itself with blunt talk and tours of Christian’s playroom (which ultimately feels more like a museum). But it loses any momentum or sense of danger once it finally indulges in the carefully framed, dimly lit, slow-moving sex scenes – showing just enough ass, tits, and pubic hair to feel risqué. You might have been a great help to the props department, but how emasculating it must have felt to never flex your flogging muscles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the 27-year-old billionaire fantasy, however, this is actually a more reasoned first reaction to the leather lifestyle. Dakota Johnson nails the neophyte virginal aura, even if she eventually overdoes her elementary tells. Jamie Dornan also strikes a good balance between mysterious and miserable. The film ironically climaxes during the contract negotiation scene, where they at least &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt; about NSFW butt plugs, genital clamps, and fisting (both vaginal and anal). This clinical consent sequence (which is the entire storyline, actually) is all done with tongue-in-whatever-cheek so pretty much anyone will feel miles away from needing a safe word. As a beginner’s guide to bondage, I can see the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that ending. A quick scan of the synopsis online tells me the script stays pretty true to E.L. James’ pop-erotica phenomenon (which I also learned, hilariously started as &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; fan fiction between Edward and Bella). But it feels like an outright condemnation of you and the people who do BDSM. It’s far from my bag, but I can’t see you getting new business after this. Rather than an exciting foray into the world of gag balls and suspension, it’s a light romp with feathers, blindfolds, and harmless spanking – right up until it goes to an only slightly darker shade of grey, and becomes outraged by the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s, as Christian says, what&amp;#39;s fifty shades of fucked up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/13/fifty-shades-of-grey.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/13/fifty-shades-of-grey.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Last Days in Vietnam</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your job involved a very particular type of extraction. You were tasked to find filmed evidence to back up the stories told by people who lived through the harrowing final days before Saigon fell to the North Vietnamese. Some of this footage you sourced from authorities like the Big Three television networks, the National Archives and Associated Press, and some was supplied by the very people involved. Regardless of origin, it must have been difficult to make decisions about which footage stayed in the picture and which didn’t. No doubt there were many ways this story could have been told. In the end, you have to stand by the choices made by the filmmakers and hope that they’re the right ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last Days&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;In&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Vietnam&lt;/em&gt; chronicles the final weeks of the American involvement in the Vietnam War, and the chaotic, zero-hour evacuation of U.S. and South Vietnamese citizens from Saigon. It is told from the perspective of the people who were there, mainly the U.S. servicemen, CIA analysts, and pilots. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like me, you must have inwardly rejoiced when you realized filmmaker Rory Kennedy wasn’t interested in investing any time in the Vietnam War’s exhausting origin story. What she wanted from you was right there in the title. With the exception of a few iconic images (helicopters being pushed off an aircraft carrier, desperate evacuees climbing a rickety ladder on what we learn was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the roof of the American embassy), most of the visuals you supply feel remarkably fresh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Kennedy’s pedestrian footage/talking head formula does not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that the personal accounts described and depicted here aren’t thrilling in their own right. Most of the servicemen involved in helping people escape were acting against direct orders from American Ambassador Graham Martin, who refused to evacuate until Saigon was literally surrounded by the North Vietnamese Army. Your footage supports the servicemen’s play-by-play of how the situation worsened as the diplomatic foot-dragging forced those trapped to resort to the most desperate of measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see incredible scenes of heroism: people racing down a runway after a commercial airliner while the flight crew frantically pulls as many aboard as they can; a South Vietnamese Chinook pilot hovering beside the USS Kirk after dropping off a load of evacuees, then abandoning his aircraft and swimming aboard the carrier. We hear Marines tell us how they were breaking rules, but that they had to do what they felt was right. When you see the tear-streaked, terrified faces waiting inside the cramped American embassy, it’s difficult to disagree with that sentiment. But like the almost forty-year-old footage you relied on, Kennedy’s focus seems a little faded and fuzzy around the edges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some bewildering omissions. Why no interviews with insiders who might have shed light on Ambassador Graham’s reluctance to evacuate? Or with any of the thousands of Vietnamese women married to U.S. servicemen who spent days waiting with their children inside the embassy, hoping for a ride out? Or what about actually &lt;em&gt;going&lt;/em&gt; to Vietnam to talk to those who didn’t make it out? Instead, Kennedy limits &lt;em&gt;Last Days in Vietnam&lt;/em&gt; to a largely white, male, American perspective (forgive me if I have a hard time believing Henry Kissinger, an unreliable narrator if there ever was one, when he says that the number one concern of the White House was saving as many lives as possible). Kennedy’s take on this dark and convoluted quagmire finds its balance somewhere between oblique reportage and post-hoc apologia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, this documentary is part of the PBS series &lt;em&gt;American Experience&lt;/em&gt;, which explicitly states right in the title who the intended audience is. Maybe &lt;em&gt;America’s Last Days&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;In&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Vietnam&lt;/em&gt; would have been a more apt description of the film. I find it interesting that Clint Eastwood has been taking flack for playing &lt;a href=&quot;http://theantimedia.org/the-real-american-sniper/&quot;&gt;fast and loose with the facts&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;American Sniper,&lt;/em&gt; but Kennedy’s skewed (and partially taxpayer funded) interpretation of the end of the Vietnam War gets a pass. But hey, jingoism is as jingoism does! Looking forward to twenty-some years from now when PBS can tell me how the Iraq war ended.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wading through those miles of celluloid must have given you a perspective on just how heart-breaking the situation was for both Americans and South Vietnamese trying to escape an escalating humanitarian tragedy. The U.S. involvement in the Vietnam War is largely remembered as a disaster, and despite some genuine heroics, the ending was just as bungled and mismanaged as the beginning and the middle. It’s obvious that you and the filmmakers sincerely wanted to honour those who worked in vain to save as many lives as they could. But Kennedy feels too intent on trying to save America’s legacy along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The footage you found was truly exceptional, it’s a shame it was used for a propaganda film.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/12/last-days-in-vietnam.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/12/last-days-in-vietnam.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ida</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m crushing a bit here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is hubris, and then there is having an entire film hinge on the performance of a complete neophyte—an apparently reluctant &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scpr.org/programs/the-frame/2015/02/03/41386/oscars-2015-ida-filmmaker-auditioned-400-actresses/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; at that. But there you are, the title character present in almost every frame of Pawel Pawlikowski’s &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in the Stalinist Poland of 1961, &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt; is the story of a young nun who is coerced by her Mother Superior into confronting her family’s complicated past. Rigorously composed and shot in black and white, the film is somehow also starkly intimate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt; is a beautiful film, with angular compositions and unconventional framing that manages to be both unsettling and serene. Much of the first act, which is spent in and around the austere silence of the convent, is largely occupied with architectural spaces and exquisitely lit compositions. Humans are often small, almost insignificant elements, sometimes given just the lower third of the frame to occupy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most jarringly exquisite film I have ever seen. The complexity and power of each image tends to feel overwhelming initially. It is like viewing an endless series of beautifully composed photos and it threatens to overshadow the rather slender narrative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What prevents the film from being buried by the stark power of its own images and transforms it into a story that is compelling, as well as tragic, is your interaction with the last surviving member of your long lost family—your aunt. She is a character, in the absolute best sense of that word, played ferociously by Agata Kulesza. A ruthless Communist apparatchik of unquestioned vigor as well as a hard-drinking atheist possessed of none of the restraint that seems to exude from you like a subtle perfume, she is also your guide into the labyrinth that is your family history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second act, &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt; becomes this poignant, and sometimes bleakly funny, road movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still perfectly composed and allowing for each moment to play out with remarkable patience, it transforms into a gritty, neo-realist trip into rural, post-war Poland. Both women have a particular gravitational pull that affects each other as well as those around them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kulesza gives an extraordinary performance—at turns bombastic and then almost witheringly despondent—but it is counterbalanced by your intuitive stillness and precocious dignity. These are two of the most arresting characters I have experienced this last year and despite the short run time (80 minutes), I feel like I know something important about each of these women by the end of the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt; evokes comparison to other works (Dreyer’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d3Q6FVhqLY0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Passion of Joan of Arc&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as just one example), it is entirely its own thing, and that is partially owing to your performance. You are both enigmatic and completely transparent, and every moment the camera spends on you, it is still never enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt; is also another example of the quiet renaissance that we are almost surreptitiously experiencing these days. Perhaps somewhat hidden by the shadow of the summer tent poles and the cries of doom and gloom, diverse filmmakers like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/20/a-most-violent-year.html&quot;&gt;JC Chandor&lt;/a&gt; and Pawlikowski, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;Dan Gilroy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Drop&amp;#39;s&lt;/em&gt; Michael R. Roskam are all creating superb, mid-budget films that are head and shoulders above most of the dreck of the last fifteen or twenty years. &lt;em&gt;Ida&lt;/em&gt; is an entirely uncontroversial nominee for an Academy Award, and these days that is saying something indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it seems like Pawlikowski was indeed correct when he insisted on your participation. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/9/ida.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/9/ida.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Jupiter Ascending</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I recognized you right away. I can spot a lone Python in the wild with the precision of a non-migratory African swallow. It wasn’t your wispy Einstein hair, unkempt beard, or mischievous, darting eyes that gave you away. It wasn’t even the familiar grumbles or snorts you made while issuing official documents from a steampunk-inspired Rube Goldberg contraption. The whole scene&amp;#39;s homage to your 1985 opus &lt;em&gt;Brazil&lt;/em&gt; predicted your arrival. It was at that moment that I realized just how much you and The Wachowskis have in common as filmmakers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because - and I say this with absolute respect to all parties involved - &lt;em&gt;Jupiter Ascending&lt;/em&gt; is a mess. A spectacular, giddy, sprawling, hot mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Brazil&lt;/em&gt; is a movie about a future overtaken by bureaucracy (now, it&amp;#39;s a training film for all new employees at Bell call centres). It satirizes and even celebrates the labyrinthine, so you must have felt right at home reading the script for &lt;em&gt;Jupiter Ascending.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot reads like the peyote-fuelled fever dream of a sci-fi nerd who stayed up for a week watching camp classics like &lt;em&gt;Dune,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Soylent Green&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Spaceballs&lt;/em&gt;  on a loop. Jupiter Jones is a housecleaner who unknowingly contains the DNA of the dead royal matriarch from a distant galaxy. The dead queen’s children fight over their inheritance which includes Earth and its inhabitants who are being harvested for a youth serum for the galaxy’s elites. Genetically engineered ex-soldier Caine Wise is sent to protect Jupiter from Balem, the eldest of the royals who wants to kill Jupiter so she will lose her claim to Earth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know right away that you wanted in? Like you, Andy and Lana Wachowski love to cram the screen with mesmerizing visuals; a thrilling chase scene through the Chicago night sky, the Rococo royal palace filled with women dressed like Vegas showgirls, and a galactic dogfight where planets and ships look like gaudy jewels against a velvet backdrop. The effects are as dizzying as the characters, and just as over the top. Eddie Redmayne channels Gary Oldman in &lt;em&gt;Fifth Element&lt;/em&gt; (and &lt;em&gt;Bram Stoker’s Dracula&lt;/em&gt;) as the scenery chewing, bare-chested villain Balem. Channing Tatum’s Caine might be part dog, but he’s all man to Mila Kunis’ cartoony Jupiter Jones. There are giant lizard minions (reminiscent of yours in &lt;em&gt;Fear &amp;amp; Loathing In Las Vegas&lt;/em&gt;), an egg-harvesting sub-plot, and Sean Bean living in a beehive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to be honest, before you made your appearance, I wasn’t really sure what the Wachowskis were up to. Until then I was awed by the jaw-dropping effects yet frustrated by the over-baked plot. But when Jupiter has to claim her royal status on a new planet, and is given a droid named Advocate Bob to herd her through the serpentine bureaucratic process (which is how she meets you), I got wise to their game. &lt;em&gt;Jupiter Ascending&lt;/em&gt; is the kind of movie you would make if you were ever given a budget larger than the one the Wachowskis spend on craft services. It’s a campy, cheesy, gleeful tribute to the space opera, an episode of &lt;em&gt;Flash Gordon&lt;/em&gt; with a limitless bank account. All that’s missing is Freddie Mercury screeching &lt;em&gt;“Jupiter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;ahhh! Savior of the universe!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wachowskis are as guilty as you have been of falling a little too in love with visuals at the expense of the pace, which in places drags under the weight of all that eye candy. The love story between Jupiter and Caine is obvious but adorable, and offers many of the film’s comedic moments. This film is almost perversely goofy, even when it tries to be serious about consumption, commodification and human enslavement. And yet it’s still unambiguously fun. In the not too distant future, I could see &lt;em&gt;Jupiter Ascending&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;12 Monkeys&lt;/em&gt; sharing a midnight double-feature bill. For now, this film just has to be patient for its inevitable bestowment of cult classic status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a shame you and the Wachowskis suffer from the same curse; being constantly, maybe even irrationally, held to the standard of your most universally adored films. &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Brazil&lt;/em&gt; are flukes, beloved cinematic freaks of nature that managed to capture the imaginations of audiences and critics to be rightfully assured a place in film history. As filmmakers, it’s not something you could duplicate even if you wanted to. Your die-hard fans know this. We will always line up to see what you’ve done because even when you fail, you fail spectacularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jupiter Ascending&lt;/em&gt; is the kind of movie people will either love, or love to hate. I loved its frivolity, pageantry and playfulness. But most of all I loved its ambition. Without ambition, we’d all just be mindless administrative drones, forever chasing the elusive 27 B stroke 6.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/6/jupiter-ascending.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/6/jupiter-ascending.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mr. Turner</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Making great art about great art is always a precarious endeavor. Impossible, some might argue. Which is why so many films about the work of great artists fixate on process: the how, the where, the when—anything that can be quantified. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the more subjective stuff – the art itself – a bit of ambiguousness is often necessary to maintain the illusion of sublimity. In &lt;em&gt;Mr. Turner&lt;/em&gt;, you and your longtime collaborator, writer/director Mike Leigh, approach this dilemma in a rather unique way: by treating Turner’s great art like an element of set design or an object from the props department. It sits off-center, out-of-focus, setting a mood or invoking a feeling, but never fully occupying the foreground.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your lush and languorous portrait of preeminent British painter JMW Turner has much in common with a painted portrait: it’s inert, fastidious, captivating. Turner, the man, occupies virtually every frame of the film: standing in silhouette as he sketches a crepuscular landscape; strolling along the beaches of Northern England; posing with deathly stillness for a daguerreotype. As embodied by Timothy Spall – who looks, here, like an Edward Gorey drawing of a Lewis Carroll character – he is a compelling presence, moving with a gorilla’s mean agility, speaking in a language of phlegmy growls and grunts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His artwork is much less prominent. When we do see it, it’s usually from an oblique angle, or from afar, or partially obscured. When the art critic John Ruskin arrives with his father to inspect a painting, the camera stays behind the canvas, and we’re forced to conjure the image in our minds based only on Ruskin’s descriptive evangelizing. Never once do we get that intimate artist’s perspective; there are no loving close-ups of the brush wetly caressing the canvas, no balletic flurry of strokes set to inspiring music. There’s little magic in Turner’s creative process—at least not in the way you express it in this film. He spits and scrapes and blows powdered paint, and does it with the dispassion of a cobbler or cooper. Indeed, he seems to approach painting as a trade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cinematographer, you had to overcome a few dilemmas specific to &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; trade: how to shoot the vistas and landscapes that inspired Turner’s canvases. There is digital trickery involved, to be sure—in one scene, as Turner is paddling along the Thames with his artist pals, the reverse shot is a near-exact recreation of his painting “The Fighting Temeraire tugged to her last berth to be broken up.” The image is radiant, otherworldly, gorgeous, but has the peculiar effect of diminishing the resultant work of art; it makes the process seem too easy, too elementary, like a simple transposition of what Turner sees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly the kind of misstep that you and Leigh so deftly avoid in so many other parts of the film. When Turner lashes himself to the mast of a ship in order to witness firsthand the eye of a storm, the camera doesn’t move from its fixed place in front of him. We see Turner, wild-eyed, pummeled by hailstones, but we never see what he sees. Later, as we see him swirling his brush to create the curling smoke plume at the center of “Snow Storm: Steam-Boat off a Harbour&amp;#39;s Mouth”, we can easily make the connection between those two moments, and how one influenced the other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without additional historical context, one might leave the film feeling like Turner was a minor figure in Victorian art, and not, as he came to be known, one of the great masters of British landscape painting (he was known as the “Painter of Light” long before Thomas Kinkade trademarked that epithet to market his Disney-themed atrocities). Is it a failing of the film that Turner’s place in history is never quite established? That the evolution of his style, which, like the paintings he creates, occurs so subtly that it’s almost invisible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, not really. The film is purposely impressionistic in the same way that Turner’s later work veered towards (and in many ways prefigured) the principles and methods of the impressionism movement. One must keep in mind that you and Leigh are painting a portrait, not a landscape, and that everything on the periphery must stay there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great art is all about clarity of purpose, and it’s clear that, in shooting this film, you possessed it. Turner would surely offer a grunt of approval.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/5/mr-turner.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/5/mr-turner.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Leviathan</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;As far as pre-Oscar buzz goes, you can’t beat a story about a foreign film facing public outrage and censorship in its home country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrey Zvyagintsev’s three hour-long  &lt;em&gt;Leviathan&lt;/em&gt; has been causing quite a stir in Russia. Hailed by some as a masterful &lt;em&gt;j’accuse&lt;/em&gt; directed at the Putin regime and the hijacked institutions that keep it in power, and decried by others as anti-Putin, anti-religious, Russo-phobic propaganda. After seeing the film, I can’t really place myself firmly in either camp. Yes, the film is critical of many things,but it isn’t exactly _anti- anything in the manner of most politically-driven works. It’s a bit more complicated than that. There’s a lot going on, a lot being said, and the film shifts so imperceptibly in tone and theme that you don’t realize until near the end that a bait-and-switch has occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a small northern fishing village, Kolya, a mechanic, enlists the help of his lawyer friend, Dmitriy, to defend him against the seizure of his land by Vadim, the mayor. This being a Russian tale, a few things are guaranteed: everyone is going to be miserably cold at all times, they’ll drink a shitload of vodka, and, no matter where the story starts, things will get progressively worse for the protagonist. So of course things don’t go Kolya’s way in court, and he is faced with the loss of his land and ancestral home, which increases the tension in his marriage and causes trouble with his sullen teenaged son. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film sets itself up as a political treatise at the start. The breathtaking, panoramic establishing shots of the mountains and cliffs that surround the village are deceptively pristine, but as your camera takes us further into the village we see images of decay and neglect; then, as we enter Kolya’s house, which, though isolated and run-down on the outside, is warm and feminine on the inside, courtesy of his wife, Lilya. Their home is the only cozy, inviting space in the whole film, which contrasts sharply with the opulence and wealth on display in the spaces occupied by Vadim and his co-conspirator/confessor, the local bishop. Juxtapose religious icons and sinister portraits of Putin (are there any other kind?) with Kolya’s old family photos, and the contrasting indicators clearly delineate good and evil, leaving the audience well-primed for what we think will be Zvyagintsev’s examination of the injustices faced by the average citizen in contemporary Russia, and the corruption eating away at both Church and State. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a sudden shift. In one scene, the film becomes about something else entirely. While strolling between vodka benders, Kolya comes across a local priest who advises him to stop fighting the system and have faith that his troubles are all part of a Plan. After all the shit this guy goes through, he’s told to just accept it. And that’s when it hit me: I’d been Job’d. We were being Job’d all along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve read my Hobbes and grudgingly done my time in Sunday school, so I had a pretty fair idea as to the thematic concerns I was likely to come across in a film called &lt;em&gt;Leviathan&lt;/em&gt;. But I wasn’t expecting a straight-up retelling of the book of Job, which is, in my opinion, the Old Testament’s most excruciating, table-flippingly frustrating book. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did I not see it coming? Your lingering shots of whale skeleton on the beach. Those panoramic mountain views. I became aware of a suffocating sense of inertia. There are moments when even the ocean seems sluggish and inert; the film was suddenly no longer about Putin’s Russia, or the politics of Church and State—it was about the universal plight of people being hammered by insurmountable forces, and the incredibly depressing idea that we are all Kolya, and by extension, Job. And because of the languid, almost lethargic way in which you capture the landscape and move around and in between the characters, the shift from political statement to modern-day religious parable crept up on me quietly and with a complete lack of “a-ha!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my aforementioned issues with the story of Job, I did experience a moment of dismay when I realized what was up. Yet I’m impressed with how you got me there. Your more straightforward contraposition of wealth/corruption versus poverty/decency sets the scene for the weightier moral and spiritual contemplation to come. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/4/leviathan.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/4/leviathan.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
