<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Dumb and Dumber To</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Must be nice to have full control of your image for once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the early buzz around &lt;em&gt;Dumb and Dumber To&lt;/em&gt; is about how you’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the movie. Whether you exercised your contractual right to veto your cameo appearance, or whether the filmmakers made a purely artistic decision to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...oh, who are we kidding? You wanted out and you got out. That’s your right, and that’s fine. But I hope your withdrawal wasn’t a judgment of the quality of the film. Because I liked it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=28GLa9T2CtI&quot;&gt;I liked it a lot&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original &lt;em&gt;Dumb and Dumber&lt;/em&gt; did a lot of things right, starting with the title (which virtually insulates it from snotty criticism). The laughs are pretty much packed wall-to-wall, stemming from characters who exist solely to be the butt-end of their own jokes. But it’s the re-watchability of the original that separates it from the average idiotic comedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know this as well as anyone, having publicly professed your love for the first film and your fondness for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joe.ie/movies/video-jennifer-lawrence-does-dumb-and-dumber-impression/47027&quot;&gt;quoting the (dare we saw ‘classic’) comedy&lt;/a&gt;. But even you must have had reservations about participating in what could have been a payday nostalgia trip for Jeff Daniels and Jim Carrey, the latter of whom hasn’t had a hit comedy in over a decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m still curious: at what point was your confidence in the film shaken?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you never got past the first 20 minutes. Honestly, I wouldn’t blame you. In what feels like painfully contrived set-up, Carrey’s Lloyd character has been committed to an institution for the past two decades. He suddenly breaks his catatonic state to reveal he was just pranking his best friend Harry. This is followed by some over-the-top physical humour, and a return to their old dungy apartment, where Harry’s new roommate is a crystal-meth maker (a wasted opportunity for a Bryan Cranston cameo). We also get a return of the blind and wheelchair-bound Billy, with a new flock of birds. At this point, things did not bode well for the film to generate new laughs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the plot unfolds – which involves Harry searching for a new kidney by tracking down the daughter he never knew he had – the film starts to reach beyond lazy gags, throwing some new quotable jokes and some of that classic character-based stupidity. I’m not sure when I let out my first hearty laugh, but I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; remember feeling like I was the only one laughing. For me, it all stemmed from falling back in love with the characters. Some small quirk (in a movie filled with huge quirks) had hit me in just the right way. I could feel Jim Carrey going for it—something he obviously didn’t feel prepared to do until now. And it felt good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe you just had a hard time looking at their faces; two men who have aged physically but regressed mentally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t be alone. Base on the trailer, that’s a valid fear. Gags that are funny when performed by a thirty-two year-old are different when performed by a fifty-two-year-old. But it’s also invigorating when done right. And I really think that, for the most part, this film does it right. Even the early mental institution gag feels, by the end, like a dare-I-say smart way to bring the time gap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the Farrelly Brothers have rediscovered their old selves, you seem to have moved on to the next iteration of your career.  The unrehearsed, unreserved, down-to-earth personality that America fell in love with over the past few years seems to be have been replaced with a guarded, slightly more calculating media presence. Staying out of this film might be the best example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just remember that it’s okay to be dumb some times. And dumber, to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>E-Team</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Most mothers will tell you that they want to make the world a better place for their children. They’ll organize food drives, start petitions and maybe even attend the occasional anti-fracking protest - all noble efforts. But your mother, Anna, goes a wee bit further. She travels to some of the most dangerous places in the world in hopes of bringing war criminals to justice. She’s trying to make the world a better place. Not just for you, but for all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bet this gets her out of having to bring cupcakes to PTA meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt; follows the Human Rights Watch emergency team which includes your mom, her husband Ole Sorang, Fred Abrahams and Peter Bouckeart. Their job is to investigate claims of human rights violations, namely the widespread reports of the killing of unarmed civilians (like Libya in 2011 and Syria in 2013). They go into areas of conflict and take statements from people who have just witnessed atrocities, then report these findings to Human Rights Watch and various news organizations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in &lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt;, when your mother and your step-father Ole prepare to leave for Syria, you are asked what you want for a souvenir. When you reply, “Bullet casings or shells, or bits of fragments are always welcome,&amp;quot; I wondered if you fully understand the complexity of your mother’s job. When the filmmakers ask if she thinks you worry about her she says, “do you remember being twelve? He has a very comfortable life.” This is why your mother does what she does, so you and other children can live the kind comfortable existence where bullet casings and shells are considered cool gifts, and not a daily and deadly part of life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You aren’t the only child featured in this film. Peter’s young daughters think Gaddafi is a cartoon villain who steals toys. We see Fred pushing his kids on a swing in New York City while his voiceover explains how he was an expert witness in the Slobodan Milosevic trial in 2002. Having been witness to the mass graves of civilians - many of them children - in Kosovo in 1998, Peter recalls the surreal yet satisfying experience of confronting the man he’d been tracking for ten years. This story alone has enough legs for its own feature doc, yet it illustrates the whole point of Human Rights Watch - to put war criminals on trial and to bring justice to victims. Fred also notes how rare it is to achieve this outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This raises the stakes when we see Anna and Ole taking statements in a town that was demolished by air strikes only minutes before, or Peter using his vast knowledge of weaponry to prove that the Syrians did indeed gas their own people. The team is pragmatic about their incremental gains and small victories. They have to be. Peter very matter-of-factly explains that his job is to confront people with the reality of what is happening in another place, and they have to make the moral choices about what they want to do. The film itself takes a similar approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other capital ‘I’ important docs, &lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt; didn’t make me feel like I was eating my vegetables. Instead of playing on my Western, middle-class guilt, &lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt; shows their subjects living similarly comfortable lives, nary a hair-shirt in sight. It’s this lack of moralizing that gives the film gravitas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s worth noting the team effort behind the camera. The cinematography is assured, and only shaky-cam nauseating once when the team sneaks into Syria in the middle of the night – but that might have just been my nerves. The framing is never intrusive, whether it be your mom and Ole commiserating with their Syrian interpreter about his wife’s pregnancy, or you back home watching &lt;em&gt;Mr. &amp;amp; Mrs. Smith&lt;/em&gt;. The camera, like the E-Team, merely observes and reports. One of the cinematographers was James Foley, who was beheaded by ISIL in August 2014. We find out the film is dedicated to him when the credits roll. It’s the last in a series of gut-punches this film delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There comes a point in every child’s life when they truly appreciate the sacrifices their mother made for them. For most people, it’s not until they move out on their own that they fully understand just how much their mother did to give them a good life. Luckily for you, there’s a film that shows you just how hard your mother works to make a difference in the world. Luckily for all of us, she’s still out there doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/13/e-team.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/13/e-team.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Interstellar</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since his feature debut, &lt;em&gt;Following&lt;/em&gt;, Christopher Nolan has specialized in making existential puzzle films with coherent-but-cryptic conclusions. As his ambitions – and budgets – have expanded, so too has the breadth of the themes he explores. So perhaps it was inevitable that he would eventually turn to the abstractions of theoretical physics: the ultimate existential puzzle with coherent-but-cryptic answers. &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; takes place in multiple galaxies, multiple dimensions, and concerns the survival of the entire human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;#39;t get much bigger or more existential than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;ve spent the last half-century aspiring to answer some of the most profound questions in the universe, Kip. And you&amp;#39;ve come closer than a lot of people. Your research in the fields of gravitational physics and astrophysics has earned you a spot on the all-star team of greatest living physicists, alongside Edward Witten and Stephen Hawking (what cosmic law of mutual attraction is responsible for the strange coincidence of &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; opening on the exact same weekend as &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;, the biopic of Hawking&amp;#39;s early life?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve seen movies based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;comic books&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/27/transformers-age-of-extinction.html&quot;&gt;toys&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/18/battleship.html&quot;&gt;board games&lt;/a&gt;—but perhaps never before based on relativistic theories of gravity. Luckily, your fields of expertise are a bit more accessible than string theory or supersymmetric quantum fields. Black holes, wormholes, gravitational waves—this is the sexy stuff upon which a good hard sci-fi premise can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were its original architect, too. &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; began as a treatment written by you and producer Lynda Obst—but what remains onscreen is apparently much different than what you had proposed. But no hard feelings, right? According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.sciencemag.org/people-events/2014/11/physicist-who-inspired-interstellar-spills-backstory-and-scene-makes-him&quot;&gt;a recent interview with&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.sciencemag.org/people-events/2014/11/physicist-who-inspired-interstellar-spills-backstory-and-scene-makes-him&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, your ultimate goal was a film in which &amp;quot;real science, ranging from truth to speculation, is embedded deep into the movie&amp;#39;s fabric from the outset.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What luck, then, that the project found its way to Nolan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as his filmography seems to suggest that he operates primarily in the realm of the fantasy, his fidelity to scientific law is indisputable. He brought real-world dynamism to the superhero world, creating a Batman who eschews hyperkinetic comic book physics in favor of practical technology (he&amp;#39;s just as much the product of a corporate R&amp;amp;D department as he is the product of a long ago street crime). In &lt;em&gt;Inception&lt;/em&gt;, he applied a systemic logic to one of the most illogical human idiosyncrasies: dreaming. Even in &lt;em&gt;The Prestige&lt;/em&gt;, Nolan&amp;#39;s film about dueling turn-of-the-century illusionists, electromagnetism is revealed to be the source of their magic (there&amp;#39;s even a cameo appearance by Nikola Tesla).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you, Nolan knows a little something about breaking new ground; he&amp;#39;s the only blockbuster filmmaker pursuing original ideas (albeit in between rebooting superhero films). He seems the heir to Spielberg, doesn&amp;#39;t he? A director whose every film is significant merely because &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone familiar with the narrative style employed by Nolan and his brother/screenwriter Jonathan, the first fifteen minutes of &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; is a treasure trove of minor plot details you just know are going to prove relevant by the end: books knocked off a shelf by a ghost; a wristwatch left behind as a memento. How these details expand in meaning and weave together is part of the fun of watching a Christopher Nolan film unfold. And &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; is fun. Even when it&amp;#39;s aspiring to a profundity that it only occasionally is able to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission to outer space that follows these earthbound scenes finds the perfect balance of realism and excess. It&amp;#39;s an adventure, but an authentic one. Disbelief is suspended at just the right height. The scenes back on our planet – where the changing atmosphere threatens the continued existence of oxygen-reliant life – are shot by cinematographer Hoyte Van Hoytema with such a radically different palette (the yellowish sepia-tone of a fading photograph) that, late in the film, when editor Lee Smith cuts back and forth between the washed-out, monochromatic sequences taking place on hostile alien planets, it really seems as if we&amp;#39;re occupying two distinct worlds simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, the finished product looks a lot like Kubrick&amp;#39;s space opus from a half-century ago. And, yes, a lot of the technical precision and visual bravado of the outer space scenes are a fraction less striking after seeing the same stuff in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/4/gravity.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; last year. And, sure, the sound design sometimes overwhelms; Hans Zimmer&amp;#39;s gorgeous Philip Glass-inspired score deserves better, I think, than to be drowned out by that patented Christopher Nolan third-act bass growl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite that familiarity, despite those few flaws, the film has stayed stuck in my head. The ideas are big, the riddles are fascinating, and even if the way the solution hangs together feels a bit too loose, too perfectly imperfect, I&amp;#39;m indescribably grateful that a big-budget blockbuster film possesses the same rare ambition that you do: to ask and answer the most fathomless cosmic questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mommy</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Living up to your name can&amp;#39;t be easy. In the late 1800s, strongman Louis Cyr was a real-life superhero in Canada — and his legend has only grown larger since. Today, icons like him who seem to defy the very laws of nature are hard to come by. But in the filmmaking world, Xavier Dolan comes pretty close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the ancient age of 25, Dolan has already directed &lt;em&gt;five&lt;/em&gt; critically (and, increasingly, commercially) successful films. I say &amp;quot;directed&amp;quot; for shorthand; in truth, he does a hell of a lot more than that. He&amp;#39;s the writer, producer, editor, costume designer – even the doggone subtitle translator – for each of these films. Not to mention the fact he stars in most of his films, too. Even though Dolan stays behind the camera (for all but a self-reflective moment) in &lt;em&gt;Mommy&lt;/em&gt;, all discussions about the film inevitably come back to him. And it always starts with the same question: can he carry the incredible weight of expectations and responsibility that have been placed upon him?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently he can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mommy&lt;/em&gt; circles back on Dolan&amp;#39;s favourite themes: misdirected angst, confused sexuality, youthful arrogance, and depressing adult pragmatism. His ability to lay bare so many issues is what has always made his work electric, honest, and just a shade clear of precious. Sure, he has plenty of haters, but that&amp;#39;s the name of the game when you achieve so much so young (ask Lena Dunham). The trick is to find a way to stay true to your voice without repeating yourself. In that regard, &lt;em&gt;Mommy&lt;/em&gt; feels like the refined version of a message Dolan has been sending for the past five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mommy&lt;/em&gt; features Dolan&amp;#39;s most troubled and co-dependent relationship yet. One that acts like a proverbial collision course between an unstoppable force meeting an immovable object. The acting, in other words, is explosive, with shouting matches between the mother of the title (Dolan&amp;#39;s oft collaborator Anne Dorval) and her dangerously spastic son, played by Antoine-Oliver Pilon, that often tip into violence. Refreshingly, this intensity is counterbalanced by Suzanne Clément&amp;#39;s performance as a stuttering and sweet-natured neighbour who volunteers to home-school the troubled teen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dolan edges much closer to melodrama that that, however. Catchy pop songs (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6hzrDeceEKc&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Wonderwall&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j-fWDrZSiZs&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;White Flag&amp;quot;)&lt;/a&gt; accompany slow-motion montages that quite literally have characters stretching their arms out while looking up to the sky. And in what initially seems like a fatal hipster indulgence, the film is shot in an Instagram aspect ratio (perfectly square). But there&amp;#39;s a certain magic to Dolan&amp;#39;s madness. By not shying away from clichés and experimentations, he pushes past novelty into a place of genuine emotional resonance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a testament to Dolan&amp;#39;s talent and tenacity that he has been able to separate himself from a generation where &amp;quot;too cool&amp;quot; detachment too often rules the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please, Louis, keep brining this young man whatever he asks for.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/7/mommy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/7/mommy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Tim&#39;s Vermeer</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Was it nepotism or necessity that got you the job on &lt;em&gt;Tim&amp;#39;s Vermeer&lt;/em&gt;? Given your relationship to the subject, my guess would be a bit of both. But I get the feeling your husband, the titular Tim, only handed you the camera as a last resort when the crew wasn&amp;#39;t around. Turns out, &lt;a href=&quot;http://leslietuckerjenison.com/&quot;&gt;you&amp;#39;re an artist yourself&lt;/a&gt;. A quilter. And a rather renowned one. You&amp;#39;ve been in numerous publications, shown your work internationally, and in addition to curating shows and writing several books, you also run workshops as a &amp;quot;fun-cilitator&amp;quot; (which frankly sounds exhausting). Being completely consumed by an art form is likely something you understand better than most. If anyone could empathize with your husband&amp;#39;s obsession, it&amp;#39;s you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely you knew Tim was a bit of an eccentric when you married him. Having designed a program that renders 3D images for film, his interest in Vermeer&amp;#39;s ability to paint photorealistic images that he describes as, &amp;quot;seem(ing) to glow like an image on a movie screen&amp;quot; goes beyond mere fascination. How is the verisimilitude of Vermeer&amp;#39;s work light years ahead of his 17th century contemporaries? This is the puzzle Tim is determined to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tim&amp;#39;s Vermeer&lt;/em&gt; shares similarities with other recent art-mystery docs like &lt;em&gt;Who The #$&amp;amp;% Is Jackson Pollock&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;My Kid Could Paint That&lt;/em&gt;, both of which dare to question the perceived truths held dear by art world elites. Tim&amp;#39;s suggestion that Vermeer could have used lenses and a variation of a camera obscura in order to achieve the near photographic precision of his paintings isn&amp;#39;t popular, nor is it new. Architect Philip Steadman and artist David Hockney both seem to think Vermeer had some help, citing that lenses were the cutting edge of technology in the 1600s. But when Tim, who is not a painter, decides to recreate Vermeer&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;The Music Lesson&lt;/em&gt;, I was reminded of another singularly obsessed genius, Philip Petit from the doc &lt;em&gt;Man On Wire&lt;/em&gt;, whose enthusiasm, like Tim&amp;#39;s, is both contagious and unsettling. Over the course of five years, Tim learns Dutch, visits Vermeer&amp;#39;s studio in Delft, then recreates it in a warehouse in San Antonio. He grinds lenses, designs exact replicas of furniture and props in &lt;em&gt;The Music Lesson&lt;/em&gt;, learns to make oil paint using the same materials Vermeer would have used, and starts painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bet you were glad you had your quilting to keep you busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an artist, did you enjoy the opportunity to pick up a camera and focus on something a little more technical? Or did you discover, as your husband did while recreating one of the most revered paintings in the world, that what he was doing wasn&amp;#39;t subjective but objective? Filmmakers (magicians and proud skeptics both) Penn and Teller are the perfect people to stitch the pieces of this mystery together, and they balance the elements of art and technology handily. From an emotive, whimsical score that never condescends, and lighting that lives up to the high standards of Vermeer&amp;#39;s mastery of light, the film hits almost all of the right notes. The only thing missing was you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn that not much is known about Johannes Vermeer, and strangely, the film doesn&amp;#39;t tell us much about Tim either. Your three daughters were involved in the film (one produced the film and another sits as the model for the painting), but they don&amp;#39;t provide any observations about their dad. We only see you once, in a college photograph of you and Tim. Like the &lt;em&gt;Girl With A Pearl Earring&lt;/em&gt;, you too are a cipher. Then again, the film isn&amp;#39;t called &lt;em&gt;Tim&amp;#39;s Wife&amp;#39;s Vermeer,&lt;/em&gt; is it? But your insight into the man who decided to devote half a decade of his life to such a strange hobby would have been welcome, much like the batting in between the layers of your quilt that, instead of just joining the pieces together, provides much needed warmth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/5/tims-vermeer.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/5/tims-vermeer.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Discussion with Jake Paltrow, Director</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As &lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt; opens in the theaters nationwide, C. Redmond talks to writer/director Jake Paltrow about what he learned from working on P.T. Anderson&amp;#39;s first film, how he communicates with each department on set, and what&amp;#39;s it like to have his godfather, Steven Spielberg, show up at his film premieres.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You come from a family of Hollywood professionals — but what made you personally want to get into the business?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young person I was very interested in special effects and practical effects. I was very interested in creature creation and monster makeup, sort of in the mold of Rick Baker. As a pre-teenager, that&amp;#39;s really what I wanted to be. Then I learned as a young teenager that I didn&amp;#39;t really have the artistic skills to do that. You know, the sculptor or the painter was such a big part of all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the thing that occurred as a side effect of that interest was making shorts, or sort of scenes built around some of these effects. You know, bullet shots, monster masks, something that would create a brief narrative for something I was creating. Out of that came the interest in actually making movies. So my interest really stemmed out of a horror background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you get into directing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In high school a teacher got me interested in the French New Wave, and the American cinema of the 30s and that really was a big eye-opener for me. When I was 19 I made a short film, but I got into actually working in movies as a production assistant. First on TV shows, then on some movies. I started travelling around the country working on these different projects with some of these assistant directors that would take you along with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I was dead set on making a short film as soon as possible, and at the time I&amp;#39;d gotten a grant from Kodak to do that, so I think I got five thousand feet of 35mm film, which at the time was a very meaningful thing. The resolution alone kind of set you apart as a professional versus an amateur because of the look. That&amp;#39;s gone now, because there&amp;#39;s an equality of material now, but at the time having 35mm film in itself was a big deal. I made a short and it got into Sundance and got a little attention, and I got offered my first TV show to direct from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was really how I got into TV, because it wasn&amp;#39;t a primary interest, even though my father had been in television. But it was an opportunity to be a professional and that&amp;#39;s how I looked at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You were a Production Assistant on &lt;em&gt;Hard Eight&lt;/em&gt;, Paul Thomas Anderson&amp;#39;s first film. What did you learn being on that set?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a lot of ways, I feel like I probably learned everything on that one. More so than on all of the other ones. It was a very small group and everyone became very close sort of right away. It was made quickly in Reno, and most people were living in the casino and I was living in a hostel nearby or something. It was very easy to tell how talented Paul was and what a great environment he created in making the picture. For me, it was really the model of how to do it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and how to do it right. It was very convincing. At the end of the day, we all watched dailies together and the results were patently good. It was a great time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did you learn from directing TV? How has that informed your work as a feature film director?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never really thought of them as too different. I always just approached them through my own interest or personal experience or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain shows are very rigid, and have a sort of rigid aesthetic, so you go along with that. Sometimes that produces a less interesting final result, because maybe it feels less and less like you. There are shows where you&amp;#39;re ultimately more of a senior technician on crew, or you may not even be the most qualified person to really be doing it. Really the producers and the crew themselves could fashion together some sort of self-regulating system of directing a show when it&amp;#39;s a very rigid aesthetic and you&amp;#39;re cranking out over twenty episodes a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A show like Boardwalk Empire is the complete opposite. There&amp;#39;s no mandate for coverage and they&amp;#39;re really pushing you to just bring your artistic sensibility to their show and they want that. They want it to feel different, and I think that&amp;#39;s something inherent at HBO and really fostered by those great producers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me about making your first feature film, &lt;em&gt;The Good Night&lt;/em&gt;. You obviously had a great cast in that film with your sister Gwyneth, Danny Devito, Penelope Cruz, and Martin Freeman. What were some of the lessons you took from that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a great experience. We made that in London. We certainly had more time than we did on this one, and I think the environment for independent movies at that time - and it was sort of a low-budgeted movie but I remember feeling like we had plenty of time to make it even though it was 37 days or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But that&amp;#39;s pretty good for a drama, no?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, it&amp;#39;s very good. We made (&lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt;) in 35 days, and it&amp;#39;s basically a visual effects movie. It has 200 or something visual effects shots and you&amp;#39;re doing it very, very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve always been somebody who plans everything as much as I can. I think for me I&amp;#39;ve learned to guard the process better from that experience. I think there are certain departmental things that I have maybe more control of now, or look out for earlier, so that we don&amp;#39;t end up with any snafus later on. I won&amp;#39;t single out any particular department, but there are things that I felt like I let slip through the cracks from the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that was a function of coming from television where the departments are much more well versed in what these things need from the director, so you&amp;#39;re getting delivered stuff that&amp;#39;s so good that you don&amp;#39;t even have to think about. A movie is created top to bottom, so there&amp;#39;s less of a machine that&amp;#39;s in place and more that you have to build from scratch. I think that we definitely did that in South Africa but we did it quite successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let&amp;#39;s talk about some specific departments on this film and how you worked with them to achieve your vision. Starting with the camera department and cinematography.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;#39;t really talk specifically about any real references for the movie except a movie called &lt;em&gt;Silent Light&lt;/em&gt;, Carlos Reygadas&amp;#39; movie about Mennonites in Mexico. We only talked about the lensing. They were using a sort of older Russian anamorphic lens that is very inconsistent and it sort of brought a compression, but it brought a real look to it just in the lensing of the movie that I really responded to. So that was something that we wanted to mirror in &lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, I&amp;#39;m very dedicated to working on film, and so is Giles (Nuttgens, the cinematographer). That&amp;#39;s something we really see eye-to-eye on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re very close collaborators, so we sort of build an idea of what we want it to look like, but not in an imposed way. We&amp;#39;re paying very close attention to what the environment is like and trying to get a very naturalistic representation of it but one that also feels heightened in a way. There&amp;#39;s no filtration, the colour correction process is so minimal, we virtually do nothing. It&amp;#39;s more of a colour balancing probably, or image balancing than it is a true colour correction. We don&amp;#39;t add contrast, there&amp;#39;s none of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a lot of people really get into the DI (digital intermediate) suites and start dialling in colours and creating a saturated look and that sort of stuff in post. We really are approaching it as a film-based process, really going from what film itself does so naturally and so well and trying to preserve that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was your approach to art direction in the film?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to explore the idea of a future of regression, regressive technology. In some ways, even though we have robots, the technology by which they&amp;#39;re living has sort of reverted to an analogue state. So it&amp;#39;s like HAM radios, absolutely no television, everything is sort of done on radio or CB, and that extended to the car. So we really approached it from a Cuba 1959 way of how one day everything just stopped when the embargoes were piled on and you have to make do with what you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sort of thought of (&lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt;) as an aesthetic from the mid-1990s. It was the end of cars being more mechanical than electrical. We really tried to approach it from a practical standpoint of how would all these things still be working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s kind of informed by the world as well, it&amp;#39;s regressive in it&amp;#39;s social mores, regressive in the roles of women in certain ways and those were all things that we tried to mirror in the environment, and it&amp;#39;s a very distressed world in every kind of way. And how do you reflect that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That applies to the costumes as well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah. A lot of their clothes are, you know the idea of rationing, of food being delivered, but also some of those clothes are delivered. Some of the clothes are colour coded for men and for women, and why would that be? Possibly because in areas of conflict, law enforcement would have a very quick idea of who were women and who were men by the clothes. It&amp;#39;s all about the undershirts. If you&amp;#39;re in T-shirts and you&amp;#39;re giving men blue and women pink which are very cliché obvious colours, but if you look at it from a law enforcement place, where they&amp;#39;ve had protests in the past, you very quickly have a sense of how many men or women you&amp;#39;re dealing with. Those sorts of things that are all integrated even though we don&amp;#39;t necessarily flesh them out narratively. Those are just the ideas we were talking about all through the process of building the movie from top to bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s why the film feels like it has a certain colour palette, those things were all sort of built in, we like to approach them from some sort of edict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And what about the editing? You have a lot of long dissolves here, almost like an old Western .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that process was quite intuitive. Even though the performances were naturalistic, I wanted the movie to feel quite storybook. It was very inspired by the S.E. Hinton novels. Even though they have a naturalism to them, they also feel sort of storybook and nostalgic. That was something I wanted to mirror. So the chapter headings and the long dissolves, to me, made it feel more storybook. It makes it feel like this is a tale that can only be told as a film. Maybe it was adapted from a book, maybe it wasn&amp;#39;t. But it feels like a movie. There&amp;#39;s no sort of Cassavetes realism to it, and that I liked. I wanted it to feel fictional, I wanted it to feel storybook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about the sound design?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a part of the process that I really love. In a lot of ways, the mix is one of the times when I&amp;#39;m most relaxed. When hiring a sound mixer, I wanted them to be very flexible and very mobile in terms of the mic-ing. Most of all the production sound was very usable, which was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Slater, who is the sound designer and mixer and everything was recommended to me by Edgar Wright, who is a friend. I was talking to him about how we wanted to create this unusual environment. So I said who is the sort of Ben Burtt in London? And he recommended Julian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hired Julian ultimately, and he has an understanding of sound that feels real but takes a tremendous amount of invention to get there. So there&amp;#39;s a real artistic quality to the elements that he&amp;#39;s creating for the movie. Really iconic sounds. I always loved the way Indiana Jones&amp;#39; pistol has such an iconic sound the way it&amp;#39;s shot. It&amp;#39;s not the way the gun sounded - it&amp;#39;s less of the realistic &amp;quot;let&amp;#39;s record that sound&amp;quot; than come up with something that feels our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Julian I feel did that many times from the gunfire, to the way that things reverberate, and the voices in the house - he just came up with very iconic sounds. And he mixed it so beautifully. Getting to hear the movie in a theatre with really great sound is one of the really wonderful experiences I hope people will find in the theatre there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You brought up Indiana Jones, so I have to ask...your godfather, Steven Spielberg, was at the Sundance premiere of your first film, and this film as well. Do you welcome the kind of attention that brings, or do you feel like it adds pressure to how the film is received? And do you feel any extra personal pressure having one of the greatest filmmakers right there beside you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean for me it&amp;#39;s obviously a very exciting thing and you know, he&amp;#39;s a great friend and somebody who I am lucky enough to get to show a cut of this movie to before it&amp;#39;s finished. I think he has a small group of people that he does that with and I feel very lucky that I&amp;#39;m one of them, really. He&amp;#39;s been a great friend and I feel very lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/5/a-discussion-with-jake-paltrow-director.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/5/a-discussion-with-jake-paltrow-director.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Young Ones</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There is a moment early on in this film where I realized you had lost me. During the slow reveal of an ad hoc water pumping station in the middle of the desert, all I could think was: that is not a water pumping station, it is a movie set inhabited by people pretending to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting as a John Ford morality tale set in a fading civilization, &lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt; utilizes a complex narrative structure, where each act follows a different character. I think I understand what you and director Jake Paltrow were reaching for, but perhaps it was one sub-genre and two characters too many. It feels like all of the various aesthetic and narrative points of reference that the major participants value are woven together, but instead of a beautiful quilt you get an orange and green plaid sweater with one too many arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt; is also defeated by its own ambitions. A film largely populated by naturalistic actors, it still attempts to create a mythic narrative. The sets are minimalist yet rich in small detail, but the natural landscape is breathtaking to the point where everything in front of it seems contrived and out of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contrast between the quiet, subdued performance of Michael Shannon and a film that is intentionally stagey and constructed (each act is announced by onscreen titles) fails to create the hoped for tensions, undermining both the actors and the plot device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say there is nothing to admire here. Shot on film and in Namaqualand, Northern Cape, South Africa &lt;em&gt;Young Ones&lt;/em&gt; is sometimes overwhelmingly beautiful. There are moments of real friction as well, although they all come as a result of interactions with Michael Shannon and he doesn&amp;#39;t see nearly enough screen time. The rest of the cast honestly feels too callow and one dimensional for the weight they have to carry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The production design fell short as well. While I enjoyed the cleverness of the mechanical donkey and some of the bits and bobs of the kind of regressive, analog universe you built—like shortwave radios and a distinct absence of iPhones and their iCousins— it still felt like an invented world rather than an inhabited one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would still rather watch a hundred films like this than a lot of other, less ambitious works that only aspire to product creation. But there are some really weak spots: the women characters particularly are reduced to narrative pivots and little else. Elle Fanning was utterly wasted in this film, and even when she was active in a scene she seemed to flail to find her place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe if everyone had dialed down their ambitions and found a crisper, more defined focus for the story the film might have matched its potential. I&amp;#39;m sorry Sharon, but I was hoping for more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/3/young-ones.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/3/young-ones.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Top 5 Most Terrifying Scenes in Movie History</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kelan Young writes postcards to the cast and crew responsible for some of the most frightening moments in movie history.&lt;/em&gt; (WARNING: Spoilers ahead)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;5. The Hallway Scare in &lt;em&gt;The Exorcist lll&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Gerry Fisher, Cinematographer,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;d be opening myself up to controversy by saying that, for the most part, jumps are among the cheapest tricks horror movies can pull. Whether it&amp;#39;s a hissing cat suddenly leaping out of a closet/cupboard/fridge, everyday noises cranked up to eleven for no discernible reason, or characters who greet one another by stealthily creeping up from behind and pouncing, it can be startling, sure. But rarely scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[A perfect example of this is the moment in &lt;em&gt;The Simpsons&lt;/em&gt; when Homer bursts into Bart&amp;#39;s bedroom in the middle of the night to show off his brand new hockey mask and chainsaw.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bring us to what is arguably the most famous scene in otherwise underappreciated &lt;em&gt;The Exorcist lll&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes it special is how unassuming the setup is. You set up a perfectly still shot of a hospital hallway while a nurse does her rounds. She leaves the frame to enter a patient&amp;#39;s room, comes back into the shot after about ten seconds, then, suddenly, the stillness is horrifically broken. You zoom forward, the soundtrack shrieks, and a figure shrouded in white comes out of the room behind her holding a pair of shears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s absolutely hair-raising, and the immediate cut to a shot of a decapitated statue informs us of the poor woman&amp;#39;s fate without actually showing a drop blood, which is pretty ingenious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/M7Yu8jCrJeg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;4. Testing The Blood in &lt;em&gt;The Thing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Rob Bottin, Special Makeup Effects Creator and Designer,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every great thing that can be said about your astonishing work on &lt;em&gt;The Thing&lt;/em&gt; has already been said. Even now, thirty years later, the effects you created to bring to life one of the all-time most frightening screen monsters haven&amp;#39;t aged a day. Contrary to the claims of some naysayers that argue the film relies too heavily on gloopy makeup, the film&amp;#39;s most effective, suspenseful scenes are those in which your makeup and design works perfectly hand-in-hand with the very smart, well-constructed script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowhere is this more evident than in the infamous blood testing scene. The steady undercurrent of paranoia has reached critical levels as &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; camp leader MacReady is forced to kill in self-defense, then designs a test to determine once and for all who is human and who isn&amp;#39;t. The tension builds superbly as one by one the survivors are cleared, until MacCready&amp;#39;s attention lapses at a crucial moment and the Thing reveals itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest is a nightmare of melting flesh and snapping jaws. It&amp;#39;s truly marvellous stuff. I have yet to meet anyone who didn&amp;#39;t jump out of their skin when they watched this sequence for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/hqVbOSEsJNo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;3. Stuck in the Tunnel in &lt;em&gt;The Descent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Shauna Macdonald, Actress,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what makes &lt;em&gt;The Descent&lt;/em&gt; such a marvel is that, long before the ill-tempered Gollum-creatures arrive and turn the whole thing into a monster movie, it functions equally well as a breathlessly suspenseful cave exploration/survival story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also remarkable that for all the blood that is spilled, the single most chilling moment in the film comes when your character gets stuck in a narrow tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve never really considered myself claustrophobic, but the discomfort and panic you convey as the situation becomes more and more dangerous is so palpable, so &lt;em&gt;raw&lt;/em&gt;, that...well, I&amp;#39;m pretty hardened when it comes to the horror genre, but of all the times I&amp;#39;ve watched &lt;em&gt;The Descent&lt;/em&gt; (which is a lot) I&amp;#39;ve never been able to keep my eyes on the screen when this scene comes up. And that&amp;#39;s primarily due to your incredibly powerful performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/HbdxvncHvCs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;2. The Attic Finale in &lt;em&gt;REC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Javier Botet, Actor,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s difficult to emphasize how profoundly disquieting the last few minutes of &lt;em&gt;REC&lt;/em&gt; are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, the entire third act is the ultimate &amp;quot;how could it possibly get worse?&amp;quot; scenario, as nearly the entire cast is abruptly (and mercilessly) bumped off and the possibility of a happy ending fades ever further into the distance. And then we get to the attic, where you finally step in front of the camera, and we find out it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; get worse after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother. Of. God. It isn&amp;#39;t enough that the makeup and design is ghastly – a skeletal body topped off by a head that seems entirely too large – but add to that your half-hunched posture and awkward, jerking movements. It&amp;#39;s those disturbing physical elements of your performance that convert the last few minutes of this film into high-octane nightmare fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/BrmpbVPTDCw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;1. The Last Shot of &lt;em&gt;The Vanishing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Tim Krabbe, Screenwriter,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a storytelling standpoint, the finale of The Vanishing is pure macabre gold. After years of fruitless searching, the film&amp;#39;s protagonist finally establishes contact with the man who abducted his girlfriend, who then offers to reveal her fate. Great, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both your book and in the screenplay you adapted from it, you perfectly capture the banality of evil in your characterization of Raymond, the abductor; he&amp;#39;s a mild-mannered, painfully ordinary individual who is nonetheless completely devoid of empathy and, as he explains to the hero, has carried out an unimaginable crime just to prove a point to himself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circumstances Rex finds himself in at the end of the film...it&amp;#39;s truly difficult to think of any other scene that has left me as rattled as this one. The concept is fairly simple, but utterly terrifying in the way it&amp;#39;s executed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s even more amazing is the way you sprinkle clues throughout the film about how everything will resolve, most notably in an early scene when Saskia recalls a dream about floating golden eggs. The awful moment of realization when the meaning of that dream becomes clear, which comes &lt;em&gt;right before&lt;/em&gt; the credits roll, is indicative of the power of genre cinema. It&amp;#39;s one of the bleakest, and most terrifying, moments in film history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/NURWfukUXuI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/31/the-top-5-most-terrifying-scenes-in-movie-history.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/31/the-top-5-most-terrifying-scenes-in-movie-history.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Before I Go To Sleep</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your resume is a veritable list of British cinema&amp;#39;s greatest hits: &lt;em&gt;Shakespeare In Love&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dirty Pretty Things&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Queen&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The King&amp;#39;s Speech&lt;/em&gt;—just to name a few. Your still photographs are used as reference material for production, promotions, and, in this case, as props in the film. Even though you&amp;#39;ve shot some of the most famous people in the world for some of the most renowned producers and directors, your job doesn&amp;#39;t really change. In fact, you were the only person behind the camera of this film who was actually &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to deliver a predictable product. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before I Go To Sleep&lt;/em&gt; is yet another wannabe sex-thriller with the kind of maddeningly vague premise that studios love because it gives the audience absolutely nothing to go on, thereby nullifying any expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christine wakes up every day with no knowledge of her past. As she struggles to piece together her existence, terrifying memories start flooding back and she begins to fear the very people she is supposed to trust. If I didn&amp;#39;t know any better, I&amp;#39;d imagine someone pitched &lt;em&gt;Before I Go To Sleep&lt;/em&gt; as &lt;em&gt;50 First Dates&lt;/em&gt; meets &lt;em&gt;Memento&lt;/em&gt; (right before they cackled like a hyena and slammed an eight-ball on the conference table). Unfortunately for &lt;em&gt;Before I Go To Sleep&lt;/em&gt;, audiences have been trained to ferret out the surprise twist in every suspense flick made since Haley Joel Osment got hair in his bathing suit area. And these days they&amp;#39;re savvy enough to know that the plot holes shouldn&amp;#39;t be bigger than the twists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your work shows up early on. Christine awakens, as she does every morning, scared and bewildered beside a man she doesn&amp;#39;t recognize. Fleeing to the bathroom, she sees a photo collage of herself and the man in happier times. I was confused too, mostly because I couldn&amp;#39;t understand why Nicole Kidman and Colin Firth were in a Lifetime movie. Your photos told us the story of a couple who were once in love before &amp;quot;the accident&amp;quot; caused Christine&amp;#39;s amnesia. We see them, smiling adoringly on their wedding day, smiling adoringly on vacation, smiling adoringly in a park. They looked just like the pictures that come with the frame when you buy it, and, sure enough, their characters turn out to be just as flimsy. Kidman&amp;#39;s perpetually open-mouthed confused-face runs the gamut from &amp;quot;Did I leave the oven on?&amp;quot;-concern to &amp;quot;Did I leave the oven on?&amp;quot;-panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poor Colin Firth just looks like he wants to slide back in that picture frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there&amp;#39;s a camera hidden in a shoebox in the back of a closet, and of course Christine finds it. Her doctor calls her every morning to remind her to take it out and film herself in order to build up a memory bank of sorts that she uses to replace her missing long term memories. At this point I was wishing I had lost my long term memory, too. That way, the shots of the dank underground parking lot, the Kubrickian hotel hallway, and the desolate industrial park with the creepy mannequin warehouse would have seemed fresh and inspired. Like I expected, this film has many questions, like: &amp;quot;Does Christine have a secret child?&amp;quot;, or &amp;quot;Can she trust her husband or her doctor?&amp;quot; and, most important to me, &amp;quot;Am I going to remember any of this movie before I go to sleep?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not unusual for someone in your line of work to go through several rolls of film (or SD cards, I guess) trying to get the one shot you need. When I was a model very briefly in the pre-photoshop days, a photographer made me jump off the same fence post repeatedly in order to get that &amp;quot;perfect shot.&amp;quot; He told me officiously: &amp;quot;A great picture isn&amp;#39;t taken, it&amp;#39;s given.&amp;quot; As my tired body involuntarily launched itself off that wooden perch for the hundredth time, I remember thinking, &amp;quot;What a jag-off.&amp;quot; But now I kind of get it. Sometimes you have to do the same thing over and over in order to achieve a desired result. But what&amp;#39;s the point of doing something that&amp;#39;s already been done if you can&amp;#39;t do it better?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/31/before-i-go-to-sleep.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/31/before-i-go-to-sleep.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>John Wick</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It must have been a dream working on this particular film, especially while working with fellow fight choreographers turned directors David Leitch and Chad Stahelski. &lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt; is a raucously perfect film when it S&amp;#39;s TFU and lets the action speak for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a medium budget film that demonstrates how entertaining a movie can be when the filmmakers truly understand that they&amp;#39;re working in a visual medium. Most of the exposition in this film is non-verbal and respects the audience enough to know we can make simple connections without being beat about the head and face. And when we do get to the actual beating of heads and faces, it&amp;#39;s genuinely clever in its simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight scenes – and there are more than a few – are exuberant and flawlessly executed. What they are not, however, is typical. Keanu, instead of reprising &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&amp;#39;&lt;/em&gt;s stiff-legged Kung-Fu style, uses grappling techniques, Jiu-jitsu, and Judo. The fights feel authentic, even a little ragged, all while being perfectly staged. Like great dialogue, the fights are extemporaneous yet exhaustively refined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film itself follows this aesthetic. It has all the usual tropes of the genre, but either manages to cleverly subvert them – mostly by using them as a kind of shorthand to move the plot forward – or simply embraces them with a refreshing lack of irony. I would imagine working with a fully-engaged Keanu Reeves was bit of a treat. While he is often a target of ridicule, it&amp;#39;s clear that the guy comes to work with his lunchbox. I never caught a whiff of the bemused &amp;quot;here I am again&amp;quot; smirk that has fouled Bruce Willis and his peers lately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the film occasionally falters is in the quieter moments. It still looks great, but feels a little stitched together when it slows down enough for everyone to catch their breath. Happily, though, such moments are few and far between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did a man&amp;#39;s job, Jon. Especially in the set piece in the bar. A sequence that probably should inspire a new category at the Academy Awards: Best Action Sequence For A Directors Reel. This is a calling card moment that rivals anything I&amp;#39;ve seen lately—including that most holy of holies, &lt;em&gt;The Raid: Redemption&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve watched a lot of film in my forty-odd years, and probably far too much of it has been this type of movie. But that sequence in the bar made me feel young again, and reminded me that I haven&amp;#39;t seen it all. And for that, Jon, I thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
