<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>John Wick</title>
				<description></description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Nightcrawler</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What did you think when you first saw Lou Bloom (aka. Jake Gyllenhaal) roaming the surreal Los Angeles landscape that you helped create? Was it worth all those lonely nights, the bad food, the lost sleep?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly think it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must have been a gruelling 28 nights of isolated, thankless work; even though it was punctuated by the excitement of shooting a couple of elaborate car chases and a set piece that is a masterwork of suspense.That kind of compressed schedule means no one sleeps, everyone is on edge, and there&amp;#39;s zero room for mistakes. Yet you and your unit managed to deliver a seamless piece of visual art, made all the more effective by Gyllenhaal&amp;#39;s Oscar-bait performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel for you, Mike. I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;ve tripped over a few creatures like Lou during in your time in the business. The kind of relentless opportunist – in this case a predatory loner who falls into the murky waters of local TV crime reporting – whose every action is purely transactional, whose each waking second is dedicated to an emotional calculus in search of leverage. Fortunately, though, one of the few perks of the second unit is that you&amp;#39;re largely clear of the studio suits. Your work is judged almost exclusively on how well it melds with the aesthetic of the director (in this case first-timer Dan Gilroy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;, that aesthetic isn&amp;#39;t the time-stamped Los Angeles of &lt;em&gt;Chinatown&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;LA Confidential&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#39;s the murky, off-brand L.A. of Michael Mann or Nicolas Winding Refn&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Drive&lt;/em&gt;. Remote, nameless streets and underpasses. Endless stretches of highway going from nowhere to nowhere. A never-ending ghost town dotted with marginal lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and the first unit worked in perfect concert to capture and sustain that mood. Even the interior scenes were desolate. The term &amp;quot;skeleton crew&amp;quot; was never more apt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you feel a slight kinship to Lou&amp;#39;s shadow existence, beginning your work when most other people disappear into sleep? Did he fascinate you the way he fascinated me—like watching a shark circle a wounded fish? Admirably, Gyllenhaal never allows Lou Bloom to betray the purity of your vision of L.A. He lives in perpetual half-light, never exposing himself, except when it&amp;#39;s time for him to feed, literally, at the trough of misery (whether accidentally or intentionally). He has the inevitability of a vulture in the desert, the moral compass of a starving hyena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are probably functional parallels between your work and the service Lou provides. You both are independent and free of direct supervision, a separate but essential piece of a larger effort. Both of you live and work in the opposite direction of most human&amp;#39;s circadian rhythms and see very few people other than those that choose, or are forced, to live that existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other parallel came to mind as I watched this film. If cinema is – and I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;ll agree with me here, Mike – a continuing conversation, then Gyllenhaal&amp;#39;s Lou Bloom is flawlessly described in this quote from another, equally vivid film about an organism attuned to its environment: &amp;quot;…a survivor, unclouded by conscience, remorse, or delusions of morality.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To all the Nightcrawlers,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Birdman or The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Yeah, you, who at the end of our screening of &lt;em&gt;Birdman or The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance&lt;/em&gt; actually said, and I quote, &amp;quot;Well, I liked it…&amp;quot; (at this point you actually paused for effect) &amp;quot;…but I didn&amp;#39;t love it.&amp;quot; I could almost hear the snap from the air-quotes bracketing the word &amp;#39;love&amp;#39;. I repressed my indignant fist clench long enough to make sure you were not being waggish—because that would have actually been pretty funny. But nope, you were just being ignorant, without any of the unexpected virtue.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow me to make very clear why I feel the way I do, even though I&amp;#39;m sure you are already constructing your pithy response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alejandro González Iñárritu is the kind of director that even when I&amp;#39;m not completely taken with a particular film (I&amp;#39;m looking at you, &lt;em&gt;Babel&lt;/em&gt;), I love that he exists. As with Michael Gondry, Von Trier, Alexander Payne, Kathryn Bigelow, and now Bennett Miller, these are men and women for who film is a place where you try and scrape at little bits of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some filmmakers for who the creative process is more akin to a demonstration of a truth, the late Stanley Kubrick and David Fincher come to mind, but Iñárritu and his peers seem to be searching for something less definitive with the films they make. And I&amp;#39;m pretty sure even they aren&amp;#39;t certain if they are going to find it at the end of one hundred and twenty minutes. To dedicate the time and energy necessary to produce &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; feature film when you are not at all clear if it will work, much less make any sense, takes some huge cojones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This film could have been a spectacular &lt;em&gt;Nymphomania&lt;/em&gt;-type disaster were it not so fundamentally well executed. It was that ambitious. The number of opportunities for missteps, the huge risks - both in performance as well as intention and structure - were countless. But it all worked, beautifully, elegantly. It has been a long time since I left a theatre feeling so sure of the value of film; of the possibilities of creating something other than a competent entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you and your banal commentary took a huge dump all over my exuberance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, that cynical disregard for the actual content of a particular work was one of the themes of &lt;em&gt;Birdman or The Unexpected Virtue of Ignorance&lt;/em&gt;. Even the naysayers, the parasitic creatures that swim around the edges of any creative endeavor looking to bathe in some of the reflected light, had their moment. Did you feel an echo in your withered soul when Iñárritu uses Keaton&amp;#39;s character as a surrogate to vent his rage against a particularly vile type of theatre critic? Or did that go over your head too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot will be written about the parallels between the actors and the characters they play; Naomi Watts as the successful but pathologically insecure actress, Keaton&amp;#39;s character is a hive of meta-references to both his and Iñárritu&amp;#39;s careers, Edward Norton as the brilliant but irredeemably disruptive talent. There is also the feigned single take that takes place over a series of weeks, which was both useful and technically brilliant. But that is all window dressing. What drives the film is the notion that sometimes vain, petty, venal men and women manage to craft some art. Somehow these very characteristics are as essential to creation as dedication, discipline and talent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m guessing this probably passed you by while you were busy crafting bon mots about the ludicrousness of Ed Norton&amp;#39;s prosthetic junk. Because it is not to enough to be petty, venal and vain unless you actually have something to bring to the dance. Otherwise you are just fodder for other people&amp;#39;s creative expression.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/24/birdman-or-the-unexpected-virtue-of-ignorance.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/24/birdman-or-the-unexpected-virtue-of-ignorance.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The One I Love</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Of all forms of art, painting still feels to me like the most romantic and sophisticated. Maybe it&amp;#39;s ignorance, or just plain envy, but I still marvel when someone can create a new world simply with a mixing of color and a flick of the wrist. Based on &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt;, I think director Charlie McDowell feels the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He shouldn&amp;#39;t feel that way. McDowell&amp;#39;s first feature film is a real doozy, and a filmmaking tutorial on how to leverage a smart script, with limited locations and actors, into something much grander than his tiny canvas should allow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s clear, from the evocative poster design to an emotional expression by co-star Mark Duplass, that he&amp;#39;s using painting as shorthand for enlightenment throughout the film. Or at least that&amp;#39;s how Elizabeth Moss, who plays Duplass&amp;#39;s wife, interprets his dabbling in the fine art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, a man who paints must be a sensitive soul, right? Or is that just a projection? And if a woman appreciates the arts, does that threaten a man who lacks those same skills?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions in this film go much further than that, of course. Should we work to improve ourselves, or change our expectations of others? At what point are we each still trying to realize our potential versus living in a fantasy? How do we see ourselves, and how do others see us? And what would happen if those two scenarios were somehow drawn together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m only teasing the outline of the film itself, but I feel that&amp;#39;s appropriate. You and I both know what the real picture looks like, Jeremy. But there are so many fun and unexpected turns in this dissection of a marriage that it would be a shame to reveal too much ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/9/gone-girl.html&quot;&gt;sounds familiar&lt;/a&gt;, I know). Yet what makes &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; so appealing is that it&amp;#39;s not just a shaded portrait of a relationship, but a tangled and interpretive piece that begs to be examined from multiple angles. A sort of filmic M.C. Escher drawing. Within the first 20 minutes, when the couple goes on a retreat at the behest of their therapist, the film transforms into something that&amp;#39;s much higher-concept and richer in theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people will no doubt take issues with the lack of clarity. McDowell has chosen to paint his world in the abstract. But I would argue that this choice is to the film&amp;#39;s credit. The larger metaphor being explored is so strong that it doesn&amp;#39;t require more information. I was happy dissecting pure emotion to discover the film&amp;#39;s truths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the sign of a great piece of art—painted or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/23/the-one-i-love.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/23/the-one-i-love.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Province of Television</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dear Television,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look at you, all grown up. Nudity, foul language, and Steve Buscemi. I hardly recognize you anymore. Of course, much of that has to do with the fact that you&amp;#39;re no longer exactly what people used to call television. Sometimes elective surgery &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be a good thing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades, the nicest thing you could have said about yourself was that you were free. Ironically, it was not until people started paying for you, one way or another, that you became something other than a delivery system for commercials every twelve minutes or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid to late 80s, with the advent of Beta and VHS cassettes, miniseries&amp;#39; began to be marketed as complete works, sans commercials. They found their way into video stores and people&amp;#39;s homes—usually event programming like &lt;em&gt;Shogun&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Rich Man, Poor Man.&lt;/em&gt; All of a sudden television wasn&amp;#39;t just what was being broadcast at any particular hour. People could choose when and how they watched their programs. Incidentally, this new marketing strategy also showed creative types what possibilities might exist for long form television, stripped of the structural constraints that were, until then, endemic to your form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coupled with the meteoric improvement in base technology (you used to have screens not much larger than an iPad) as well as production quality, what was being broadcast into people&amp;#39;s homes came more and more to mimic the gold standard. HBO and it&amp;#39;s imitators began to make shows that not only eschewed the usual rigid structural constraints of network television, but began to introduce content that you would have blushed at in your Mary-Ann and Ginger days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In brief, you came more and more to resemble the very thing that had held you at arm&amp;#39;s length for decades: cinema. Until that moment, your only point of contact with your older, more sophisticated sibling had been &lt;em&gt;Love Boat&lt;/em&gt; guest shots for faded stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinema and its adherents had long held you in contempt—like a child everyone wished had stayed hidden in the basement, eating fish heads. But that all changed once emerging specialty channels began to demonstrate the valuable demographics they were able to pull—and what kind of creative freedom those markets promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctions between the two forms – cinema and whatever you are becoming – are now breaking down so quickly that we will probably have to come up with a new word. &lt;em&gt;Cinevision&lt;/em&gt;, or something similarly trite. But the transition is not complete yet, and the distinctions are not simply technical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way that you can easily watch a film at home without losing much of the experience, technically or atmospherically, I have also been to more than a few &lt;em&gt;Dr. Who&lt;/em&gt; cinema experiences. National Geographic also plays regularly on IMAX screens, and it&amp;#39;s not strange at all to see something that straddles both medias, like Joss Whedon&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Firefly/Serenity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing you are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, though, is the soul of wit. Concision is not your strong suit. Not yet, anyways. The very thing that you offer as your greatest gift: the richness and possibilities of long form story telling, is the quality that limits you most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taxi Driver&lt;/em&gt; would flail as anything other than a tight 114 minutes. &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; can only exist at 119 minutes—not a minute more. Some creations are not meant to live long lives. Just fierce, brief ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as the technical aspects have equalized, and as much as we&amp;#39;re seeing the same actors and directors, these two forms – film and television – are still as disparate as books and music, theater and sculpture. It&amp;#39;s not that you cannot successfully adapt something as profoundly well-executed as &lt;em&gt;Fargo&lt;/em&gt;, or competently rework the curiously epicurean world of &lt;em&gt;Hannibal&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#39;s just that in doing so you change them fundamentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feeling you get at the conclusion of &lt;em&gt;Deadwood&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The Hour&lt;/em&gt;, as opposed to stepping out of an experience like &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt;, is a subtle one, but – for me, anyways – profound. &lt;em&gt;Amelie&lt;/em&gt;, and more recently Michael Haneke&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Amour&lt;/em&gt;, are also superb examples of stories that would collapse under their own weight if they were stretched out to accommodate the scope of a miniseries. You could produce something with similar themes, even with the same participants, that may well be outstanding. But it will never duplicate the intensity and impact of those two hours in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&amp;#39;m glad you look the way you do. Just yesterday I witnessed an excellent example of what you do so well: a Welsh/BBC series called &lt;em&gt;Hinterland&lt;/em&gt;. Great writing, interesting visuals, competent performances. The strange thing was that the very first episode was ninety minutes long, self-contained, and gave no previous context for the world or characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn&amp;#39;t bite in quite the same way. There was a restraint inherent in the storytelling, a tendency to bow to the one expediency television can never escape: that there is always a next episode.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/22/the-province-of-television.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/22/the-province-of-television.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Conversation with Jess Gonchor, Production Designer</title>
				<description>&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the set of &lt;em&gt;Hail, Caesar!&lt;/em&gt; – his sixth film with the Joel and Ethan Coen – Academy Award-nominated Production Designer Jess Gonchor talks to Christopher Redmond about his craft, his career, and what it takes to rise through the ranks in Hollywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What made you want to become a Production Designer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason I always felt that I had an eye for what could tell a story. What looks good and what does not look good to tell a story. Not in context to the world, but what is a background that is going to help tell a story. If there was an actor out there that couldn&amp;#39;t speak, what could support telling a story visually? I fell into studio set building, which I also loved, and I embraced that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And now you&amp;#39;re working on your sixth Coen Brother&amp;#39;s film, &lt;em&gt;Hail, Caesar!&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I&amp;#39;m sort of back in Hollywood for the first time on a big build movie. We have six sound stages that we&amp;#39;re building sets on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the guys, one of the painters that&amp;#39;s on the crew, came up to me and goes, &amp;quot;Hey, do you remember me? It&amp;#39;s Bobby so-and-so.&amp;quot; And I&amp;#39;m like, &amp;quot;Yeah, I remember you.&amp;quot; And he goes, &amp;quot;Congratulations,&amp;quot; and he sort of nudged the guy next to him, and he goes ,&amp;quot;this is a guy twenty years ago who said &amp;#39;I&amp;#39;m gonna be a production designer some day,&amp;#39; and we all laughed.&amp;quot; But here I am! And I&amp;#39;ve got a couple hundred people working on this job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking at your resumé, it really seems like you worked your way up through the art department to get to where you are.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s sort of been my path, and I don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s the normal path, because you do get labeled in this business for something that you do—especially if you&amp;#39;re good at it. It&amp;#39;s hard to work your way out of that type of thing sometimes. But I always got to the point where I wasn&amp;#39;t fed up with it, but I just sort of had enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building sets ran their course with me. Being in charge of people that were building the sets ran its course. And then drawing the sets up for people to build ran its course. And then telling the people who draw the sets up how to draw them up, being an art director, ran it&amp;#39;s course. And then the opportunity to start designing came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How exactly did you get your first gig as a production designer on a film?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very hard to get my first job doing it, so I went into commercial production design and started designing commercials. I had hoped that I would do a good enough job in that for someone to recognize my work. But as luck would have it, and as hard work would have it, I worked with Bennett Miller on a lot of commercials, and he had yet to direct something. So he turned to me one day and said, &amp;quot;Jess, you want to go to Winnipeg and do a movie about Truman Capote?&amp;quot; And I was like, &amp;quot;Sure, let&amp;#39;s go!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, at least my work was recognized and people could see that I had an eye and I could tell a story visually, and I could design something, and I could be fiscally responsible for a budget. There&amp;#39;s so many things that go around for production design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Could you define, in your own words, what it is that a production designer does?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that the responsibility of the production designer is to tell a story visually. Take away all the acting and take away all the singing and all the performance and see a movie without that. Does it still tell a story if words aren&amp;#39;t spoken? Does it still mean something? Does it move itself along page-by-page visually? That&amp;#39;s what a production designer does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You read a script and you figure out, &amp;quot;Okay, how can I tell this story visually?&amp;quot; And you have to go out into the world and say, &amp;quot;Okay, this is going to have to be a practical location where we&amp;#39;ll fix up and do something, then we&amp;#39;re going to have to go to a stage for this. Then we&amp;#39;re going to go shoot a scene on a train, then we&amp;#39;re going to go back to the set.&amp;quot; So you have to put a lot of pieces together. And then you have to answer to a dollar amount. You really can&amp;#39;t go over, or you may be looked at as somebody who&amp;#39;s too extravagant, someone who doesn&amp;#39;t understand what it takes just to shoot a scene and just build two walls if that&amp;#39;s all you&amp;#39;re going to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m a big believer in a concept for a movie. Like, what am I trying to get out of the production design? What&amp;#39;s it trying to say? Is there a colour palette or style that I&amp;#39;m working with? Am I helping keep pace with my scenery for the movie?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s anything from cars, to practical sets, to big giant stage builds, to a pen that somebody&amp;#39;s writing with or a piece of paper that they&amp;#39;re writing on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you get involved with the Coen brothers? What attracted them to you? I assume it was easy to be attracted to them…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I was always a fan of their movies. Listen, a lot of this business is timing. Across the board, with actors, designers, all sorts of people. A lot of this has to do with timing. &lt;em&gt;Capote&lt;/em&gt; had just came out, they saw it, and they were looking for someone to design &lt;em&gt;No Country for Old Men&lt;/em&gt;. I know that they interviewed a lot of people and they were exhausted with that (laughs). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, truth to be told, the story is I was on a movie, and they called my agent after they saw &lt;em&gt;Capote&lt;/em&gt; and said, &amp;quot;Hey, this guy Jess…we want to talk to him. He may fit into our family over here. We&amp;#39;re pretty down to earth, pretty low-budget, pretty simple. When we overstate the look of something, it&amp;#39;s still understated in a way.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was on a movie and I was unavailable and the movie went down. My agent said, hold on, and she got me an interview with the guys. So I put together some really nice images of what I thought, after reading the script, what &lt;em&gt;No Country&lt;/em&gt; should look like. And we hit it off. Since then I&amp;#39;ve learned what they like, they&amp;#39;ve learned what I like, and together we&amp;#39;ve formed a bond of just being on the same page for filmmaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And they obviously trust you with their designing movies now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the trust that they instil in me is pretty amazing. I&amp;#39;m super thankful for that. They know that I get them, so there&amp;#39;s a trust now. Yes, there&amp;#39;s a lot – a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; – dialogue between us, but this is the sixth movie I&amp;#39;ve made with them right now, so we know how to gauge it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All through the first movie we did, I think I came out of the gate with something special, and they recognized it and then obviously things worked out after. It takes a lot of hard work, but it worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I had an art director tell me to ask this question: what percentage of your vision do you feel shows up in the final film?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um, 90 per cent. I mean, what else is there? It&amp;#39;s all your vision. If they use something or not, it&amp;#39;s all… I mean I don&amp;#39;t know. I might go to 100 per cent. I don&amp;#39;t want to be a pig about it, but… maybe not. Let&amp;#39;s just say 90. That&amp;#39;s a tough question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If I name a couple of your films can you describe them to me from a production designer&amp;#39;s point of view? Let&amp;#39;s start with Capote.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bleak. Bleak, desperate, telling a story of this family that was murdered in cold blood, and the two guys that were guilty of it. Like an Andrew Wyeth painting, it&amp;#39;s just really wintery, cold. It had to feel vulnerable, bleak. If I sewed it all up tight in a blanket I would say it&amp;#39;s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Winnipeg?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(laughs) Winnipeg was the perfect place to go, when it was all said and done. But it was like a still life painting to me, and I still feel that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How about The Devil Wear&amp;#39;s Prada?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you something. I did not have a movie out yet that I could call my own. I had art directed a bunch, but &lt;em&gt;Capote&lt;/em&gt; wasn&amp;#39;t out yet. I interviewed with the director and the producer and I&amp;#39;m pretty sure if they saw &lt;em&gt;Capote&lt;/em&gt;, I would not have been the guy to get that job! (laughs). It was complete polar opposite of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I remember this was in 2005 and I had just got my first iPod and it was a white one with silver on the back and this black dial. I had this thing and I had a few photos of Vogue, and this that, but I had this iPod in my pocket. And they asked me, &amp;quot;so what do you think the movie is?&amp;quot; And I pulled out this brand new, shiny iPod, and I said: &amp;quot;I think this is what the movie looks like.&amp;quot; David Frankel and Wendy Finerman were like, &amp;quot;Hmm, okay, tell us more.&amp;quot; So that sort of piqued their interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was just high fashion, polished colours, beautiful shades of white with some colour mixed in. It is what it was. It was opening up a 500-page issue of Vogue magazine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And then going to No Country For Old Men?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;No Country&lt;/em&gt;, I had a very specific colour palette in mind for that too. (pauses) It feels like an easy one but it was sort of a hard one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a sense of being desperate. To me, the whole movie was about the colours of the desert. Being out in harsh environments. I just started to look at shapes against the sky. Just sort of open land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/features/inline/a-conversation-with-jess-gonchor-production-designer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jess Gonchor&amp;#39;s colour palette for No Country for Old Men&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started looking at negative space for that movie. I don&amp;#39;t want to get too deep, but I was just embracing the sky in everything we did. So instead of looking at the outline of a trailer, I sort of looked at it upside down like, &amp;quot;what&amp;#39;s the outline of the sky?&amp;quot;.It helped me to define the landscape. The landscape of West Texas and how hot it was and how thirsty you were out there. Getting that message across of space and dessert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the colour palette I made for that: I knocked off a Rothko painting and had pretty much just the colours you would find in the West Texas desert. I put a splatter of blood to top it off. So it was a few shades of brown, a shade of rust, and shade of concrete, and then a spatter of blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you communicate your vision to the rest of the department exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have extensive, extensive research done. We plaster our department with research. Our entire hallway (for &lt;em&gt;Hail, Caesar!&lt;/em&gt;), which probably runs 300 feet—both sides of the hallway are covered with research of the era. The period movies like a Gene Kelly movie, a song and dance thing, an Ester Williams thing, a Nöel Coward thing. All of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I&amp;#39;ll have my concepts and illustrations and drawings on the other side of the hallways. And I&amp;#39;ll break it down into scenes, so everybody on the whole movie can walk through the hallways and see, &amp;quot;Oh, we open in a Chinese restaurant, here&amp;#39;s the research on it.&amp;quot; This takes a couple of months but someone can walk through the whole movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What would you do on a smaller film like Capote?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did on &lt;em&gt;Capote&lt;/em&gt; was I made up a colour palette, a 5x7 card, with six colours on it. I laminated the card and on one side I had the colours on it, and on the other side I had my name and my cell number. I punched a hole in it and put a little clip on it and I gave it to all the people on the set, namely the set PAs. I said, &amp;quot;If anybody sees any colour that is not on this card, call me up and I will get it out of this set. I don&amp;#39;t care if it&amp;#39;s a pen, a car, a hat, you know what I mean?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I always make up some kind of colour palette to get on board with the costume designer, and sometimes he or she will agree on another colour, but I feel it&amp;#39;s important to maintain continuity between something like that and the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So how big was your card for The Lone Ranger? It couldn&amp;#39;t have been just 5x7.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Laughs) No, it wasn&amp;#39;t. It wasn&amp;#39;t. But that was a movie about landscapes too. You know that was really a true Western. It didn&amp;#39;t want to be a pulp Western, like a Roy Rogers thing. It wanted to be a void of a lot of colour. Like reds. There was a little bit here and there, but mainly we really tried to stay true to the old John Ford Westerns. Almost black and white type of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell me about your different approach between &lt;em&gt;The Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;True Grit&lt;/em&gt;? Two Westerns, but a very different approach.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, the budget. &lt;em&gt;Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt; was ten times the budget that &lt;em&gt;True Grit&lt;/em&gt; was. But they were different sort of eras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt;, they were building the train line so people were just traveling across America and discovering this new World. There was a lot of open landscapes and a lot of America discovering itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;True Grit&lt;/em&gt;, the train line was already in. These towns were established, so it wasn&amp;#39;t this saloon swinging movie. It had an established town, it was built up, it was functioning, people had a purpose, people had jobs, people had responsibilities. It wasn&amp;#39;t the old Wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt; was like the Wild West of yesteryear. I fell like &lt;em&gt;True Grit&lt;/em&gt; was more of a modern day Western. I mean, it took place in Arkansas. Some people say it was an Eastern. We were also able to stylize it into a Coen Borthers way with some of the sets. Mixing the grocery in with all the produce and the meats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you prefer the big pulpy type of world-building like &lt;em&gt;The Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Devil Wears Prada&lt;/em&gt;, or the more subtle stuff like &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt; and *A Serious Man?&lt;/strong&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#39;s an equal challenge. Big movies come with big problems and small movies come with big problems. There are no small-problem movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really feel a movie like &lt;em&gt;Inside Llewyn Davis&lt;/em&gt; is so much harder to do than a &lt;em&gt;Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt; or a &lt;em&gt;True Grit&lt;/em&gt;, because the camera is locked-off. It&amp;#39;s like looking at a photograph. The audience gets to examine. And I tried to avoid that, because I want them to look at the performance and I want my stuff just supporting that. But if somebody&amp;#39;s looking around, a movie like &lt;em&gt;Inside Llewyn Davis&lt;/em&gt;, which is very slow-paced with the camera locked off, just looking at the performances and singing performances, is much more of a challenge than doing a giant movie where you&amp;#39;re flying by things on horses, on trains, on cars. Those things are much more forgiving. Challenging in their own way – you have to do monstrous stuff – but I find the finer details stuff is much less forgiving as a production designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think an actor will say that too. If an actor is on a boat chase, they&amp;#39;ve got the wind and someone&amp;#39;s chasing them, and they&amp;#39;re acting above that, as opposed to citing Shakespeare on a stool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If someone said, &amp;quot;Okay Jess, we&amp;#39;re going to make the film you want to make.&amp;quot; Would you prefer a period-piece, something sci-fi, or what?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A period piece, really. I love the 50s and the 60s. It&amp;#39;s fun to do the period pieces. The futuristic things, I would love to get in there but it&amp;#39;s definitely more intimidating, because we don&amp;#39;t know what the future looks like. We can draw on the past and put our own twist on the past, so it&amp;#39;s definitely more comfortable to do things that have already happened. I sort of gravitate to that. But I would definitely like somebody to ask me to put my spin on what the future would look like too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary—look, as long as the script is great. To me, it&amp;#39;s all about the script. A movie like &lt;em&gt;Foxcatcher&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;#39;s an amazing script, my buddy&amp;#39;s directing it, he&amp;#39;s got a great cast, it&amp;#39;s 1980s and I think I ended up assigning a really good look to that movie, but it&amp;#39;s sort of contemporary. So you have to figure out how you&amp;#39;re going to make something like that look good. And I think it&amp;#39;s amazing. I think I did come up with some good concepts for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the contemporary things, as long as the script is good. But if there&amp;#39;s a good script in the Civil War, yeah, that&amp;#39;s a home run right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I noticed you were the Second Unit Director on Foxcatcher. Is that part of the career path or just a one-off?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, I think it&amp;#39;s part of the career path. I don&amp;#39;t think I could ever stop doing production design, I love it. You&amp;#39;re the first person on the movie, besides the director. On a movie like &lt;em&gt;Hail, Caesar!,&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;#39;ve got five months of prep, because that&amp;#39;s what it takes. On &lt;em&gt;The Lone Ranger&lt;/em&gt;, you get nine months of prep. So you&amp;#39;re with the script, you&amp;#39;re with the director, you&amp;#39;re with the environment, and they trust you to tell the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I actually said to (Bennett Miller): &amp;quot;Look, I know you have your hands full. If there&amp;#39;s anything I can help with and go shoot, I would love to do it.&amp;quot; He&amp;#39;s like, &amp;quot;Nobody knows the story better than you, Jess, and that would be fantastic. I would embrace that.&amp;quot; So no giant scenes with acting, but whatever I could do to do and fill in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get to this point on a movie, you get the material. You get it better than most people on the movie, just because you&amp;#39;ve been living with it for longer, having dialogue with the director for a long time. So yeah, I&amp;#39;d like to do more of that. Or directing on my own. We&amp;#39;ll see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not easy to do that and design a movie, but it was probably one of the most satisfying film experiences I&amp;#39;ve ever had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So do you look at someone like Robert Stromberg (director of Maleficent) as an inspiration? Because there aren&amp;#39;t that many directors who go through the avenue of a production designer into directing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, Alfred Hitchcock. I mean that&amp;#39;s why his movies looked so good. He was an art director for a while, and his visual style is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, I&amp;#39;m friendly with Rob and thrilled to death with what he&amp;#39;s done. And &lt;em&gt;hell yeah&lt;/em&gt; I look up to him, absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He came up the visual effects side though, and you&amp;#39;re doing more the classical route. Are more people coming in the visual effects side, now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, they are, because there&amp;#39;s a lot more movies like that. A lot of visual effects in movies, so people are crossing over who are artists and creating the worlds that some movies require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think that it all starts with the script. Whatever your training, if you can understand the story you&amp;#39;re trying to tell and not just upstage everything with a background that looks good, then I think you can do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My path was the theatre, I started in high school. I will credit forever that backstage crew that I with in high school, learning about what it takes to do something with absolutely nothing. Just a roll of duct tape and a couple of twigs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/21/a-conversation-with-jess-gonchor-production-designer.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/21/a-conversation-with-jess-gonchor-production-designer.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Open Windows</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;My first thought when I saw your job title was: &amp;quot;Well, that sounds stupid—it must be a mistake.&amp;quot; Which was similar to the thought I had when I first heard the concept for &lt;em&gt;Open Windows&lt;/em&gt;. But after watching the film – and looking up the definition of &amp;quot;documentalist&amp;quot; – I can say that both things, sadly, actually exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start with the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Told completely through the point-of-view of a computer desktop, &lt;em&gt;Open Windows&lt;/em&gt; tries to combine the experience of multitasking (which people do when watching a bad movie) with, well, a bad movie. It would be amazingly meta, if only it wasn&amp;#39;t so stupid,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is notable for a few reasons: it&amp;#39;s yet another low-budget/high-concept thriller starring Elijah Wood, who can&amp;#39;t seem to get enough of these types of films lately; it also stars Sasha Grey, famous for her low-budget/low-concept/high-intensity porn. Both play to their strengths, Wood as wide-eyed, whiny geek, and Grey as a low-energy, emotionally detached rape victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts off promisingly enough, with plenty of visual possibilities, especially compared to restricted-premise films like &lt;em&gt;Buried&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/10/locke.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Locke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In this case, we have the ability to navigate between screens/scenes at a ComiCon-type conference in a hotel, before twisting into an impossibly absurd game of cat and mouse. Or, more accurately, mouse and click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which bring us to you. Your job, by definition, is to search databases on behalf of other users. In other words, you operate similarly to the film&amp;#39;s mysterious villain, who keeps hacking into security cameras, cellphones, and other people&amp;#39;s accounts to give Wood&amp;#39;s fanboy character the perfect view of everything that&amp;#39;s happening to his beloved starlet. What this really meant for you on set, I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it was doing research to understand what type of 3D rendering is possible by syncing a bag full of webcams, then I&amp;#39;m afraid you failed miserably. In the film&amp;#39;s most &amp;quot;inventive&amp;quot; action sequence, the interpretation of events looks like a bad animation test for YTV&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;ReBoot&lt;/em&gt;. Or maybe you were doing more practical research: trying to find English voiceover actors for this Spanish production. Even bigger fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s really nothing to recommend here, other than you need a new job. And a new title.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/20/open-windows.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/20/open-windows.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Fury</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Day in and day out, surrounded by piles of animal viscera. The smell of decaying flesh, the convincing simulacra of human bodies subject to disfiguring misuse—it must have worn on you. Or at some point did you become indifferent to the mud-caked entrails? What was it like, knowing that your work spoke directly to the butchery humanity will engage in, often on the shallowest of pretenses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War often comes down to a very straightforward choice: kill or be killed. That dilemma, and whether or not a third option exists in an operational theater of war, is the preoccupation of your film, &lt;em&gt;Fury&lt;/em&gt;. Or as Brad Pitt&amp;#39;s character, Sgt. Don (Wardaddy) Collier opines: &amp;quot;Ideals are peaceful, history is violent.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would imagine you must have had mixed feelings about this particular job. On one hand, the job of set decorator can be somewhat mundane. For instance, your work on KAVANAGH QC is mostly dull, British, middle-class interiors and bare wooden benches. Bit of a yawner, I would guess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fury&lt;/em&gt; appears anything but dull. How often is set decoration a fundamental component of a film&amp;#39;s aesthetic? Usually its value is in it melding seamlessly with the background. But your work was pivotal in setting a tone of bleak and relentless carnage. Everywhere the camera turned, there was a new vista of destroyed buildings, dead and looted animal corpses, and human beings crushed into paste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps your work on &lt;em&gt;Band of Brothers&lt;/em&gt; prepared you, but this piece is far more graphic. And it really is ever-present; except for one short interval, the whole 135-minute run time is backlit by your grisly landscape of total war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That relentlessness was obviously intentional, designed to give us a sense of what it might have been like to wade through the mire day after day. The whole film seems designed to create a pall of moral ambivalence. An ambivalence that seems the only possible way to survive the daily horror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did your job, Malcolm, no matter how unsettling or grotesque it may have seemed. &lt;em&gt;Fury&lt;/em&gt; is, in many ways, about how humans push through revulsion in order to perform a necessary task. The importance of overcoming the inherent human tendency to abhor violence and killing – not the fear of death but of taking another&amp;#39;s life – has always been an underexplored aspect of war films. Yet it has always been the most complex part of creating useful soldiers. It&amp;#39;s even more difficult to break the prohibition against killing than it is to suppress people&amp;#39;s fear of their own death. In this sense, &lt;em&gt;Fury&lt;/em&gt; is an effective study of how one man is broken down, incrementally, until he can operate efficiently in circumstances few of us could imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your filmis perhaps the most courageous English language production I have seen in its meticulous attention to the details of war. Never once did I feel the camera pull away simply because an image was unpalatable. Nor did it linger simply for prurient reasons. If the camera stayed fixed for a moment or two, it was only to give us a chance to absorb the profound wrongness of what we were seeing. That unflinching regard may cost this film the box office (and even some of the critical acclaim) it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some clumsy narrative construction, &lt;em&gt;Fury&lt;/em&gt; is a remarkable examination of the kind of moral quandary that otherwise good people must face when thrust into armed conflict. And while the story is told from an American point of view, it becomes clear, rather quickly, how little moral distance there is between soldiers when the shooting starts. Neither side escapes being dragged, both literally and metaphysically, through the mud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The honesty, courage, and effectiveness of those details are due, in part, to your dedication to authenticity, Malcolm. I wish I could applaud you for that. But the best I can do is recommend that people see for themselves why this film, and your work in it, is worth watching. Even if it wears heavily.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/17/fury.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/17/fury.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Tusk</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll be up front and say that if I hadn&amp;#39;t known beforehand that Johnny Depp would appear in &lt;em&gt;Tusk&lt;/em&gt; under a pseudonym – a &amp;quot;secret&amp;quot; that everybody and their grandmother seems to know by this point – I would never have recognized him. So you deserve some props for that. However, while he&amp;#39;s hidden beneath that brilliant makeup, Depp (or &amp;quot;Lapointe&amp;quot;) overacts to such a horrific degree that&amp;#39;s it&amp;#39;s almost unbearable to watch. Which is indicative of the problem with &lt;em&gt;Tusk&lt;/em&gt; as a whole: it never seems sure what type of movie it&amp;#39;s trying to be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s take, for instance, a late-in-the-game flashback sequence in which his retired homicide detective recalls the time hefirst met the film&amp;#39;s villain, played by Michael Parks. I sat in my seat, utterly aghast, as the two actors stared awkwardly at each other, forcing out allegedly humorous dialogue (apparently faux-Quebecois accents are Kevin Smith&amp;#39;s idea of biting satire) in a bit that goes on for so long that the unspooling of quantum time ceases to retain any meeting. And then, all of a sudden, Lapointe returns to the present and somberly states that he was once missed an opportunity to save one of Parks&amp;#39; victims. I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;ll agree that there are talented filmmakers out there who can walk the line between humour and tragedy. Kevin Smith, sadly, doesn&amp;#39;t seem to be one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;#39;t much of a surprise that &lt;em&gt;Tusk&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#39;s biggest issue is how it treats it&amp;#39;s central character, Wallace Bryton of the Not-See Party podcast. [As an aside: did you ever stick around on the set once Depp&amp;#39;s makeup was applied, and, if so, did you notice Smith quietly chuckling to himself every time a character mistakes &amp;quot;Not-See Party&amp;quot; for &amp;quot;Nazi Party&amp;quot;? I feel like that would have made for a pretty unpleasant drinking game.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo...as soon as we meet Bryton, he&amp;#39;s already such a loud, crude, belligerent asshole (for lack of a better term) that it&amp;#39;s impossible sympathize when Parks abducts him and reveals his plans to surgically alter him into a man-walrus hybrid. To be fair, the initial reveal is by far the funniest moment of the film; the group I saw the film with was nearly in tears. And yet, we&amp;#39;re also supposed to empathize with Wallace, even though he&amp;#39;s the focus of a goofy sight-gag one second, then tearfully reflecting upon his lost humanity in the next. The wild tonal shifts are enough to give you whiplash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that point, the ludicrous design of Wallace the Walrus makes it abundantly clear that we&amp;#39;re supposed to be laughing &lt;em&gt;at&lt;/em&gt; him; Smith never attempts to hide just how artificial the costume really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s odd that such a messy film would have a villain as compelling as Michael Parks. As goofy as the material is, he imbues the character with an interesting mix of madness and sadness, all slowly revealed as the reasons for his walrus-love become apparent. It&amp;#39;s captivating stuff, but given how scattershot the rest of the film is, it&amp;#39;s a safe assumption that this speaks more to Parks&amp;#39; strength as an actor than it does to the quality of the material he was working with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really don&amp;#39;t know how I could sell someone on this movie. It certainly doesn&amp;#39;t work as a horror movie. Or even a thriller. And yet, there&amp;#39;s really nothing funny about it. Here&amp;#39;s hoping that your actor-concealment skills are put to better use in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/16/tusk.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/16/tusk.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Citizen Marc</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At one time or another everyone has wanted to be a superhero. Who hasn&amp;#39;t imagined what it would feel like to stand victorious, fist raised, cape flowing? There&amp;#39;s something honourable about battling evil, about wanting to make the world a better place. There&amp;#39;s also something distinctly adolescent about the idea. It appeals to our basest desires of wanting to be powerful and universally adored. But isn&amp;#39;t fighting a noble cause supposed to be a reward in itself? Isn&amp;#39;t that why, after the villain is vanquished, Bruce Wayne, Peter Parker, and Clark Kent don&amp;#39;t stick around waiting for the news vans to show up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently all the comic books that marijuana activist Marc Emery read as a kid were missing the last page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interspersed between numerous news clips and interviews in the documentary &lt;em&gt;Citizen Marc&lt;/em&gt;, your animations depict Emery as a bespectacled, chiseled superhero with a receding hairline, battling against the Big Bad Government of Canada—and anyone else who dares keep him from his goal of legalizing marijuana. The tone is perfectly balanced between mockery and begrudging admiration. After all, Emery may be a cartoonish megalomaniac, but he also may be right when he claims to have done more than anyone else to advance the marijuana movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Citizen Marc&lt;/em&gt;, instead of lionizing Emery, portrays him as a narcissistic mercenary. This is clear in his origin story: Emery&amp;#39;s love affair with the almighty dollar began as a pre-teen, when he started selling comics to friends, an endeavour that he tells us soon had him earning more than his father. At seventeen, Emery dropped out of school and bought the City Lights bookstore in London, Ontario, the site of what he calls &amp;quot;The Prophecy&amp;quot;. A woman fell in front of his store and had a vision of three symbols pertaining to him: a dollar sign, a spiky leaf, and a brain with a cage around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could only be more ridiculous if he was bitten by an infected spider. Oh yeah, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cnews.canoe.ca/CNEWS/Canada/2011/07/17/18432866.html&quot;&gt;that happened too.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most superheroes, who are content to toil away in obscurity, Emery seems to get stronger with every self-aggrandizing publicity stunt. Sure he&amp;#39;s the Prince of Pot, but he&amp;#39;s also the King of Over-Sharing. It must have been difficult for you and the filmmakers to decide just which period of his life to animate. But you chose well. Against a black background, you outline our caped cannabis crusader in white with the initials M E on his chest, dropping green seeds over the world in his attempt to &amp;quot;overgrow the government.&amp;quot; You show this Ayn Rand-loving libertarian shoveling money into a fire as he buys his way into politics. You depict this sound-bite machine as a modern-day Moses, who inserts himself into religious imagery and bathes in cannabis oil (like Jesus, he claims), referring to his toker acolytes as &amp;quot;the chosen people.&amp;quot; Your simple black and white animation is the perfect juxtaposition for a man whose ideology is painted in broad strokes of grey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all superhero movies there are the innocent bystanders who watch helplessly as their city gets hijacked. &lt;em&gt;Citizen Marc&lt;/em&gt; shows us that it&amp;#39;s not the citizens themselves, but their movement that is being hijacked by Emery&amp;#39;s ego (which, one of his detractors observes, &amp;quot;is 40% of his body weight&amp;quot;). The narrator tells us, over your animation of Emery throwing fireballs at a sentient government building, that his capitalist views and anti-government message aligns him more closely with the Republican agenda. This plays rather strikingly against the footage of Gandhi and Martin Luther King—two masters of civil disobedience to whom Emery guilelessly compares himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know how superheroes get around; Superman is faster than a speeding bullet, Spiderman has his webs, and Batman has a flashy car. &lt;em&gt;Citizen Marc&lt;/em&gt; seems content to let The Prince of Pot hoist himself by his own petard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/15/citizen-marc.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/15/citizen-marc.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
