<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>This is where I Leave You</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Some might find it strange that a dialogue-driven, ensemble dramedy like &lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt; required any stunts. Those people are probably only-children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my brothers and I were kids, we used to stage fights. Mostly in slow-motion with the &amp;quot;nun-nun-nun-nun&amp;quot; sound effect from &lt;em&gt;The Six Million Dollar Man&lt;/em&gt; to accompany punches that purposely didn&amp;#39;t make contact. But sometimes we got into serious fights, with real blood and broken furniture and punches that were most certainly meant to connect. Would I be correct in assuming yYou must have siblings as well.? From the fight scenes, stunt driving, and various choreographed physicality executed by you and your team, it would seem that you have a firm grasp of complex family dynamics. Some might find it strange that a dialogue-driven, ensemble dramedy like &lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt; required any stunts, but those people are probably only-children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;ve seen stunts in a script that you intuitively knew wouldn&amp;#39;t read on screen. Or maybe they were just over-complicated and unnecessary. &lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt;also fights a lot with its proverbial parent – the novel. The film suffers from the typical novelbook-to-film adaptation problem in that where there&amp;#39;s just too much story to pack into 100 minutes. This film is genuinely funny, poignant, and true, with fine performances that unfortunately only scratch the surface of a deeper truth about family and forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the patriarch of the Altman family dies, his widow demands their four adult children spend the week mourning together in the family home. Middle son, Judd, is hiding the fact that he&amp;#39;s flying solo because his wife cheated on him with his boss. His sister Wendy has her hands full with two toddlers, and a workaholic husband. Oldest brother Paul and his wife are trying to get pregnant, and youngest brother Phillip is a loveable ne&amp;#39;er do well who is engaged to his therapist. The Altman matriarch, Hilary, is herself a free-spirited therapist who wrote a tell-all best seller about raising her brood, much to their chagrin. Throughout the course of the week,Which means the Altman siblingss will regress, fight, mourn, and make some heavy life decisions over that timethe course of those seven days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle son Judd takes a physical and emotional beating in this film, and Jason Bateman is certainly a deft enough actor to handle the challenge of skating the thin line between comedy and drama. It helps that you made sure the stunts never feel like slapsticky pratfalls. In an early scene, Judd attempts to break up a particularly ugly fight between his brothers and gets a piece of glass embedded in his forehead for his trouble. After a sufficiently appropriate pause, the rest of the family continues talking and eating like nothing happened. The scene is noteworthy, not because it&amp;#39;s played for humour, but because it&amp;#39;s played for honesty. This film reminds us that in a big family, you&amp;#39;re not more important than anyone else. You just have to take your lumps and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could apply that philosophy to your job, which requires you to coordinate with many different departments - from makeup and costumes, to prop masters, effects coordinators, and of course, the producers and director. That&amp;#39;s a lot of egos to manage, and it&amp;#39;s important that they are all given equal consideration. It seems that director, Shawn Levy, felt the same way about his talent-heavy cast. Working from a screenplay adapted from Jonathan Tropper&amp;#39;s novel, Levy had a lot of character arcs to juggle, so it&amp;#39;s no surprise he had a hard time keeping them all in the air. In addition to Bateman, Jane Fonda, Tina Fey, Adam Driver, Corey Stoll, Kathryn Hahn, Rose Byrne, Timothy Olyphant, Dax Shepard and Connie Britton all punch well above their weight here with the juicy, multi-dimensional characters they get to play. But it&amp;#39;s too much of a good thing. While Levy was spoiled for choice, the audience is starving for a little depth of focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of a film&amp;#39;s genre, when stunts are done well they are suspenseful and clever, and exciting to watch. When done poorly, they&amp;#39;re confusing, repetitive and can bring the narrative to a screeching halt. The same can be said for ensemble pieces. The problem isn&amp;#39;t that &lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;#39;t hit all its marks, it&amp;#39;s that there are just too many marks to hit. And Levy tries to hit them all. Maybe he should have consulted you first.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/3/this-is-where-i-leave-you.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/3/this-is-where-i-leave-you.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Trip to Italy</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s perhaps a bit self-indulgent to write this letter to you. There&amp;#39;s so much else that is essential to the success of &lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt;: the majestic seaside vistas, the stunning culinary creations, the moving soundtrack from Richard Strauss and, yes, Alanis Morrisette. But, first and foremost, I&amp;#39;m a Steve Coogan fan, and I was drawn to this film – and its predecessor, &lt;em&gt;The Trip&lt;/em&gt; – because of your involvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s often hard, here on the left side of the Atlantic, to keep up with your body of work. You&amp;#39;d think that your most successful British show, &lt;em&gt;The Alan Partridge Show&lt;/em&gt; (one of the great comedy series of all time, British or otherwise), would be more readily available over here. But, no. We get &lt;em&gt;The Office&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Extras&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Little Britain&lt;/em&gt;—but no &lt;em&gt;Partridge&lt;/em&gt;. Even the feature-length Alan Partridge film was late in arriving to the New World, and, when it did, appeared only on a modest number of screens. So &lt;em&gt;The Trip&lt;/em&gt; films, for me, are like a distant cousin&amp;#39;s wedding or school reunion: a chance to catch up with my faraway friends and loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;#39;ve revealed my bias, my thoughts on &lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt; might seem obvious and irrelevant. But the film itself plays out behind a veil of irrelevance. It meanders, digresses, loiters, philanders (both figuratively and literally)—but all to a higher purpose. So of course I loved it. Of coursed I loved your performance. Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first &lt;em&gt;Trip&lt;/em&gt; film, which followed you and your travel companion Rob Brydon on a restaurant tour of Northern England, you each played to your respective strengths: Brydon as earnest, motor-mouthed family man; you as the acerbic bachelor injured by his failed ambitions. Here, in subtle degrees of patience and composure, your performance has evolved. The Steve Coogan in this film is a different Steve Coogan than the one who appears in the first. Which is significant, considering how difficult it is, in the first place, to play a plausible version of oneself onscreen. We get a different Rob Brydon, too (though his transformation is expressed primarily through action). While the role-reversal conceit might seem a little too familiar – shades of a body-swap comedy – your delivery makes it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a tribute to you, Brydon, and director Michael Winterbottom, that a two-hour film built from a series of semi-improvised conversations on topics ranging from the number of Batmen Michael Caine has buried to Byron&amp;#39;s culpability in the death of Percy Bysshe Shelley is able not just to maintain its velocity, but to hit a few genuinely affecting beats. The comedy is broad, but the sentiments aren&amp;#39;t. Brydon&amp;#39;s marital struggles don&amp;#39;t play out the way one imagines they will, and remain, by the end of the film, frustratingly (and credibly) unresolved. Your own minor crisis concludes in a quiet scene aboard a small yacht floating in the sunset off the southern Italian coast: a very simple conversation between father and son, unadorned with movie-star impressions or punch-lines or self-sabotaging sarcasm. It unfolds like the thousand other father/son conversations that preceded it, but in the context of your character&amp;#39;s arc through both films, feels sort of profound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this moving stuff in a film that delivers, consistently, lines like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Where do you stand on Michael Bublé?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;On his windpipe?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;#39;re playing yourself, or Alan Partridge, or Paul Calf, or Tommy Saxondale, it&amp;#39;s exactly this sort of alchemic mixture of sympathy and antipathy that makes your characters so likably unlikable, so hilarious, &lt;em&gt;so human&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt; achieves this balance, too. Hopefully, like all superior sequels, it will spawn a slightly disappointing concluding chapter. Might I suggest the wintry climes of central Ontario?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Walk Among the Tombstones</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a sequence halfway through &lt;em&gt;A Walk Among the Tombstones&lt;/em&gt; that is astonishingly well put together. It plays out like a typical meet-cute: a young girl walks into the path of two men, time slows down, their gazes lock, and cheery tunes plays on the soundtrack as man stare after her, slack-jawed. Except it&amp;#39;s anything but typical, since the girl in question is the daughter of a Russian drug dealer, and the two men she&amp;#39;s just entranced are a pair of demented serial killers who target the loved ones of organized crime figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your excellent cutting really generates tension and puts a sinister spin on a familiar trope—too bad everything around it feels so ordinary by comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be completely honest with you, I&amp;#39;m still not entirely sure how I feel about this one. On one hand, we have the great Liam Neeson turning in another fine performance as a private eye with a tortured past. It&amp;#39;s also refreshing to see Neeson play a character who is much more human and grounded in reality than some of his other recent roles (providing, of course, one can accept the reality of watching a man renowned for his badassery be on the receiving end of countless beatings). Additionally, the villains on display are certainly formidable, with the actors exuding menace through subtle gestures instead of dialogue. That, and the brief glimpses we see of the killers videotaping and tormenting their victims, are genuinely chilling—and very difficult to watch. It`s hard not to get excited by the prospect of Neeson taking these loathsome bastards down, and you edit the final physical confrontation together very nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what&amp;#39;s my beef? Well, let&amp;#39;s start with Neeson&amp;#39;s sassy, streetwise, teenage sidekick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. My. Goodness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I understand (and even appreciate) the desire to add some levity to such dark subject matter, but this just isn&amp;#39;t the right way to go about it. The humour works when Neeson tells a bad guy that he was able to trail him simply because of how much of a weirdo he is. But the pipsqueak aspiring detective mouthing off to waitresses and telling them not to offer him &amp;quot;sperm-killing sodas&amp;quot;: horrendous. I suspect that, if you thought you could have gotten away with it, you might have cut him from the film altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ends up really hurting is how by-the-numbers it all feels. We learn who the killers are and why they&amp;#39;re doing what they&amp;#39;re doing almost immediately, and the reveal that they&amp;#39;re rogue DEA agents doesn&amp;#39;t pay off with as much power as it could (and perhaps &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;). Neeson does lots of old-fashioned detective work in the pre-internet setting, but nothing he learns feels surprising in the least. After all, there&amp;#39;s nothing more enjoyable than watching someone slowly come to the same conclusions you&amp;#39;ve made about twenty minutes earlier. There are no real twists, and everything pretty much plays out exactly like you think it will. Which is kind of a drag.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;A Walk Among The Tombstones&lt;/em&gt; was the pilot episode of a new crime procedural, with you retaining editing duties week after week, I&amp;#39;d definitely be more enthusiastic. Instead it&amp;#39;s just a barely-serviceable crime thriller that I&amp;#39;ve already forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/30/a-walk-among-the-tombstones.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/30/a-walk-among-the-tombstones.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Equalizer</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of crazy ways to die. No less than a thousand &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spike.com/shows/1000-ways-to-die&quot;&gt;according to Spike TV,&lt;/a&gt; and up to a million &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/9/a-million-ways-to-die-in-the-west.html&quot;&gt;according to Seth MacFarlane&lt;/a&gt;. Many successful film franchises, like &lt;em&gt;Final Destination&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Saw&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt;, have made their reputations by finding creative ways to kill people off. That&amp;#39;s fine for a horror film – and even the occasional comedy – but in the case of &lt;em&gt;The Equalizer&lt;/em&gt;, the fact the filmmakers kept turning to an art department employee like you for their inspiration represents everything that&amp;#39;s wrong with the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was my fault to expect something of substance in the reunion of Denzel Washington and Antoine Fuqua, the director who coached him to an Academy Award in &lt;em&gt;Training Day&lt;/em&gt;. After all, neither of them have made much else besides this sort of action vehicle since then. But even with lowered expectations, &lt;em&gt;The Equalizer&lt;/em&gt; is constantly firing blanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things start slow. Painfully slow. Richard Wenk&amp;#39;s script doesn&amp;#39;t seem to know where to begin or where to end, and relies on the presence of Denzel Washington to maintain our emotional interest. His character, Robert McCall, is a big fat zero on the scale of human charisma and interest. He has no depth, no flaws, no enigmas. When he&amp;#39;s not readings book alone in a dinner, he&amp;#39;s stocking shelves at a generic &amp;quot;Home Mart&amp;quot; department store. Because he&amp;#39;s just your average tool man, like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except this joe-job and dull-drum existence is supposed to be making a point. After an inordinate amount of time, it&amp;#39;s revealed that (surprise!) McCall is just trying to live a normal life after a career doing covert U.S. government dirty work. He only fights crime after clocking out of his 9-5, which is when he becomes a monosyllabic unstoppable killing machine. What (with the exception, of course, of _The Terminator) _could be more boring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Killing – or more specifically, the &lt;em&gt;ways&lt;/em&gt; people are killed – shouldn&amp;#39;t be the only pulse in a serious action-drama-thriller. Seeing bad guys get their comeuppance is cathartic when, after the tension reaches a breaking point, violence explodes. But that&amp;#39;s not the case in &lt;em&gt;The Equalizer&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#39;s inspired by a TV show, not only in content but in form: the film is unevenly paced up and continues to deviate into side story adventures that offer little relevance to the A-plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that story involves a lot of your tools and the creative ways they kill people. Which is fine, until McCall literally starts stepping over machine guns in favour of hardware store props—you know, just to keep his life interesting. He calmly walks into countless confrontations with villains, always &amp;quot;giving them a chance&amp;quot; before dispatching them with ease. He&amp;#39;s never in any real danger, and lazy cross-cutting tries to trick the audience into believing the bad guys are always right on his tail. Instead, he&amp;#39;s always five steps ahead in ways the filmmakers don&amp;#39;t even try to explain. He has every tool he ever needs, be it electronic gizmos or hedge- (and head-) trimming shears.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/29/The-equalizer.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/29/The-equalizer.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Pride</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;While you may not have received a production credit, this film, and the bizarre historical circumstance it chronicles, would have never occurred where it not for you and your ridiculous, draconian policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m sure you must recall the circumstance in question: a seemingly fragile alliance between segments of London&amp;#39;s Lesbian and Gay community and a group of Welsh miners and their families from the village of Onllwyn in South Wales. You did that, Maggie, with your simultaneous repression of the working class and anyone you saw as a &amp;#39;deviant&amp;#39;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pride&lt;/em&gt; picks up midway through the UK miner&amp;#39;s strike of 1984 with a small group of gay men and women in London finding common cause with the Welsh miners in a single televised moment. The movie then tells the story of how this particular relationship evolves and grows despite what might seem to be unmanageable differences: Cosmopolitan English vs. Rural Welsh, Dance Club vs. Bingo Hall. That the homosexual community didn&amp;#39;t much care for you is no surprise. But I imagine it must unman you some to see what the solid, working class citizens of the Welsh coalfields ultimately made from this union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I forget to mention Bill Nighy, Maggie? Despite playing a supporting role, his character, Cliff, is the human core of this film. He is the living memory of what coal and mining – both the good and the bad - has meant to the towns and villages of the North of England. In some ways the rest of the cast, despite being based on very real historical figures, are reduced to window dressing in a film that strives mightily to make a point. That is often a weakness in this kind of polemical fare, from &lt;em&gt;Made In Dagenham&lt;/em&gt; to even something as well made as Ken Loach&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Bread and Roses&lt;/em&gt;. The message, however legitimate, overwhelms the human stories to the point where characters sometimes feel like place holders. Dominic West as UK AIDS patient #2 is a prime example in this film. Still, there were certainly moments of real passion; for instance, an impromptu rendition of &amp;#39;Bread and Roses&amp;quot; in the union welfare hall surprised more than a few tears from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You certainly understand what it is to make people into caricatures though, don&amp;#39;t you Mags? You spent an entire political career doing just that. However, in this instance, with this story, it is not a fatal flaw. &lt;em&gt;Pride&lt;/em&gt; is an uneven but ultimately enjoyable piece of working class cinema that will probably play very well with its constituency, which definitely includes me in those ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you, Maggie-darling, I&amp;#39;m hoping that this film is on perpetual repeat on whatever passes for cable in your particular district of Hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yours so very sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/25/pride.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/25/pride.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Battered Bastards of Baseball</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In the Netflix documentary about the legendary Portland Mavericks, &lt;em&gt;The Battered Bastards of Baseball,&lt;/em&gt; we see scratchy footage of you catering to the players, managing equipment and egos, and generally running your butt off. I wonder, was it this early commitment to multi-tasking that prepared you for your future career as an Oscar nominated filmmaker? You&amp;#39;ve worked with some of the greats: Stanley Kubrick, Woody Allen, Bing Russell. Sure, some might not think Bing Russell belongs on that list. His own son, superstar Kurt Russell, lovingly calls him a &amp;#39;plumber&amp;#39;; the kind of Hollywood supporting actor who went to work every day and got the job done. But many might not know that Bing gave you your first big break in the 70s, as a bat boy for his rag-tag Class A baseball team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your films are complex character dramas, but Bing and his Mavericks are a classic underdog story. Bing grew up in Florida, where the Yankees held spring training. He hung around the field and quickly became a favourite of stars like Lefty Gomez and Joe DiMaggio. As an adult, Bing moved his young family to Hollywood where he became a utility player alongside box office titans like John Wayne, and Steve McQueen. For thirteen years he played Deputy Clem Shepherd in Bonanza until the series ended. But baseball was always his obsession, so when Portland Oregon&amp;#39;s farm team moved out in 1972, Bing decided to build an independent baseball team there from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mavericks were a joke right from the start, holding open try-outs for any schlub willing to drag himself to the diamond. Footage shows three hundred or so wannabes dropping pop-flys, tripping around bases and striking out. But there you were, looking like an extra from the &lt;em&gt;Bad News Bears&lt;/em&gt;, picking up dropped equipment, mudding balls and sprinting around the diamond. Bing called you up to his seat in the stands and told you you were hired. Among Bing&amp;#39;s other hires that day were players who had been injured in the majors, or had been under-utilized and left to rot on farm teams. He built his team around oddballs and has-beens full of untapped potential, who just wanted another shot at playing the game they loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened next is the kind of epic rise to glory that films like &lt;em&gt;The Natural&lt;/em&gt; and even &lt;em&gt;Major League&lt;/em&gt; have tried to capture, but that you saw happen firsthand. It&amp;#39;s a story that still seems unbelievable even to those that lived it. Filmmakers (and Bing&amp;#39;s grandsons) Chapman and Maclain Way have an obvious affection for Bing, but it&amp;#39;s the interviews from former Mavericks themselves that make this documentary more that than just a love letter to an eccentric grandad. The footage builds in such a way that it&amp;#39;s impossible to not get caught up in the enthusiasm of a bunch of unruly players and their larger-than-life Hollywood owner defying the conventions of the uptight Minor League establishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Bing&amp;#39;s uncompromising attitude, and ability to see talent where others couldn&amp;#39;t, influenced your decision making as director, especially in terms of casting. The big story surrounding your film &lt;em&gt;Little Children&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;a href=&quot;http://abcnews.go.com/Nightline/story?id=2848316&quot;&gt;the comeback of actor Jackie Earle Haley&lt;/a&gt;(an original_ Bad News Bear&lt;em&gt;) after years of being _persona non grata&lt;/em&gt; in Hollywood. You gave him a pivotal role for which he received an Oscar nomination. &lt;a href=&quot;http://deadline.com/2014/01/sundance-todd-field-eyeing-adaptation-of-battered-bastards-of-baseball-docu-670940/&quot;&gt;Rumour has it&lt;/a&gt; that you are even planning to give Bing and the Portland Mavericks the big screen treatment, and though it seems like a perfect fit, though I hope you resist the temptation to go as deep and dark as your other films have gone. It would be a shame to lose the kooky sense of fun that made Bing, the Mavericks, and &lt;em&gt;The Battered Bastards of Baseball&lt;/em&gt; so enjoyable to watch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/24/the-battered-bastards-of-baseball.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/24/the-battered-bastards-of-baseball.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>9 Things You Probably Didn&#39;t Know About The Little Mermaid</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;To celebrate the 25th anniversary of &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, co-writers/co-directors Ron Clements and John Musker spoke at the 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animationfestival.ca&quot;&gt;Ottawa International Animation Festival&lt;/a&gt; about kick-starting the Disney Renaissance. Here are some of the behind-the-scenes tidbits they revealed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The idea for &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt; was &amp;quot;gonged&amp;quot; when it was first pitched to Disney.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In a classic case of almost-wasn&amp;#39;t, Ron Clements&amp;#39; original two-page proposal got shot down by Disney execs Michael Eisner and Jeffery Katzenberg at an animator presentation called &amp;quot;The Gong Show&amp;quot;. This was partly a knee-jerk reaction to rumours of a sequel to &lt;em&gt;Splash&lt;/em&gt; being in the works. But that wasn&amp;#39;t the only reason…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Before &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt; , Disney hadn&amp;#39;t made a fairy tale since the 1950s.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Even though most people think of Disney as a fairy tale factory, the company hadn&amp;#39;t brought one to the big screen since &lt;em&gt;Sleeping Beauty&lt;/em&gt; in 1959. Audience sensibilities were thought to have moved too far away from the coming-of-age classics that focused on women. Or, in other words…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Executive Producer Jeffery Katzenberg believed that &amp;quot;girl movies don&amp;#39;t make money.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The budget for the film was modest for a big theatrical release because Katzenberg didn&amp;#39;t think the film would do any better than Disney&amp;#39;s release the previous year, &lt;em&gt;Oliver &amp;amp; Company&lt;/em&gt;. Oliver &amp;amp; Who? Oh, how the times have changed (well, not really).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. The name Ariel was inspired by a character in the &lt;em&gt;Footloose&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Forget Hans Christian Anderson—Clements had Kevin Bacon on the brain (or, more specifically, Lori Singer) when he came up with the name for his Siren. Clements says it wasn&amp;#39;t a conscious thing, but now admits that the parallels between a town that prohibited dancing and a women who has to give up her voice no doubt collided in his mind during the creative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Sebastian was originally going to be British, and named Desmond.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Clements and Musker originally wrote Ariel&amp;#39;s crabby sidekick as a stuffed-shirt British servant. Song producer and lyricist Howard Ashman is the one who suggested (insisted, even) that they make the character a Rastafarian Jamaican, which would allow him to bring in some Calypso-themed music. Good move, especially since the film won Ashman and composer Alan Menken an Oscar for &amp;quot;Under the Sea&amp;quot;. You can watch that night&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HIuTSrBtYF4&quot;&gt;cringe-worthy performance here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Ariel was supposed to have a dolphin best friend voiced by Robin Williams.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
It only makes sense to have a dolphin in a sea-themed movie, right? Problem was, Clements and Musker had overloaded their script with characters. They also realized that Ariel had been written as too passive—inspired by Laura from &lt;em&gt;The Glass Menagerie&lt;/em&gt;. So they decided to cut the dolphin and put that character&amp;#39;s agency into Ariel. Then they put Robin Williams in their next film, &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Jim Carrey auditioned for the role of Prince Eric.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Four years before he became Ace Ventura, Jim Carrey auditioned for the role of Ariel&amp;#39;s prince charming. He lost out to 16-year-old Christopher Daniel-Barnes, who everyone thought sounded much older than he actually was. While Jim Carrey went on to become – well, Jim Carrey – Barnes became famous for playing Greg Brady in &lt;em&gt;The Brady Bunch&lt;/em&gt; films before parlaying the skills he developed with Disney into a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0055549/&quot;&gt;fairly spectacular voice-acting career&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Ursula was inspired by Bea Arthur, Joan Collins, and Divine—and Roseanne Barr auditioned for the part.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Different animators brought different aspects to Ursula&amp;#39;s personality, but the script specifically referenced Bea Arthur in &lt;em&gt;The Golden Girls&lt;/em&gt;. This &amp;quot;unflattering&amp;quot; comparison to a sea-witch apparently turned Arthur (or her agent) off from considering the part. But that didn&amp;#39;t matter, because the personality was rounded out as part drag queen, part &amp;quot;matron of Miami&amp;quot;—complete with Octopus tentacles. Although the directors admit to cheating on the number of tentacles (because it was &amp;quot;easier to animate 6 than 8&amp;quot;). But Ursula also has two arms, so there you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Early focus-test screenings completely changed how the movie was marketed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In the final stretch of production, it became clear that Disney might have a hit on their hands. Even Jeffrey &amp;quot;Girl Movies Make No Money&amp;quot; Katzenberg came around. &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt; received the highest audience scores &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; for Disney at the time, and, most surprisingly to the suits, resonated with adults, too. In fact, Disney decided to do the first-ever all-adult test screening for an animated film, and realized how differently it played for them. The marketing department therefore decided to sell it as a date-night movie for adults—and the rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/23/9-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-the-little-mermaid.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/23/9-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-the-little-mermaid.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Frank</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Nothing sells tickets like plastering a big ol&amp;#39; movie star&amp;#39;s face on the poster. And who has a hotter face right now than Michael Fassbender? He&amp;#39;s one of the hottest actors on the planet, fresh off an unforgettable performance in the Oscar-winning Best Picture &lt;em&gt;12 Years a Slave&lt;/em&gt;. He&amp;#39;s also a critical darling, and a man revered by men as much as he is coveted by women. What could possibly be complicated about marketing his newest film &lt;em&gt;Frank&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe using the star&amp;#39;s head isn&amp;#39;t really an option when it&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; covered in plaster for most of the film. But instead of running away from that challenge, you faced it head on. The oversized cartoonish cranium is, after all, the heart and soul of the entire film, and the hook that&amp;#39;s going to get people talking. That was certainly the case for Chris Sievey – the musician and comedian from the 80s whose alter ego, Frank Sidebottom, inspired the film. Although in director Lenny Abrahamson&amp;#39;s version, Frank is the object of affection, and not the protagonist. This story follows a character named Jon (inspired by the film&amp;#39;s co-writer, Jon Ronson), who stumbles into Frank&amp;#39;s band as a keyboard player and becomes swept up in Frank&amp;#39;s eccentric allure. Luckily, the mystery of the man behind the mask doesn&amp;#39;t consume the entire narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, your whole campaign is promoting this as a film starring Michael Fassbender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So without the benefit of facial expressions, or even much mobility, Fassbender channels his emotions through the broken and comical cadence of a mid-western American accent. He doesn&amp;#39;t aim for brooding and mysterious. Instead, he sounds more like a lost child, eager to please and almost aloof to the fact that his mask is a choice. This allows for the film&amp;#39;s other main star, Domhall Gleeson, to feel like he&amp;#39;s witnessing the birth of a misunderstood genius, rather than being caught up in a gimmick gone too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is, will the audience buy it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did. Maggie Gyllenhaal&amp;#39;s performance as a loyal but no-bullshit band member provides a refreshing counterweight to the whole premise. Gleeson&amp;#39;s anti-charisma as an actor is also played just right, as he tweets about his banal efforts to write great songs between his #epicsandwiches. Even the music, which is always just to the left of ever being truly melodic, feels right for a band that&amp;#39;s trying to consciously break into the scene sideways. The filmmaking plays it a little safer, giving us an easy entry point with the Jon character and emotional arc to follow, even if it&amp;#39;s not a predictable path to stardom and success. Then again, I never expected Frank&amp;#39;s big fake head to make deadmau5 kind of waves ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.macleans.ca/work/jobs/a-sneak-peek-at-our-who-earns-what-issue/&quot;&gt;$23M last year alone&lt;/a&gt; – mouse mask and all). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frank&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;#39;t look to be headed towards that kind of business, but don&amp;#39;t consider that a failing on your part. Even &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/7/shame.html&quot;&gt;Fassbender&amp;#39;s penis&lt;/a&gt; has a hard time selling tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/22/frank.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/22/frank.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>10 Questions with Randall William Cook, Animation Supervisor.</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;11 years after &lt;em&gt;The Return of the King&lt;/em&gt; took home 11 Oscars, Christopher Redmond speaks with three-time Academy Award winner Randall William Cook about what it was like to work on the groundbreaking &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy, misconceptions about his profession, and the state of blockbuster filmmaking today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&amp;#39;re best known for your work on &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy. Can you talk about how you got that job?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hired and employed as Animation Director until about a month before the film came out, then I was told, &amp;quot;Oh, the DGA (Director&amp;#39;s Guild of America) won&amp;#39;t let us give you that. So can you come up with your own credit? Whatever you want.&amp;quot; Well I wanted Animation Director, but never mind. So we settled for Animation Designer and Supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter and I worked together in a way that isn&amp;#39;t industry standard - that is to say that he hired me and I was answerable directly to him. I was the first American hire that they made back in 1998 - and I was hired on to design action scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He actually said, &amp;quot;you can do that better than I can so you design the action scenes&amp;quot; which is funny knowing who he is now. But back then, he was still, flatteringly enough, someone who had liked my stop-motion and my 2nd Unit Directing and effects directing in films like &lt;em&gt;The Gate&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;I Mad Man&lt;/em&gt; and other bargain basement fare like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was called down there to supervise the pre-vis department and create scenes for him in computer animation, which would then be referred to and sometimes followed slavishly on the set. I got to lay-out, choreograph, pick cam angles, pick editorial cut points all that stuff, and Peter allowed me this freedom because he&amp;#39;d seen my other stuff, and we had had conversations and found that we shared similar aesthetic values. So when it came time for them to choose an Animation Director, they asked me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are Animation Supervisor&amp;#39;s always hired that early in the process?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual Animation Director, from what I can ascertain, is hired by the Visual Effects Director after the visual effects and the scenes have been designed. In my case, I was in on thinking up sequences, not just being a traffic cop as I had been on &lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; picture, where I didn&amp;#39;t design anything. I just said, &amp;quot;a little faster, a little slower, have him do this instead of that, make sure that all the limbs are in the frames so we know what he&amp;#39;s doing.&amp;quot; Fairly tame stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the day-to-day responsibilities of a standard Animation Supervisor, both during production and in between productions?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve never been an in-house Animation Supervisor, I&amp;#39;ve only been hired on a per case basis, but the prescribed duties are, in many ways secondary to the end result, which involves application of art and taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re overseeing animation, with any sort of authority, you need to be directing the animation characters, because an animation character who isn&amp;#39;t acting isn&amp;#39;t really pulling his weight. Even the monsters act. Going back to 1933 &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt;, there was a lot of acting there that&amp;#39;s what gave it its charm. It&amp;#39;s not that the brushstrokes in the original &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; yielded photographic results, but they were very bold and the brushstrokes were in the right places so they gave an impression of drama, an impression of fury, an impression of character. You got to know the character of that big monkey who was just little hunk of rubber and plastic. You got to know the character of that big monkey through the way he was compelled to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately it all comes down to the needs of the performance at any given moment in the arc of the story. I&amp;#39;m not somebody who makes a differentiation between acting and animating, I think it&amp;#39;s the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then talk to me about motion-capture performances and how that has changed in the past ten years.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well the past ten years it has greater fidelity to capturing all sorts of nuances. I haven&amp;#39;t worked with all the facial capture stuff they&amp;#39;ve done recently - but I&amp;#39;m told that a lot of that, as it was ten years ago, is still heavily edited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an evolving art form and it&amp;#39;s a tool which when it becomes more transparent can be better and better. It&amp;#39;s more about the end result of the performance and it doesn&amp;#39;t really matter how you get here so long as it&amp;#39;s compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To the average person who is not in the film business, what is the most misunderstood part of your profession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose it&amp;#39;s the notion that everything that goes through the computer is untouched by human hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a studio is rushing to complete a Christmas release, they&amp;#39;ll hire all the animators they can get a hold of, so they&amp;#39;ll all fly to wherever, work on the project then they&amp;#39;ll fly to another hemisphere to work on the summer releases. The studios can&amp;#39;t really publicize their personnel, so they have to publicize their technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, this emphasis on technology is generally the thing that&amp;#39;s talked about the most, to the devaluation of the artist, because the artist is just a temporary hire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re painting a house, it doesn&amp;#39;t matter if you have Picasso or Diego Rivera or some schmuck from down the street. You&amp;#39;re going to have a painted house. And a lot of the big movies are painted houses - some of them well-painted houses, but still - if you&amp;#39;re doing a heartfelt character there has to be not only guidance from a good director and animation director or supervisor, or whatever the DGA will let us call ourselves these days, but also guidance from top notch animators. So it&amp;#39;s a collaborative work. This all of course builds on top of a performance that may have come from an actor, and it may not have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there a standard career path to getting where you got?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell no! When I was seven I thought I was going to be Ray Harryhausen, not knowing that that job was already taken. I didn&amp;#39;t know what I was going to be. Because I&amp;#39;m interested in so many different things, I did a lot of butterfly chasing in my career. I guess I never made a huge success at any of it because I was not so interested at having a steady job as I was in doing something that was interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did films like &lt;em&gt;The Gate&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;I Mad Man&lt;/em&gt;, I pretty much had control of what the characters would be doing on screen and had control of how I would achieve the various effects, be it trick perspective shots or stop-motion. I gravitated towards opportunities that didn&amp;#39;t pigeonhole me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are people out there right now who you feel are really exciting in the world of animation? Can you name some specific animators?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, because I may not get them on my show. And why piss off the other ones?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll tell you one thing though, and I mean this sincerely; I was really worried when I took on &lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; because I didn&amp;#39;t know any of the crew, I didn&amp;#39;t know any of the animators. And a lot of them were Sony animators who&amp;#39;d just come off the fucking &lt;em&gt;Smurfs&lt;/em&gt; , so I was really worried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something&amp;#39;s changed in the last 15- 20 years, as things always do. When I got there, I was shocked at how many top-notch talents there were out there - a number of them superstars. Virtually all the people that we had on that crew, and it was like a 30-40 person crew, I lost count.I was shocked at the number of highly talented people. I say &amp;#39;people&amp;#39; because a lot of them were female animators, which wasn&amp;#39;t the case when I was a young stop-motion animator and it wasn&amp;#39;t the case when I was at Disney, really. Disney was a very patriarchal place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You worked there for a year, but were Disney films a big inspiration growing up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t have any interest in doing Disney animation because those films never particularly beguiled me. I spent my childhood with the Cyclops, and &lt;em&gt;The Beast from 20 Fathoms&lt;/em&gt;, not with Thumper and Jiminy and that lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But somebody online recently showed a picture of Mowgli climbing a tree, it was a Milt Kahl pencil test for The Jungle Book — it&amp;#39;s a kid climbing a tree using his hands and feet, but it was so well acted, and so well realized, and so entertaining because it&amp;#39;s a kid trying to climb a tree like a monkey. And this great animator, did a great job - if you were going to do it now, you&amp;#39;d get the stunt team in, you&amp;#39;d rig him up, put wires and all that shit, and the reality of just getting him from the ground to the top of the tree without any serious injury, sort of supercedes any attempts at pantomime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of lines on paper, drawn by a master, you have a wonderful human trying to be an animal performance that&amp;#39;s believable, and funny, and true. It&amp;#39;s not just doing things that are impossible, getting every fucking superhero jumping through the air for a quarter of a mile then making a heroic three-point landing in front of the camera. Yeah, people can&amp;#39;t do that, but eventually people won&amp;#39;t be able to stand watching it. The contribution of something that is human and true and funny and accessible is something that animation, like acting, when done well, can be surprising and wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Were there people you looked up to for guidance when you were coming up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell for &lt;em&gt;The7th Voyage of Sinbad&lt;/em&gt; when I was 7 yrs old. That was just a different way of seeing things. You can&amp;#39;t see that sort of thing in real life - this big cyclops stomping around a beach - and Ray Harryhausen was my first childhood idol in the movies. He idolized Willis O&amp;#39;Brien, who made &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; and was a big fan of &lt;em&gt;The Thief of Bagdad&lt;/em&gt; so he grew up making movies about &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; stomping around through Bagdad. I was fascinated by the fact that these unreal characters were doing things and interacting with human beings. I was inspired not only to the sense of the fantastic, but to a sense of design and imaginative happenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also inspired by Lon Chaney Sr. I found an encyclopedia with pictures of him very early on and since I had a budding ability to draw I was interested in artists and illustrators like NC Wyeth at an early age. He of course illustrated Treasure Island and a number of books of that ilk, all the classic Scribner children&amp;#39;s adventure books – &lt;em&gt;The Deerslayer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mysterious Island&lt;/em&gt;. I looked at the Chaney photos and thought, this is a guy who can change himself like an illustrator! It&amp;#39;s like delineating a character like N.C. Wyeth does. I thought that was fascinating so I got interested in makeup too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another boyhood crush of mine was Jonathan Winters who played all these characters. He&amp;#39;d create all these improvisational characters and all these different voices. The Winters voices and the Chaney faces were something that obsessed me for a long time, and got me to pay attention to more subtle kinds of acting. I was always interested in big overt things like Orson Welles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it safe to say that your greatest success would be winning those three Oscars?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a statistic, and it was real nice that we did work that was recognized by a number of voters. But that&amp;#39;s a team effort. Most Oscars are. When you&amp;#39;ve got a 12-man animation team on film one, and a 44 animation team on film three, you have to look at those statues and figure which percentage of it belongs to which other people on the crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night we got the first one, at an after ceremony dinner, I spoke to Robert Redford. He said &amp;quot;how does it feel?&amp;quot;, because he&amp;#39;d won one that night as well. I said, &amp;quot;it&amp;#39;s alright, but two weeks ago, Ray Harryhausen came down to visit in New Zealand to give a little talk, and he brought along the skeleton that had appeared in &lt;em&gt;The 7th Voyage of Sinbad&lt;/em&gt; and I got to hold that skeleton in my hands. That&amp;#39;s really what got me into this racket, and that was a lot bigger thrill.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/20/10-questions-with-randall-william-cook.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/20/10-questions-with-randall-william-cook.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Price We Pay‎</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Documentaries about corporations and the bad things they do always seem to be a popular choice with festival audiences, including this former Poli-Sci major (who, admittedly, napped through most of second-year International Political Economy). Harold Crooks&amp;#39; &lt;em&gt;The Price We Pay&lt;/em&gt; tackles the issue of corporate tax avoidance and offshore tax havens. While a decent primer on the subject, I found the film got carried away with spotlighting corporate bad guys and neglected to answer some key questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid relying too heavily on talking heads, Crooks incorporates footage from UK parliamentary commissions and hearings with various executives from companies like Apple, Google, and Amazon. The British MPs emerge as the stars of the production. Their feisty, acerbic take-downs of the suits in the hot seat approaches near fervor at times, giving the audience plenty to boo and hiss about. Enjoyable as that was, Crooks drops the ball when it comes to making the case for the link between corporate tax avoidance and an increasingly heavy tax burden on the public. I accept the thesis, but I would have liked to see some more numbers to back it up. You can&amp;#39;t call your film &lt;em&gt;The Price We Pay&lt;/em&gt; without telling me what that price actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-postcard-2-the-price-we-pay.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-postcard-2-the-price-we-pay.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
