<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>God&#39;s Pocket</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’re best known as Joan Harris, the chilly office manager at the fictional ad agency in &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;. Joan is the proud figurehead of the Good Ship &lt;em&gt;Sterling Cooper &amp;amp; Partners&lt;/em&gt;, and not just because of her bombshell appearance. She’s the confident queen bee, feared, respected. But beneath the facade she’s a complicated, vulnerable woman. Joan is a character that comes along once in an actor’s lifetime. The kind of role that really showcases your gifts, and, no doubt, the kind of role that spoils you for future work. Especially roles like &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, in which your character is a literal figurehead: sculpted, wooden, and designed to lead men into a storm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; is the passion project of your &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; co-star John Slattery. It’s not only his feature directorial debut—he also co-wrote the script (adapted from Peter Dexter’s novel) and produced. You’re part of a dream cast of character actors he has assembled to tell the story of God’s Pocket, a gritty neighbourhood in the late-70s full of losers and crooks. Slattery, who has directed several &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; episodes, is obviously comfortable filming detailed period pieces; the art direction in &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; excels in capturing the colours, designs, and setting of the era while still managing to give the film a sense of timelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film’s problem isn’t style, its substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, of course, have no problem drifting through this bygone world. You play Jeanie, the mother of sociopathic loud-mouth Leon, who gets killed at his blue-collar job. You beg your husband Mickey to find out what really happened to Leon, while ensuring that he gets a proper funeral. Problem is, Mickey, a low-level crook, has no cash, and his boss, Arthur, is into the local loan shark for 20-Large. Meanwhile, local newspaper columnist Richard Shelburne, an alcoholic has-been and third-rate celebrity, gets involved in your case. But, of course, he ends up falling in love with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do you do? You sob, you sleep, you glare, you sashay around in too-tight house coats—talents perhaps better-suited to your torpid &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; co-star January Jones. This left me wondering why Slattery didn’t cast &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; in this lifeless role. But at least you didn’t have to suffer alone. Philip Seymour Hoffman plays Mickey as a schlubby Philip Seymour Hoffman-type, drifting through scenes covered in flop sweat and self-loathing. And there must have been a surplus of flop-sweat and self-loathing in the make-up trailer, because it’s doused liberally all over Richard Jenkins newspaperman and Eddie Marsan’s slimy funeral home director. What’s left is spritzed over the denizens of the local watering hole, where inveterate drunks get cut off and respond with things like: “You can’t cut off the truth!” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bet you were missing Matthew Weiner right about then. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery of your son’s death is just one of many unsatisfying threads that unravel into oblivion. There are horse races, dead bodies in meat trucks, unfulfilling sex scenes, and the occasional brutal act of violence—all of which are apparently essential to the ambling plot, though none are particularly intriguing. You only have about fifteen lines in the whole film, and half of them are, “I know something happened to Leon, I just &lt;em&gt;know!&lt;/em&gt;” Your job is to pose with laundry, in dirty kitchens, while being alternately avoided and pursued. This may be &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s still a man’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; feels like three separate movies. And none of them moved me. Particularly because in their attempt to combine unflinching, urban drama and dry humour, they succeeded at neither. This must have been particularly frustrating for you, since you’re so used to balancing both as the acid-tongued Joan. It’s even more unfortunate since &lt;a href=&quot;http://on.aol.com/video/roger-sterlings-best-one-liners-517732993&quot;&gt;John Slattery’s Roger Sterling is legendary&lt;/a&gt; for delivering some of &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;’s best lines while having arguably the most surprising character evolution on the show. It’s obvious, though, that his strengths as a director lie in visual storytelling. The writing of copy is a skill best left to somebody else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just sorry that 
you have to go back to the 60s to play a female character who is more than just a pretty face. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/25/gods-pocket.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/25/gods-pocket.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Virunga</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding ungracious, your work on &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; hurt my enjoyment of the film. Not because it was sub-par. Quite the opposite. The fact is, the sonic gloss you applied to Orland von Einsiedel’s documentary was so perfectly polished that it seemed at times to work against the very nature of the film and its intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your imprint is everywhere. From slow-motion shots of water droplets to ear-ringing gun shots and bombs, your hyper-realistic sound effects actually disengaged me from the material—albeit subconsciously. I felt like I was watching a Hollywood film. That says a lot, considering &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/change/2010/10/christopher-redmond.html&quot;&gt;my ongoing relationship&lt;/a&gt; with East Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the privilege of visiting the volcanic Virunga region of the Democratic Republic of Congo, and even spent time at Dian Fossey’s Gorilla Rehabilitation and Conservation Education (GRACE) center. Much of &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; plays out there, telling the story of a similar gorilla orphanage and the rangers tasked with protecting the surrounding national park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by protecting, I do mean with AK-47s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand firsthand the shock of seeing soldiers brandish their weapons so freely— and I understand the temptation to play that up. I’m guilty of the same dramatics when I recount my experiences travelling with mountain trackers and guides who are armed with guns to protect us not from the gorillas, but from the &lt;em&gt;guerillas&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is no doubt why the director indulges in a few dramatic point-of-view shots down the barrel of a gun. In that sense, your work is only complimenting his vision. Which isn’t entirely unjustified. The DRC is a ridiculously dangerous place. More people have been killed in the Congolese Civil War than in any other conflict since WWII. So when the story of &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; quickly turns from being that of a safari to surviving an armed take-over by M23 rebels, I know why you went full-clip on the sound effects. A simple shaky camera (in huge contrast to the film’s otherwise beautiful cinematography) is energized tenfold by the overwhelming echo of shelling and gunshots. But by laying that continuous sound bed over so many cuts, the danger felt almost manufactured. I felt manipulated, like you were trying to give me what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I wanted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not so different from my experience with the gorillas themselves. With only 800 in the world, seeing a majestic Silverback in the wild has truly been one of the highlights of my life.  In contrast, seeing a baby gorilla in one of those concrete rehab centers was one of the most depressing. It’s hard to articulate the profound nature of that difference, but it repeatedly came to mind watching the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is, while I’m spending a disproportionate amount of time fixating on your amplification of the drama, real drama does occur in this film. I hope that more people spend the money to visit these parks and support their preservation. I just hope you haven’t scared them away (I guess we’ll just have to remind them that entering the park from the Rwandan and Ugandan side is much, much safer).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/24/virunga.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/24/virunga.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 1</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It seems fitting that The Hunger Games saga got new costume designers for &lt;em&gt;Mockingjay&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;. Not only is your surrogate fashionista character gone from the series (Lenny Kravitz’s Cinna), but this film marks a big structural change for a franchise that, after just two films, is already in desperately in need of a makeover. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After being rather dazzled by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html&quot;&gt;original Hunger Games film&lt;/a&gt;, then lukewarm over the sequel &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/22/the-hunger-games-catching-fire.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Catching Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; I knew &lt;em&gt;Mockingjay&lt;/em&gt; needed to buck the trend of sending the kids into a deathmatch competition, and start exploring the larger world of Panem. I wasn’t sure was how the film would manage to do this without losing sight of what made the series special in the first place. For my money, that’s not so much the love triangle between Jennifer Lawrence, Josh Hutchinson, and Liam Hemsworth (that’s every YA franchise today), but rather the allegory about our contemporary media culture. So it wasn’t until the characters started talking about costumes that the film felt both on-brand and freshly re-launched. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a cold open on Katniss in a state of emotional distress, the story slowly rebuilds itself around her reluctant anointment as the face of the rebel movement. As always, she’s being used: this time by her liberators to motivate an uprising. She initially shows no interest in the job—until, of course, she sees the designs for her sexy warrior costume. The point isn’t played as shallow as I’m making it sound, but it certainly is an early turning point for her character. She apparently needs to look the part before she feels comfortable playing it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most stars probably feel that way—I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this theme has repeated itself in all three films. A flaming dress or cocktail gown will imbue Katniss with the confidence she needs to bust out of her shell (a point which is brought up several times by her image consultant, Effie). The film takes itself fairly seriously, though, and when Katniss &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; finally witness the destruction of The Capitol firsthand, it’s more important that we feel her anger than marvel at how good she looks when she’s getting angry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, setting much of this film in a rebel bunker was probably a pretty big disappointment to you guys. Although there’s always women in side-ponytails and brown leatherjackets at Halloween, most fans of The Hunger Games prefer to dress up as citizens of the Capitol  Glitter and excess rule the day. But we’re cut off from that city in this film. Instead, there’s a lot of plotting and scheming, with the occasional off-site adventure. Enjoyable, for the most part, but it feels incomplete. Probably the same way you guys felt about doing the costumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t suppose many people will be throwing Hunger Games parties wearing the grey overalls that dominate most of this film. But you never know. Fashion, and youth franchises, can sometimes surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/21/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-1.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/21/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-1.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>After Tiller</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your job is to work with the filmmakers – in the case of &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt;, producers/directors Martha Shane and Lana Wilson – to assemble their footage into an effective narrative. It’s all about offering choices, and I’m sure some of those choices were difficult. You help shape the story, offer advice, but, ultimately, the final decisions are not yours to make. You need to trust that the people making these decisions know what’s best. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike scripted films, documentaries aren’t typically “written” until all the footage has been compiled. It’s only &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; viewing the footage that the story is uncovered, pieced together by editing. Shane and Wilson relied on your expertise to guide them through the murky moral waters of the abortion debate to tell a part of the story that has so far been overlooked: that of the abortion provider. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your advice to them: &lt;a href=&quot;http://video.pbs.org/video/2365315295/&quot;&gt;tell the truth.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing easy about &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt;. Not the watching &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; the telling. With a topic as divisive as abortion – and, in this case, the highly controversial practice of late-term abortion (performed after 20 weeks) – trying to force the narrative onto common ground is more than impossible, it’s unnecessary. The abortion issue is more complicated than most people realize, but the truths &lt;em&gt;After Tille&lt;/em&gt;r presents are simple: the four doctors still performing late-term abortions in the U.S. do so because they believe abortion is a healthcare issue, not a political or religious one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tiller in &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt; is Dr. George Tiller, a former member of the armed forces, an active Christian, and a late-term abortion practitioner in Kansas. After decades of threats, which included having his clinic bombed in 1985, and being shot in both arms in 1993, Dr. Tiller was murdered while attending church in 2009. The four remaining practitioners – Dr. Carhart in Nebraska, Dr. Hern in Colorado, and Dr. Robinson and Dr. Sella in New Mexico – considered him not just a colleague, but a mentor and a friend. There was no question about whether or not they would carry on with their respective practices following his murder. As hard as it is for many to believe, these doctors love what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film tracks along the prosaic Middle American landscapes of highways and strip malls, past churches and schools, past medical buildings. But once behind the doors of these doctor’s offices, &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt; shows us a world few of us ever see. The camera captures the mundane internal goings-on: fluorescent lights flicker, paperwork is signed, phones ring. The only hint that these offices are different than your average GP’s is the Department of Justice letter taped to the front desk, with handwritten instructions on how to proceed should a member of staff receive threats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We witness each doctor in counselling sessions with the women seeking their services. We don’t see the women’s faces. Instead, the camera focuses on the women’s hands as they fidget with tissues and gesture while describing the painful reasons they need to terminate their pregnancies. Late-term abortions make up less than 1% of all abortions performed in the U.S. (the majority of these are planned pregnancies in which severe foetal abnormalities are found after the 20th week). You and the filmmakers choose to focus on the doctor’s faces, wrought with concern and compassion for the unthinkable situations their patients are facing. We see the doctors comforting their patients, and listening, holding their hands, and often holding back tears themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Robinson recalls working in a state where the woman is required to tell a compelling story to not one, but two separate doctors, in order to obtain an abortion. “And some women just aren’t good storytellers,” she says. As Dr. Hern counsels a rape victim, we see that his lapel button says, “Trust Women.” Dr. Sella admits that she struggles because she still thinks of them as babies, not mere tissue to be removed. As the film progresses, you show us how the issue gets even more convoluted as patients come in seeking abortions with perhaps less concrete reasons for ending their pregnancies. Some were in denial after sexual assault and waited too long, some are poor and had to work to afford abortions that were no longer viable by the time they had the funds. One is a devout Catholic teenager who was afraid to tell her parents before her pregnancy became obvious. Your decision to focus on these challenging narratives shows us just how multifaceted this issue is despite how simple the detractors aim to make it appear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these doctors wanted to be political activists. They just want to help women. And they still grapple with ethical conundrums on a daily basis, all while keeping Dr. Tiller’s ethos at the forefront of their practices: that a woman’s body is smarter than a doctor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth you encouraged Shane and Wilson to seek is the real hero of this story. Thank you for guiding its journey. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/20/after-tiller.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/20/after-tiller.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Wolves</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not big on horror movies. It’s not that they scare me (they terrify me), it’s that they leave me underwhelmed (crying behind the couch), because they are so formulaic and hackneyed (I am unable to sleep for days). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is I scare easier than a cat fleeing a vacuum cleaner. I don’t like monsters, I don’t like blood, and I don’t like things that go bump in the night. I was fully prepared to turn down the invitation to review David Hayter’s feature film debut, &lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt;, then my editor nonchalantly mentioned, “It’s the new movie with Jason Momoa.” Like he &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; I wouldn’t be able to refuse. Such underhanded tactics aside, I thought I should take the opportunity to step outside my comfort zone, so I marshalled my courage and settled in to watch. After turning every light in the house on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High school football hero Cayden Richards leads a charmed life, albeit recently punctuated by sudden, inexplicable bursts of strength and temper. He blacks out while on a date, waking up to find his parents brutally murdered and the police at the door. This is where things start to get hairy (sorry). Cayden turns into a werewolf and makes a run for it. The furry fugitive finds his way to a small farm town where the locals are unusually hostile. He is given refuge by gruff but kind John Tollerman, who warns him about Connor Slaughter, leader of the local band of drunken toughs and lowlifes. Given that the film isn’t called &lt;em&gt;Wolf&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt;, we can guess what happens next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt; attempts to blend the conventions of action and horror film, using tropes and archetypes from both the fugitive, the damsel in distress, the monster and its origin myth. But it never really finds its footing, and I was at a loss as to whether I was supposed to be afraid or amused “Are they &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to be funny?” was something I asked myself a lot during the film. The performances across the board seem phoned in, from Cayden’s monotone voice-over to the stone-faced delivery of lines and the weird, inconsistent accents of many supporting characters. Plot developments and twists feel just as forced. Your performance therefore stands out as the only one with a hint of life in it. Connor is the only character on screen who looks like he’s having any fun at all, and the only one who embodies the aggression and ferocity one would want to see in a movie about werewolves, or in a horror film in general. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of me was relieved that &lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt; was less of a fright-fest than expected, if only for the sake of my dignity. But I wish more of your fellow cast members would have shared some of your energy and enthusiasm for their characters. Unfortunately, one decent performance is not enough in a film that comes off as a sustained shrug of indifference. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/19/wolves.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/19/wolves.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Big Hero 6</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The marketing materials for &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; proudly exclaim “From the people who brought you &lt;em&gt;Frozen, Tangled,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wreck-it Ralph&lt;/em&gt;”, and that had me wondering if your job had gotten trickier in the last few years now that Disney seems to own, well, almost everything. You see, this could easily have been sold as “From the people who brought you &lt;em&gt;Cars 2&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Toy Story.&lt;/em&gt;” Or even “From the people who brought you &lt;em&gt;The Avengers&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Iron Man 3&lt;/em&gt;.” While it’s not marketed as either an official Pixar or Marvel film, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero&lt;/em&gt; 6 is certainly as much a product of both of those entities as it is Disney alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; introduces us to Hiro(!), a 14-year old loner who is a genius with robot design but is squandering his gift in the underworld of robot fighting - think &lt;em&gt;Real Steel&lt;/em&gt; meets &lt;em&gt;Bloodsport&lt;/em&gt; but with less, you know, blood.  After Hiro’s older brother/father figure, Tadashi,  tricks him into visiting the university robot lab where he studies, Hiro realizes he could do a whole lot more with his gifts. He’s also introduced to Tadashi’s motley assortment of classmates who have been conveniently pre-nicknamed by the class clown just in case they ever need secret identities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiro’s mind is opened to new possibilities when he meets Baymax, Tadashi’s personal project. Baymax is a cuddly medical robot designed to treat all manner of illness and injury (in perhaps a nod to the lonely child relationship of &lt;em&gt;E.T. The Extra Terrestrial&lt;/em&gt;, Baymax is activated when it hears someone say “Ouch”). Hiro sets his sights on impressing Tadashi’s professor, Dr. Callaghan, and landing a spot in the robot lab. &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt;’s first act details Hiro’s transformation from punk kid to budding academic, culminating with Hiro’s creation of Micro-robots, small, intelligent, mind-controlled building blocks that can be used to construct anything their user can think of. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, no hero’s journey is complete without the tragedy that sets him on the path to righteousness, and &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t break any new ground here. Anyone with a passing understanding of Joseph Campbell can guess at the fate of father figure-types. Suffice it to say, Hiro finds himself at a low point with Baymax as his only company. Also like &lt;em&gt;E.T.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; gets a lot of second act mileage from Hiro trying to overcome Baymax’s rudimentary programming by teaching him how to behave more human. It also leads them to discover that Hiro’s Micro-robots, once thought lost to the aforementioned tragedy, are being used for some unclear nefarious purpose. Eventually the rest of the Robot Lab is brought in to help figure out what exactly is going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s at this point in the film that I started to think of the marketing quandaries you must have faced, Amy. You see, despite your and your team’s best efforts, I went into &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; pretty ignorant of not only what it was about, but also of its origins. It wasn’t until Hiro and his friends spot the obligatory Stan Lee cameo, that I realized, &lt;em&gt;this is also a Marvel movie!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might not think that’s a huge deal, but it fundamentally changed my relationship to &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt;. I could instantly see how the final two acts of the movie (&lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; is, atypically, broken into four acts) would play out; the heroes are assembled, each with a specific skill, they have one or two setbacks before coming together as a true unit and overcoming the villain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a disappointment to realize that what I thought was a quirky and original film was slowly turning into the same formula I‘ve seen over and over. I’m not saying that you misled me—or even that the rest of &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; is bad. In fact, it’s still highly enjoyable. The animation is great, as one would expect from a studio that is now overseen by Pixar’s braintrust,. The voice work by Scott Adsit, Ryan Potter, James Cromwell, and especially T.J. Miller, is top-drawer.  And like &lt;em&gt;The Incredibles&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; has some of the best action scene construction this side of Steven Spielberg. But once my expectations were set by that cameo, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; settled into little more than meeting them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said in the opening to this letter, you could have just as easily marketed &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; as a product created by any one of those corporate entities. It really feels like the result of that most 90s of terms, &lt;em&gt;corporate synergy&lt;/em&gt;: the strategies and missions of each brand is met, but the result strips out whatever makes it unique. Watching &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; is sort of like seeing that happen in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Rosewater</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What we usually try to do with these reviews is shine the spotlight on some of the less appreciated players in filmmaking, but &lt;em&gt;Rosewater&lt;/em&gt; is so much a child of your making that in this case it would be disingenuous to address this letter to anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A film that faithfully chronicles the sometimes surreal 118-day imprisonment of journalist (and Canadian educated) Maziar Bahari by Iranian authorities in 2009, &lt;em&gt;Rosewater&lt;/em&gt; is an intimate and contemplative film. And it doesn’t surprise me at all that you decided to direct this particular story in the way that you did. Shot in Amman, Jordan with a skeleton crew of often only five or six people, it is small in scale but pretty large in ambition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UciFeVCaozE&quot;&gt;“Technology has democratized who is going to be bearing witness.”&lt;/a&gt; This is something you said in the context of a conversation about how repressive and autocratic regimes struggle to maintain control over messaging in a modern technological environment. It was also, in many ways, the central conceit of &lt;em&gt;Rosewater&lt;/em&gt;: how technology is changing the nature of the often fraught relationship between governments - both autocratic and democratic - and the people. An iPhone and a few satellite dishes have become the tools of the revolutionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rosewater&lt;/em&gt; is also concerned with the smallness of character that Bahari’s captors demonstrate, their ignorance of the world outside their own stunted, distorted lives. That they are frightened, oblivious creatures rather than fundamentally evil is a point that you drive home time and again, often with a kind of gallows humor that Gael Garcia Bernal, whom you chose to play Bahari, is wonderfully adept with. You also make it clear that you feel this ignorance is an aspect of their authoritarian leanings rather than something that is specific to any particular nation. By the way, Jon, Bernal was an exceptional choice to play the real life Bahari—his performance is remarkable for its restraint and honesty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, despite the setting and difficult subject matter, the film is often engaging, filled with a dry humor and an observational wit that makes it more than simply about the hardships Bahari endured. You were quietly circumspect about the torture he endured and seemed far more interested in exploring the monotony and isolation that Bahari himself describes as the worst parts of his captivity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were also clever in that once your protagonist entered prison we as an audience are pretty much stuck there as well, only coming in contact with the outside world when the prisoner does. This does make the middle act difficult in some ways because it translates into an uncomfortable time for the audience. There were a lot of subtle touches like this that spoke to a well conceived and executed script. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rosewater&lt;/em&gt; is a film that feels like a logical extension of your work up until now. The Daily Show has always been about skewering the ignorant and authoritarian leanings of bureaucracies, as well as reminding the media of how integral they are to the functioning of a healthy democracy. One person with a camera and some courage can be a catalyst for change, simply by bearing witness. This is a remarkably perceptive and mature debut. I can only hope you have a few more films like this in you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/17/rosewater.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/17/rosewater.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Dumb and Dumber To</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Must be nice to have full control of your image for once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the early buzz around &lt;em&gt;Dumb and Dumber To&lt;/em&gt; is about how you’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the movie. Whether you exercised your contractual right to veto your cameo appearance, or whether the filmmakers made a purely artistic decision to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...oh, who are we kidding? You wanted out and you got out. That’s your right, and that’s fine. But I hope your withdrawal wasn’t a judgment of the quality of the film. Because I liked it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=28GLa9T2CtI&quot;&gt;I liked it a lot&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original &lt;em&gt;Dumb and Dumber&lt;/em&gt; did a lot of things right, starting with the title (which virtually insulates it from snotty criticism). The laughs are pretty much packed wall-to-wall, stemming from characters who exist solely to be the butt-end of their own jokes. But it’s the re-watchability of the original that separates it from the average idiotic comedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know this as well as anyone, having publicly professed your love for the first film and your fondness for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joe.ie/movies/video-jennifer-lawrence-does-dumb-and-dumber-impression/47027&quot;&gt;quoting the (dare we saw ‘classic’) comedy&lt;/a&gt;. But even you must have had reservations about participating in what could have been a payday nostalgia trip for Jeff Daniels and Jim Carrey, the latter of whom hasn’t had a hit comedy in over a decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m still curious: at what point was your confidence in the film shaken?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you never got past the first 20 minutes. Honestly, I wouldn’t blame you. In what feels like painfully contrived set-up, Carrey’s Lloyd character has been committed to an institution for the past two decades. He suddenly breaks his catatonic state to reveal he was just pranking his best friend Harry. This is followed by some over-the-top physical humour, and a return to their old dungy apartment, where Harry’s new roommate is a crystal-meth maker (a wasted opportunity for a Bryan Cranston cameo). We also get a return of the blind and wheelchair-bound Billy, with a new flock of birds. At this point, things did not bode well for the film to generate new laughs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the plot unfolds – which involves Harry searching for a new kidney by tracking down the daughter he never knew he had – the film starts to reach beyond lazy gags, throwing some new quotable jokes and some of that classic character-based stupidity. I’m not sure when I let out my first hearty laugh, but I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; remember feeling like I was the only one laughing. For me, it all stemmed from falling back in love with the characters. Some small quirk (in a movie filled with huge quirks) had hit me in just the right way. I could feel Jim Carrey going for it—something he obviously didn’t feel prepared to do until now. And it felt good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe you just had a hard time looking at their faces; two men who have aged physically but regressed mentally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t be alone. Base on the trailer, that’s a valid fear. Gags that are funny when performed by a thirty-two year-old are different when performed by a fifty-two-year-old. But it’s also invigorating when done right. And I really think that, for the most part, this film does it right. Even the early mental institution gag feels, by the end, like a dare-I-say smart way to bring the time gap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the Farrelly Brothers have rediscovered their old selves, you seem to have moved on to the next iteration of your career.  The unrehearsed, unreserved, down-to-earth personality that America fell in love with over the past few years seems to be have been replaced with a guarded, slightly more calculating media presence. Staying out of this film might be the best example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just remember that it’s okay to be dumb some times. And dumber, to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>E-Team</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Most mothers will tell you that they want to make the world a better place for their children. They’ll organize food drives, start petitions and maybe even attend the occasional anti-fracking protest - all noble efforts. But your mother, Anna, goes a wee bit further. She travels to some of the most dangerous places in the world in hopes of bringing war criminals to justice. She’s trying to make the world a better place. Not just for you, but for all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bet this gets her out of having to bring cupcakes to PTA meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt; follows the Human Rights Watch emergency team which includes your mom, her husband Ole Sorang, Fred Abrahams and Peter Bouckeart. Their job is to investigate claims of human rights violations, namely the widespread reports of the killing of unarmed civilians (like Libya in 2011 and Syria in 2013). They go into areas of conflict and take statements from people who have just witnessed atrocities, then report these findings to Human Rights Watch and various news organizations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in &lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt;, when your mother and your step-father Ole prepare to leave for Syria, you are asked what you want for a souvenir. When you reply, “Bullet casings or shells, or bits of fragments are always welcome,&amp;quot; I wondered if you fully understand the complexity of your mother’s job. When the filmmakers ask if she thinks you worry about her she says, “do you remember being twelve? He has a very comfortable life.” This is why your mother does what she does, so you and other children can live the kind comfortable existence where bullet casings and shells are considered cool gifts, and not a daily and deadly part of life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You aren’t the only child featured in this film. Peter’s young daughters think Gaddafi is a cartoon villain who steals toys. We see Fred pushing his kids on a swing in New York City while his voiceover explains how he was an expert witness in the Slobodan Milosevic trial in 2002. Having been witness to the mass graves of civilians - many of them children - in Kosovo in 1998, Peter recalls the surreal yet satisfying experience of confronting the man he’d been tracking for ten years. This story alone has enough legs for its own feature doc, yet it illustrates the whole point of Human Rights Watch - to put war criminals on trial and to bring justice to victims. Fred also notes how rare it is to achieve this outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This raises the stakes when we see Anna and Ole taking statements in a town that was demolished by air strikes only minutes before, or Peter using his vast knowledge of weaponry to prove that the Syrians did indeed gas their own people. The team is pragmatic about their incremental gains and small victories. They have to be. Peter very matter-of-factly explains that his job is to confront people with the reality of what is happening in another place, and they have to make the moral choices about what they want to do. The film itself takes a similar approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other capital ‘I’ important docs, &lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt; didn’t make me feel like I was eating my vegetables. Instead of playing on my Western, middle-class guilt, &lt;em&gt;E-Team&lt;/em&gt; shows their subjects living similarly comfortable lives, nary a hair-shirt in sight. It’s this lack of moralizing that gives the film gravitas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s worth noting the team effort behind the camera. The cinematography is assured, and only shaky-cam nauseating once when the team sneaks into Syria in the middle of the night – but that might have just been my nerves. The framing is never intrusive, whether it be your mom and Ole commiserating with their Syrian interpreter about his wife’s pregnancy, or you back home watching &lt;em&gt;Mr. &amp;amp; Mrs. Smith&lt;/em&gt;. The camera, like the E-Team, merely observes and reports. One of the cinematographers was James Foley, who was beheaded by ISIL in August 2014. We find out the film is dedicated to him when the credits roll. It’s the last in a series of gut-punches this film delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There comes a point in every child’s life when they truly appreciate the sacrifices their mother made for them. For most people, it’s not until they move out on their own that they fully understand just how much their mother did to give them a good life. Luckily for you, there’s a film that shows you just how hard your mother works to make a difference in the world. Luckily for all of us, she’s still out there doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/13/e-team.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/13/e-team.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Interstellar</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since his feature debut, &lt;em&gt;Following&lt;/em&gt;, Christopher Nolan has specialized in making existential puzzle films with coherent-but-cryptic conclusions. As his ambitions – and budgets – have expanded, so too has the breadth of the themes he explores. So perhaps it was inevitable that he would eventually turn to the abstractions of theoretical physics: the ultimate existential puzzle with coherent-but-cryptic answers. &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; takes place in multiple galaxies, multiple dimensions, and concerns the survival of the entire human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;#39;t get much bigger or more existential than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;ve spent the last half-century aspiring to answer some of the most profound questions in the universe, Kip. And you&amp;#39;ve come closer than a lot of people. Your research in the fields of gravitational physics and astrophysics has earned you a spot on the all-star team of greatest living physicists, alongside Edward Witten and Stephen Hawking (what cosmic law of mutual attraction is responsible for the strange coincidence of &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; opening on the exact same weekend as &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;, the biopic of Hawking&amp;#39;s early life?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve seen movies based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;comic books&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/27/transformers-age-of-extinction.html&quot;&gt;toys&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/18/battleship.html&quot;&gt;board games&lt;/a&gt;—but perhaps never before based on relativistic theories of gravity. Luckily, your fields of expertise are a bit more accessible than string theory or supersymmetric quantum fields. Black holes, wormholes, gravitational waves—this is the sexy stuff upon which a good hard sci-fi premise can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were its original architect, too. &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; began as a treatment written by you and producer Lynda Obst—but what remains onscreen is apparently much different than what you had proposed. But no hard feelings, right? According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.sciencemag.org/people-events/2014/11/physicist-who-inspired-interstellar-spills-backstory-and-scene-makes-him&quot;&gt;a recent interview with&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.sciencemag.org/people-events/2014/11/physicist-who-inspired-interstellar-spills-backstory-and-scene-makes-him&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, your ultimate goal was a film in which &amp;quot;real science, ranging from truth to speculation, is embedded deep into the movie&amp;#39;s fabric from the outset.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What luck, then, that the project found its way to Nolan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as his filmography seems to suggest that he operates primarily in the realm of the fantasy, his fidelity to scientific law is indisputable. He brought real-world dynamism to the superhero world, creating a Batman who eschews hyperkinetic comic book physics in favor of practical technology (he&amp;#39;s just as much the product of a corporate R&amp;amp;D department as he is the product of a long ago street crime). In &lt;em&gt;Inception&lt;/em&gt;, he applied a systemic logic to one of the most illogical human idiosyncrasies: dreaming. Even in &lt;em&gt;The Prestige&lt;/em&gt;, Nolan&amp;#39;s film about dueling turn-of-the-century illusionists, electromagnetism is revealed to be the source of their magic (there&amp;#39;s even a cameo appearance by Nikola Tesla).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you, Nolan knows a little something about breaking new ground; he&amp;#39;s the only blockbuster filmmaker pursuing original ideas (albeit in between rebooting superhero films). He seems the heir to Spielberg, doesn&amp;#39;t he? A director whose every film is significant merely because &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone familiar with the narrative style employed by Nolan and his brother/screenwriter Jonathan, the first fifteen minutes of &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; is a treasure trove of minor plot details you just know are going to prove relevant by the end: books knocked off a shelf by a ghost; a wristwatch left behind as a memento. How these details expand in meaning and weave together is part of the fun of watching a Christopher Nolan film unfold. And &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; is fun. Even when it&amp;#39;s aspiring to a profundity that it only occasionally is able to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission to outer space that follows these earthbound scenes finds the perfect balance of realism and excess. It&amp;#39;s an adventure, but an authentic one. Disbelief is suspended at just the right height. The scenes back on our planet – where the changing atmosphere threatens the continued existence of oxygen-reliant life – are shot by cinematographer Hoyte Van Hoytema with such a radically different palette (the yellowish sepia-tone of a fading photograph) that, late in the film, when editor Lee Smith cuts back and forth between the washed-out, monochromatic sequences taking place on hostile alien planets, it really seems as if we&amp;#39;re occupying two distinct worlds simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, the finished product looks a lot like Kubrick&amp;#39;s space opus from a half-century ago. And, yes, a lot of the technical precision and visual bravado of the outer space scenes are a fraction less striking after seeing the same stuff in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/4/gravity.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; last year. And, sure, the sound design sometimes overwhelms; Hans Zimmer&amp;#39;s gorgeous Philip Glass-inspired score deserves better, I think, than to be drowned out by that patented Christopher Nolan third-act bass growl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite that familiarity, despite those few flaws, the film has stayed stuck in my head. The ideas are big, the riddles are fascinating, and even if the way the solution hangs together feels a bit too loose, too perfectly imperfect, I&amp;#39;m indescribably grateful that a big-budget blockbuster film possesses the same rare ambition that you do: to ask and answer the most fathomless cosmic questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
