<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Theory of Everything</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Synopsizing an entire life isn’t easy. That’s why biopics tend to focus on either a definitive period (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/11/16/lincoln.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lincoln&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, Walk the Line&lt;/em&gt;) or take the skipping-stone approach to key milestones (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/2/mandela-long-walk-to-freedom.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mandela: Long Walk to Freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, Ali&lt;/em&gt;). The right choice is always relative to the story you want to tell. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_The Theory of Everything doesn’t focus on a single period in Stephen Hawking’s life, nor does it hang a narrative on his famous scientific achievements. Rather, it tells a complicated love story that spans decades, all of which is perfectly summarized in your final sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, your job was pretty straightforward. By creating a montage that reverses both the chronology and speed of the film, you had the enviable task of cherry-picking all the most touching moments. And there are plenty to choose from. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warm, lush cinematography perfectly compliments this twirling romance, and barrels us back to a moment when everything was much simpler (in theory, anyway). We get to experience some wish fulfillment, watching Hawking’s degenerative ALS disease reverse itself until he’s spinning freely on his feet rather than in his electric wheelchair. It’s a beautiful and bittersweet ending that helps us re-experience and re-examine everything that comes before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes the performances. By using a distinctly cinematic technique, my attention was temporarily fixated on the filmmaking itself. Specifically, the stand-out performance by Eddie Redmayne. He captures more emotion in a pained smile than most impressionistic biopic performances manage altogether—which is equally a compliment to the film’s script by Anthony McCarten and the direction by James Marsh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t want to overlook what Felicity Jones brings to the role of Hawking’s wife, Jane. As far as the film is concerned, Hawking’s existence effectively begins on the night they meet. Which makes sense, considering Jane Hawking authored the book on which the film is based. But more importantly, the “Big Bang” sparks that occur that night are, in quantum terms, the singularity that brought this story into existence. But the film itself only pays passing interest to those theories; instead of chronicling Hawking’s noble pursuit for a simple equation to define the universe, &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt; looks at love as the only rational reason for being. Even if the formula can’t be proven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s how Stephen Hawking made a name for himself: by creating brilliant theories, then being their biggest critic. And looking back, love was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/1/the-theory-of-everything.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/1/the-theory-of-everything.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Horrible Bosses 2</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roar&lt;/em&gt; is the kind of song that gets you up in the morning.  You charge around the house, hairbrush microphone in-hand, making mirrored eye contact with yourself while mumbling 90% of the lyrics, but really belting out that chorus. At precisely 8:15 you rush out the door and catch the bus to work, where you sit silently, and avoid eye contact at all costs. &lt;em&gt;Horrible Bosses 2&lt;/em&gt; follows the same trajectory — moments of ambitious fantasy spoiled by harsh reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s still worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we rejoin Nick Hendrick, Kurt Buckman, and Dale Arbus, they’ve successfully moved on from their previous employers (in that they don’t have jobs) and have started a business. They’ve created the Shower Buddy, an all-in-one shower system designed to shave minutes off your morning routine. It’s pretty much a shopping channel dream. But they fumble their first promotional opportunity on a popular morning show thanks to minor product failure, overt sexual innuendo, and unintended racism. Afterwards, Nick, Kurt, and Dale commiserate in a bar, pondering their return to the cubicle. But that’s when they get the call. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what better ringtone to set the tone for what happens next?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Bert and Rex Hanson, a father-son team whose company, Boulder Stream, specializes in the manufacture of things that no one thought they needed. Bert, the patriarch of Boulder Stream, admires the boys’pull-themselves-up-by-the-boot-straps attitude and fuels their American Dream with a massive order. Cue&lt;em&gt;Roar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that dream ends with all the subtlety of a bucket of cold water to the face when Bert cancels the order with the intent of bankrupting their company, &lt;em&gt;Nick-Kurt-Dale&lt;/em&gt; (say it fast), and picking it up for pennies on the dollar. Not ones to settle conflict in traditional ways, Nick, Kurt, and Dale devise a plan to kidnap the younger Hanson for ransom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, as they discovered the first time around, they’re just not killers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, they’re not really kidnappers either and the whole plan goes sideways with a nitrous-oxide incident that results in Rex Hanson taking advantage of the situation and effectively kidnapping himself.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, things don’t go smoothly from this point but their plan is as entertaining as it is ineffective.  The film does try and touch on some of the bigger issues of a class system, but never too seriously, or too critically, so don’t expect to come out with a greater understanding of workforce empowerment in America. But let’s be honest, if you’re going to see this movie, you’d probably be disappointed if they brought you down with reality. This is the movie equivalent of your song; so grab a hairbrush microphone, suspend your disbelief for a bit, and enjoy your time in front of the mirror before you have to rush out the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cue &lt;em&gt;Roar&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Smart&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/28/horrible-bosses-2.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/28/horrible-bosses-2.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Laggies</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve wrangled many animals in the past, mainly dogs, and mainly on kid’s movies. All of which, I’m sure, requires a level of patience as a job prerequisite. But director Lynn Shelton’s latest mumblecore musing, &lt;em&gt;Laggies&lt;/em&gt;, ambles along at a deliberate pace. Shelley, the tortoise in your charge, moves so slowly that sometimes it must have seemed like she wasn’t going anywhere—but to Shelley, it probably felt like everything was blurring past at warp speed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28 year-old Megan is overeducated and underemployed. She lives with her high school sweetheart Anthony while working sporadically for her dad. Megan is content to stand on the sidelines as her high school besties tick off the wedding and baby boxes on their checklists. When Anthony suddenly proposes, Megan pretends she has a week-long seminar to attend, but instead hides out with her teen friend Annika. During that week, Megan vicariously relives her high school years and makes some serious decisions about her future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While other animal actors need constant grooming and PETA-approved trailers, it must have been refreshing to work with an actor and a director who are so low maintenance. Shelton often shoots in her native Seattle, which gives &lt;em&gt;Laggies&lt;/em&gt; an unobtrusive, organic quality. She does away with the glamourizing that plagues many quarter-life crisis films. Keira Knightley’s Megan looks less like a Chanel spokesmodel and more like the poster child for an Old Navy factory outlet. The homes and cars are unapologetically suburban, and instead of fancy coffee shops or nightclubs, the characters visit drive-thrus and strip mall restaurants. Megan doesn’t want the same cookie-cutter life as her friends, and it’s easy to see why it’s taken her so long to admit to herself that she’s outgrown them; their lives are comfortably bland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cast – Shelley The Tortoise included – is the best kind of understated. Chloe Grace Moretz plays Annika’s sadness about her mother’s absence matter-of-factly rather in the mode of a default Hollywood emotion. When Annika’s dad discovers Megan in the house, he sits her down for a friendly but guarded chat. Sam Rockwell possesses a rare, innate charm that can convince an audience he would let a strange woman stay at his house and not hit on her, while simultaneously making us wish he would. Knightley’s recognition of her untenable stasis is never forced, nor does her evolution feel artificial. She tells her sensitive new-age fiancée that her power animal is a tortoise, and it’s easy to see why he believes her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shelton has a knack for filming the literal and figurative spaces between people, and Andrea Seigel’s contrived (albeit likeable) script is at home in Shelton’s navel-gazing universe. She balances the self-analytical tone without allowing it become too precious or too cynical. The turtle-as-power-animal metaphor might have been a bit too facile if it wasn’t for the cast’s sincere delivery of Seigel’s unironically witty dialogue. It doesn’t take a tortoise wrangler to know that their shell protects a fragile soul. What’s less obvious (and perhaps more cumbersome) is the weight of our lives and how we owe it to ourselves to build ones worth carrying around for the long haul. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As every famous tortoise knows, life is a long distance race, not a sprint to the finish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/27/laggies.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/27/laggies.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Town That Dreaded Sundown</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The real-life events that occurred in the town of Texarkana in the late 1940s – an unidentified killer terrorizing the local populace – inspired filmmaker Charles B. Pierce to release &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; in 1976 (a pretty darn solid film in its own right, if memory serves). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remake, which you worked on, takes place in a universe where Pierce’s film is screened annually on Halloween, much to the chagrin of those old enough to remember the murders. Texarkana feels as if it never progressed past the 70s, with everybody possessing a wicked cool vintage car, popped collars, and era-appropriate feathered hair. But it’s primarily your excellent production design makes the town feel inexorably trapped in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe calling it a remake is a bit of a misnomer. On the one hand, some of the more iconic moments from the original are recreated – including the (in)famous trombone murder – and the present day investigation has intriguing parallels with the 1976 film. But this new version feels more like a sequel than anything else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constant references to Pierce’s original movie, even going so far as to have the director’s son appear as a total weirdo and potential suspect, could have lead to some truly unbearable meta-wankery. How fortunate then, that the writer and director are (for the most part) as capable as you are at balancing the ironic and sincere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a truly harrowing opening kill sequence, the premise for this reveals itself to be kinda brilliant: the heroine determines that the key to unmaking the modern day killer lies in getting to the truth of what happened half a century ago. Along with some impeccably orchestrated set-pieces – most notably a chase scene taking place in what appears to be a graveyard for used billboards (no idea how you thought this up, but it’s amazing) – we get a genuinely compelling mystery to tie it all together. It’s very welcome. I mean, there are some hiccups along the way, like the hilariously unbelievable romance between the Final Girl and a guy working at the town’s archive, but these are petty complaints in light of everything that works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then we get to a final act, which is so lackluster that it very nearly derails everything that came before it. I mean, I don’t think it’s fair to compare every self-referential movie to &lt;em&gt;Scream&lt;/em&gt;, but when the killer’s mask comes off and they explain their actions, the script seems to have borrowed liberally from the preeminent 90s meta-slashfest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy oh boy, is it ever lousy. Not just because it’s a reveal that any astute viewer can see coming from a country mile away. To be fair, there is a kind of cool secondary twist on the heels of this (non-)revelation, but it makes so little sense that the movie itself has to acknowledges how illogical it is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really hoping this would be a homerun, as your production work definitely suggested that this wasn’t simply going to be a remake/sequel/reimagining that would be content to go through the motions. And for the most part it isn’t. But that ending is such a goodwill-killer, which is a damn shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully we’ll be seeing more of your vision in future horror movies, as you bring a freshness sorely lacking in most of today’s genre output.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/26/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/26/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>God&#39;s Pocket</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’re best known as Joan Harris, the chilly office manager at the fictional ad agency in &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;. Joan is the proud figurehead of the Good Ship &lt;em&gt;Sterling Cooper &amp;amp; Partners&lt;/em&gt;, and not just because of her bombshell appearance. She’s the confident queen bee, feared, respected. But beneath the facade she’s a complicated, vulnerable woman. Joan is a character that comes along once in an actor’s lifetime. The kind of role that really showcases your gifts, and, no doubt, the kind of role that spoils you for future work. Especially roles like &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, in which your character is a literal figurehead: sculpted, wooden, and designed to lead men into a storm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; is the passion project of your &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; co-star John Slattery. It’s not only his feature directorial debut—he also co-wrote the script (adapted from Peter Dexter’s novel) and produced. You’re part of a dream cast of character actors he has assembled to tell the story of God’s Pocket, a gritty neighbourhood in the late-70s full of losers and crooks. Slattery, who has directed several &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; episodes, is obviously comfortable filming detailed period pieces; the art direction in &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; excels in capturing the colours, designs, and setting of the era while still managing to give the film a sense of timelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film’s problem isn’t style, its substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, of course, have no problem drifting through this bygone world. You play Jeanie, the mother of sociopathic loud-mouth Leon, who gets killed at his blue-collar job. You beg your husband Mickey to find out what really happened to Leon, while ensuring that he gets a proper funeral. Problem is, Mickey, a low-level crook, has no cash, and his boss, Arthur, is into the local loan shark for 20-Large. Meanwhile, local newspaper columnist Richard Shelburne, an alcoholic has-been and third-rate celebrity, gets involved in your case. But, of course, he ends up falling in love with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do you do? You sob, you sleep, you glare, you sashay around in too-tight house coats—talents perhaps better-suited to your torpid &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt; co-star January Jones. This left me wondering why Slattery didn’t cast &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; in this lifeless role. But at least you didn’t have to suffer alone. Philip Seymour Hoffman plays Mickey as a schlubby Philip Seymour Hoffman-type, drifting through scenes covered in flop sweat and self-loathing. And there must have been a surplus of flop-sweat and self-loathing in the make-up trailer, because it’s doused liberally all over Richard Jenkins newspaperman and Eddie Marsan’s slimy funeral home director. What’s left is spritzed over the denizens of the local watering hole, where inveterate drunks get cut off and respond with things like: “You can’t cut off the truth!” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bet you were missing Matthew Weiner right about then. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery of your son’s death is just one of many unsatisfying threads that unravel into oblivion. There are horse races, dead bodies in meat trucks, unfulfilling sex scenes, and the occasional brutal act of violence—all of which are apparently essential to the ambling plot, though none are particularly intriguing. You only have about fifteen lines in the whole film, and half of them are, “I know something happened to Leon, I just &lt;em&gt;know!&lt;/em&gt;” Your job is to pose with laundry, in dirty kitchens, while being alternately avoided and pursued. This may be &lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s still a man’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God’s Pocket&lt;/em&gt; feels like three separate movies. And none of them moved me. Particularly because in their attempt to combine unflinching, urban drama and dry humour, they succeeded at neither. This must have been particularly frustrating for you, since you’re so used to balancing both as the acid-tongued Joan. It’s even more unfortunate since &lt;a href=&quot;http://on.aol.com/video/roger-sterlings-best-one-liners-517732993&quot;&gt;John Slattery’s Roger Sterling is legendary&lt;/a&gt; for delivering some of &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;’s best lines while having arguably the most surprising character evolution on the show. It’s obvious, though, that his strengths as a director lie in visual storytelling. The writing of copy is a skill best left to somebody else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just sorry that 
you have to go back to the 60s to play a female character who is more than just a pretty face. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/25/gods-pocket.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/25/gods-pocket.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Virunga</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding ungracious, your work on &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; hurt my enjoyment of the film. Not because it was sub-par. Quite the opposite. The fact is, the sonic gloss you applied to Orland von Einsiedel’s documentary was so perfectly polished that it seemed at times to work against the very nature of the film and its intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your imprint is everywhere. From slow-motion shots of water droplets to ear-ringing gun shots and bombs, your hyper-realistic sound effects actually disengaged me from the material—albeit subconsciously. I felt like I was watching a Hollywood film. That says a lot, considering &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/change/2010/10/christopher-redmond.html&quot;&gt;my ongoing relationship&lt;/a&gt; with East Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the privilege of visiting the volcanic Virunga region of the Democratic Republic of Congo, and even spent time at Dian Fossey’s Gorilla Rehabilitation and Conservation Education (GRACE) center. Much of &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; plays out there, telling the story of a similar gorilla orphanage and the rangers tasked with protecting the surrounding national park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by protecting, I do mean with AK-47s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand firsthand the shock of seeing soldiers brandish their weapons so freely— and I understand the temptation to play that up. I’m guilty of the same dramatics when I recount my experiences travelling with mountain trackers and guides who are armed with guns to protect us not from the gorillas, but from the &lt;em&gt;guerillas&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is no doubt why the director indulges in a few dramatic point-of-view shots down the barrel of a gun. In that sense, your work is only complimenting his vision. Which isn’t entirely unjustified. The DRC is a ridiculously dangerous place. More people have been killed in the Congolese Civil War than in any other conflict since WWII. So when the story of &lt;em&gt;Virunga&lt;/em&gt; quickly turns from being that of a safari to surviving an armed take-over by M23 rebels, I know why you went full-clip on the sound effects. A simple shaky camera (in huge contrast to the film’s otherwise beautiful cinematography) is energized tenfold by the overwhelming echo of shelling and gunshots. But by laying that continuous sound bed over so many cuts, the danger felt almost manufactured. I felt manipulated, like you were trying to give me what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I wanted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not so different from my experience with the gorillas themselves. With only 800 in the world, seeing a majestic Silverback in the wild has truly been one of the highlights of my life.  In contrast, seeing a baby gorilla in one of those concrete rehab centers was one of the most depressing. It’s hard to articulate the profound nature of that difference, but it repeatedly came to mind watching the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is, while I’m spending a disproportionate amount of time fixating on your amplification of the drama, real drama does occur in this film. I hope that more people spend the money to visit these parks and support their preservation. I just hope you haven’t scared them away (I guess we’ll just have to remind them that entering the park from the Rwandan and Ugandan side is much, much safer).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/24/virunga.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/24/virunga.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 1</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It seems fitting that The Hunger Games saga got new costume designers for &lt;em&gt;Mockingjay&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;. Not only is your surrogate fashionista character gone from the series (Lenny Kravitz’s Cinna), but this film marks a big structural change for a franchise that, after just two films, is already in desperately in need of a makeover. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After being rather dazzled by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html&quot;&gt;original Hunger Games film&lt;/a&gt;, then lukewarm over the sequel &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/22/the-hunger-games-catching-fire.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Catching Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; I knew &lt;em&gt;Mockingjay&lt;/em&gt; needed to buck the trend of sending the kids into a deathmatch competition, and start exploring the larger world of Panem. I wasn’t sure was how the film would manage to do this without losing sight of what made the series special in the first place. For my money, that’s not so much the love triangle between Jennifer Lawrence, Josh Hutchinson, and Liam Hemsworth (that’s every YA franchise today), but rather the allegory about our contemporary media culture. So it wasn’t until the characters started talking about costumes that the film felt both on-brand and freshly re-launched. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a cold open on Katniss in a state of emotional distress, the story slowly rebuilds itself around her reluctant anointment as the face of the rebel movement. As always, she’s being used: this time by her liberators to motivate an uprising. She initially shows no interest in the job—until, of course, she sees the designs for her sexy warrior costume. The point isn’t played as shallow as I’m making it sound, but it certainly is an early turning point for her character. She apparently needs to look the part before she feels comfortable playing it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most stars probably feel that way—I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this theme has repeated itself in all three films. A flaming dress or cocktail gown will imbue Katniss with the confidence she needs to bust out of her shell (a point which is brought up several times by her image consultant, Effie). The film takes itself fairly seriously, though, and when Katniss &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; finally witness the destruction of The Capitol firsthand, it’s more important that we feel her anger than marvel at how good she looks when she’s getting angry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, setting much of this film in a rebel bunker was probably a pretty big disappointment to you guys. Although there’s always women in side-ponytails and brown leatherjackets at Halloween, most fans of The Hunger Games prefer to dress up as citizens of the Capitol  Glitter and excess rule the day. But we’re cut off from that city in this film. Instead, there’s a lot of plotting and scheming, with the occasional off-site adventure. Enjoyable, for the most part, but it feels incomplete. Probably the same way you guys felt about doing the costumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t suppose many people will be throwing Hunger Games parties wearing the grey overalls that dominate most of this film. But you never know. Fashion, and youth franchises, can sometimes surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/21/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-1.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/21/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-1.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>After Tiller</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your job is to work with the filmmakers – in the case of &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt;, producers/directors Martha Shane and Lana Wilson – to assemble their footage into an effective narrative. It’s all about offering choices, and I’m sure some of those choices were difficult. You help shape the story, offer advice, but, ultimately, the final decisions are not yours to make. You need to trust that the people making these decisions know what’s best. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike scripted films, documentaries aren’t typically “written” until all the footage has been compiled. It’s only &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; viewing the footage that the story is uncovered, pieced together by editing. Shane and Wilson relied on your expertise to guide them through the murky moral waters of the abortion debate to tell a part of the story that has so far been overlooked: that of the abortion provider. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your advice to them: &lt;a href=&quot;http://video.pbs.org/video/2365315295/&quot;&gt;tell the truth.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing easy about &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt;. Not the watching &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; the telling. With a topic as divisive as abortion – and, in this case, the highly controversial practice of late-term abortion (performed after 20 weeks) – trying to force the narrative onto common ground is more than impossible, it’s unnecessary. The abortion issue is more complicated than most people realize, but the truths &lt;em&gt;After Tille&lt;/em&gt;r presents are simple: the four doctors still performing late-term abortions in the U.S. do so because they believe abortion is a healthcare issue, not a political or religious one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tiller in &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt; is Dr. George Tiller, a former member of the armed forces, an active Christian, and a late-term abortion practitioner in Kansas. After decades of threats, which included having his clinic bombed in 1985, and being shot in both arms in 1993, Dr. Tiller was murdered while attending church in 2009. The four remaining practitioners – Dr. Carhart in Nebraska, Dr. Hern in Colorado, and Dr. Robinson and Dr. Sella in New Mexico – considered him not just a colleague, but a mentor and a friend. There was no question about whether or not they would carry on with their respective practices following his murder. As hard as it is for many to believe, these doctors love what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film tracks along the prosaic Middle American landscapes of highways and strip malls, past churches and schools, past medical buildings. But once behind the doors of these doctor’s offices, &lt;em&gt;After Tiller&lt;/em&gt; shows us a world few of us ever see. The camera captures the mundane internal goings-on: fluorescent lights flicker, paperwork is signed, phones ring. The only hint that these offices are different than your average GP’s is the Department of Justice letter taped to the front desk, with handwritten instructions on how to proceed should a member of staff receive threats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We witness each doctor in counselling sessions with the women seeking their services. We don’t see the women’s faces. Instead, the camera focuses on the women’s hands as they fidget with tissues and gesture while describing the painful reasons they need to terminate their pregnancies. Late-term abortions make up less than 1% of all abortions performed in the U.S. (the majority of these are planned pregnancies in which severe foetal abnormalities are found after the 20th week). You and the filmmakers choose to focus on the doctor’s faces, wrought with concern and compassion for the unthinkable situations their patients are facing. We see the doctors comforting their patients, and listening, holding their hands, and often holding back tears themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Robinson recalls working in a state where the woman is required to tell a compelling story to not one, but two separate doctors, in order to obtain an abortion. “And some women just aren’t good storytellers,” she says. As Dr. Hern counsels a rape victim, we see that his lapel button says, “Trust Women.” Dr. Sella admits that she struggles because she still thinks of them as babies, not mere tissue to be removed. As the film progresses, you show us how the issue gets even more convoluted as patients come in seeking abortions with perhaps less concrete reasons for ending their pregnancies. Some were in denial after sexual assault and waited too long, some are poor and had to work to afford abortions that were no longer viable by the time they had the funds. One is a devout Catholic teenager who was afraid to tell her parents before her pregnancy became obvious. Your decision to focus on these challenging narratives shows us just how multifaceted this issue is despite how simple the detractors aim to make it appear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these doctors wanted to be political activists. They just want to help women. And they still grapple with ethical conundrums on a daily basis, all while keeping Dr. Tiller’s ethos at the forefront of their practices: that a woman’s body is smarter than a doctor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth you encouraged Shane and Wilson to seek is the real hero of this story. Thank you for guiding its journey. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/20/after-tiller.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/20/after-tiller.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Wolves</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not big on horror movies. It’s not that they scare me (they terrify me), it’s that they leave me underwhelmed (crying behind the couch), because they are so formulaic and hackneyed (I am unable to sleep for days). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is I scare easier than a cat fleeing a vacuum cleaner. I don’t like monsters, I don’t like blood, and I don’t like things that go bump in the night. I was fully prepared to turn down the invitation to review David Hayter’s feature film debut, &lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt;, then my editor nonchalantly mentioned, “It’s the new movie with Jason Momoa.” Like he &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; I wouldn’t be able to refuse. Such underhanded tactics aside, I thought I should take the opportunity to step outside my comfort zone, so I marshalled my courage and settled in to watch. After turning every light in the house on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High school football hero Cayden Richards leads a charmed life, albeit recently punctuated by sudden, inexplicable bursts of strength and temper. He blacks out while on a date, waking up to find his parents brutally murdered and the police at the door. This is where things start to get hairy (sorry). Cayden turns into a werewolf and makes a run for it. The furry fugitive finds his way to a small farm town where the locals are unusually hostile. He is given refuge by gruff but kind John Tollerman, who warns him about Connor Slaughter, leader of the local band of drunken toughs and lowlifes. Given that the film isn’t called &lt;em&gt;Wolf&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt;, we can guess what happens next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt; attempts to blend the conventions of action and horror film, using tropes and archetypes from both the fugitive, the damsel in distress, the monster and its origin myth. But it never really finds its footing, and I was at a loss as to whether I was supposed to be afraid or amused “Are they &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to be funny?” was something I asked myself a lot during the film. The performances across the board seem phoned in, from Cayden’s monotone voice-over to the stone-faced delivery of lines and the weird, inconsistent accents of many supporting characters. Plot developments and twists feel just as forced. Your performance therefore stands out as the only one with a hint of life in it. Connor is the only character on screen who looks like he’s having any fun at all, and the only one who embodies the aggression and ferocity one would want to see in a movie about werewolves, or in a horror film in general. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of me was relieved that &lt;em&gt;Wolves&lt;/em&gt; was less of a fright-fest than expected, if only for the sake of my dignity. But I wish more of your fellow cast members would have shared some of your energy and enthusiasm for their characters. Unfortunately, one decent performance is not enough in a film that comes off as a sustained shrug of indifference. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/19/wolves.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/19/wolves.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Big Hero 6</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The marketing materials for &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; proudly exclaim “From the people who brought you &lt;em&gt;Frozen, Tangled,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wreck-it Ralph&lt;/em&gt;”, and that had me wondering if your job had gotten trickier in the last few years now that Disney seems to own, well, almost everything. You see, this could easily have been sold as “From the people who brought you &lt;em&gt;Cars 2&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Toy Story.&lt;/em&gt;” Or even “From the people who brought you &lt;em&gt;The Avengers&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Iron Man 3&lt;/em&gt;.” While it’s not marketed as either an official Pixar or Marvel film, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero&lt;/em&gt; 6 is certainly as much a product of both of those entities as it is Disney alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; introduces us to Hiro(!), a 14-year old loner who is a genius with robot design but is squandering his gift in the underworld of robot fighting - think &lt;em&gt;Real Steel&lt;/em&gt; meets &lt;em&gt;Bloodsport&lt;/em&gt; but with less, you know, blood.  After Hiro’s older brother/father figure, Tadashi,  tricks him into visiting the university robot lab where he studies, Hiro realizes he could do a whole lot more with his gifts. He’s also introduced to Tadashi’s motley assortment of classmates who have been conveniently pre-nicknamed by the class clown just in case they ever need secret identities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiro’s mind is opened to new possibilities when he meets Baymax, Tadashi’s personal project. Baymax is a cuddly medical robot designed to treat all manner of illness and injury (in perhaps a nod to the lonely child relationship of &lt;em&gt;E.T. The Extra Terrestrial&lt;/em&gt;, Baymax is activated when it hears someone say “Ouch”). Hiro sets his sights on impressing Tadashi’s professor, Dr. Callaghan, and landing a spot in the robot lab. &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt;’s first act details Hiro’s transformation from punk kid to budding academic, culminating with Hiro’s creation of Micro-robots, small, intelligent, mind-controlled building blocks that can be used to construct anything their user can think of. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, no hero’s journey is complete without the tragedy that sets him on the path to righteousness, and &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t break any new ground here. Anyone with a passing understanding of Joseph Campbell can guess at the fate of father figure-types. Suffice it to say, Hiro finds himself at a low point with Baymax as his only company. Also like &lt;em&gt;E.T.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; gets a lot of second act mileage from Hiro trying to overcome Baymax’s rudimentary programming by teaching him how to behave more human. It also leads them to discover that Hiro’s Micro-robots, once thought lost to the aforementioned tragedy, are being used for some unclear nefarious purpose. Eventually the rest of the Robot Lab is brought in to help figure out what exactly is going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s at this point in the film that I started to think of the marketing quandaries you must have faced, Amy. You see, despite your and your team’s best efforts, I went into &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; pretty ignorant of not only what it was about, but also of its origins. It wasn’t until Hiro and his friends spot the obligatory Stan Lee cameo, that I realized, &lt;em&gt;this is also a Marvel movie!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might not think that’s a huge deal, but it fundamentally changed my relationship to &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt;. I could instantly see how the final two acts of the movie (&lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; is, atypically, broken into four acts) would play out; the heroes are assembled, each with a specific skill, they have one or two setbacks before coming together as a true unit and overcoming the villain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a disappointment to realize that what I thought was a quirky and original film was slowly turning into the same formula I‘ve seen over and over. I’m not saying that you misled me—or even that the rest of &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; is bad. In fact, it’s still highly enjoyable. The animation is great, as one would expect from a studio that is now overseen by Pixar’s braintrust,. The voice work by Scott Adsit, Ryan Potter, James Cromwell, and especially T.J. Miller, is top-drawer.  And like &lt;em&gt;The Incredibles&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; has some of the best action scene construction this side of Steven Spielberg. But once my expectations were set by that cameo, &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; settled into little more than meeting them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said in the opening to this letter, you could have just as easily marketed &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; as a product created by any one of those corporate entities. It really feels like the result of that most 90s of terms, &lt;em&gt;corporate synergy&lt;/em&gt;: the strategies and missions of each brand is met, but the result strips out whatever makes it unique. Watching &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; is sort of like seeing that happen in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
