<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Left Behind</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#39;t know this, but you shaped my childhood in a large way. My father is super into End Times Prophecy, and my family used to watch &lt;em&gt;This Week In Bible Prophecy&lt;/em&gt; (the show you co-hosted with your brother Peter), which disseminated how the weekly world news was actually fulfilling the prophecies of Revelation. My dad also read several of Tim LaHaye&amp;#39;s (co-author of the &lt;em&gt;Left Behind&lt;/em&gt; series of novels) &amp;quot;non-fiction&amp;quot; works, so I am well-versed on your theological stance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#39;m not here to debate that. I&amp;#39;m here to talk about your storytelling skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, I came into this movie without ever having read the novels or seeing the first trilogy of films based on them. I had fresh eyes. I also tried &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard not to let my now-atheistic beliefs bias me against your film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;#39;s the thing: despite the surprisingly competent – dare I say &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; - performances of the film&amp;#39;s stars, they really didn&amp;#39;t have much to work with. The only two things that really happen in the entire film are: 1) all the Christians and children suddenly disappear about halfway through, and 2) a plane almost crashes. That&amp;#39;s barely enough to sustain an episode of an hour-long television episode, let alone a 110-minute film (and I&amp;#39;m currently binge-watching the episodes of &lt;em&gt;Supernatural&lt;/em&gt; dealing with the Apocalypse, so I should know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religious beliefs aside, both the Rapture (an event which, strangely, is never referred to in the film as such) and the Apocalypse are fascinating stories that offer a lot of potential. It&amp;#39;s a shame you wasted them here. Maybe that&amp;#39;s the fault of Tim LaHaye and Jerry B. Jenkins - like I said, I haven&amp;#39;t read the source material, so I don&amp;#39;t know what you were working with - but, as the co-writer AND the producer, you had the opportunity to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final aside: I know the producers make the final decision when it comes to the score, so you should know that it&amp;#39;s pretty shlocky at times.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/12/left-behind.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/12/left-behind.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Why Gone Girl Makes Me Sad for the State of Cinema</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You had a good run. Quite frankly, you changed the world. But in the 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;
 century, the world has changed you. Look no further than David Fincher&amp;#39;s latest film &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; for proof. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s the canary in the cinematic coal mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; is a good film. Almost a great film. It has a runtime of two and a half hours, but earns every minute – and then some. The story is juicy and complex, the performances are dialed in just right, and the plot twists are both frequent and fascinating. In any other era, &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; would have been worthy and welcomed in movie theaters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; belongs on television. As a mini-series, where all great stories are told – unencumbered by the restraints of cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, restraints. Less than a generation ago, TV was widely considered a second-class medium. It was the domain of craftsmen instead of artists. A world filled with topical jokes and disposable drama. A place for censored stories and restrictive, sponsor-driven structures. Not to mention production limitations galore. Of course that&amp;#39;s no longer the case, as &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Boardwalk Empire&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Homeland&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;, and countless other TV programs have proved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new Golden Era of Television, the rulebook has been thrown out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone heralds HBO as the game changer, but that channel is more poster child than messiah. Fantastic television mini-series have always existed (&lt;em&gt;Roots&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;North and South&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jesus of Nazareth&lt;/em&gt;), but today, the mini-series has become the gold standard for great storytelling. Turning to a mini-series for a rich, nuanced and ambitious story is no longer the exception, but the &lt;em&gt;expectation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt;. A film whose scope, scale and stars are all better suited for a serialized TV format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Fincher should have known better. He&amp;#39;s one of the most exciting American directors working today, and a rare example of an auteur who doesn&amp;#39;t write his own screenplays. Fincher&amp;#39;s recently proven with &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt; that he&amp;#39;s the perfect candidate for helming a mini-series, which makes his &amp;quot;step-backwards&amp;quot; into cinema all the more frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not read Gillian Flynn&amp;#39;s much-loved book, so this is certainly not one of those complaints about &amp;quot;how much better the book was&amp;quot;. Flynn did a fine job adapting the screenplay herself. How do I know this? Because by the film&amp;#39;s third act, I was craving more time with the characters, more detail about their relationships and more scope to the story. It could be &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; I didn&amp;#39;t read the book that I wanted to savour the story even more. And why I felt the weakness of film as a medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the delicately paced first act of &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt;, the twists and turns almost start to feel rushed as the film gains momentum. Character turns become pulpy instead of relatable. There are moments of revelation that almost beg the audience to take a breather to reflect and engage in conversation, the way you can with a mini-series. Instead we barrel forward to the climax and a time-crunching denouement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of me craves the discussion that a mini-series affords before everything is wrapped up and answered for us. How can I not? The past year alone has brought us &lt;em&gt;True Detective&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Honourable Woman&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Knick&lt;/em&gt;. Even a film like &lt;em&gt;Fargo&lt;/em&gt; – which is a clinic in economical storytelling – lead to a dreaded-but-surprisingly-incredible re-imagining of that story. And at no time did that story seem stretched out or watered down on the small screen – it felt completely at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t take this the wrong way, Cinema, but to be worthy of a mini-series today is a wonderful thing. It&amp;#39;s probably the best medium for entertainment we have right now, so you really need to go big, or we&amp;#39;ll go home. Of course, there would be no justification for &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; to go any bigger. Everything was already scaled perfectly for a network to take on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that delicious story…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You really can&amp;#39;t compare books and film. Think about it: it&amp;#39;s one thing for Michael Crichton to write about a park filled with dinosaurs, but it&amp;#39;s quite another to bring them to life in a way that&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/4/4/top-10-uncredited-heroes-of-jurassic-park.html&quot;&gt;still believable 20 years later.&lt;/a&gt; But the distinction between film and television is now almost non-existent. &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; proves that we live in an era where film can simply mean &amp;quot;less&amp;quot; than TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess when it comes to &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt;, I wanted more than you can offer. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/10/why-gone-girl-makes-me-sad-for-the-state-of-cinema.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Gone Girl</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Despite his famous ego as an auteur, Orson Welles paid a great compliment to Gregg Toland by sharing a title card with the cinematographer on &lt;em&gt;Citizen Kane&lt;/em&gt;. This crossed my mind as I saw your name in the opening credits for David Fincher&amp;#39;s thriller &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl.&lt;/em&gt; Your name&amp;#39;s not on the screen alongside Fincher&amp;#39;s, but the placement is telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound designers, like you, are usually listed in the end credits — the end of the end credits, actually. Without going into the politics of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/9/neighbors.html&quot;&gt;movie credit hierarchy&lt;/a&gt;, I think it might be a bit of nod to the importance of your contribution that your name is listed so highly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; is directed by David Fincher — often referred to as one of the most stylistically baroque filmmakers working today. So you might expect a sound design to match. But Fincher&amp;#39;s come a long way since the days of &lt;em&gt;Alien 3, Seven&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Fight Club&lt;/em&gt;. He&amp;#39;s now one of Hollywood&amp;#39;s most consistently reliable directors for turning in smart, exquisitely crafted dramas (let&amp;#39;s all agree to overlook &lt;em&gt;The Curious Case of Benjamin Button&lt;/em&gt;, shall we?) that know exactly when—and more importantly when &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;—to go over the top. Fittingly, your sound design here syncs up perfectly with this more understated approach. And thank God for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve grown increasingly tired with modern sound design where everything, diagetic or not, needs a sound effect. Everything. I don&amp;#39;t know exactly when this started, but I became acutely aware of it in the mid 90s, around the time foley artists decided cigarettes needed to make a burning sound whenever a character took a drag. Little did I know we were heading into an era where even filmmaking techniques—camera pans, fades edits—would have their own library of sound effects. So much for the invisible arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Fincher, a savant to film craft if there ever was one, is far too smart to fall for these trappings. By taking everything—your sound design included, Ren—down to their basic, least intrusive forms, Fincher creates a setting that feels natural even as events start to go, well, bananas. Gillian Flynn&amp;#39;s 2012 novel is well-known for some pretty out-there plot twists, and her script keeps the craziness in-tact. Fincher and all of his collaborators respond to this, toning everything else down. And it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alfred Hitchcock famously said that tension was created when the audience knew more than the characters did. The camera, providing an omniscient point of view, could reveal details to us that the characters could not know. In &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl,&lt;/em&gt; Fincher and Flynn flip this premise on its head. Ben Affleck&amp;#39;s Nick Dunne returns home on his fifth wedding anniversary to find his wife Amy missing, and signs of a struggle in the house. After bringing in the authorities to investigate, Dunne quickly becomes the prime suspect. Did he do it or not? That&amp;#39;s the question that preoccupies much of &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-Hitchcock element here is that the one person who knows this answer for sure—Dunne—is both our point-of-entry to the story and an opaque mystery. Where something like &lt;em&gt;The Fugitive&lt;/em&gt; gets its righteous propulsion from our knowledge that Richard Kimble is innocent, &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; asks us to invest ourselves in someone who might very well be a murderer. Again, and against the odds, it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casting Affleck as Dunne may be the film&amp;#39;s greatest strength: Affleck brings just enough &amp;quot;how could this happen to a fun-loving guy like me?&amp;quot; entitlement that, along with the more tangible character faults of Dunne himself, make us want to question his every motive. That Rosamund Pike as Amy, the titular girl, represented almost entirely in flashbacks informed by her own diary entries gives us one more level of remove from Dunne — and one more reason not to trust him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;#39;s just part of what &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; has in store. As the film moves from its early procedural tone to something much more outlandish, it actually starts to feel like a combination of both the old and new Fincher, specifically a grafting together of &lt;em&gt;Zodiac&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Game&lt;/em&gt;. And as things get crazier—and lets face it, much of &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#39;s second half is flat out ridiculous – your sound design goes along for the ride. I&amp;#39;m not saying you ever go full-out-Tony-Scott-sound-design crazy, but the sound definitely starts to become a bigger presence near the end. As it does this, though, the film itself shifts tone again, trading in claustrophobic thriller for something approaching black comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all subtle changes, mind you. The intentional shifts in the film&amp;#39;s style give us permission to enjoy &lt;em&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/em&gt; for the tawdry, insane narrative it is. That&amp;#39;s a tricky balancing act to pull off without turning into a parody, but everyone involved does just that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/9/gone-girl.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/9/gone-girl.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Night Moves</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;#39;t think of a worse gig for someone like you than a Kelly Reichardt film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;ve seen her earlier work – notably &lt;em&gt;Wendy and Lucy&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Meek&amp;#39;s Cutoff&lt;/em&gt; (both starring Michelle Williams) – you&amp;#39;ve undoubtedly noticed the simultaneously essential and throwaway nature of mixing the location sound. In order to achieve her distinctive brand of neo-realism, Reichardt often forces the audience to strain to make out the mumbled dialogue hidden behind campfire crackles or desert winds. At other times, she will eschew dialogue completely for 15 minutes at a time and just let the simplest location sounds support her minimal aesthetics. This might have lead you to assume that &lt;em&gt;Night Moves&lt;/em&gt; would be either the easiest job of your life, or the hardest. But that wasn&amp;#39;t the case, was it? &lt;em&gt;Night Moves&lt;/em&gt; probably turned out to be just another job, the same way it turned out to be just another film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reichardt, a true American auteur, has decided to take a modest step towards the commercial center in this story about environmental activists plotting to destroy a hydro dam. The narrative, motivations, and dialogue, are all fairly clear and easy to follow. Her trademark wandering characters are in control for most of this film, and her technical approach follows suit. The lighting is sparse and natural, the camera is slow and distant, and your location sound is dialed back but ever-present. This time, however, Jeff Grace&amp;#39;s soundtrack is covering much more of the transitions and mood shifts. It all ends up feeling a little too conventional, especially after the bold impression she left with her last film, &lt;em&gt;Meek&amp;#39;s Cutoff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, this is far from a standard thriller. Reichardt is once again exploring the relationship between people and nature, but in a much more aggressive and direct approach than in the past. Jesse Eisenberg, in the central role, gives a restrained and introspective performance, but his co-stars Dakota Fanning and Peter Saarsgard are allowed to play within a slightly wider and more relatable range. They can smile, be sarcastic and openly debate consequences rather than bottle them all up inside. Perhaps this is why their character arcs are more sympathetic than Eisenberg&amp;#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, it&amp;#39;s what&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being said or heard that usually makes Reichardt&amp;#39;s films unique. After toiling in independent obscurity for years, it&amp;#39;s hard to blame her for trying to make something less challenging on the audience. Except easy is never as rewarding – not for a viewer, and not even for a crew member like you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/8/night-moves.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/8/night-moves.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Maze Runner</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: teenagers are jerks. But I&amp;#39;m sure I don&amp;#39;t have to tell a teacher that. In the ninth grade, when &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Flies&lt;/em&gt; was handed out, I opened my copy to see that the kid who&amp;#39;d had the book before me had written &amp;quot;Piggy dies&amp;quot; on the first page. But for this heartless ballpoint scrawl, it may have taken me much longer to determine the fates of those characters. Unfortunately, the same can&amp;#39;t be said for the pedestrian young adult actioner, &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt;, which manages the impressive feat of making a homicidal labyrinth seem predictable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m sure, through the course of your career, you&amp;#39;ve had to read more than your fair share of book reports on the dystopian teen novel of the moment. The granddaddy of them all would be the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Flies&lt;/em&gt; (from which &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt; borrows liberally). There&amp;#39;s also &lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt; Trilogy, the &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; Series, &lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;—the list goes on, and you&amp;#39;ve no doubt become familiar with all the genre&amp;#39;s tropes. Sadly, so has the audience for these novel to film adaptations. Sure, the market is oversaturated, so it would be easy to say that &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt; suffers from a case of bad timing. But lack of originality isn&amp;#39;t the film&amp;#39;s biggest problem. It&amp;#39;s the lack of heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas is a 16 year-old who wakes up in a rusty box in the middle of a maze with no memory of his past. The centre of the maze, called The Glade, is inhabited by a group of boys who have been trying to find a way out with no luck. Thomas must convince the boys to give up the relative security of The Glade for a chance at freedom by risking escape through the ever-changing, monster-inhabited maze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kids are naturally curious, so spending your days with them means you have to be quick with answers. The biggest puzzle in this film is that none of the boys know where they came from or why they&amp;#39;re there. Which would be fine if the film wasn&amp;#39;t so reluctant to feed us any interesting clues. Without backstory it&amp;#39;s impossible to care about these boys, so, instead of characters we can root for, we get archetypes: Thomas, the fearless protagonist; Alby the damaged leader; Minho, the ethnic sidekick; Gally, the bully. We even get Chuck, the loveable fat kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can guess what happens to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder, as an adult authority figure, if you&amp;#39;ve ever had to utter the phrase, &amp;quot;Because I said so&amp;quot;? Even as you say it, you know it&amp;#39;s a weak argument. But it&amp;#39;s usually enough to placate the little brats, isn&amp;#39;t it? But only for so long. When the adults in &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt; do show up, it&amp;#39;s only to offer a Cole&amp;#39;s Notes explanation for their actions. By this point they&amp;#39;d lost all credibility. So, like a petulant child, I stopped listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your job exists because child labour laws require that minors working on a film set are supervised at all times. In addition to teaching, you have to ensure the health and welfare of the children in your charge—from watching what they eat at the craft service table, to making sure Teamsters don&amp;#39;t curse in front of them. You spend so much time with these kids that I&amp;#39;m sure you grow attached. In the case of &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt;, the teen cast is inordinately talented. But instead of being given fully fleshed-out characters to play, they&amp;#39;re primarily relegated to physical activity and/or exposition delivery. It doesn&amp;#39;t matter how ominous and imposing the maze is, or how terrifying the monster special effects are...if we&amp;#39;re not emotionally invested in the kids&amp;#39; future, the whole endeavour is a lesson in futility.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/7/the-maze-runner.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/7/the-maze-runner.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>My Old Lady</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There is a certain stagnant claustrophobia in the sprawling Paris apartment that serves as the setting for Israel Horowitz&amp;#39;s screen adaptation of his play, &lt;em&gt;My Old Lady&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;#39;ve had this feeling as a child when visiting the homes of elderly relatives. Apart from the furniture and decades of accumulated clutter, there is something intangible that blocks natural light and sucks the air out of the room, making you grateful for the first opportunity to step outside. I felt the same way watching this film, because Horowitz has the building blocks of what should be something truly remarkable, but instead he delivers something quite stale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When failed novelist and recovering alcoholic, Mathias Gold, played by Kevin Kline, inherits an apartment in Paris from his estranged father, he is eager to sell the place as soon as possible. The presence of Maggie Smith&amp;#39;s Mathilde, an elderly tenant, and her daughter, Chloe, played by Kristin Scott Thomas, combined with the weirdest real estate laws I have ever heard of, throw a wrench into his plans. Broke, and stuck paying rent to Mathilde for occupying a room in the apartment he now owns (like I said, weirdest laws ever), Mathias pokes around in various drawers and cupboards discovering hidden family secrets and scandals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horowitz&amp;#39;s flippant dialogue is clever enough, and with powerhouse actors like Kline, Smith, and Scott Thomas, I expected great things. Instead, the film is just another adaptation that isn&amp;#39;t as good on screen as on stage. The plot feels misdirected, coming across as a charming romantic comedy at first, swerving clumsily into deep melodrama, and then back to whimsical love story. The apartment itself, though spacious and tastefully appointed, fosters a sense of tedium and inertia that clashes with the actors&amp;#39; increasingly animated performances. As deeper and darker grievances come to light, the cramped setting suffocates the performances to the point where they feel phoned in. This tug-of-war between the film&amp;#39;s stylistic elements ultimately jars the flow of the narrative. Take the soundtrack, for example. I get that every film set in Paris absolutely &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; feature the same too-charming organ grinder/violin/accordion music, but it just doesn&amp;#39;t fit here. Following up the melodramatic emotional unravelling of your main character with an abrupt transition to that saccharine, tinny, &amp;#39;ah, l&amp;#39;amour&amp;#39; waltz-y business really kills the mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did do a fine job giving Mathilde&amp;#39;s apartment (or is it Mathias&amp;#39; apartment? I still don&amp;#39;t actually know) that frozen-in-time quality that perfectly matches the mindset of its occupants. The space complements a narrative that treats the topics upon which it touches like dusty curios in an old room; childhood baggage, infidelity, and filial antagonisms are picked up, examined with mild interest, and set aside when the next, more interesting object is spied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reasonably well-wrought on their own, the narrative and stylistic elements simply do not fit together, chafing against each other in a way that indicates an overall lack of certainty, resulting in a film that isn&amp;#39;t quite sure what it wants to be. To be fair, &lt;em&gt;My Old Lady&lt;/em&gt; is not without its charming moments, but they all take place in the brief sojourns from the main plot. Mathias&amp;#39; friendship with a local realtor, and a random riverside encounter with an opera singer brought a smile to my face, and made me wonder if Mathias &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to go home right then or if he could stay outside and play just a little while longer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/6/my-old-lady.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/6/my-old-lady.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>This is Where I Leave You</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Some might find it strange that a dialogue-driven, ensemble dramedy like &lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt; required any stunts. Those people are probably only-children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my brothers and I were kids, we used to stage fights. Mostly in slow-motion with the &amp;quot;nun-nun-nun-nun&amp;quot; sound effect from &lt;em&gt;The Six Million Dollar Man&lt;/em&gt; to accompany punches that purposely didn&amp;#39;t make contact. But sometimes we got into serious fights, with real blood and broken furniture and punches that were most certainly meant to connect. You must have siblings as well. From the fight scenes, stunt driving, and various choreographed physicality executed by you and your team, it would seem that you have a firm grasp of complex family dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt; also fights a lot with its proverbial parent – the novel. The film suffers from the typical book-to-film adaptation problem where there&amp;#39;s just too much story to pack into 100 minutes. This film is genuinely funny, poignant, and true, with fine performances that unfortunately only scratch the surface of a deeper truth about family and forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the patriarch of the Altman family dies, his widow demands their four adult children spend the week mourning together in the family home. Which means the Altman siblings will regress, fight, mourn, and make some heavy life decisions over the course of those seven days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle son Judd takes a physical and emotional beating in this film, and Jason Bateman is certainly a deft enough actor to handle the challenge of skating the thin line between comedy and drama. It helps that you made sure the stunts never feel like slapsticky pratfalls. In an early scene, Judd attempts to break up a particularly ugly fight between his brothers and gets a piece of glass embedded in his forehead for his trouble. After a sufficiently appropriate pause, the rest of the family continues talking and eating like nothing happened. The scene is noteworthy, not because it&amp;#39;s played for humour, but because it&amp;#39;s played for honesty. This film reminds us that in a big family, you&amp;#39;re not more important than anyone else. You just have to take your lumps and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could apply that philosophy to your job, which requires you to coordinate with many different departments - from makeup and costumes, to prop masters, effects coordinators, and of course, the producers and director. That&amp;#39;s a lot of egos to manage, and it&amp;#39;s important that they are all given equal consideration. It seems that director, Shawn Levy, felt the same way about his talent-heavy cast. Working from a screenplay adapted from Jonathan Tropper&amp;#39;s novel, Levy had a lot of character arcs to juggle, so it&amp;#39;s no surprise he had a hard time keeping them all in the air. In addition to Bateman, Jane Fonda, Tina Fey, Adam Driver, Corey Stoll, Kathryn Hahn, Rose Byrne, Timothy Olyphant, Dax Shepard and Connie Britton all punch well above their weight here with the juicy, multi-dimensional characters they get to play. But it&amp;#39;s too much of a good thing. While Levy was spoiled for choice, the audience is starving for a little depth of focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of a film&amp;#39;s genre, when stunts are done well they are suspenseful and clever, and exciting to watch. When done poorly, they&amp;#39;re confusing, repetitive and can bring the narrative to a screeching halt. The same can be said for ensemble pieces. The problem isn&amp;#39;t that &lt;em&gt;This Is Where I Leave You&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;#39;t hit all its marks, it&amp;#39;s that there are just too many marks to hit. And Levy tries to hit them all. Maybe he should have consulted you first.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/3/this-is-where-i-leave-you.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/3/this-is-where-i-leave-you.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Trip to Italy</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s perhaps a bit self-indulgent to write this letter to you. There&amp;#39;s so much else that is essential to the success of &lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt;: the majestic seaside vistas, the stunning culinary creations, the moving soundtrack from Richard Strauss and, yes, Alanis Morrisette. But, first and foremost, I&amp;#39;m a Steve Coogan fan, and I was drawn to this film – and its predecessor, &lt;em&gt;The Trip&lt;/em&gt; – because of your involvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s often hard, here on the left side of the Atlantic, to keep up with your body of work. You&amp;#39;d think that your most successful British show, &lt;em&gt;The Alan Partridge Show&lt;/em&gt; (one of the great comedy series of all time, British or otherwise), would be more readily available over here. But, no. We get &lt;em&gt;The Office&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Extras&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Little Britain&lt;/em&gt;—but no &lt;em&gt;Partridge&lt;/em&gt;. Even the feature-length Alan Partridge film was late in arriving to the New World, and, when it did, appeared only on a modest number of screens. So &lt;em&gt;The Trip&lt;/em&gt; films, for me, are like a distant cousin&amp;#39;s wedding or school reunion: a chance to catch up with my faraway friends and loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;#39;ve revealed my bias, my thoughts on &lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt; might seem obvious and irrelevant. But the film itself plays out behind a veil of irrelevance. It meanders, digresses, loiters, philanders (both figuratively and literally)—but all to a higher purpose. So of course I loved it. Of coursed I loved your performance. Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first &lt;em&gt;Trip&lt;/em&gt; film, which followed you and your travel companion Rob Brydon on a restaurant tour of Northern England, you each played to your respective strengths: Brydon as earnest, motor-mouthed family man; you as the acerbic bachelor injured by his failed ambitions. Here, in subtle degrees of patience and composure, your performance has evolved. The Steve Coogan in this film is a different Steve Coogan than the one who appears in the first. Which is significant, considering how difficult it is, in the first place, to play a plausible version of oneself onscreen. We get a different Rob Brydon, too (though his transformation is expressed primarily through action). While the role-reversal conceit might seem a little too familiar – shades of a body-swap comedy – your delivery makes it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a tribute to you, Brydon, and director Michael Winterbottom, that a two-hour film built from a series of semi-improvised conversations on topics ranging from the number of Batmen Michael Caine has buried to Byron&amp;#39;s culpability in the death of Percy Bysshe Shelley is able not just to maintain its velocity, but to hit a few genuinely affecting beats. The comedy is broad, but the sentiments aren&amp;#39;t. Brydon&amp;#39;s marital struggles don&amp;#39;t play out the way one imagines they will, and remain, by the end of the film, frustratingly (and credibly) unresolved. Your own minor crisis concludes in a quiet scene aboard a small yacht floating in the sunset off the southern Italian coast: a very simple conversation between father and son, unadorned with movie-star impressions or punch-lines or self-sabotaging sarcasm. It unfolds like the thousand other father/son conversations that preceded it, but in the context of your character&amp;#39;s arc through both films, feels sort of profound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this moving stuff in a film that delivers, consistently, lines like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Where do you stand on Michael Bublé?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;On his windpipe?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;#39;re playing yourself, or Alan Partridge, or Paul Calf, or Tommy Saxondale, it&amp;#39;s exactly this sort of alchemic mixture of sympathy and antipathy that makes your characters so likably unlikable, so hilarious, &lt;em&gt;so human&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt; achieves this balance, too. Hopefully, like all superior sequels, it will spawn a slightly disappointing concluding chapter. Might I suggest the wintry climes of central Ontario?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Walk Among the Tombstones</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a sequence halfway through &lt;em&gt;A Walk Among the Tombstones&lt;/em&gt; that is astonishingly well put together. It plays out like a typical meet-cute: a young girl walks into the path of two men, time slows down, their gazes lock, and cheery tunes plays on the soundtrack as man stare after her, slack-jawed. Except it&amp;#39;s anything but typical, since the girl in question is the daughter of a Russian drug dealer, and the two men she&amp;#39;s just entranced are a pair of demented serial killers who target the loved ones of organized crime figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your excellent cutting really generates tension and puts a sinister spin on a familiar trope—too bad everything around it feels so ordinary by comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be completely honest with you, I&amp;#39;m still not entirely sure how I feel about this one. On one hand, we have the great Liam Neeson turning in another fine performance as a private eye with a tortured past. It&amp;#39;s also refreshing to see Neeson play a character who is much more human and grounded in reality than some of his other recent roles (providing, of course, one can accept the reality of watching a man renowned for his badassery be on the receiving end of countless beatings). Additionally, the villains on display are certainly formidable, with the actors exuding menace through subtle gestures instead of dialogue. That, and the brief glimpses we see of the killers videotaping and tormenting their victims, are genuinely chilling—and very difficult to watch. It`s hard not to get excited by the prospect of Neeson taking these loathsome bastards down, and you edit the final physical confrontation together very nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what&amp;#39;s my beef? Well, let&amp;#39;s start with Neeson&amp;#39;s sassy, streetwise, teenage sidekick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. My. Goodness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I understand (and even appreciate) the desire to add some levity to such dark subject matter, but this just isn&amp;#39;t the right way to go about it. The humour works when Neeson tells a bad guy that he was able to trail him simply because of how much of a weirdo he is. But the pipsqueak aspiring detective mouthing off to waitresses and telling them not to offer him &amp;quot;sperm-killing sodas&amp;quot;: horrendous. I suspect that, if you thought you could have gotten away with it, you might have cut him from the film altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ends up really hurting is how by-the-numbers it all feels. We learn who the killers are and why they&amp;#39;re doing what they&amp;#39;re doing almost immediately, and the reveal that they&amp;#39;re rogue DEA agents doesn&amp;#39;t pay off with as much power as it could (and perhaps &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;). Neeson does lots of old-fashioned detective work in the pre-internet setting, but nothing he learns feels surprising in the least. After all, there&amp;#39;s nothing more enjoyable than watching someone slowly come to the same conclusions you&amp;#39;ve made about twenty minutes earlier. There are no real twists, and everything pretty much plays out exactly like you think it will. Which is kind of a drag.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;A Walk Among The Tombstones&lt;/em&gt; was the pilot episode of a new crime procedural, with you retaining editing duties week after week, I&amp;#39;d definitely be more enthusiastic. Instead it&amp;#39;s just a barely-serviceable crime thriller that I&amp;#39;ve already forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/30/a-walk-among-the-tombstones.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/30/a-walk-among-the-tombstones.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Equalizer</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of crazy ways to die. No less than a thousand &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spike.com/shows/1000-ways-to-die&quot;&gt;according to Spike TV,&lt;/a&gt; and up to a million &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/9/a-million-ways-to-die-in-the-west.html&quot;&gt;according to Seth MacFarlane&lt;/a&gt;. Many successful film franchises, like &lt;em&gt;Final Destination&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Saw&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt;, have made their reputations by finding creative ways to kill people off. That&amp;#39;s fine for a horror film – and even the occasional comedy – but in the case of &lt;em&gt;The Equalizer&lt;/em&gt;, the fact the filmmakers kept turning to an art department employee like you for their inspiration represents everything that&amp;#39;s wrong with the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was my fault to expect something of substance in the reunion of Denzel Washington and Antoine Fuqua, the director who coached him to an Academy Award in &lt;em&gt;Training Day&lt;/em&gt;. After all, neither of them have made much else besides this sort of action vehicle since then. But even with lowered expectations, &lt;em&gt;The Equalizer&lt;/em&gt; is constantly firing blanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things start slow. Painfully slow. Richard Wenk&amp;#39;s script doesn&amp;#39;t seem to know where to begin or where to end, and relies on the presence of Denzel Washington to maintain our emotional interest. His character, Robert McCall, is a big fat zero on the scale of human charisma and interest. He has no depth, no flaws, no enigmas. When he&amp;#39;s not readings book alone in a dinner, he&amp;#39;s stocking shelves at a generic &amp;quot;Home Mart&amp;quot; department store. Because he&amp;#39;s just your average tool man, like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except this joe-job and dull-drum existence is supposed to be making a point. After an inordinate amount of time, it&amp;#39;s revealed that (surprise!) McCall is just trying to live a normal life after a career doing covert U.S. government dirty work. He only fights crime after clocking out of his 9-5, which is when he becomes a monosyllabic unstoppable killing machine. What (with the exception, of course, of _The Terminator) _could be more boring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Killing – or more specifically, the &lt;em&gt;ways&lt;/em&gt; people are killed – shouldn&amp;#39;t be the only pulse in a serious action-drama-thriller. Seeing bad guys get their comeuppance is cathartic when, after the tension reaches a breaking point, violence explodes. But that&amp;#39;s not the case in &lt;em&gt;The Equalizer&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#39;s inspired by a TV show, not only in content but in form: the film is unevenly paced up and continues to deviate into side story adventures that offer little relevance to the A-plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that story involves a lot of your tools and the creative ways they kill people. Which is fine, until McCall literally starts stepping over machine guns in favour of hardware store props—you know, just to keep his life interesting. He calmly walks into countless confrontations with villains, always &amp;quot;giving them a chance&amp;quot; before dispatching them with ease. He&amp;#39;s never in any real danger, and lazy cross-cutting tries to trick the audience into believing the bad guys are always right on his tail. Instead, he&amp;#39;s always five steps ahead in ways the filmmakers don&amp;#39;t even try to explain. He has every tool he ever needs, be it electronic gizmos or hedge- (and head-) trimming shears.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/29/The-equalizer.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/29/The-equalizer.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
