<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Black Panther</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/black-panther.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Moviegoers, Change Agents, <br />
  				<p>A part of me wanted to give this movie five stars, just so I wouldn’t derail the <em>Black Panther</em> hype train that has been charging through the cultural consciousness for the last several months.</p>

<p>Unless you’ve been living under a rock, you’re probably at least a little aware that <em>Black Panther</em> has been the talk of North America (and maybe the world) since the beginning of 2017. It’s the story about T’Challa, the new kingd of the fictional African country of Wakanda, who is forced to take up the mantle of Black Panther and govern his nation after his father’s untimely death in the events of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/5/18/captain-america-civil-war.html">Captain America: Civil War</a>.</p>

<p>Oh yeah—this is a Marvel movie. And by those standards, a pretty average one. You’ll find all the familiar beats: the massive fight scene with laser beams, the one-liners, the last-minute heroic saves, and the tried and true story arc in which the hero rises, falls, and then rises again when he/she finally learns to accept the significance of the power they hold.</p>

<p>As a superhero fan, I was slightly disappointed by how common the framework of <em>Black Panther</em> was. Maybe I got swept up by the hype and forgot that <em>Black Panther</em> is, for all intents and purposes, and origin film, which tend to be pretty basic in their execution (you have to wait for the inevitable sequels to get a little more depth). Yes, the movie is beautiful and the themes of afro-futurism were alive and well, and it all made for a unique moviegoing experience. Still, I was expecting more.</p>

<p>But…</p>

<p>I decided to stop and think for a second; take a step back from my role as critic and shift my perspective. What are the undeniable truths about this film?</p>

<p><em>Black Panther</em> is the first superhero blockbuster film to feature a predominantly black cast and crew. It’s not the first black superhero (don’t worry, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120207/">Shaq</a>, I didn’t forget about you) but it <em>is</em> the first superhero film that ties its entire narrative to the realities of being black in the modern day.</p>

<p>It’s also the first Marvel film to be featured on a <a href="http://time.com/black-panther/">Time magazine cover</a>.</p>

<p>It’s also sitting at <a href="https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/black_panther_2018/">97% on Rotten Tomatoes</a>.</p>

<p>And the <a href="https://www.essence.com/entertainment/23000-kids-black-panther-blackpantherchallenge">#BlackPantherChallenge</a>, an initiative that give black children who cannot afford a movie ticket a chance to see <em>Black Panther</em> in theatres, has raised over $300,000 since its inception.</p>

<p>Needless to say, it’s a big deal. It’s a big deal because <em>Black Panther</em> is less of a movie than it is a statement—a giant vibranium claw across Hollywood’s outdated perception of what a blockbuster should entail and who should be leading it ( <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/amphtml/news/arts-and-entertainment/wp/2017/05/07/chris-pines-snl-monologue-reminds-us-how-bad-hollywoods-superhero-diversity-problem-is/&amp;freshcontent=1">Chris</a> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/amphtml/news/arts-and-entertainment/wp/2017/05/07/chris-pines-snl-monologue-reminds-us-how-bad-hollywoods-superhero-diversity-problem-is/&amp;freshcontent=1"><sup>4</sup></a>), to the media’s ongoing portrayal of people of colour as a lesser race consisting of thugs and criminals, to the systemic racism that has been woven into American society since the early days of colonialism. It’s fierce, empowering, and calculated. Black Panther didn’t drop out of the sky and fall into this position of magnitude: Ryan Coogler and company were hell bent on changing the status quo with every frame.</p>

<p>And that’s where the optimism begins to creep into my cynical heart. Movies like <em>Black Panther</em>, <em>Wonder Woman</em>, the new-gen <em>Star Wars</em> films feature visible minorities and have proven at every turn that diversity sells. As someone who was born in India and moved to North America at a very young age, I’ve faced my share of prejudice and seen how those from an Asian heritage are treated on and off-screen. Sprinkle a quip about how we smell here and there, add a pinch about how we’re undesirable and unattractive, and please, oh please, don’t forget the mimicry of our accents. That’s a real crowd pleaser.</p>

<p>It might seem weird to go off on a tangent about Asian discrimination when talking about a black superhero, but, for me, it’s all related. <em>Black Panther</em> has given me and many other minorities the opportunity to discuss racial perception, and as more and more high profile movies featuring minority ensembles grace the big screen, we’ll have more opportunities to educate, learn, and grow. <em>Black Panther</em> is a moment in history, and will have more impact outside of the theatertheatre than in.</p>

<p>So, objectively, even though I found <em>Black Panther</em> to be a pretty by-the-books Marvel movie in terms of execution and flow, I also found myself in a blissful position: that my opinion doesn’t matter. Because <em>Black Panther</em> is bigger than you or me; it’s a step forward into a much-needed diverse future.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/2/17/black-panther.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/2/17/black-panther.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Raw is Unhinged and the Best Film of 2017</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/raw-is-unhinged-and-the-best-film-of-2017.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Fellow Critics, <br />
  				<p>I want to tell you why I picked <em>Raw</em> as the best movie of 2017…</p>

<p>...but I can’t.</p>

<p>I’ve written four different drafts of this piece, each with different explanations and angles. They’re all valid, but they’re not the <em>true</em> reason I love <em>Raw</em> so much. The true reason is rooted in something beyond mere personal taste, something hidden, something secret.</p>

<p>Even admitting that it’s a secret has me worried. Are people going to think I’m a cannibal? Are they going to think I have a penchant for murder? If it helps my case, those aren’t the reasons—my favourite meat is chicken, and while some people really piss me off, murder has never crossed my mind. Don’t worry, you can still hang out with me.</p>

<p>All I can say – all I feel comfortable saying – is that in my battles with stress, depression, and anxiety, I suffered some side-effects, and they freaked me out. And when I watched <em>Raw</em>, I was able to relate to it in a way that was almost reassuring to me. Funny right? A movie about cannibalism that reassured me during a battle with my own inner darkness? Ankit, are you <em>sure</em> you’re not a cannibal?</p>

<p>Yes! I’m sure. If you’ve seen <em>Raw</em> (and I highly recommend that you do), it instantly becomes clear that this movie is an allegory for discovering who you are, flaws and all. Nobody is perfect, and if you’re struggling with something, anything, you have to seek out people who can help you survive and find solutions. It’s only when you try to ignore it that things go awry.</p>

<p>It took an extreme concept like <em>Raw</em> – and its beautiful handling by director Julia Ducournau and star Garance Marillier – to make me understand that.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 03:25:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/25/raw-is-unhinged-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/25/raw-is-unhinged-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Your Name is Unexpected and the Best Film of 2017</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/your-name-is-unexpected-and-the-best-film-of-2017.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Fellow Critics, <br />
  				<p>Pardon the long preamble, but I think you’ll agree that choosing a “best film of the year” in 2017 is rather…complicated. It’s more than just our typical annual contribution to the time capsule of critical consensus. It feels like a mission statement.</p>

<p>Why? Because this was a year in which an entire decade’s worth of social and political (and, for some, personal) upheaval was joylessly crammed into twelve hyperkinetic and hellish months. And to choose a film as the best example of what the art of cinema can accomplish during a year like that is to place yourself at specific coordinates relative to that upheaval. Some chose the film that <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/16/it-comes-at-night-is-unsettling-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html">helped them survive</a>. Some chose the film that they felt was most <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/15/get-out-is-unreal-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html">culturally on-point</a>. Some chose the film that was <a href="http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/movies/sc-mov-lady-bird-review-1106-story.html">a tonic in the Harvey Weinstein era</a>.</p>

<p>So, where do I stand? What was my relationship with (and reaction to) the events of 2017, and how was it processed in the movie-watching part of my brain?</p>

<p>I was exhausted by it all, frankly. I was exhausted by the <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/20/split.html">awkward</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/6/12/the-mummy.html">attempts</a> of big studios to build half-assed cinematic universes. I was exhausted by the <a href="https://www.vox.com/culture/2017/12/18/16791844/star-wars-last-jedi-backlash-controversy">misplaced sense of childish entitlement</a> fans demonstrated towards their favourite franchises.</p>

<p>I was exhausted, too, by male protagonists. A movie like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/10/17/blade-runner-2049.html"><em>Blade Runner 2049</em></a> should have electrified me, what with its thumping synth score and introspective Baby Goose (aka. the best kind of Baby Goose). But I found myself far more interested in the hero’s ethereal AI girlfriend, and the mysterious memory-building bubble-girl than I was in the two macho leads (which means, sadly, that Denis Villeneuve’s <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/1/12/sicario-is-definitely-the-best-film-of-2015.html">hot</a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/17/arrival-is-the-best-and-profoundest-film-of-2016.html">streak</a> comes to an end this year). And while there were films featuring female leads that I really enjoyed – <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/15/mollys-game.html"><em>Molly’s Game</em></a> and <em>I, Tonya</em> in particular, I am remiss to note that my enjoyment of them is tempered by the fact that both movies were written and directed by men; their protagonists, despite being strong-willed and multidimensional, still danced to a beat played by men, and whatever agency they may have had in real life (both films are based on true stories) feels diminished by it.</p>

<p>I saw <em>Wonder Woman</em> three times in the theater, and each time enjoyed it more than the last. What seemed, at first, to be a sort of milquetoast superhero flick that <em>just happened</em> to feature a woman in the lead proved itself, upon multiple viewings, to be more important. But it would seem disingenuous for me to choose it as the best film simply because I have observed (and appreciated) the effect it has had on others.</p>

<p>To that end, there was a surprising diversity and verisimilitude to the superhero movies that came out this year. From <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/3/3/logan.html"><em>Logan</em></a> to <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/11/13/thor-ragnarok.html"><em>Thor: Ragnarok</em></a>, filmmakers seemed to figure out that the genre is much broader than many think; there’s room, within all the punching and world-saving, for improv comedy and gritty melodrama. This essay was very, very close to being all about <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/7/10/spider-man-homecoming.html"><em>Spider Man: Homecoming</em></a>. It was the one movie this year that I immediately wanted to see again because it couldn’t <em>possibly</em> have been as good as it was. It captured something pure and jubilant that big movies in the last decade seem to have forgotten. It was an adventure. It was grounded. It was funny. It had <em>stakes</em>. No other blockbuster action movie, with their myriad world-ending threats, could match the tension of an anxious teenage boy riding to prom in the back of his girlfriend’s dad’s car.</p>

<p>But I’m not writing about Spider-Man, am I? I’m writing, instead, about a teenage-romance anime that was, technically, released in 2016. In a year full of surprises, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/7/18/your-name.html"><em>Your Name</em></a> <em>(Kimi no Na wa)</em> was the movie that surprised me the most.</p>

<p>I can’t even recall where I first heard of it. Maybe on an episode of <a href="https://www.filmspotting.net/"><em>Filmspotting</em></a>? Maybe from my anime-addicted younger sister? And I can’t recall why, way back in July, I sought it out.</p>

<p>It was a rare Saturday night alone at home, the little one was in bed, and I had two free hours ahead of me. Instead of doing what I usually do, which is to find the most brainless flick available and feed my lizard brain a little cinematic junk food, I decided to do something else: watch that obscure* anime flick I’d heard about.</p>

<p>[*Obscure to me; it had already broken numerous box office records across East Asia.]</p>

<p>I was rewarded for my effort. <em>Your Name</em> was the only film I saw this year that felt like it came from some other place. And I don’t just mean another country or another culture. I mean another planet, another century, another dimension. It felt completely alien to me, and yet eerily familiar; utterly original, yet deeply rooted in the classic language of cinema. For days afterwards, the world appeared to me in colourful flat planes. I ran Airbnb searches for the rural countryside of Japan, just for fun. I winced through jaunty, roaring, assaultive J-Pop tunes. All of it, I suppose, an attempt to recreate the altered state I found myself in while watching the film. It is a strange experience, to be outside yourself and completely present at the same time; this movie worked that kind of magic on me. Which is fitting since this inside/outside sensation is the dilemma that sets the whole plot forward; the movie’s two heroes, Mitsuha and Taki, a country girl and city boy, find themselves randomly swapping bodies.</p>

<p>I can foresee this film becoming a comfort movie for me. You know, those films with which you share some inexplicable emotional connection – either because of the content, or the context in which you saw it, or, most likely, some combination of both – which you turn to when you’re feeling particularly low and need to be buoyed. They aren’t comfort movies because they’re great pieces of art (though many of them are), but because of how great they make you feel. <em>Your Name</em> made me feel great. It’s a film about great promise, and how that promise can be squandered. The third act involves a major natural disaster which should be depressing but it’s not. The world is redeemed, not by grand gestures, but by small acts of kindness and generosity and sacrifice. And what better truth to abide by in a year that revealed the fragility of the peace between us?</p>

<p>In its final moments, <em>Your Name</em> refuses to give us the satisfaction of a happy ending. But it does offer us hope for one. Maybe the coming year will do the same.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 07:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/22/your-name-is-unexpected-the-best-film-of-2017.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/22/your-name-is-unexpected-the-best-film-of-2017.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: The Shape of Water is Unparalleled and the Best Film of 2017</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/the-shape-of-water-is-unparalleled-and-the-best-film-of-2017.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Fellow Critics, <br />
  				<p>My pick for top film of the year usually says something about the kind of year I’ve had, or how I responded to its highs and lows. However, if I stuck to choosing favourites that way, every year I’d just be lauding movies where women sensationally and violently lose patience with the men around them. This year I thought I’d switch things up with a sappy, soggy tale of romance, and a love letter to misfits and outcasts everywhere.</p>

<p>Guillermo del Toro’s visually stunning <em>Beauty and the Beast</em>-meets-<em>Amelie</em> tale was panned by a few of you, and sure, in a way it’s uncomplicated and uncontroversial in its messaging… except it isn’t. Your tastes might lean more towards complex stories with multifaceted, conflicted characters, and on the surface, you could read <em>The Shape of Water</em> as cute but superficial, but you’d be wrong. As adorable and quirky as it is, del Toro brings a deep sadness to his story that you might not fully appreciate right away.</p>

<p>Rather than a fairy tale reimagined, I thought the film took the conventions of the fairy tale and scraped away at the wallpaper, so to speak. I enjoyed the lighter moments like the musical number and the mischievous eroticism that winks its way through much of the plot, all eggs and gushing water, but the ending was tough. I walked away with a deep sense of melancholy, and it took me a while to figure out why.</p>

<p><strong>SPOILER ALERT</strong> (Seriously, I’m fixing to talk about the ending…)</p>

<p>We get the requisite fairy tale ’happily ever after’, but I had a hard time seeing it as an actual happy ending. In stories where one Other falls in love with another Other, we don’t really think past the couple getting together, and I always feel like we miss one glaring point; In choosing a life together, one of the two must sacrifice life as they know it and leave their world behind.</p>

<p>I’ve seen <em>The Shape of Water</em> most commonly compared to <em>Beauty and the Beast</em>, but there’s definitely a touch of <em>The Little Mermaid</em> in the ending. I never understood how Ariel sacrificing hanging out under the sea (because Darling, it’s better/down where it’s wetter, etc.) to marry some good-looking dullard was a win for her. And while Ariel and Belle both had a chance to spend time in their new worlds and establish that they ’fit in’ before they get to ’happily ever after’, I had no such reassurance as to Elisa’s fate. Obviously, she and her six-packed water bae can’t remain here in our world because we are not kind to Others, especially when they hook up with other Others (stay with me), but how do we know she’ll fit into his world any better than he fit into ours? Elsa’s loneliness is so beautifully wrought throughout the film that I questioned whether the ending gives us enough of a guarantee that she will never be lonely again (which I took to be the story’s focus).</p>

<p><em>The Shape of Water</em> is my favourite film of 2017 for the bittersweet complexity of that ending. It is, in other ways, a simple story beautifully told. Maybe I’m over-thinking it, or maybe it was just refreshing to watch love blossom without misogyny being clumsily couched as romance (and if Hollywood were to replace roughly 43 percent of its leading men with non-verbal amphibious creatures I would be totally cool with that), but I feel like any film that left me that conflicted and still completely enamoured with it deserves emphatic props all around.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 06:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/19/the-shape-of-water-is-unparalleled-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/19/the-shape-of-water-is-unparalleled-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Call Me By Your Name is Unapologetic and the Best Film of 2017</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/call-me-by-your-name-is-unapologetically-the-best-film-of-2017.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Fellow Critics, <br />
  				<p>2017, for me, was a bullshit year. I lived for ten months in a gutted house undergoing renos. I lost one of my best friends very suddenly. I took in an ill family member, spent an exorbitant amount of money and sleepless nights on a beloved dog with an unknown illness, all while personally enduring medically induced menopause and its inherent delights (weight gain, hot flashes, mood swings).</p>

<p>And that’s just the bullshit I’m willing to share. Honestly, there were days when I felt like I was <em>in</em> a movie (the kind I’d pan for being too contrived).</p>

<p>For the first time in many years movies weren’t just my job, they were a refuge. Films like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/9/6/good-time.html"><em>Good Time</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/7/21/dunkirk.html"><em>Dunkirk</em></a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/7/21/dunkirk.html">,</a><em>Get Out</em>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/12/18/lady-bird.html"><em>Lady Bird</em></a>, <em>I, Tonya</em>, <em>The Darkest Hour</em>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/11/21/ingrid-goes-west.html"><em>Ingrid Goes West</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/4/27/the-lost-city-of-z.html"><em>The Lost City of Z</em></a> – and so many more – reminded me why I love watching movies. In a year when I struggled to keep my emotions in check, movies allowed me to experience them in the most unapologetically selfish way. 2017 was the year I realized just how much I <em>need</em> movies. And no movie exemplified this more than <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/8/call-me-by-your-name.html"><em>Call Me By Your Name.</em></a></p>

<p><em>Call Me By Your Name</em> is a coming-of-age, coming-out, first-love story. There’s no elaborate camera work (the entire film was shot using a single lens), no special effects, no larger social allegory to lend it gravitas. The characters are privileged, good-looking, and white. The drama isn’t necessarily grand (in the cinematic sense). This is a simple story to tell, and yet it would have been very easy to get it wrong. This film asks next to nothing of us – there are no leaps of logic or faith, no suspension of disbelief required – but it gives so much in return.</p>

<p><em>Call Me By Your Name</em>, more than anything else, gives us permission to feel.</p>

<p>It should be easy to fall in love with a film about falling in love, especially when the two lovers are Timothee Chalamet and Armie Hammer, and especially when the falling happens in a rustic villa in the Italian countryside. Yet <em>Call Me By Your Name</em> challenges the viewer in ways I wasn’t expecting. This film doesn’t wash over you. Rather it expects you to engage with the characters, and the insecurities that belie their seemingly effortless lives. It requires you to be patient while relationships develop, and trust that the payoff will be gratifying.</p>

<p>Director Luca Guadagnino singles out the elements of longing – lust, excitement, fear, awkwardness – and distills them into a palpable, physical ache; that <em>wanting</em> we feel for another human being. He takes what is indescribable about love and attraction and defines it: specifically for these characters, and universally for the audience.  All of us, at least those most fortunate among us, have felt this kind of desire. Yet none of us have felt it quite like Elio and Oliver. The individual moments – dancing to Psychedelic Furs, swimming at dawn, playfully touching feet – belong entirely to them. But Guadagnino makes their desire so corporeal, so visceral, that it somehow feels like it’s happening to us. It is nothing short of cinematic sorcery.</p>

<p>I saw this film twice, wondering if upon second viewing that the magic spell would hold. It does.</p>

<p>The first viewing I focused on Elio, the 17 year-old protagonist who is brilliant and precocious and naïve and serious sometimes all in the same scene. Chalamet’s performance is as brave as it is unselfconscious, floating between childhood and adulthood, too smart not to be deeply aware of his predicament. When Oliver arrives to spend a summer working alongside Elio’s father, he is an American Adonis, oozing charm and confidence. It’s almost impossible for Elio not to fall for him. He is everything Elio is not.</p>

<p>Upon second viewing, I paid more attention to Oliver. “The interloper,” as Elio calls him. Oliver is the affable and erudite American, a role that doesn’t seem like much of a stretch for Hammer—until fragments of his vulnerability are revealed. Elio is the product of a cool, Euro-centric upbringing, he is beloved by his intellectual parents, he is a gifted musician, and exudes a quiet self-assuredness beyond his years. Oliver masks his attraction to Elio with bravado and faux-indifference. The second time around I noticed how layered Hammer’s performance was, and how neither man feels worthy of the other. Only in Oliver’s case is this most likely true.</p>

<p>Guadagnino crafts a thoroughly modern film that manages to seem trapped in amber. Against a backdrop that is lush, sumptuous, and fecund, interiors that feel like masters paintings, with a soundtrack that features songs by Kenny Rogers and Sufjan Stevens, a cast so natural I can’t help but imagine them still living in that Italian village, <em>Call Me By Your Name</em> is as real as anything I’ve experienced. This film doesn’t allow you to be passive. It practically demands an emotional response. And it does so subtly, without manipulation or coercion, and in such a way that you quite simply don’t know what hit you. Much like falling in love.</p>

<p>And then it breaks your heart.</p>

<p>Following Oliver’s return to America, Elio’s father, sensing his son’s loss, delivers one of the most eloquent and affecting monologues I think I’ve ever heard on film. I prefer its potency to remain intact for those who still haven’t seen the film, but will share this one beautiful line, delivered with sweetness and not a hint of condescension by the brilliant Michael Stuhlbarg;</p>

<p><em>“We rip out so much of ourselves to be cured of things faster than we should that we go bankrupt by the age of thirty and have less to offer each time we start with someone new. But to feel nothing so as not to feel anything—what a waste!”</em></p>

<p>Beyond my personal travails, 2017 was surreal, fraught with daily reminders that the free world is being run by a literal madman, and that the “normal” I took for granted was gone (or perhaps never existed). There was barely time to register outrage before a newer, more cruel absurdity replaced the last. So much happened that I think, for many of us, adopting a neutral emotional disposition was a coping mechanism, a defense against utter despair. So I actively suppressed my emotions because I truly feared that indulging them might end me.</p>

<p>I cried for the last ten minutes of <em>Call Me By Your Name</em>. Then I cried even harder during the credits, (which will make sense if you’ve seen the film). I cried my way out of the theatre, to my car, and during my whole drive home. Then I got home and cried for another 40 minutes. I cried for Elio and Oliver, and for my own unrequited loves, and for love itself.  I cried because I feared I was one of those who Elio’s father claimed went bankrupt by thirty. And then I cried for all the times I wanted to cry but didn’t.</p>

<p>Would <em>Call Me By Your Name</em> be my favourite film of 2017 if it didn’t make me cry? I don’t know. But it is my favourite film because it did.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 06:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/18/call-me-by-your-name-is-unapologetically-the-best-film-of-2017.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/18/call-me-by-your-name-is-unapologetically-the-best-film-of-2017.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: It Comes at Night is Unsettling and the Best Film of 2017</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/it-comes-at-night-is-unsettling-and-the-best-film-of-2017.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Fellow Critics, <br />
  				<p>When people talk about “best films”, the number of people having the conversation is usually equal to the number of different criteria involved. More and more I find that when a film connects with me on a personal level, reaching inside and pulling out something I wasn’t even aware was there, it jumps to the top of my list.</p>

<p>That doesn’t mean it has to be about anything in particular, or be made by someone with whom I have a shared cultural or social history. What it does mean is that the people responsible for it have managed to express something profound and new in a way that is accessible. But that’s the case with any interaction with a piece of art—it’s substance, or lack of it, is always contained in that intimate back-and-forth. To be able to do that requires technical skill, great writing, superb performances and adept storytelling. Not an easy or simple task. But the thing that really makes the difference is the intention to connect, and the ambition to do so in a significant way. All the other elements are simply tools the film makers use to achieve that end.</p>

<p>Some of the films that I’ve found most affecting in the last few years—films like <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html"><em>Spotlight</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/2/20/timbuktu.html"><em>Timbuktu</em></a>, <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html"><em>Moonlight</em></a>, and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/2/28/i-am-not-your-negro.html"><em>I Am Not Your Negro</em></a>—are about people and circumstances of which I have had very little personal experience. Yet they bridge that gulf in a way that allows me inside their world, and in turn that expands my own.</p>

<p><em>It Comes At Night</em> was different in a fundamental way. It spoke directly to me on a personal level about things I’ve actually experienced. Usually films like that don’t mean as much to me because they seem kind of vapid and pointless. This isn’t necessarily because there is anything wrong with them per se, instead it’s because there are very few people who have spent the time and energy I have examining, re-examining, and then making schematics about the moment to moment turns of my life. What the film maker has to say is usually something I’ve already puzzled out for myself, or even worse, is less interesting than whatever shibboleths I’ve already constructed in my own head.</p>

<p>Not something I’m proud of but still the truth.</p>

<p>When I write that <em>It Comes At Night</em> is about things I’ve experienced on a personal level, I don’t mean the aftermath of a viral apocalypse or how easy it becomes to discard what once seemed like unbreakable taboos. What I’m talking about is seeing both my parents die within about two years of one another and how even a 50-ish adult can be completely unmoored by sudden oprhanhood.</p>

<p><em>It Comes At Night</em>, while masquerading as a post-apocalyptic rumination on how easily the veneer of civilization falls away, is really a film about the utter dislocation the loss of a parent can evoke. And don’t just take my word for it. As director Trey Edwards Shults has explicitly stated, in numerous interviews, this film was a response to watching his father die of pancreatic cancer. I didn’t know this going in, and while I’m better for having experienced this film, I’m not sure I would have been quite so eager had I understood exactly what I was signing up for.</p>

<p>The text of this film is fascinating enough, and can easily hold your attention with its quiet, but completely relentless build towards an ending that is paradoxically shocking, and yet completely inevitable. Even the inversion of the natural order hinted at with a death at the very beginning of the film and the death(s) than end it, make sense in the meticulously crafted narrative Shults has created. Two families, families who could be described as decent well-meaning people, are tested in the harshest of crucibles, and are found badly wanting. This is an honest and often bleak film, but is worth the effort. If that was all there was to say about <em>It Comes At Night</em> it would be in the running for me.</p>

<p>But that isn’t all.</p>

<p>Watching  the plug being pulled on my father after four years of pain and misery, seeing a face I no longer recognized relax and go slack, was day one of the end of the world as I knew it. Every fiction I had thoughtlessly entertained about how the world worked, the rules that governed it, and my place in it crumbled to pieces in that moment. An apocalypse on a very small scale.</p>

<p>Like Shults, my relationship with my father was difficult and often distant. But what he represented for me (and my mother as well, although in a different register), was a world that had concrete rules and barriers. A world that had its own internal logic. A world that, while often disinterested, was generally benign. And as <em>It Comes At Night</em> progresses, the symmetry between the utter disruption the loss of that world and its comforts and what was happening up on screen was unsettling.</p>

<p>The sub text of <em>It Comes At Night</em> literally screamed at me throughout. Not due to any lack of subtlety, but because it was so finely tuned to my own experience. It felt like my subconscious was being projected onto the screen, which I assure you is not something I would wish on my worst enemy: the blind panic of adults faced with circumstances far beyond their control or competency; the fragility of good will; the turning on one another as everything they depend on is revealed as nothing but smoke and good intentions. Finally, the sad truth that your parents always fail you in the end, because they leave you alone in the world. All of these moments exist in the film, and were also direct parallels to my recent past.</p>

<p>The best metaphors are ones that take something almost unbearably complex and translate them in a way that helps achieve clarity without over simplifying. Shults uses the upside down world his characters inhabit to express how all the mythic overlays we ascribe to our parents collapse in a heap when we are faced with their mortality. This can ultimately be a good thing, because hopefully by the time your parents pass you have managed to unravel—or at least begin to see—all the fictions we are fed to avoid premature existential crises.</p>

<p>Still, I’m not sure anyone is ever prepared for that moment. And if you go by the narrative of the film, for many it may be too much, at least initially.</p>

<p>There is an arresting visual metaphor near the beginning of the film: a panicked man runs through a night time forest, searching for an unnamed threat with only the narrow beam of a flashlight as his guide. All of a sudden a familiar world is cast in shadows, filled with threats unseen and previously unimagined, all caused by the extinguishing of the sun. A daily occurrence that is both natural and predictable, yet still can elicit terror, given the right circumstances, in any of us.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 11:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/16/it-comes-at-night-is-unsettling-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/16/it-comes-at-night-is-unsettling-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title> Feature: Get Out is Unreal and the Best Film of 2017</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/get-out-is-unreal-and-the-best-film-of-2017.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Fellow Critics, <br />
  				<p>It’s tough when the best film of the year comes out in February. Even worse when you don’t yet know it will be the best film. I’ve seen films as early as <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/1/11/inside-out-is-easily-the-best-film-of-2015.html">June</a> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/1/16/swiss-army-man-is-the-best-and-ballsiest-film-of-2016.html">July</a> that have pretty quickly declared themselves #1 in my heart, but traditionally we look forward to the festival circuit in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/5/yes-nightcrawler-is-the-best-film-of-2014.html">September</a>, or maybe an end of the year surprise, to really give us something special. So I had no intention of calling <em>Get Out</em> the best film of the year until it simply became inevitable.</p>

<p>I surprised myself with my <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/12/30/2017-c-redmonds-top-films-of-2017.html">year-end Top 10</a>. I kept slotting other films at the top just to try it out, but nothing felt right and I couldn’t figure out why. White guilt? Why else did we not even review <em>Get Out</em> on the site in 2017? Personally, I may have felt somehow unqualified to tackle this racially-charged <a href="http://www.indiewire.com/2017/04/get-out-breaks-record-jordan-peele-debut-screenplay-highest-grossing-1201799905/">milestone</a> movie - like it wasn’t <em>my</em> movie to claim. After all, isn’t appropriation what the whole film’s about?</p>

<p>But ultimately, I had to be honest with myself. There’s not a movie that I thought about more, talked about more, or that inspired me more (in terms of what films I want to support - and make). <em>Get Out</em> kicked every other film’s ass this year by being unapologetic with its politics, audacious with genre, and culturally on point.</p>

<p>Oh, not to mention it’s just fun as hell.</p>

<p>Even more so on a second viewing (for me, anyway). I had avoided all the film’s trailers, and I still went in expecting that whatever horror elements emerged would be… grounded. Instead, they were sunken. And while the visual treatment of this headspace was beautifully rendered, the decision to go there took me out of the film altogether. As someone who has undergone hypnosis publicly and privately multiples times, I have a very good understanding of how it works. You can’t just “get” hypnotized, you have to embrace it, accept it, and most of all, <em>trust</em> it. Clearly, none of these circumstances existed when Daniel Kaluuya’s character gets “tricknotized” (patent pending). Suddenly, I was out, because in movies and hypnosis, all it takes in one small thing to break the “spell” you’re under.</p>

<p>After all, films are a form of hypnosis. That’s really what we’re doing when we suspend our disbelief. We are trusting the filmmaker’s voices, surrendering ourselves to their power, and saying “I <em>allow</em> this to be true.” That’s how movies move us.</p>

<p>My personal hang-up initially robbed me of appreciating the film at a deeper level, even if all the technical merits were still in full evidence: The razor-sharp script that’s allergic to lulls. The perfect choice of actors and their perfect choices in every scene. The unforgettable close-ups and imagery throughout that are loaded with emotional complexity. All the pieces were right, and I thoroughly enjoyed the movie, I just thought some of it &quot;didn’t work&quot; (a favourite critic catch-all  phrase to shield our personal biases). Then, because of that early release date, the film got the most powerful ally possible: time.</p>

<p>Now I had  time to let go of the film. To find it again. To read some insight from writer/director Jordan Peele, and most importantly, to stop judging the film for what it isn’t (ie. realistic) and start judging the film for what it is (ie: truthful). I let the metaphor be the metaphor and guess what?</p>

<p>Boom. I was hypnotized. In the sunken place. And loving every minute of it.</p>

<p>Modern day slave trade? Yup, I buy it. Brain transplants? Sure! Peele never had to ask for these creative allowances, I somehow just wasn’t ready to grant them initially. That was on me. He was making a popcorn movie, not a documentary (despite what he’s jokes about on Twitter.) It just happens to have incredibly thoughtful touches throughout (picking cotton to <em>save</em> himself, among my favourite) to elevate it beyond what we normally associate with a popcorn movie.</p>

<p>In fact, it had all the elements to elevate it beyond <em>every</em> movie in 2017.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 10:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/15/get-out-is-unreal-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/15/get-out-is-unreal-and-the-best-film-of-2017.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Molly&#39;s Game</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/mollys-game.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Josh Leichner, Technical Advisor, <br />
  				<p>Private, invitation-only, high-stakes poker games are being played every night in cities all over the world. It’s a world of poker that only a select few are familiar with, and a level of play that often involves unsavoury elements: drugs, mobsters, illegal activity, etc. Elements that demand discretion. Maybe that’s why, when I googled “<em>who were the poker advisors on Molly’s Game</em>”, I didn’t see any famous poker players from TV.  Instead, I found you.</p>

<p><em>Molly’s Game</em>, Aaron Sorkin’s directorial debut, tells the true story of the one-time Olympic hopeful turned &quot;Poker Princess&quot; Molly Bloom. Like Molly, you ran illegal games, and like Molly <a href="https://www.thestar.com/news/crime/2008/10/17/police_raid_unbelievably_lucrative_gaming_houses.html">, you got caught</a>. Then you went legit, and now you and your partner (Albert Choi, another of the film’s advisors) run All In Entertainment, which focuses on charity fundraising. You have successfully stayed under the radar, eschewing fame for stability. Molly didn’t have that option. In order to dig herself out of her oblique involvement with Russian mobsters and a Ponzi scheme which led to racketeering charges, she wrote the best-selling not-so-tell-all book upon which this film is based.</p>

<p>I have absolutely no affinity for gambling in the abstract or poker in particular. But I was immediately caught up in the game as it comes to life in this film. Sorkin’s trademark rapid-fire writing style is a solid match for this modern rags-to-riches-to-rags story, in particular because he lets Jessica Chastain hold all the cards. This is her movie, and she elevates it from pretty good to great. Sorkin sets up the story at a break-neck (or break-spine, as it were) pace, and Chastain’s transformation from naïve gambling neophyte to master of her game is a thrill to watch. Sorkin gives Chastain some cracking narration to deliver but most of it is expository when it should have been personally revealing. He saves Molly’s inner struggles for flashbacks, and in doing so, tips his hand. A classic rookie mistake.</p>

<p>The standard Sorkin dialogue crackles between Chastain and the eminently watchable Idris Elba as her lawyer, Charlie Jaffey. Sorkin is a master of caustic, witty back-and-forths, and Chastain and Elba spar beautifully over Molly’s legal predicament. It’s when Molly notices how Charlie’s overbearing treatment of his young daughter mirrors her own troubled relationship with her father that this film loses its credibility. Distilling what should have been a complex character study of a woman competing and excelling in man’s world down to her &quot;daddy issues&quot; isn’t just obvious and hackneyed, it’s also reductive as fuck.</p>

<p>Instead it places Molly’s successes and failures – on the slopes and at the poker table – on the shoulders of her father, a man she constantly tried to please, yet felt she could never truly make proud. When daughter and father finally have their moment of redemption it is so contrived it felt like it was ripped from a discarded <em>Highway to Heaven</em> script, and not from someone who has been hailed as one of Hollywood’s best screenwriters.</p>

<p>Thankfully, Sorkin surrounded himself with the right people like Chastain, and you, a poker expert who helped him make the gambling scenes the most exciting part of the film, even for non-gamblers. These scenes are reminiscent of the best parts of Sorkin’s writing—rhythmic, clever, and bursting with information and character development without feeling pedantic. But when compared to most of the rest of the film, these scenes feel like they were from a completely different movie.</p>

<p>This is Sorkin’s first time directing, and it’s <em>also</em> his first time writing a female lead. Anyone who has been paying attention would know that Sorkin has, um, <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/you-dont-need-to-read-aaron-sorkins-leaked-emails-to-realise-hes-a-sexist-just-watch-the-west-wing-9934107.html"><em>problems</em></a> <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/you-dont-need-to-read-aaron-sorkins-leaked-emails-to-realise-hes-a-sexist-just-watch-the-west-wing-9934107.html">with his female characters</a>. And anyone who was hoping he would quiet his critics with <em>Molly’s Game</em> will be disappointed. He was dealt an excellent hand – compelling source material, a brilliant lead, and sizeable budget to bring his script to life – but in the end, he just didn’t know what to do with his queen.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/15/mollys-game.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/15/mollys-game.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Downsizing</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/downsizing.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Ann-Marie Ferney-Tellez, Props Buyer, <br />
  				<p>I will not be giving you props for your work on this movie. I understand the buck doesn’t stop with you (in fact, as a buyer, it <em>starts</em> with you), but someone in the art department really should have cared more about how a downsized world should look. Far too many times sloppy decisions were allowed through the cracks. Writer/Director Alexander Payne is nothing if not an expert in tone and handling multiple complex human emotions, but when it comes to production design… well let’s just say, I’ve never longed for a movie to be directed by Tim Burton in my life. Until now.</p>

<p>The first hour of <em>Downsizing</em> didn’t make me feel this way. Payne takes a big swing at a high concept in this film, where certain environmentally (and fiscally) conscious members of society decide to scale down, swapping feet for inches. And as we see the first 5-6 inch people walk around and extol the virtues of life on the small side, the film seems to be building strong and layered metaphors. I was excited to imagine all the possibilities and complications of what it would be mean to literally shrink our footprint on the earth - especially to transition into this approach. And the story does touch on some of these issues with intriguing details. But that’s conceptually. When Matt Damon’s character finally decides to undergo the procedure and wakes up in the operating room, it didn’t take long for the spell to be broken. </p>

<p>It was the knobs. The knobs knocked me out of it.</p>

<p>Out of all the aesthetic decisions that could have been used in a medical facility, for some reason your team decided to put wood knobs on the bed posts. So what, right? Well the wood grain, for starters. No consideration seemed to have been paid to how wood grain would look from that perspective (ie, much thicker lines). And then I noticed wood all around the room. Same thing. The film makes explicit that the science doesn’t shrink objects (hence why they need to remove fillings from people’s mouths before undergoing the procedure), but no one in the art department seems to have taken the cue. Don’t even get me started on the rain, which from that perspective (and the rate it falls at one point) should have been enough to almost knock people off balance. Instead it was just, you know, <em>rain</em>. Volume and distance between drops, no different than another other falling water. <em>Honey, I Shrunk the Kids</em> did a better job than this. </p>

<p>I would have been happy to overlook, or at least forgive, these types of details if the film had lived up to its own promise. But by the time the story hits the midpoint and decides to take a left turn into some heavy-handed moralizing about the disenfranchised, the film had lost track of a lot more than just the props department. Suddenly the least interesting threads were being followed, and much like the characters themselves, the larger world was allowed to slip away. It feels like a really long way to go just to parallel how much the world is still like ours.</p>

<p>Maybe you bought it, but I didn’t.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 05:35:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/9/downsizing.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/9/downsizing.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Review: Call Me By Your Name</title>
				<description>
  				<![CDATA[
  				<img src="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/assets/img/posts/thumb-600/call-me-by-your-name.jpg" />
  				<p>Dear Valerio Rapisarda, Runner, <br />
  				<p>Everyone remembers their first time—though not all of us were lucky enough to have the Italian countryside as the backdrop. I could be talking about a first love, or a first consensual sexual encounter, both of which serve as an unofficial marker of our leap from childhood to adulthood. In your case, I’m talking about your first movie job. And, like most firsts, it’s a little confusing.</p>

<p>You’re credited as being a “runner” on <em>Call Me By Your Name</em>, and as an office PA on <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/3/all-the-money-in-the-world.html"><em>All the Money in the</em></a> <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/3/all-the-money-in-the-world.html"><em>World</em></a>, which were filmed concurrently in Italy. Both must have been memorable for their own reasons ( <a href="http://www.news.com.au/entertainment/movies/new-movies/how-ridley-scott-erased-kevin-spacey-in-all-the-money-in-the-world/news-story/c5e7e342056d586b153cdd5e4add71ea">one maybe more so than the other</a>). Like Elio, the young protagonist of <em>Call Me By</em><em>Your Name</em>, you had two firsts, but only one of them really counted. Perhaps it’s too soon for you to decide.  We often don’t appreciate the most meaningful events of our lives until after they happen.</p>

<p><em>Call Me By Your Name</em> is the kind of film that doesn’t feel special right away. It meanders, it hints at self-indulgence, and dares us to be as bored as Elio, the 17 year-old son of an archaeology prof, who, over the course of a lazy Italian summer, falls for Oliver, his father’s 24 year-old American grad student. Their friendship evolves slowly and awkwardly. Both pursue side relationships with local girls, dalliances which prolong the inevitable: an affair which feels perfectly organic, not <em>despite</em> the lengthy and frustrating build-up, but <em>because</em> of it. Elio and Oliver spend their remaining time together in giddy infatuation, well aware that their relationship has a fast-approaching expiry date. By the time the film reaches its foregone conclusion, the short arc of Elio and Oliver’s brief relationship feels like it has spanned a lifetime.</p>

<p>As you ran the grounds of the villa, fetching espresso and tidying the sets, did you recognize that you were a part of something special? Did you realize that this simple coming of age story about a gifted Jewish teen who transcribes Bach and lives with his liberal, academic parents in early -80s Italy where he falls in love with an older man would be so universally adored? I personally wasn’t sure what all of the fuss was about, cynical as I am about anything that is universally adored. I saw lush cinematography that took advantage of the fertile, Lombardian surroundings. I befriended the comely leads, Timothee Chalamet’s Elio, and Armie Hammer’s Oliver. I heard characters who were as charmingly maladroit as they were painfully erudite. I worried over the plot, which seemed agonizingly languorous. I started to wonder, like I have during other James Ivory productions, that maybe the yearning was too contrived. That maybe this movie just wasn’t for me.</p>

<p>Then it happened. This film overwhelmed me.</p>

<p>I can’t pinpoint exactly when this happened. Perhaps it was when Elio and Oliver finally decide to consummate their affair, and the initiation is drawn out excruciatingly (and humourously). It might have been when Elio admits he wishes they hadn’t waited so long to be together, hadn’t wasted so much time. It could have been the many moments in between when I knew that my rooting for their love to last was pointless. Still, I couldn’t help myself. By the end of the film, when Michael Stuhlbarg (as Elio’s father) delivers what is surely one of modern cinema’s most achingly beautiful monologues, I was a puddle. I can’t even talk about the end credits yet. It’s still too soon.</p>

<p>You may work on bigger films with bigger stars. You may work your way up the ladder and direct your own films one day. But you will always have a soft spot for your first. I am going to see <em>Call Me By Your Name</em> again tomorrow and I can’t wait. I want to engage with what I dismissed the first time. I want to relive the beauty and the pain, to appreciate the moments that hit me to know if they still hold true. I don’t know if this will happen. I may not walk away from this film as fond of it as I was the first time. But that’s the blessing and the curse of firsts; you only get to experience them once.</p>

  		    ]]>
				</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 06:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/8/call-me-by-your-name.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2018/1/8/call-me-by-your-name.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
