<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>As Above So Below</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll admit it was a bit disappointing to learn that, contrary to what the promotional materials told us, the bulk of action in your new film As Above, So Below took place not in the famous Paris catacombs, but rather a series of offshoot tunnels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a set designer, it must come as a blow when you come onboard a project only to be told there will be no need for the liberal use of skulls as a decorative feature. Which, for this movie, feels especially like a missed opportunity. That said, like the oppressive stone labyrinth our protagonists find themselves trapped in, the whole film feels remarkably solid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get over the lack of skulls, one of As Above&amp;#39;s greatest strengths is the constant sense of unease and claustrophobia evoked by your sets; everything feels appropriately dark and cramped. Unlike past efforts like, say, The Cave, which was home to an underground system so spacious and well-lit there could have been a Starbucks tucked inside it. Also worth noting is the creepiness generated by the increasingly confusing geography of the tunnels as they begin looping back in on themselves—and even breaking all rational laws. The surviving leads are faced with the realization that the only way of reaching the surface is heading ever downwards.  It&amp;#39;s a pretty dynamite setting for a horror movie, and despite the lack of elaborate set decoration, it never feels cheap. You can definitely pat yourself on the back for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have to say that I was a bit surprised by how downplayed the actual horror elements are. It feels like a spiritual successor to Indiana Jones more than anything.  We get an opening scene establishing our heroine as a borderline lunatic willing to risk her life exploring a tomb set for demolition, then plenty o&amp;#39; cryptic riddle-solving as a documentarian films her team in their search for the Philosopher&amp;#39;s Stone, an artifact of untold power in the field of alchemy. It&amp;#39;s a good setup, and combined with the likeable (though admittedly one-dimensional) characters, it&amp;#39;s just enough to keep our attention before the scary shenanigans get under way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know about you, but I appreciated that the filmmakers didn&amp;#39;t needlessly explain the nature of the threat facing our intrepid explorers. There is mention of past sins coming back to haunt them, and the possibility is raised that they are, in fact, traversing Hell—but other than this, there&amp;#39;s no needless exposition. In fact, the horror here is most effective when it’s at its quietest: childhood items inexplicably appearing in the depths, creepy calls on rotary telephones, half-glimpsed apparitions, etc.  Too bad that the final twenty minutes or so devolve into the worst attributes of a found footage film, with lots of confused running around and the sudden appearance of hooded weirdos.  This loses much of the goodwill the film earns—though at least you make up for it with a satisfyingly non-tragic ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing I&amp;#39;d like to mention, because I&amp;#39;m very curious as to what happened on the set during that particular bit where a certain someone gets trapped in a crevice and has a prolonged panic attack before it begins to cave-in.  It&amp;#39;s certainly uncomfortable to watch, but also very clearly lifted from The Descent.  Is this a case of cinematic plagiarism? Or perhaps an homage of some kind?  Whatever the case, it&amp;#39;s incredibly distracting for anyone who has seen both films. I’m curious to know what your thoughts are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I&amp;#39;d say this film belongs squarely in the realm of in-one-ear-out-the-other entertainment, but it&amp;#39;s certainly watchable, and you can definitely do worse when it comes to end of summer fare. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/as-above-so-below.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/as-above-so-below.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Summer of 2014: The Revisitation</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our brief cinematic fling is over, and it’s time to look back on what we had together. Sure, I wasn’t your only lover. But where others chose to only &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/summer-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;look back on your biggest “objective” achievements and lament what could have been&lt;/a&gt;, I thought – hey wait, that’s no way to talk to a lover. Our affair was more nuanced and complex than that. Behind the predictable victories of Marvel and Disney movies at the box-office, there’s a more interesting story to be told. So let me fill in the cracks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, too many people have overlooked your best offering of the season. Maybe they simply assumed &lt;em&gt;Edge of Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;’s generic title was the sign of a generic product. Even the Warner Bros. marketing department seems to &lt;a href=&quot;http://thedissolve.com/news/2991-wait-edge-of-tomorrow-has-become-live-die-repeat-a/&quot;&gt;realize this mistake&lt;/a&gt;. Yet its certainly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/6/edge-of-tomorrow.html&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;the most fun I’ve had at the movies all summer&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; and gave me everything I could hope for in a big budget summer spectacle. And still, it was trounced at the box-office by a teenage romance with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/23/the-fault-in-our-stars.html&quot;&gt;comparatively unknown stars and faultless adherence to the genre&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what, though? My enthusiasm for the film wasn’t diminished by its returns at the box-office.  It does, however, highlight the way Marvel is creating a monopoly on what qualifies as a blockbuster film. Even the critical praise for &lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt; is mostly measured against other Marvel films. I certainly don’t mind visiting the Marvel universe, but I sure as hell don’t actually want to live in it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fellas have taken an unhealthy ownership of summer movies. We act like every film that doesn’t perfectly transport us back to being 13 years old &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;is a failure&lt;/a&gt; (even if the box-office says otherwise), and every film that energizes a female fan base is the end of cinema (see every &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; film—which, &lt;em&gt;mea culpa&lt;/em&gt;, we don’t even bother to review). This might be why two films this summer, both coincidentally starring Scarlett Johansson, were overlooked. One is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;striking technical achievement&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/31/he-said-she-said-dissecting-the-gender-politics-of-under-the.html&quot;&gt;challenging think-piece on gender politics&lt;/a&gt;, and the other is a rare female-lead action film that managed to destroy even &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/13/hercules.html&quot;&gt;Dwayne Johnson as the mighty &lt;em&gt;Hercules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the box-office. The story of &lt;em&gt;Under the Skin&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Lucy&lt;/em&gt; are both equally essential to assessing your true value to the cinematic landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people may have skipped the theatre completely on those non-Marvel opening weekends, but overall the box-office outlook really isn’t that bad. Yes, a 15 percent drop is large, but considering last year was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/seasonal/&quot;&gt;highest grossing summer of all-time&lt;/a&gt;, the sky is hardly falling. Plus, if last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/21/catching-fire.html&quot;&gt;dystopian vision of the future&lt;/a&gt; was any indication, the biggest earner of the year is yet to come with &lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mockingjay:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;. Presumably, another film with a strong female lead (well, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html&quot;&gt;in the first film&lt;/a&gt;, anyway) coming after a year when Disney finally found a runaway hit by making it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/28/frozen.html&quot;&gt;cool to be a princess again&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t deemed suitable to your season, maybe we should forgive the relatively lackluster theatrical performance of another extreme winter picture like &lt;em&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/em&gt;. Or better yet, we could look to understand how&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.indiewire.com/thompsononhollywood/exclusive-harvey-weinstein-explains-how-snowpiercer-became-a-gamechanger-we-crunch-theater-vs-vod-numbers-20140721&quot;&gt;revolutionary it actually was&lt;/a&gt; to have a multi-platform release of a major studio title. For once, box-office numbers don’t tell the whole story. Especially for a film with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;hard R rating&lt;/a&gt; that is never going to draw in the 13-year-olds necessary for a four quadrant hit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should really stop knocking boyhood though. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;I loved that film&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m trying to say is that our annual love affair may be over, but you gave me more than I was willing to admit. I just hope I can convince others of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>If I Stay</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your name has become synonymous with the type of excellence that implies prestige, superiority and exclusivity. You are widely regarded as one of the foremost learning institutions providing education to the highest calibre of young performing artists from around the world. With an admissions acceptance rate hovering around 7%, it’s no wonder your audition process is notoriously intense. In books, television and movies, when a character is trying to get into Juilliard, it is shorthand for a person with slavish dedication and phenomenal talent. It’s unfortunate, then, that your name goes slumming in the mawkish teen weeper &lt;em&gt;If I Stay&lt;/em&gt;, where it gets dragged through cloying, pedestrian sewage and drowns in sentimental cliches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck getting rid of that stink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mia is a cello phenom living in Portland with her ex-punk rocker parents and tow-headed little brother. Her moody boyfriend, Adam is a rising rock star who she hasn’t seen in weeks since their fight about you, Juilliard. See, if you accept Mia as a student, Adam won’t continue their relationship, because long-distance is just too hard for him. Instead of waiting at home in anticipation of an acceptance letter from you, she joins her family on a snowy car ride that turns tragic when they are struck by another vehicle. While in a coma, Mia has an out of body experience that gives her the power to decide whether she should live or die. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I could go back, I would have brought a bottle of Jack Daniels with me to the theatre to play the &lt;em&gt;If I Stay&lt;/em&gt; Drinking Game. Had I taken a swig every time your name was mentioned, I would have been blissfully wasted by the end of the first act, saving me from another hour of maudlin inevitibility. The booze would have helped numb the repetitive stress that my eyeballs sustained every time I rolled them back in my head upon hearing faux-spirational lines like, “sometimes you make choices, sometimes choices make you”. Or when the middle-aged, African-American nurse, in full Magical Negro mode, whispers to the comatose Mia, “You control this, baby. Whatever you got left in you, pull it out now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On second thought, I should have brought chloroform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I Stay is told mainly in flashbacks; Mia’s parents raising her in dive bars, Mia’s parents settling down but never losing their punk edge despite their hippie-dippy parenting style, Mia and Adam falling in love. The story’s naïveté is matched only by its dullness. Some of your former playwright students, Wendy Wasserman (The Heidi Chronicles), John Guare (Six Degrees of Separation), and Tony Kushner (Angels In America), employed flashbacks in fresh and thought-provoking ways, two qualities If I Stay’s comatose script (based on the novel by Gayle Forman) sorely needed. Chloe Grace Moretz, who plays Mia, showed early promise in Let Me In and Kick Ass, but fails to deliver here. She spends most of the movie with furrowed brow, forever on the verge of tantrum while running through hospital hallways. It’s a soap-operatic performance worthy of an after-school special. The saving grace, you might be happy to know, is that at least the soundtrack and score were exceptional. Or maybe they just stood out so much because they felt like they came from another, better film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realize that If I Stay was not targeted for my demographic, people over forty who like good movies. But when I was 14-years-old, one of my favourite films was, and still is, &lt;em&gt;Running On Empty&lt;/em&gt;.  It shares similar themes with If I Stay, yet doesn’t wallow in hackneyed sentimentality. Directed by Sidney Lumet, it’s the story of a young piano prodigy who is constantly on the run with his fugitive, ex-hippie parents who are wanted for bombing a federal building to protest the Vietnam War. The teenage son, played by River Phoenix, must decide whether to keep running with his parents and brother, or attend Juilliard and risk never seeing them again. It’s a quietly complex character study masquerading as a coming of age movie, with politics, romance and nary a false note. The screenplay was nominated for an Oscar, as was River Phoenix for Best Supporting Actor, proof that it’s possible to make a movie about love, loyalty, and loss, for adults and teens, that condescend to neither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course none of this is your fault, but brand association is something you should be more concerned with. On the ride home from seeing If I Stay, I asked my 13-year-old niece if she even knows what Juilliard is. Her response? “Oh yeah, it was in one of the High School Musical movies.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe you consider this a step up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 17:59:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/1/if-i-stay.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/1/if-i-stay.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: Elmer Bernstein</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You learned a little something, over your long and storied career, about how to score comedy films. You came to it late, though. In the early 1980s, even though you were already one of the most famous film composers in the business, John Landis still had to fight with the studio brass to bring you onboard National Lampoon’s Animal House (sure, he was probably a fan—but he also grew up down the street from you and was pals with your kids). They didn’t think you could score a straight-up comedy flick. And, boy, did you prove them wrong. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You followed up Animal House with a run of comedy scores that can only be described as legendary: Meatballs, Airplane!, The Blues Brothers, Stripes, and Trading Places (for which you were nominated for an Academy Award). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scoring a comedy film is less about themes and melodies than it is about tone—and tone, in comedy, is a precarious thing. Which is ,why the music you composed for Ghostbusters is so brilliant. Classical orchestral elements mixed with wavering Theremin notes and a bit of synth, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ghostbusters soundtrack is so preeminent that your score is often forgotten. Play Ray Parker’s Jr.’s eponymous theme song (or Huey Lewis’ “I Want a New Drug,” for that matter), and, even without the lyrics, it’s instantly recognizable. Play the main theme from your score, however, and I wonder how many people – though it would seem familiar to them – would identify the melody with the world’s most famous team of paranormal investigators. But that jaunty piano march is the perfect balance to the pop music that proliferates throughout the rest of the film. More than the cinematography, more than the directing, more than the performances, it’s the regulating element that prevents the special effects and supernatural mythology from overwhelming the film’s &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghostbusters, at its heart, is a small film, filled with wonderful small moments that are more than the sum of their parts. And it was your score that gave them room to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 18:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/29/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-elmer-bernstein.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/29/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-elmer-bernstein.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: Harold Ramis</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’re in the bottom half of the Ghostbusters hierarchy. Murray and Ackroyd are the names and faces everyone remembers—Murray for his half-there, in-on-the-joke performance as Peter Venkman; Ackroyd for his weird real-life parallelism with his supernatural conspiracy-theorist character Ray Stanz. But that was the place you seemed most comfortable; to operate quietly at the periphery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the entire generation of kids born in the late 70s and early 80s, Ghostbusters was a seminal cultural product for me: I wore out my Betamax copy of the movie, watched the Saturday morning cartoon religiously, and collected the toys (the one action figure that I owned: Egon Spengler [with Gulper Ghost]). But I came to appreciate your contribution to the film primarily through your other work; most notably the early years of SCTV. You started out in front of the camera, and while you created a handful of memorable characters (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NYCbF0Fat-c&quot;&gt;Moe Green&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BftMylPpChw&quot;&gt;Curtis Edgit: Plainclothes Mountie&lt;/a&gt;), it was clear that your true talents lay elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generosity of spirit to bring out the best in others is an underrated virtue—especially in a place like Hollywood. While Murray and Ackroyd and Reitman get much of the credit, the simple fact is: there would be no Ghostbusters without you. And it’s not because your performance as Egon is singular, and not necessarily because of what you contributed to the screenplay. It’s because your presence allowed those around you to flourish. It was true back in the Toronto studios of SCTV, and, if your legion of grateful collaborators are to be believed, true on the set of every film you worked on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 11:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/29/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-harold-ramis.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/29/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-harold-ramis.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: David E. Blewitt</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What a weird movie this must have been to edit. &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters _had so many disparate elements to balance. There&amp;#39;s the shambling, semi-improvised comedy in the style of _Caddyshack, Stripes&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Meatballs&lt;/em&gt; that requires a light touch to get the pacing just right. Then there&amp;#39;s the high-budget special effects extravaganza that forces itself into the comedy, requiring beats more akin to an action movie. And speaking of beats, there&amp;#39;s also the seemingly random soundtrack that mixes all manner of song genres, with each song requiring a moment in the spotlight with its own mini-montage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, David, you were the perfect man for the job. With your career experience, mainly in documentary filmmaking, you were certainly qualified to filter through and stitch together what--based on the players involved--must have been a mountain of footage. Murray, Aykroyd, and Ramis certainly didn&amp;#39;t need your help to be funny. No doubt they were thankful to have your expertise in choosing which improvised bits were not only funniest, but best served the story. And maybe because _Ghostbusters _was a new kind of cinematic beast at the time, you chose the most straight-ahead stylistic approach. Comedy, effects and action are all treated with a similar documentary-like feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; director of photography Laszlo Kovacs also had extensive documentary experience, and together you gave the film exactly what it needed. The almost detached point of view that lets the growing insanity feel that much more, well, _insane _against the backdrop of  very real 1980s New York City. That&amp;#39;s what made the ghosts both funny and scary; we were never told exactly what to feel, and could therefore feel anything we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 15:35:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/28/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-david-e-blewitt.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/28/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-david-e-blewitt.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: Chuck Gaspar</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s the eggs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eggs make me most appreciate your work on &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters.&lt;/em&gt; As special effects supervisor, you were responsible for all of the practical, on-set effects work. The really big set-pieces—proton packs, Slimer, Terror Dogs, Gozer, Stay Puft Marshmallow man, and so on—those were the domain of Richard Edlund, and his visual effects team. Your team had the task of making all of those post-production elements feel real, and appear to interact with the real on-set elements. Chandeliers exploding after a missed shot, a dining cart smashed into a wall by a frantic ghost; that was all you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I keep coming back to those eggs on the counter of Dana Barrett&amp;#39;s Upper West Side Apartment. It&amp;#39;s certainly not the most spectacular effect you rigged in &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters,&lt;/em&gt; but when revisiting the film after all these years, I was struck by how well that simple trick works. The eggs come alive, vibrating in their carton, jumping out, smashing on the counter and frying sunny-side-up. Apart from the logistics necessary to execute even this simple scene (was there a whole griddle rigged to that counter top?), I started contemplating how this would be created today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the entire sequence would be CGI. A graphic artist would spend hours creating wire frame models, adding texture maps, creating photorealistic eggs that could be manipulated in any manner. Sure, those eggs would really be able to really fly out of that carton, and the lighting on them would be perfect for any angle you could conceive of: the camera could be anywhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of it would have half the whimsy of the simple effect you created in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 11:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/28/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-chuck-gaspar.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/28/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-chuck-gaspar.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: Jim Bullock</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I could be in another room, on another floor, in another &lt;em&gt;building&lt;/em&gt; while &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; is on, and even if I only hear ten seconds, I know exactly what&amp;#39;s happening. Maybe that&amp;#39;s because I&amp;#39;ve seen the film at least a hundred times. Or maybe it&amp;#39;s because you transformed what must have been a thousand hours of audio tracks into the soundscape that helped make &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; one of the most beloved films of the last thirty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the very first scene your work sets the literal and figurative tone for the entire film; the librarian softly pads between rows of books over a seemingly benign score. The wood cabinet drawers slide open and catalogue files shuffle into the air. Then horns, a xylophone, and a Theremin amplify the tension as the librarian realizes she is not alone. Her footsteps quicken to a run, the score builds to a crescendo and we hear a deep, other-worldly roar pierced through by her blood-curdling scream that fades into Ray Parker Jr.&amp;#39;s titular song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were responsible for assembling layers of sound that have now become iconic; from the eggs rattling in their carton, then popping and frying on Dana&amp;#39;s kitchen counter; the green blob cackling and gulping and breaking plates; the _whoosh _as ghosts are incarcerated in the vapour trap. The assorted beeps, pulses, and hums of equipment, the deep growls of ghost hounds, and the splitting crack as the heavens open up and threaten to rain hellfire down on New York city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this noise, and yet you made sure the cacophony never drowned out some of the most quotable dialogue in comedy history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time you came to &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt;, you were already an expert, having spent the 50s and 60s as sound editor on dozens of shows: &lt;em&gt;I Love Lucy, Peter Gunn, _and even one with a ghost protagonist, _My Mother the Car. _You tried your hand at acting in the 80s, appearing in _Knight Rider, The Wonder Years,&lt;/em&gt; and my favourite bad movie, &lt;em&gt;Rocky IV&lt;/em&gt;. Those gigs alone are enough to make my inner child geek-out. Add &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt;, and I think you just might be my new hero.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 19:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/27/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-jim-bullock.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/27/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-jim-bullock.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: Bernie Brillstein</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I knew who you were even before &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt;. Which, considering I was eleven years-old at the time, either says a lot about your reputation, or says a lot about what an odd kid I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d seen your name on the credits of &lt;em&gt;Hee-Haw, The Muppet Show&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Saturday Night Live&lt;/em&gt;. I read that you became John Belushi&amp;#39;s manager by accident when he refused to sign his SNL contract minutes before the first show went to air. He would commit only if &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, Lorne Michaels&amp;#39; manager, represented him. You agreed, and Belushi became your first star client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You broke a lot of ground in the late-70s and early-80s. You convinced Atlantic Records to pony up a hundred-and-twenty-five grand to produce an album by the as-yet-unknown Blues Brothers&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; You were one of the first to profit from packaging TV shows, hiring your own writers to create projects, then filling them with your own stars, and executive producing the programs yourself. After selling them to networks, this scheme guaranteed you a producing credit and points on the back end. Until you gamed the system, an exec producer was largely a figurehead. But, by packaging talent, you held all the cards. It&amp;#39;s a tactic that has since become the industry standard, and one you carried on into the 1990s with shows like &lt;em&gt;The Sopranos, Politically Incorrect&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The Larry Sanders Show.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might consider that approach a little too close to bribery. But no one seemed to mind it coming from you. By all accounts you were a real mensch. While you were busy reinventing the wheel and trying to keep Belushi from killing himself, Dan Aykroyd had been developing a script for him and Belushi to star in. It was set in a future, where teams of ghost disposal units were as common as firefighters and paramedics. He called it &lt;em&gt;Ghost Smashers.&lt;/em&gt; After Belushi&amp;#39;s passing, Aykroyd and Harold Ramis reworked the script, and Aykroyd pitched it to you. As a testament to just how trusted you were, Aykroyd sold it to you for a dollar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it was passed over by several studios and directors who just didn&amp;#39;t get it, the film, retitled &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt;, went on to make over $291 million worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your dollar investment paid off. But more than that, it made you the original gatekeeper of Zuul.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 14:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/27/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-bernie-brillstein.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/27/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-bernie-brillstein.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ghosts of Ghostbusters: László Kovács</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You were certainly an unfunny choice for this movie. But with a motley cast, a motley crew, and a motley group of characters out to save the world, why not hire the cinematographer from &lt;em&gt;Easy Rider&lt;/em&gt; and_ Five Easy Pieces?_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both you and director Ivan Reitman have talked about how comedies typically have a look--and how this movie should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have that look. Instead of a simplistic comedy approach with high-key shots and bright colors, _Ghostbusters _is shot like a serious film. You added a distinct color cast, but otherwise let the scene define the tone (rather than imposing yourself on it). There are sequences that look like drama, documentary newcasts, and epic adventure (that 2.35:1 anamorphic aspect ratio!). This allows you to set real stakes in a plot that is patently ridiculous. It also allows for a very broad range of humor: from pun-tastic setpieces and light improv to dark sarcasm and tragic irony--all within the same film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a consistently (and I imagine painstakingly) unobtrusive filmmaking approach, you allowed the movie to conjure it&amp;#39;s own reality. By making a comedy that didn&amp;#39;t look like a comedy, you made people believe this unbelievable story. I think that&amp;#39;s a key reason it&amp;#39;s stood up so well - and even improved - over all these years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 18:03:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/26/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-laszlo-kovacs.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/26/ghosts-of-ghostbusters-laszlo-kovacs.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
