<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Kurt Cobain: Montage of Heck</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Without you, this film doesn’t exist. Writer/director Brett Morgen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecredits.org/2015/05/brett-morgen-on-kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck-how-frances-bean-made-it-happen/&quot;&gt;has said so&lt;/a&gt; several times, in no uncertain terms. This incredibly intimate,unflinching, and insightful documentary about your father, Kurt Cobain, provides the personal access many fans have been craving for years from the late media recluse. But I can’t imagine how much the film must have meant to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world lost an important voice, but you lost so much more: the chance to grow up loved by a man who, the doc makes brutally clear, suffered many demons in his life – from drugs, to debilitating illness, to a trainwreck of a wife. The sum total became a pain he seemingly couldn’t overcome, and now Morgen is literally picking up the pieces to try and salvage the soul of the man. Partly for us curious fans, sure, but really he did it for you – Kurt’s only child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks to your involvement, warring factions from all sides of the post-Nirvana legal drama appear:  friends, family, past lovers, bandmates , and of course, Courtney Love -  your “biological mother” (as you refer to her on Twitter in between restraining orders and general estrangement). Love is certainly an important puzzle piece to the story structure, but her most essential contribution is the treasure trove of original material she provided the filmmakers, rather than anything of substance in her interviews. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your father’s early sketches, for example, play a major role in the “montage” aspects of the titular “heck”. There’s a maniacal restlessness and chaos to their design, which almost vibrate off the page with their excessive motion lines and frenetic accentuations. Mountains of home videos, diary entries, and raw recordings, and even original animation used to create re-enactments all help to construct a truly compelling portrait of a man whose legend has only grown in the music scene in the 20 years since his suicide. But most importantly, the clearance of music means that not only do we get to hear all the songs that made Nirvana the rock phenomenon they became, but even the score deconstructs and rebuilds classic tracks to help set an intimate atmosphere that always feels like an extension of your father’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most surprising is how the film doesn’t shy away from your father’s faults and foibles. One particular story, about the time he tried to lose his virginity to an overweight girl who was mentally challenged, before attempting to commit suicide, is intense and revealing. Most children would never grant permission to use a story like that when charged with preservation of their parent’s legacy. But I think you saw the bigger picture –how the need to connect meant not just giving the people the man they want, but offering a glimpse of the complex man he really was (in as much as any two hour film could ever attempt to do).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most disappointing, however, is the non-inclusion of Nirvana’s former drummer/current rock superstar Dave Grohl. Morgen has said Grohl was interviewed, but only 10 days before the film’s scheduled premiere, and that he just couldn’t fit him into the film. I won’t start any more rumours, but suffice to say that even a single line from the man would have helped make the film feel complete. Then again, I guess achieving that feeling was never going to be possible, for fans or for you. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/13/kurt-cobain-montage-of-heck.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Maggie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;After all these years of doing battle with the likes of Satan, sport-hunting aliens, assorted criminal scumbags, and a headache that was definitely not a tumor, I can say with a reasonable degree of certainty that, when word first came that you would be starring in a zombie flick, we all had the same generic shoot ‘em up playing in our heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, the whole zombie thing is a sub-genre I&amp;#39;ve burnt out on, and even with your name on the marquee I had a fair amount of reservations before sitting down to watch &lt;em&gt;Maggie&lt;/em&gt;. So you can imagine my delight when it proved to be a far more than your typical zombie film—and, on top of that, offered a performance from you that is unlike anything we&amp;#39;ve ever seen from you. After four decades, that’s pretty amazing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what makes &lt;em&gt;Maggie&lt;/em&gt; work so well is its neat sidestepping of the expected thematic beats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No petty infighting amongst the survivors. No climactic siege. No &amp;quot;perhaps &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; is the real monster after all&amp;quot; moralizing when the dust settles. Indeed, outside of an early attack scene, there are only a handful of moments where the undead are onscreen. Yet they never feel inconsequential to the story. The moody shots of a decimated landscape tell us every thing we need to know about how much the world has been impacted, and the script makes the wise decision to never provide an explanation as to how we wound up in this predicament in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the character type of “everyman” doesn&amp;#39;t immediately come to mind when one glances at your filmography. But as a humble Midwestern farmer spending what little time he has left with his infected daughter, there was never a moment where I questioned your commitment to the role. It&amp;#39;s a very sad and introspective performance, and reveals just as much through body language as dialogue. And there’s some heavy stuff to deal with; your character, Wade, must come to terms not only with the fact that his daughter is dying, but that he may have to be the one to end her suffering before she can become a danger to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your co-star Abigail Breslin really knocks it out of the park, as well. As Maggie, she brings a real sense of tragedy and pathos to the role. Even as the infection worsens, her humanity always shines through, and, just like Wade, we never see her as the monster others fear her to be. The chemistry you two share is wonderfully genuine, and even though there’s a certain degree of inevitability to how a story like this can end, it doesn&amp;#39;t make the actual moment any less gut-wrenching when it finally comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a move I wish more action stars of your calibre (and age) would take: act in smaller parts that offer greater opportunity to flex dramatic muscles (you know, instead of attempting to relive the high-octane days of yore).  It’s the reason I&amp;#39;ve never thought twice about &lt;em&gt;The Expendables&lt;/em&gt; and its sequels; seeing someone step outside their comfort zone is far more exciting than watching them rehash what made them famous in the first place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why I’m hoping that I can look forward to seeing you in similar roles in the future. Just think of the dramatic muscles as yet another part of your physical form that needs to be pumped up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/12/maggie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/12/maggie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ex Machina</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It’s not easy to replicate human movement. There’s a non-mathematical rhythm to people’s physical motion that reflects their inner emotions – from nervous ticks, to sloppy posture, to general social awkwardness. It’s what makes us human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An actor’s job is to master these subconscious tells, and in &lt;em&gt;Ex Machina&lt;/em&gt;, you’re one of the many digital artists responsible tracking those very calculated movements. By compositing a mechanical structure to actress Alicia Vikander’s body, your mission is to make her character, Ava, look both real and distinctly… not. You’re creating a reverse &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_test&quot;&gt;Turing test&lt;/a&gt; on the audience. When you succeed, it’s a thing of beauty. But nowadays, that’s the easy part. The failure is that I had to spend so much time, both during and after the film, trying to understand the basic story logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a scientific experiment, it might sound fascinating for an eccentric tech billionaire to bring an unsuspecting employee to a remote location to determine if his latest invention possesses true artificial intelligence. But as a film treatment, it’s sorely lacking a dramatic thesis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know the robot was reverse engineered from an actor’s performance. Her face is completely recognizable, and her movements are that of a flesh-and-blood woman. So while we might initially spend some time admiring your digital effects work on the legs, arms and abdomen, we never actually question the humanity on display. Our journey is inverse from that of the protagonists – do we buy her as a robot? But while the characters are looking for the intangible elements that would reveal true emotional and developed intelligence (rather than programmed responses), we have time to ponder banal questions like – how could one solitary man ever create such an elaborate and secretive replica of the human eye (for example), complete with reds in the corners and veins? You know, the stuff you didn’t bother to touch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I ask myself, why is true A.I. so much more impressive than whatever this nearly-A.I. being is that we’re seeing? Based on Domhnall Gleeson’s reactions, it’s clearly an unparalleled feat in-and-of itself. So even if the story takes place in the near future (it never specifies), Oscar Isaac’s character would be the equivalent of Henry Ford withholding the release of the Model T until it could run on pure oxygen and emit zero emissions. And that’s where the film becomes too mechanical in its execution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen a few female characters (usually played by Scarlett Johansson) in the last year going on this same journey to discover what it means to be human. The novelty has become ho-hum from an audience perspective. But what works about the film is when writer and director Alex Garland contrasts clinical art direction with a seemingly laid-back mystery man at the center. It tells us something is off. Cracked glass in a window, and excessive drinking provide the types of flaws that makes surroundings and characters compelling.  But finding flashes of life in the human characters is far less interesting than what we might have seen in a robot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/8/ex-machina.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/8/ex-machina.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Superhero Craze Isn&#39;t Superficial</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most prevalent (and lazy) criticisms of the current spate of superhero themed movies is that they aren’t really about anything. At least anything other than filling sacks of cash for Disney or Warner or Sony or whoever else wants to throw a couple of hundred million dollars at Joss Whedon and his ilk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this particular criticism is that it is demonstrably wrong. It is so clearly incorrect that I am often baffled at how people who seem perceptive and well intentioned become so vexed that they lose the use of their critical faculties &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/04/are-the-avengers-really-saving-the-world-if-the-sequels-are-inevitable&quot;&gt;(like this guy)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-avengers-age-of-ultron.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/4/captain-america-the-winter-soldier.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain America: The Winter Soldier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or any of the other colon-ridden movies are not (a.) great art or (b.) without strong profit motive. But then again you could say that about almost all of culture since we first decided to tell stories around a campfire. You can, however, make distinctions about good and bad, and those distinctions have nothing to do with the box office returns a particular movie, or set of movies, generates (if they did then Michael Bay would be considered an auteur, and no one wants to live in that universe).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re talking about the MCU (Marvel Comics Universe) one of the reasons that some miss the forest for the trees has to do with the cross-pollination of sequential comics with traditional filmmaking. Most movies, even when you’re dealing with trilogies and sequels, are hermetically sealed. It is one of the defining features of mainstream cinema—a complete story is told in ninety or one hundred and twenty minutes. Comics work in a slightly different way. And that difference is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the comic book movies do differently, on a structural level, is that the main plot carries through several different films. Think of them as chapters rather than whole novels. Each chapter carries the narrative forward toward an eventual endpoint. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious caveat to be made here: some people do not want to spend the time, money, and energy necessary to engage with this kind of storytelling. For instance, I have never watched the entirety of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin_Alexanderplatz_(miniseries)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berlin Alexanderplatz&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, despite its universal acclaim. But my lack of interest says absolutely nothing about its intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who read, or have read, comics understand this kind of story telling intuitively because it is in the DNA of the form; broad, sprawling mythologies that often span several different titles and can take years to play out. Sometimes it is well done (see: Neil Gaiman’s &lt;em&gt;Sandman&lt;/em&gt; or Marvel’s &lt;em&gt;Civil War&lt;/em&gt; series). Other times, not so well (Marvel’s &lt;em&gt;The Ultimates&lt;/em&gt;). But when executed properly, they manage to tell a big, rambunctious story with some pretty interesting themes and a depth of character that can surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those responsible for the Marvel films, like Joss Whedon and Kevin Feige, understand this kind of structure intuitively. Whedon in particular wields enormous creative influence and has managed to do something I would have considered impossible even five years ago—he invested these movies with a pretty interesting through-line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What these movies are really exploring—from the beginning with the first &lt;em&gt;Iron Man&lt;/em&gt; through to the current &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; and beyond—is the inherent tension between the desire for security and personal liberty. Oddly enough, the strongest advocate for this chaotic and often-dangerous kind of freedom is the character that could have been the most banal and jingoistic: Chris Evan’s Captain America. This split becomes explicit in &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; and will play out in the coming Civil War storyline. And if the Russo Bros. do it justice, as I suspect they will, it will be a fascinating ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shield versus The Sword. The difference between preemptive paranoia and the idea that life is inherently dangerous and a certain amount of risk has to be accepted. In short, everyone eventually dies and the thing that matters is the quality of your life, not its length (even if death is an elastic concept in the MCU). This is the central conflict of these films and you don’t have to look very hard at any of them to see these two viewpoints banging up against one another. The idea that saving the world over and over again is the singular theme of these films is missing the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if this all sounds a little hyperbolic, that’s because it is. There isn’t much nuance here. However, the best of these movies carry an earnest power that subverts a certain tendency, in some quarters, to see the uncomplicated as something that lacks value. But like most entertainments worth that label, these films have an undercurrent that touches on things we all care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also drawbacks to this kind of narrative strategy. It risks sprawl. It risks commerce subverting the creative aspect so that some movies become nothing but placeholders (&lt;em&gt;Iron Man 2&lt;/em&gt;, I’m pointing in your direction). There is also an unevenness that is inevitable because no matter strong the central planning is, some directors and screenwriters are just more adept than others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well—and this is perhaps where the rubber hits the road—some of this critical contempt is less about the films themselves and more about how their fans engage with them. The idea of sweaty nerdlings losing their minds about men and women in costume puts some people off. An attitude which, while perhaps understandable, really has nothing to do with the films as creative enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On balance, the people at the helm of this particular Juggernaut have managed to smooth out most of the rough edges and create a body of work that holds up over time. These are thoroughly enjoyable films. They don’t speak to everyone, but what does (other than the truly banal).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best of them—&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Iron Man,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/5/3/iron-man-3.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iron Man 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Captain America: Winter Soldier&lt;/em&gt;—are quality works of genre fiction. They are well-written, well-executed, beautiful to look at, and emotionally compelling. More importantly, they move the whole story towards something that might be truly special. Fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am sure of is that the pointless hand-wringing over these films and their supposed lack of depth is misplaced. They are primarily entertainments, in the same way that most Broadway musicals are—or any kind of music, or most books, or any piece of cultural ephemera we consume. They are worth exactly as much time, energy, and attention as you want to give them. And if you prefer other things one of the very great features of middlebrow culture (at this point in history) is that you can never see a Marvel film as long as you live and still not lose a minute of sleep or lack any number of quality alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-superhero-craze-isnt-superficial.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/the-superhero-craze-isnt-superficial.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Avengers: Age of Ultron</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ll indulge me for a moment, I’m going to do a little reminiscing of my own. Something along the lines of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html&quot;&gt;letter you penned to your younger self&lt;/a&gt; when you first saw 2012’s &lt;em&gt;The Avengers.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what stage of superhero worship you would have found yourself in during the spring of 1984 – you’d have been what, 4 years old? – but it was probably deeper than mine. I was 11-years old, and more of a &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;G.I. JOE&lt;/em&gt; comic guy. Like &lt;em&gt;The Avengers,&lt;/em&gt; they were published by Marvel, but even back then I knew the truth: they were monthly, 30-page advertisements for toys. Superheroes just weren’t my thing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that day in May when I wandered into Checkers Convenience and saw &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars&lt;/em&gt; #1 on the spinner rack, even my Hasbro-addled brain knew it something special, something &lt;em&gt;big.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I wasn’t quite up-to-speed with the convoluted mythologies behind Iron Man, The Hulk, Captain America, Spider-Man, The X-Men didn’t matter—I wanted in. I ate up all 12 issues of the miniseries as fast as I could. And as a marketing vehicle, &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars&lt;/em&gt; achieved its purpose: it drew me into the larger Marvel Universe: &lt;em&gt;Peter Parker:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spectacular&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Uncanny X-Men&lt;/em&gt; became regular reading for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the following year, &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II&lt;/em&gt; came out. And in the very first issue – which managed to cross-reference &lt;em&gt;every single&lt;/em&gt; Marvel title being published at the time –I checked out. Making sense of it all was just too much damn work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be worried about where I’m going with this. You probably think that I’m going to say that &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; is the Marvel Cinematic Universe’s &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II;&lt;/em&gt; it buckles under the burden of too much baggage from past filmsand too many future plot-threads to establish; that it too obviously exists only to propagate more Marvel films. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; worry me going into the film. And I’ve levelled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/4/captain-america-the-winter-soldier.html&quot;&gt;similar complaints&lt;/a&gt; against the the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html&quot;&gt;ever-expanding&lt;/a&gt; Marvel Universe before (no one wants to have to do homework just to watch a summer blockbuster).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t worry. I come from the future to tell you to rest easy, slightly-younger Jared. For in the end, &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; is … fine. Your endlessly optimistic twelve-year-old-self might find &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; a huge disappointment, but now that you’re old enough to know that all things are not, in fact, possible, and that recreating past triumphs is mostly a fool’s errand, and that very few things in life are as fun the second time round, then...you’ll probably like this movie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, not love. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I was looking forward to this second instalment – even with my misgivings, I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; excited – I did feel a little bit of disappointment when Captain America, Thor, Iron Man, The Hulk, Black Widow, and Hawkeye reassembled on screen. Not disappointment in what I saw onscreen, but disappointment in my visceral reaction to it. Everything is executed as well as it was the first time around, but this time around it all felt kind of...well, expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, yes, you might argue that this is the curse of any sequel. About &lt;em&gt;Jurassic Park: The Lost World&lt;/em&gt;, Roger Ebert asked: where is the awe, the sense of wonder? (Answer: in the first movie.) I get it. I myself am always quick to point out that you should never review any film – even a sequel – by comparing it to another. But expectations are fair game. Expectations that, in these past three years – as Marvel schools other studios and publishers on how to build the ultimate interlocking franchise – have grown impossibly big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; certainly wastes no time in trying to meet those expectations. It opens with an extended action sequence, the scale of which any regular-sized movie would save for its climax. It’s way too long, sure, but it does immediately give us what we came for: The Avengers at their ass-kicking best. It also serves to introduce a new super-powered duo: the twins Pietro and Wanda Maximoff (of the two, Elizabeth Olsen’s Wanda makes much more of an impression, even if I still don’t understand exactly what her powers were supposed to be). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Olsen stands out is no small feat. This playing field is crowded with big personalities. While &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; might not have the same reverence for the characters you found in the original, Joss Whedon is determined to use his second outing as writer and director to give each of them their due—almost to a fault (the one exception is Thor, who is reduced to a walking joke delivery system when he’s not smashing things with his hammer). One thing that can be said for Whedon: he loves his character-building, and things get pretty Whedon-y in &lt;em&gt;Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt;. For the most part, this is good: Jeremy Renner’s Hawkeye is an actual character this time around, and the action slows down enough to explore budding relationships and tensions within the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to give you a point-by-point plot summary here. The amount of footnotes I’d need to explain everything would make this the &lt;em&gt;Secret Wars II&lt;/em&gt; of reviews. So I’ll itemize what you, so recently in love with Whedon’s first installment, will want to know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes: the show-stopping fight between The Hulk and Iron Man is just that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: as the movie’s big bad, James Spader’s Ultron is no match for Loki. Spader does admirable voice work, and Whedon makes him an interesting screen presence, but when you’re forwarding the story by cutting away from the goddamned Avengers, you better have something on-screen with hell of a lot of charisma. Charisma that the sleek, all-CGI Ultron just doesn’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: the plot is not particularly tight. Wanda Maximoff’s ill-defined powers left me confused about who was affected by what and for how long. And, not to pick on Thor again, but his particular arc seems to exist only to set up future installments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No: the climactic action scene is not any more sensible this time around. Which is a shame, given that it’s the exact same urban destructathon.* Ultron’s army of indistinguishable robots is almost as indistinguishable as the armoured Chitari in &lt;em&gt;The Avengers&lt;/em&gt;. When this much pyrotechnic skill is on display the last thing I need to be thinking is, “I don’t know where anyone is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, yes: Marvel has shoehorned as many extra characters into this film as it possibly could, all in the interest of franchise building. War Machine, The Falcon, and The Vision (a brand new character introduced in the film’s last act) add very little, story-wise, but provide a way forward for more adventures. It’s here that you will see where Whedon’s idiosyncrasies come up against the behemoth that is Marvel. The mechanics of world building push Whedon’s interests out of the picture, quite literally. The side effect of this tension is that &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Age of Ultron&lt;/em&gt; feels more like a product than an entertainment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, hey, don’t let me ruin the 2012 afterglow. I still enjoyed the movie. Whedon’s dialogue and attention to (and love for) the characters goes a long way in overcoming the larger business interests of Marvel. And look on the bright side: when it came time for your childhood heroes to be turned into movies, the reigns were handed to Joss Whedon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1046173/&quot;&gt;Steven Sommers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0418279/?ref_=nv_sr_2&quot;&gt;Michael Bay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/avengers-age-of-ultron.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/7/avengers-age-of-ultron.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Going Clear: Scientology and the Prison of Belief</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Without you Alex Gibney’s &lt;em&gt;Going Clear: Scientology and the Prison of Belief&lt;/em&gt; probably never gets made. This isn’t just because you are the Pulitzer Prize winning author whose 2013 non-fiction book prompted Gibney to make the film in the first place. The most important contribution you made to this film was your professional integrity and the rigor of your work. Because if you are going to go after Scientology you had better be sure all the I’s are dotted and T’s are crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the early revelations of the film is this pertinent fact: in 1993 Scientology succeeded in strong-arming the I.R.S. into granting them &lt;a href=&quot;file://localhost/Users/Timothy001/Desktop/www.nytimes.com:.webloc&quot;&gt;tax-exempt status&lt;/a&gt; (as a religious non-profit). This means they managed to coerce—by means both litigious and extra-legal—the single most powerful non-military U.S. government agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson here is: if you are going to take a swing at these guys you had better be prepared for a long, protracted and bloody war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That your book managed to clear all the legal hurdles required set the stage for Gibney to make his film. And what a film it turned out to be. &lt;em&gt;Going Clear: Scientology and the Prison of Belief&lt;/em&gt; manages to balance tone and content in a way that treats the subject with the gravity it deserves without ever losing sight of the more surreal and absurd aspects of the whole sordid mess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gibney also removed the word &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; when adapting the title of your book for his project. He seems to have decided that while there is some salacious value in the antics of people like Tom Cruise and John Travolta, they aren’t really the story here. The film exclusively concerns itself with how people allow themselves—gradually and through a toxic stew of self-deception, wishful thinking and a lack of critical attention—to be lured into a pyramid scheme of the most puerile sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structurally the film quickly dispenses with the necessary, but cartoonishly absurd, origin story of Scientology—and a short bio of its founder, L. Ron Hubbard. After that the narrative moves into more interesting territory. In a series of interviews intercut with low-key re-enactments and unsettling archival footage (of both LRH and the current leader David Miscavige), Gibney examines both the development of the church and, in parallel, the methods used to ensnare and retain its adherents. The interviews with various former members of the Church are persuasive in their frank descriptions of the kind of surreal behavior they participated in—and were subject to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost as an afterthought you see clips of Cruise and Travolta, but mostly as object examples of how the church achieves their ends by leveraging people’s own vanity and need for absolution. At various times both men were considering leaving the Church and the strong implication seems to be that their own personal confessions were used to discourage that particular course of action. These personal revelations were obtained during what Scientology describes as ‘auditing’. A process that is essentially a melding of the Catholic confessional and talk therapy—without any of the institutional prohibitions on disclosure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most affecting is the story of Paul Haggis, a producer and filmmaker that was a member of the Church for over thirty years. He left Scientology in 2009—ostensibly after a disagreement with the Church hierarchy over their support of Prop 8 in California. His story is a template for all of the stories in the film. A man looking to make some improvements in his life finds himself ensnared—after decades of slow ascension through the ranks—in an enterprise that proves to be, at its core, a ludicrous fabrication. A fabrication invented by a man (LRH) that was likely a victimof his ownprofound mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that you enter the story, Lawrence. In 2011 you published your 25,000 word essay in the New Yorker called &lt;a href=&quot;file://localhost/Users/Timothy001/Desktop/www.newyorker.com:.webloc&quot;&gt;‘The Apostate”&lt;/a&gt;. It is a brilliant piece about Haggis and his 34-year relationship with the church—and how the scales finally fell from his eyes.  From that article came the book—and eventually, Gibney’s film. After that, the threats of lawsuits, intimidation and generally bad behavior that were the inevitable consequence of exposing the Emperor’s junk to the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for taking all of that on, we owe you a real debt, Lawrence. A couple of beers at the absolute minimum. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/5/going-clear-scientology-and-the-prison-of-belief.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/5/going-clear-scientology-and-the-prison-of-belief.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Age of Adaline</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a fan of wildlife programs? You know, the kind where a herd of gazelles lazily sips at a watering hole while a lioness prepares to pounce, all while David Attenborough’s soothing voice runs a play-by-play of the grisly proceedings? &lt;em&gt;Age of Adaline&lt;/em&gt; shares a few similarities with those classic zoological telecasts: it’s expertly photographed, the creatures and landscapes are gorgeous, and your sonorous voice provides context to the action. And like those nature programs, &lt;em&gt;Age of Adaline&lt;/em&gt; provides very little in the way of character development or dramatic tension. The difference is, we usually have more of a reason to root for the gazelle than the simple fact that she’s pleasing to look at. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Blake Lively is most certainly easy on the eyes. As Adaline, Lively isn’t just ageless—she’s &lt;em&gt;timeless&lt;/em&gt;. She emanates old Hollywood glamour, completely at ease in every era in which the film takes place. Unfortunately, she is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in a vintage Chanel ad, where being aloof, chilly and opaque are acceptable qualities. She’s supposed to be in a modern romantic fairy tale. But it’s unfair to lay all the blame at Blake’s lovely feet. For a movie about a woman who has lived for more than a hundred years, it’s disappointing – and more than a little bit baffling – that Adaline is so lacking in dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in 1906, Adaline led a normal life...until the age of 29 when her car plunged into a frigid river and was then struck by lightning. She survived, but she was unable to age. In present day San Francisco, she falls for a man named Ellis, who turns out to be the son of William, a man she had a fling with in London in the Sixties. She now must face the truth about her circumstances or risk losing yet another chance at love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn about Adaline’s backstory through the three laziest screenplay devices available: old newsreel footage (that she watches because she works at a library), flashbacks, and narration (no offense). This is when we’re introduced to your authoritative voice. You describe Adaline’s first few years in a historical context: a newspaper declaring her as the first baby born on New Year’s Day 1906, the Great San Francisco earthquake and fire, the building of the Golden Gate Bridge where she meets her husband, an engineer who perishes during construction, leaving her a young widowed mother. And then you continue Adaline’s curious backstory ten months after the death of her husband when she drives her car off a snowy road and into the river. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an external narrator is used well, it gives the audience a sense of remove, an objectivity (think &lt;em&gt;Magnolia&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Little Children&lt;/em&gt;). In &lt;em&gt;Age of Adaline&lt;/em&gt;, your job is purely expository. Instead of allowing Adaline to tell her own life story (and in the process, provide the opportunity for some much needed character development), the filmmakers instead decide to give you the task of explaining her preposterous plight. As Adaline plunges into the chilly water, you explain the pathology of anoxic shock, combined with head injury and the defibrillating properties of being struck by lightning which, when combined, leads to agelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You then go on to tell us how Adeline spent years trying to make sense of her medical predicament, while making up excuses for her inability to age. In the Fifties a traffic cop questions Adeline’s age, and then the FBI gets involved (because, &lt;em&gt;communism!)&lt;/em&gt;, and she goes on the run, leaving behind her now college-aged daughter. Flash-forward to present day and she’s fallen for Ellis, a quasi-stalker with scruffy hair, who loves history and drives a late-model Saab despite the fact he’s a millionaire (which is apparently shorthand for “endearing Mr. Right-type”). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get a break when the film is turned over to the veterans. Ellen Burstyn as Adaline’s daughter Flemming, Harrison Ford as William, and Kathy Baker as his wife. They manage to navigate the stray plot threads gamely and elevate the script’s sappiness. Ford seems more invested than he has in years, and he and Baker provide most of the film’s genuine laughs. A special mention should go to newcomer Anthony Ingruber for his uncanny portrayal of young William. With his adorably spot-on grimacing, he almost manages to out-curmudgeon Harrison Ford. But it’s Ellen Burstyn who steals every scene she’s in, believably playing “younger” than Lively’s Adaline. She’s so convincing that it’s a shame the writer’s didn’t give &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt; the narration job (again, no offense). That might have given the film the depth and warmth that your bystander perspective just couldn’t provide (no offense, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you return in the third act, you’re describing another car careening on a slippery road in a snow storm. But at this point we’re expecting it. Unfortunately, since we’ve never learned about Adaline’s hopes or desires, or who she really is beyond the obvious, your narration might as well have been done by Charlie Brown’s teacher, because by that point, all I could hear was, “wha, wha, wha, wha, wha, wha…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, seriously, no offense.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/1/age-of-adaline.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/5/1/age-of-adaline.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>We Need to Talk About Adam</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;If you are a 13-year-old-boy, ignore this letter. Carry on with your Xboxing and your YouTubing or whatever it is you kids are into these days. But if you have pubes, and a fully developed prefrontal cortex, you also have some explaining to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who the hell are you, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to figure you out for years. When I picture you in my head it’s not pretty. I see monobrows, Cheeto-dusted sweatpants, and Crocs. I imagine too many digits and not enough teeth. I realize this sounds horribly condescending, especially because I was once one of you. But that was a long time ago. Clinton was president. Napster was a thing. Adam Sandler was funny. I was high. Pretty much all the time. But even now, when the most mind-altering substance I imbibe is Tazo Calm tea, I still think &lt;em&gt;The Wedding Singer&lt;/em&gt; is funny. Everything he’s done since then would require me to ingest Chris Farley-levels of recreational pharmaceuticals to find even mildly amusing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So really, who are you? I’ve asked around and no one will readily admit to being an Adam Sandler fan. But you must be out there. It’s kind of like how everyone likes to hate on U2, yet their massive stadium shows sell out in minutes. Someone’s going, but nobody wants to cop to it. Like that barbed wire tattoo you thought was cool for twelve minutes in ‘99, if you can hide it now why wouldn’t you? And I can’t say I blame you. Admitting you like Adam Sandler’s films means admitting to yourself what you know deep inside must be true: Adam Sandler thinks you’re stupid. He thinks you’re sexist, and racist and borderline sociopathic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least it seems that way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why else would he continue to make sophomoric drivel set in a Hooters, or in an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.citypress.co.za/entertainment/movie-review-tired-offensive/&quot;&gt;Africa rendered so insulting and full of stereotypes&lt;/a&gt; that he might as well have just shot it at The Rainforest Cafe? Why would he keep playing the same sad-sack Everyman with a bullying streak and an uncontrollable temper? It’s because he thinks you’re a bunch of mouth-breathing rubes who will happily pay to see whatever insipid dreck he deigns to shart out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the topic of sharting, Adam Sandler movies can best be compared to the McRib; they both come around about once a year surrounded by inflated hype, they’re molded into a pre-formed shape with the cheapest material, are completely devoid of nutritional value, and they cover you in shame sweat immediately following consumption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also make an inexplicably obscene amount of money. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast food chains don’t make food as much as they sell &lt;em&gt;product&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/the-three-types-of-adam-sandler-movies/&quot;&gt;Sandler operates in much the same way.&lt;/a&gt; To him, comedy isn’t art, it’s commerce. Like McD’s, he succeeds because he keeps operating costs low thus ensuring a high return on investment. His movies aren’t movies, they are units sold. Quantity versus quality. His goal isn’t to make millions of people laugh, it’s to make a few people rich. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Sandler stopped trying years ago. He admits as much himself. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.avclub.com/article/adam-sandler-confirms-his-movies-are-just-paid-vac-204952&quot;&gt;His films are an excuse for him and his friends to get a paid vacation&lt;/a&gt;. Which wouldn’t be so sad if his movies were even marginally funny. Instead they take aim at the marginalized. His style of comedy isn’t just lazy, it’s mean. And it’s mean &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; it’s lazy. The easiest, cheapest laughs are the ones you get from punching down, from harvesting the lowest hanging fruit. They aren’t effortless, they are effort-free. There is no subtext, no hidden metaphors, no subtlety whatsoever. Chicago Tribune’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2015/04/adam-sandler-has-finally-hit-the-limit-of-satire/391550/&quot;&gt;Michael Phillips nailed it&lt;/a&gt; when he said, &amp;quot;People of color, to say nothing of women, who have been marginalized, patronized or humiliated by a stupid joke in an Adam Sandler movie over the last few years constitute the biggest club in modern Hollywood.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for some reason, you’re all still laughing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, a group of Native American actors walked off the set of Sandler’s latest cinematic abortion, &lt;em&gt;Ridiculous 6&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/2015/04/23/native-actors-walk-set-adam-sandler-movie-after-insults-women-elders-160110&quot;&gt;They had been told the movie wasn’t racist, and that the production had hired a Native consultant.&lt;/a&gt; They went ahead in good faith that their culture would be represented respectfully. But once on set, they raised several concerns (inappropriate character names and costumes to name a few) which were summarily dismissed. It would have been bad enough if they &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; had to endure a bunch of people “whitesplaining” what should and shouldn’t offend them. They were then told by producers, “If you’re overly sensitive, you should leave.” Netflix, the company behind the film, released an overly defensive statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;The movie has ridiculous in the title for a reason: because it is ridiculous. It is a broad satire of Western movies and the stereotypes they popularized, featuring a diverse cast that is not only part of — but in on — the joke.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make one thing crystal clear: Adam Sandler wouldn’t recognize satire if it shat in his mouth. But it’s no surprise Netflix is going to stand firm. Last fall they inked a four (!) picture deal with Sandler (who approved of the union, saying &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/netflix-signs-adam-sandler-to-a-4-year-movie-deal-2014-10&quot;&gt;Netflix rhymes with “wet chicks”&lt;/a&gt;), and they aren’t necessarily in the same financial position that bigger studios like Disney and Sony are to weather the kind of box-office stinker that &lt;em&gt;Ridiculous 6&lt;/em&gt; is destined to be, let alone endure three more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, Sandler himself has remained mum on the incident. But his co-star &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rollingstone.com/movies/news/vanilla-ice-on-ridiculous-6-this-movie-isnt-dances-with-wolves-20150427&quot;&gt;Vanilla Ice has leaped to the film’s defense&lt;/a&gt; stating, “I’m part Chocktaw Indian” which is the Native equivalent of saying “I can’t be racist, I have a black friend.” If this was Sandler’s idea, maybe he does have a sense of humour after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, you have a few options, you can admit you’re a horrible person who has helped to line the pockets of a self-loathing, man-child because you also think poking fun at the disenfranchised is the height of comedy. You can admit you’re a stupid person, because you think jokes like, &lt;a href=&quot;http://defamer.gawker.com/these-are-the-jokes-that-caused-actors-to-walk-off-adam-1699990455&quot;&gt;“Say honey, how about after this, we go some place and I put my pee-pee in your tee-pee?”&lt;/a&gt; are funny and you just can’t be bothered to try harder because thinking hurts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can admit that admiring an entitled 48 year-old millionaire doofus who wears cargo shorts and ballcaps is embarrassing, grow the fuck up, and finally make an appointment to get that barbed wire tattoo lasered off. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/30/we-need-to-talk-about-adam.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Unfriended</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Remember that gag in &lt;em&gt;The Simpsons&lt;/em&gt; with Luke Perry analogue Kyle Darren, as a teen heartthrob whose face transforms into a sea of wrinkles when he smiles?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tip my hat to you for being able to avoid the embarrassing spectacle of an actor desperately trying to convince the audience they&amp;#39;re years younger than they appear by casting people who actually resemble high school students. It adds a nice feeling of authenticity, and if there&amp;#39;s one thing I can give &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt; major props for it&amp;#39;s the use of actual search engines and social media sites; nothing ridiculous like FaceParty or YouSearch. Since the entirety of the action unfolds within a teenage girl&amp;#39;s computer monitor as she juggles a Skype group chat with her friends while scouring the internet for advice on how to deal with the vengeance-minded spirit of a former classmate, it&amp;#39;s important that everything feels as real world as possible.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a pretty novel and cool twist on the incredibly tiresome found-footage conceit, and I&amp;#39;ll be honest by saying I was actually kinda anticipating this. Unfortunately, once you take away the flashy window dressing, almost nothing about&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt; works at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, I&amp;#39;m a sucker for revenge stories. Few things satisfy me more than seeing the baddest of the bad receive their much deserved comeuppance. The idea of a girl driven to suicide only to return and punish her tormentors is a pretty solid one, but the way the film executes it feels incredibly confused and problematic. For better and (mostly) worse, you were able to find actors who could hit all the requisite levels of superficiality, despicability, and selfishness I imagine are present amongst many in that age bracket. However, even though it is revealed that our protagonists were somewhat complicit in the events leading up to Laura&amp;#39;s death, nothing about their systematic bumping-off holds any real emotional resonance. They aren&amp;#39;t callous enough for their deaths to feel justified and satisfying, yet on the flipside they don&amp;#39;t even come close to being likeable enough for us to feel sad about what&amp;#39;s happening to them. It all feels pretty hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing as the shenanigans are kicked off by a humiliating video of Laura being posted online, I must commend the filmmakers for having the good taste not to adopt a ripped-from-the-headlines approach and have the footage contain a sexual assault. That said, the video basically amounts to nothing more than Laura getting blackout drunk and having an accident. Embarrassing to be sure, but going on to torment her friends feels oddly unearned. Even more eyebrow raising are the implications that in life Laura may have herself been a bully and her conduct could have been far more egregious than those of her victims&amp;#39;, despite her near endless moral postulating (&amp;quot;You all deserve this, you&amp;#39;re all terrible people&amp;quot;, etc). Other than a minor twist or so towards the end, we have people being punished for basically leaving mean comments on YouTube, and an antagonist whose righteousness completely falls apart under the slightest scrutiny, despite the way the film handles her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, what about the scares, you may ask? I must admit that some of the death scenes are well done and even a little disturbing due to how unexpectedly graphic they are, but even then they&amp;#39;re severely undercut by the ludicrousness that follows. For instance, after witnessing the horrifying death of one of their friends, the survivors proceed to spend what feels like an eternity screaming, &lt;em&gt;screaming&lt;/em&gt; at each other over relatively minor secrets the ghost forces out of them. C&amp;#39;mon guys, big picture. You can argue over who totalled whose truck later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate horror that tries to address real life issues, but &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt; is just a mess on nearly every level. That said, you do have a good eye for age-appropriate casting so hopefully your services will be called upon for the next teen-centric horror exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/28/unfriended.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/28/unfriended.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Far From The Madding Crowd</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In some ways your book &lt;em&gt;Far From The Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; could stand as a proto-feminist manifesto. In other ways, important ways, it is an antecedent to some of the worst melodrama know to humanity. That the two things come together so artlessly in the 2015 film adaptation of your novel is unfortunate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This iteration of &lt;em&gt;Far From The Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; begins well. Your awkwardly named protagonist, Bathsheba Everdene, is fiercely independent and, thanks to a timely inheritance from a doting uncle, beholden to no one. For a woman to be propertied and untethered to any man was a rare circumstance at the end of the 19th Century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the rest of the story is a tangled web of contrivance involving three different Harlequin Romance archetypes. The quiet, self assured cowboy (in this case a shepherd played by Matthias Schoenaerts) the moneyed but damaged bachelor—Michael Sheen, of course—and even a faithless cad of a soldier, played by Tom Sturridge. As the story progresses it becomes hopelessly, and pointlessly, labyrinthine. A film that could have been a fascinating examination of class and gender in Victorian England devolves into a series of romantic mishaps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The names of Bathsheba’s suitors betray a kind of on-the-noseness that is present throughout the narrative: Gabriel Oak as the Shepherd, William Boldwood (I’ll bet it is) as the aging bachelor and Sergeant Troy as the philandering gambler in soldier’s clothing. Even the date of the original publication doesn’t excuse this clumsy wordplay, since there are far too many novels that come from the same period—&lt;em&gt;Jane Eyre&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;War and Peace&lt;/em&gt; just to name two—that rise far above this kind of genre laziness. I have also seen adaptations of &lt;em&gt;Far From the Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; where the tone and the melodrama were circumvented in useful ways—&lt;em&gt;Tamara Drewe&lt;/em&gt; most recently. But this particular version, helmed by director Tomas Vinterberg, is entirely too self-important and earnest to finesse the more leaden aspects of the plot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the performances are uniformly competent, the film itself is beautifully shot and the source material is rich enough that it might have been used to create something far more interesting. But the film falls apart in the last two acts. By choosing to focus on the Bathsheba’s inept management of her personal relationships, Vinterberg undercuts the moments that could have elevated this beyond a high-end gothic romance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are glimpses of what would have been (at the time) seditious egalitarianism as Bathsheba mucks it up with her various employees, literally getting covered in shite—thereby confounding the Monty Python method of identifying the ruling classes. But these become throwaway moments as more and more of the film occupies itself with describing the ungainly four way relationship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a way to make all of this work, I’m sure. But in this instance at least part of the problem is there is far too much story packed into too little time. Either this should have been a mini-series or there should have been some editorial decisions about what the film was going to focus on, because as it exists it is neither beast nor fowl—and that confusion is fatal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adaptations always carry a certain peril—lose the thread and you will be crucified by the fans. Or stick too closely and you run the risk of being hamstrung by the limitations of the original text. In this case a more liberal interpretation of your source material may well have served everyone better. As it stands &lt;em&gt;Far From The Madding Crowd&lt;/em&gt; is a film that is weighed down by a story that once must have felt revolutionary, but now seems trite.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/27/far-from-the-madding-crowd.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/27/far-from-the-madding-crowd.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
