<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Unbroken</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Ideally, when navigating uncharted waters, there’s a team of experts guiding your every move. Otherwise, a seemingly routine mission can spiral out of control and set in motion a life-changing sequence of events. That’s what happened to Louis Zamperini during a rescue effort off the Pacific Coast in the Second World War. It could also have happened to second-time director Angelina Jolie, but she was smart (and lucky) enough to surround herself with some of the best in the business. People like you, Sean, who were looking out for her safety. &lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; for the safety of the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wise choice. And while you’re at it, why not bring in the Coen Brothers to write your script? And Roger Deakins to shoot your film? And William Goldenberg to edit it? That’s more than just “the safe thing to do”—in this case, it helped save the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zamperini was an unlikely hero before he went to war. As the child of non-English speaking Italian immigrants, he scrapped his way through small town bigotry before representing the United States as a long-distance runner at the 1936 Berlin Olympics. His incredible finish in the 5,000 meter race won him worldwide attention—and even a personal meeting with Adolf Hitler (though that scene is omitted from the film; Jolie must have decided it was safer to not have her hero seen shaking hands with the world’s vilest villain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the opening aerial shots – filmed with Deakins’ trademark confidence and perspective realism – we immediately get a sense of the scale and import of the story. The dialogue is sparse, never cute, and dials back much of the bravado that might have crept in (think &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/1/9/lone-survivor.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lone Survivor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Jolie herself has said that she would have never been drawn to that type of macho storytelling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shark attacks, on the other hand? Well, she dove right in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the film is at its best during the lost-at-sea storyline. The danger is more desperate and lonely, and there’s a cosmic cruelty that is detached from any political commentary. As a result, it amplifies every injustice suffered in the latter half of the film.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony, of course, might be that this is a very safe film for mainstream audiences to enjoy over the Christmas break. But, hey, the words “safe” and “cinema” are allowed to go together sometimes, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/29/unbroken.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/29/unbroken.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Night at the Museum: Secret of the Tomb</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Did you know? Could you see the fatigue? Did you spend more time than usual on set? Because from where I was sitting all I could see was a man who seemed emptied out. The word “bereft” and all that it implies was at the forefront of my mind every time he was onscreen. I didn’t love Robin Williams the same way &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/12/dear-robin.html&quot;&gt;many people seemed to&lt;/a&gt;. But I found myself getting pretty upset as I sat and watched his light going out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Night at the Museum: Secret of the Tomb&lt;/em&gt; is most notable for the fact that it’s one of the last films Robin Williams made before ending his life. Otherwise it is a pretty forgettable return to a franchise that is largely...well, forgettable. The whole gang (plus a Neanderthal version of Ben Stiller—don’t ask how that happens) head off to England to...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...never mind. It really isn’t important. There’s a MacGuffin about the moon and Ben Kinsley as Pharaoh and a tablet that looks like an Egyptian iPad, but that’s all just an excuse to change locations to the British Museum in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did the set feel different? In an industry that often eats its young as a matter of course, I sometimes wonder how reptilian you must become to manage. You might actually know, eh, Hugh? You’ve spent a lot of time as the invisible man on set. Your IMDB page reads like the CV of a Ricky Gervais character: Fair Goer (uncredited) &lt;em&gt;Philomena,&lt;/em&gt; Wealthy Gentleman (uncredited) &lt;em&gt;Parks and Recreation,&lt;/em&gt; Hospital visitor (uncredited) &lt;em&gt;Gangsta Granny.&lt;/em&gt; I can’t imagine the bad behavior and prima donna tantrums you must have witnessed (especially on &lt;em&gt;Gangsta Granny&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching this film, for me, was mostly an exercise in trying not to choke up every time Robin Williams appeared onscreen. It felt faintly ghoulish, to be honest; watching a person recently dead struggle through threadbare dialogue while trying to project anything but pathos. The kids in the theatre seemed to enjoy what was in front of them. So there’s that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a moment late in the film when Robin Williams, in the guise of Theodore Roosevelt, turns to Ben Stiller and gives him some advice about the best way to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment is so bursting with sad irony that both my wife and I actually started crying. Yet the children who surrounded us were happily unaware that anything other than a pause in the action was occurring. It was a surreal way to spend two hour so if you’re a parent who has any connection to Robin Williams as a performer, maybe it would be better to take the kids to &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6,&lt;/em&gt; or wait for &lt;em&gt;Into The Woods.&lt;/em&gt; I doubt anyone except the producers of _Night at the Museum: Secret of the Tomb will suffer for your choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for you Hugh, I hope you got to spend a little time with the man Robin Williams used to be—because the Robin Williams I saw up on the screen was the ghost of a person who has yet to pass.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/22/night-at-the-museum-secret-of-the-tomb.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/22/night-at-the-museum-secret-of-the-tomb.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Annie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was nine years old in 1982 when the original film adaptation of &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; came out. For girls my age, this was our &lt;em&gt;Frozen.&lt;/em&gt; We bought the books, the toys, and the cassette tapes. We drove our parents insane shout-singing “Hard-Knock Life” and “Tomorrow” in the backs of station wagons. No one owned VCRs yet – they were ridiculously expensive and roughly the size of a Datsun B210 – so we waited many months to finally see the movie again when it was released on Pay TV. Betamax? No—the one family that owned a Betamax was unceremoniously shunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry for my little nostalgic digression. I hope you were able to follow along despite my ancient technological references. I also hope that a few years from now, when the graphics you designed for the 2014 re-imagining of &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; are hilariously dated, that the story itself will still hold up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wouldn’t bet my vintage Swatch on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 21st Century Annie is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an orphan, as she reminds us throughout the film. She’s a foster kid. She lives in Harlem with her mean foster mom, Miss Hannigan, and five foster sisters, but continues to hold out hope that her real parents will come back for her someday. Annie is saved from an oncoming car by gruff telecom billionaire Will Stacks, who is lagging behind in the city’s mayoral race. Stacks’ handlers convince him to “foster” Annie to help improve his image with voters. While the arrangement starts out as a publicity stunt, Annie and Stacks eventually realize they’ve found the only family either of them has ever known. Their bond is tested when Annie’s supposed parents reappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is a major plot point in &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt;. Stacks’ campaign manager and Girl Friday are perpetually scanning websites to assess how their boss is being portrayed online. When a visit to a soup kitchen goes horribly wrong, the moment is re-played on screens large and small, and is even auto-tuned into a pop song on YouTube. Events happen at lightning speed, and you had to design a constant stream of graphics for Twitter, Google and major news sites. Of course, someone manages to film Stacks saving Annie and it “goes viral.”. In Stacks’ penthouse, a never-ending stream information and images is displayed on floor-to-ceiling screens. Annie can change the graphics in her room from unicorns and glitter to puppies and moonbeams. She chooses to sleep under a desk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say I blame her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1982 &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; is set in New York City during Prohibition, and the film embraces this era completely. The musical numbers reflect that golden age of Hollywood with Busby Berkeley-esque dance routines and over-the-top orchestration. The sheer number of grinning children, adults, and animals crammed into each scene could have only been managed by a director like John Huston. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; is contemporary and urban but feels strangely small—and not in an intimate way. Director Will Gluck missed many opportunities to scale up the song and dance sequences, opting to fill the empty spaces with your dizzying graphics (instead of actual people). Or maybe he thought repeating a flash-mob – like the one he staged for &lt;em&gt;Friends With Benefits&lt;/em&gt; – was just &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The updated songs – and even the originals – capture the film’s saccharine tone perfectly. What Quvenzhane Wallis lacks in vocal chops she makes up for with sheer positivity and charm. She’s the perfect choice for Annie. It would seem the entire cast was chosen less for their singing prowess and more for their bankability. Jamie Foxx can sing, but the fact that he sounds a little too much like R. Kelly doesn’t make his relationship with a young girl any less icky. Poor Cameron Diaz has the toughest shoes to fill. Carol Burnett was a force of nature as the original Miss Hannigan (for a master class in drunk singing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDkEXszYtdo&quot;&gt;see her version of “Little Girls”&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, Cameron isn’t a good enough singer or comedienne to inject the villainous Miss Hannigan with enough malice or pathos to make her as cartoonishly menacing as she needs be. For some reason her backstory involves being bitter at having been kicked out of C+C Music Factory before their first appearance on Arsenio—two references that aren’t getting any fresher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is to imply that you didn’t do a good job. On the contrary.Your detail-rich work is an accurate reflection of the ever-connected world we live in. But that world and its technology is evolving daily, and for a tech-heavy film that can be a liability. The best musicals don’t always have the most intricate librettos or the most elaborate art direction, but they do share one important quality: they’re timeless. &lt;em&gt;Annie&lt;/em&gt; has some fun and clever moments – especially a scene involving a movie premiere and its product tie-ins – but it’s probably not going to be the kind of repeat-viewing hit that Sony was hoping for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, parents of &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/28/frozen.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-addicted kids. You’ll have to wait for a better musical to come along before your kids will finally Let It Go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/20/annie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/20/annie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>2014 Silver Stamps</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Readers,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chasing awards is a fool’s errand. Just when you think AIDS is the new cool, ALS comes along and throws a bucket of ice water (and quantum physics) on your head. The lesson? Keep it fresh. Up the ante. No one wants to be last year’s disease. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s our motto for the Silver Stamps. We can’t keep beating on the same ol’ &lt;em&gt;Man of Steel&lt;/em&gt; drum every year (though we would if we could). So here’s a brand-spanking-new list of winners and losers who helped define the last year in cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 2014 Awards&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Based on Good, Hard Science&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/19/particle-fever.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Particle Fever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Based on Good, Hard Fantasy&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/1/guardians-of-the-galaxy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Inspired by Cosmology&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/1/the-theory-of-everything.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Film Endorsed by Cosmologists&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Example of Why Chivalry is Dead&lt;/strong&gt; – Wes Bentley in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/10/interstellar.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interstallar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Example of Why Sexism is Alive&lt;/strong&gt; – Every Character in &lt;em&gt;Sin City 2: A Dame to Kill For&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Unintentionally Meta Film in The Unofficial Year of Meta Films –&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/20/open-windows.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Windows&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trailer of the Year, Sponsored by Spoilerphobes Anonymous&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Red Band version)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Breakers Award for Most Conflicted Boner&lt;/strong&gt; – tie: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/28/nymphomanic-vol-1-and-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nymphomaniac&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under the Skin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Overlooked, Underseen, and Confusingly Marketed Film of the Year&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/6/edge-of-tomorrow.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edge of Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (aka. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Live. Die. Repeat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Man-Crush 2014&lt;/strong&gt; – Jake Gyllenhall for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/11/enemy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enemy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Inspiring Return to Form&lt;/strong&gt; – Jim Carrey in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/14/dumb-and-dumber-to.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dumb and Dumber To&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Runner Up: Keanu Reeves in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/30/john-wick.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Depressing Return to Form&lt;/strong&gt; – Arnold Schwarzenegger in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/15/sabotage.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Runner Up: Michael Bay for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/27/transformers-age-of-extinction.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transformers: Age of Distinction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proving that Franchises Can Actually End:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/content/2014/12/17/the-hobbit-the-battle-of-the-five-armies.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hobbit: The Battle of the Five Armies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proving that Everything is Now a Franchise:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/18/big-hero-6.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Inexplicably Improved Franchise&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/21/planes-fire-rescue.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planes: Fire &amp;amp; Rescue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Incongruous Musical Score&lt;/strong&gt; – James Newton Howard, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/29/nightcrawler.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightcrawler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Prison Break Action Sequence:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/30/x-men-days-of-future-past.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;X-Men: Days of Future Past&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second-Best Prison Break Action Sequence&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/10/the-raid-2-berendal.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raid 2:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Berendal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third-Best Prison Break Action Sequence:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/1/guardians-of-the-galaxy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst Sequel in a Year of Terrible Sequels:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Sequel in a Year of Great Sequels&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trip to Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Jared Young: Osage County Award for Wildly Overpraising Sub-Par Cinema&lt;/strong&gt; (Presented by Christopher Redmond) – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/1/the-trip-to-italy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trip To Italy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Man of Steel&lt;/em&gt; Award for Total Incompetence in Comic Book Adaptations:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Enjoyable Earworm:&lt;/strong&gt; “Everything is Awesome” from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/2/7/the-lego-movie.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lego Movie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Authentically Canadian Film:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/18/the-grand-seduction.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Grand Seduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst Faux-Canadian Film:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/16/tusk.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tusk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitchiest Heartthrob Performance of the Year:&lt;/strong&gt; Andrew Garfield in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Dead-Eyed Heartthrob Performance of the Year:&lt;/strong&gt; Aaron Taylor-Johnston in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/16/godzilla.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst Excuse For A Studio To Fund A Star’s Safari Vacation&lt;/strong&gt;:  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/5/23/blended.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blended&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Performance Of An Evil Dystopian Leader Masquerading As A Benign Mother Figure&lt;/strong&gt;: Three-way tie – Meryl Streep in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/the-giver.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Kate Winslet in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/3/22/divergent.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; Patricia Clarkson in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/10/7/the-maze-runner.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 3rd Annual Roger Deakins Award for Excellence in Being Roger Deakins&lt;/strong&gt; – Roger Deakins for &lt;em&gt;Unbroken&lt;/em&gt; (sight-unseen)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st Annual Jeff Bridges Award for Excellence In Bridgearian Acting&lt;/strong&gt;: Jeff Bridges in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/the-giver.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How’d we do? Make your own nominations below before December 31, 2014 and we’ll include some of our favourites in our official list!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/18/2014-silver-stamps.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/18/2014-silver-stamps.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Hobbit: The Battle of the Five Armies</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Has any major filmmaker of the last two decades followed a stranger and sadder path than Peter Jackson? It seemed as if his journey from schlock-horror cult director to the godfather of digital spectacle was going to be analogous to the one taken by the stalwart band of hobbits in the &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy. But it turns out that Jackson is more corruptible man than incorruptible hobbit. Like Prince Isildur, he’s been seduced by unlimited power. In this case, the power of the pixel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see why Jackson might identify with those hairy-footed Shirefolk: he comes from a small, out-of-the-way place (New Zealand), he’s pretty hairy himself, and he made a name for himself by accomplishing a seemingly unconquerable task: making epic high-fantasy relevant in a post-9/11 world. When &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Return of the King&lt;/em&gt; won the Oscar for Best Picture in 2003, Jackson seemed destined for membership in the modern pantheon of cinematic deities alongside guys like James Cameron, Ridley Scott, and, of course, Steven Spielberg. I wasn’t the only who had high expectations. But Jackson’s directorial output, since then, has provided exponentially diminishing returns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; was bloated, visually overindulgent, and just barely managed to retain a bit of the sweet sentimentality that made &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Lord of the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Rings&lt;/em&gt; more than just geek-bait VFX-porn. &lt;em&gt;The Lovely Bones&lt;/em&gt; was likewise bloated, visually overindulgent, and awash in near-diabetic levels of that sweetness. So Jackson, seeking firmer ground (one supposes), returned to the scene of his past successes: Middle Earth. But upon his return it seems he has forgotten some of the basic tenets of filmic storytelling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new Hobbit trilogy, which concludes with &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit: Battle of the Five Armies&lt;/em&gt;, Jackson’s once-lovely floating camera has become unmoored. It plummets and spins and turns sickening spirals around tiny digital figures surrounded by unintelligible spaces and incalculable masses of moving objects. Shooting characters small in the frame can be, when used sparingly, a dramatic way to establish scale. But the camera, here, remains at such a remove, and the frame is filled with such incomprehensible digital chicanery, that sitting through these films feels akin to watching a friend hack and chop his/her way through increasingly cluttered levels of a slick-looking video game. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, no, you’re right, Akshay: making pejorative comparisons to “being like a video game” is a lazy way to frame the complaint. But even though video game cut-scenes have appropriated the language and rhythm of film (visual images shot by a subjective virtual camera, edited together to form a narrative sequence), films shouldn’t look like cut-scenes; in games they serve as a narrative bridge from one controllable moment to the next. In mainstream gaming, no mater how well-crafted or compelling, the narrative is still subtext: interactivity is the primary text. In film, what we see and hear onscreen is the primary text. And when what we see and hear onscreen is this shallow, this indistinct, this two-dimensional (oh, the irony!), it feels less like an interaction with a piece of art than it does a &lt;em&gt;Clockwork Orange&lt;/em&gt;-style sensory resilience test. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is &lt;em&gt;Hobbit: The Battle of the Five Armies&lt;/em&gt; the worst offender of these new films? Not necessarily. But if I’m going to defend the &lt;em&gt;Inception&lt;/em&gt;-like nested endings of &lt;em&gt;ROTK&lt;/em&gt; by arguing that the entire trilogy is one long tale told in three chapters, and that the resolution(s) of that final film are perfectly in scale with the scope of the story that preceded it, then I must also treat these new Hobbit flicks as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, I’m happy that Jackson has had a chance to reunite with his old pals. Ian McKellen, Cate Blanchett, Christopher Lee, Orlando Bloom—they’ve all returned to reprise their roles, despite the fact that none of them (with the exception of Gandalf) actually appear in Tolkien’s book. The presence of these familiar faces is justified by paper-thin subplots that Jackson and his writing team have cobbled together from the deepest of Tolkien deep cuts—which speaks, I think, to his desperation to recreate the magic of the first three films. Poor Blanchett looks particularly embarrassed to be back: Galadriel was always the most supernaturally composed of the trilogy’s regal figures, but in this latest film she’s just another strutting action hero, appearing briefly in a superfluous fight sequence that also, laughably, features 92 year-old Christopher Lee flipping and spin-kicking like a Tekken avatar being controlled by your hyperactive little brother. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I feel sorriest for Orlando Bloom, though, who is ostensibly playing a centuries-younger version of himself, yet looks as worn and swollen as Jackson’s increasingly unimpressive shots of armies cresting hilltops at magic hour.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about Peter Jackson, we should be talking about him as a peer of Christopher Nolan, not as a peer of Michael Bay. But judging his place in the spectrum of contemporary filmmakers by these last three movies, he’s erring heavily towards the latter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Akshay, why am I telling you all this? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing IT support for the vast array of interconnected computers required to design and render this dog’s breakfast of orcs, trolls, goblins, eagles, bats, elves, dwarves, caribou, hogs, castles, villages, mountain strongholds, neo-brutalist fortresses, and oceans of gold coins is no small feat. It’s a thankless, taxing job. But it isn’t necessarily an &lt;em&gt;influential&lt;/em&gt; job. There’s a good chance you’ve never even met Peter Jackson. Which is why you’re perfect for this mission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need you to get some friends together. Some food, too (might I suggest a calorie-rich ethnic bread?). And some supplies (rope, mithril). You’re going to undertake a vital, perilous task: to venture into the heart of Wellington, New Zealand – to the headquarters of WETA Digital – and press CTL+ALT+DLT on the entire system. It is an evil fate, yes. You will be expected to find a way where the great ones cannot or dare not go. But when all seems lost, when all bonds of fellowship are broken, just remember: even the smallest person can change the course of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 18:01:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/17/the-hobbit-the-battle-of-the-five-armies%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/17/the-hobbit-the-battle-of-the-five-armies%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Canada’s Hottest Filmmaker is Making a Hollywood Movie — and a Classic Mistake</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Xavier Dolan,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop! Please, I beg you. Stop before it’s too late. Don’t make your next film. At least don’t make the one everyone’s talking about.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get it. Your career has never been hotter. Your films have never earned more praise. There’s never been a better time to make your English-language Hollywood debut. Casting news is coming out almost daily, and people are excited. They &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be exited. The names you’re attracting are a dream team of female talent: Jessica Chastain, Susan Sarandon, Kathy Bates. Yet all I can do is cringe. I’m a huge &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/11/7/mommy.html&quot;&gt;fan of your films&lt;/a&gt; and an unabashed supporter of Canadian cinema—which is why I’m crushed by a sense of déjà vu. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every director dreams about making a Hollywood film. Bigger budgets, bigger stars, bigger audience. Which is totally understandable. But time and time again, celebrated Canadian filmmakers don’t just make Hollywood films—they make films &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; Hollywood. And they tend to suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denys Arcand started the sorry trend with &lt;em&gt;Stardom&lt;/em&gt; (2000), a looping, messy, fish-eyed look at overnight success starring a then-unknown Jessica Paré (a.k.a. Megan Draper on &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;). Two years later, Deepa Mehta took a crack at mainstreaming her career with &lt;em&gt;Bollywood/Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; (2002), which was set in Canada (and also featured Paré), but tried to have its curry-flavoured apple pie and eat it too. Soon after, Don McKellar was inspired by meeting Haley Joel Osment on a red carpet and followed-up his fantastic, distinctly Canadian directorial debut &lt;em&gt;Last Night&lt;/em&gt; (1998) with the lousy and forgettable &lt;em&gt;Childstar&lt;/em&gt; (2004). Not to be outdone, Atom Egoyan looked south to break his own self-imposed filmmaking curse by casting Kevin Bacon and Colin Firth in the showbiz period piece &lt;em&gt;Where the Truth Lies&lt;/em&gt; (2005), which today is remembered (if at all) only for the threesome scene that temporarily earned the film an NC-17 rating. And this year the Godfather of Canadian Cinema David Cronenberg comes out with &lt;em&gt;Maps to the Stars&lt;/em&gt; (2014), which has been a box-office disappointment, considering the cast, but revered by at least some critics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now you’ve announced &lt;em&gt;The Death and Life of John F. Donovan&lt;/em&gt;. The plot synopsis: “an American movie star finds his correspondence with an 11-year-old actor exposed, prompting assumptions that begin to destroy his life and career.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m scared, man. History is not on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just Canadians who have a hard time making films about Hollywood. &lt;em&gt;Everyone&lt;/em&gt; does. There’s scarcely a film this side of Robert Altman’s &lt;em&gt;The Player&lt;/em&gt; (1992) that is even worth mentioning. &lt;em&gt;The Artist&lt;/em&gt; (2011) would be an exception: a black and white ode to the silent era, which, ironically, sounds like it could only have been pulled off by Canada’s Guy Maddin (it was actually a French film by Michel Hazanavicius). But skewering the already absurd just doesn’t seem to pay dividends to anyone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, another Canadian filmmaking trend you could follow. Fellow Quebecois directors Jean-Marc Vallée (&lt;em&gt;Dallas Buyers Club&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;), Philippe Falardeau (&lt;em&gt;The Good Lie&lt;/em&gt;), Ken Scott (&lt;em&gt;Delivery Man&lt;/em&gt;) and Denis Villeneuve (&lt;em&gt;Enemy, Prisoners&lt;/em&gt;) are all making a real go at it stateside, creating interesting genre films that are still thematically linked to (or, in Scott’s case, a direct remake of) their projects back home. To varying degrees, it seems to be working. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re better equipped than most to make larger-than-life characters connect with an audience. Heightened personal drama is your bread and butter. So I have no doubt you’ll get incredible performances from your A-list stars. And at age 25 (dear God), chances are you’ll get a couple of cracks at it even if this film doesn’t pan out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because you’re so young, you need to know that this project is much higher risk than you think. It’s not your fault – it’s hereditary. I’m begging you: please don’t repeat the sins of your forefathers. After all, we’re counting on you for the future of &lt;em&gt;Canadian&lt;/em&gt; cinema.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/16/canadas-hottest-filmmaker-is-making-a-hollywood-movie-and-a-classic-mistake.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/16/canadas-hottest-filmmaker-is-making-a-hollywood-movie-and-a-classic-mistake.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Exodus: Gods and Kings</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At the very least, they got &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; right. In a film that is tonally flat and visually bloated, you’re pitch perfect: jealous, capricious, and inscrutable. Old Testament God as genocidal child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ridley Scott has always been one of &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; directors, the kind whose films you see simply because they’re involved. Or perhaps he &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; to be one of those directors. Because &lt;em&gt;Exodus: Gods and Kings&lt;/em&gt; is a mess. It’s a film marred by uneven pacing, a wasted cast (Sigourney Weaver has three, maybe four lines), and long stretches of monotonous exposition. Christian Bale and Joel Edgerton, the leads, feel like expedient choices, as if Scott had to sell the idea to the studios rather than pick the actors who would work best (in fact, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thewrap.com/exodus-director-ridley-scott-explains-controversial-casting-decision/&quot;&gt;he’s admitted as much&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder, perhaps, if biblical epics are simply prone to this kind of weird mixture of hubris and lazy storytelling. It has permeated the genre almost from the very beginning. The cultural ubiquity of the core stories, even when married with spectacle, can’t quite cover up the gossamer thin characterization and laughably sloppy plot contrivances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind of like the source material when you really think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are the single redeeming feature for me, Yahweh. Your brief, enigmatic interactions with Moses are sharp and interesting. They give &lt;em&gt;Exodus: Gods and Kings&lt;/em&gt; a narrative focus that is otherwise lacking throughout the film. There is a chemistry between you and your initially reluctant prophet. For a few moments we see something resembling real human emotion on screen, even if it comes from a pissed off pre-teen deity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not the case in the rest of the two-plus hours of this particular Ridley Scott production. He has had a pretty good track record picking his leads, but his last three or four films – &lt;em&gt;Robin Hood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/content/2012/6/12/prometheus.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prometheus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/content/2013/11/7/the-counselor.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Counselor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – have all seemed slightly miscast despite the star power each of them boast. Here it’s no different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott, like much of the Old Testament work you inspired, depends a great deal on conjuring a sound and fury that ultimately signifies nothing. Why bother making this film? It’s just a limp, episodic re-telling of a familiar story bereft of any motivating force—there is simply no THERE there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the bible without belief, a myth that doesn’t revel in it’s own fantasy. Unlike Aronofsky’s &lt;em&gt;Noah,&lt;/em&gt; which clearly saw God as metaphor rather than immanent – more Spinoza than Augustine, if you will – this film doesn’t really take a stance one way or another. Your depiction as an impatient, powerful adolescent sits in a weird vacuum since the rest of the movie doesn’t reflect that sensibility at all. Which is too bad, since that might have been a film worth seeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead Scott seems to have borrowed from your playbook: neglecting narrative discipline for a kind of meandering hodgepodge of contradictory and incoherent exposition, then trying to pull it all together with a big ending. An ending, which while beautiful and awe inspiring, is ultimately empty. None of it means a thing if you lose us in the first act. And I just didn’t buy it from the genesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/12/exodus-gods-and-kings.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/12/exodus-gods-and-kings.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Fading Gigolo</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite things about listening to vinyl records was poring over the back of LP covers looking for familiar names. I was always pleasantly surprised when famous musicians lent backing vocals or guitar licks to a friend’s album, like John Lennon on Bowie’s &lt;em&gt;Fame&lt;/em&gt;, or Nile Rogers on the Vaughan Brothers’ &lt;em&gt;Family Style&lt;/em&gt;. I imagined that these mates jamming together gave the songs a relaxed, loose vibe. Sure, the songs weren’t necessarily the artists’ best work, but you could always feel the love coming through the speakers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same thing can be said of John Turturro’s &lt;em&gt;Fading Gigolo&lt;/em&gt;. He brought a lot of friends to the jam session and they didn’t hit all the notes, but the result was still kinda catchy in spite of itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turturro plays Fioravante, a mild-mannered florist having money issues. His best friend Murray proposes he pimp out Fioravante to his doctor who is interested in having a threesome Soon Fioravante has built up a clientele, but falls for Avigal, the widow of a Hassidic Rabbi which leads to a cacophony of moral conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, I’m curious if you met John through the Coen brothers. You’ve both worked for them so many times it would seem likely that you’ve run into each other on occasion. Turturro turned in many iconic performances like the titular &lt;em&gt;Barton Fink&lt;/em&gt;, and the scene-stealing Jesus in &lt;em&gt;Big Lebowski&lt;/em&gt;. Your job was to secure musical clearances for &lt;em&gt;No Country For Old Men&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Inside Llewyn Davis&lt;/em&gt; to name a few&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; The Coen’s music is just as carefully considered and executed as their characterizations of men pushing at the boundaries of their existence. Similarly, the choices you made for the music in &lt;em&gt;Fading Gigolo&lt;/em&gt; are deliberate and evocative. Standards like Dean Martin’s &lt;em&gt;Sway&lt;/em&gt;, playfully sexy tango numbers, and original jazz compositions all add to the lush world Fioravante inhabits. It’s a shame that Fioravante just lays there dead on the page. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We never learn enough about Fioravante to be truly invested in his journey. The interplay between he and Woody Allen’s pitch perfect Murray sounds like a well rehearsed duet. When Murray turns Fioravante out a little too easily and without much resistance, Turturro misses a chance to show us some of Fioravante’s depth. Instead, he rushes headlong into his role as unconventional lothario and the arms of Sharon Stone’s unfulfilled Dr. Parker. They slow dance to a soft jazz selection, which showcases your curating skills and Dr. Parker’s vulnerability, but leaves Fioravante a dull mystery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music, as with the earthy set design, and the elegantly textural jewel-toned costuming, create a rich and sensual backdrop that make up for the flat characters and the somewhat improbable plot. We’re never exactly sure why Fioravante falls for pious Avigal, or why Murray sets them up in the first place. Luckily, watching a talented cast – including Vanessa Paradis, Liev Schreiber, Sofia Vergara – wander through New York City accompanied by songs from jazz greats Dalida and Gene Ammons isn’t entirely unpleasant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit I’m not a big jazz aficionado, but I’ve learned that the best way to enjoy it is to just let it waft over me like a warm breeze. When I do that, there doesn’t need to be an obvious structure, or beginning, middle and end for me to appreciate the assembled components. I felt the same way watching this film. If I tried too hard to find the melody I might have missed out on some inspired solos, yours included. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/11/fading-gigolo.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/11/fading-gigolo.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Third Person</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A good love story is hard to beat. So the promise of three separate yet intricately connected love stories must be even better, right? That’s what Paul Haggis promises us in &lt;em&gt;Third Person&lt;/em&gt;, a film that follows three couples in Paris, Rome, and New York. The initial draw is wondering how everything will tie together in the end. Which is great, except that the “twist” is given away quite early in a bit of ham-handed dialogue, leaving us with a meditation on the fictions we create and what – and who – we choose to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is anchored by Michael, an author struggling with his new book, and his muse/protegé/lover Anna, who toy with each other&amp;#39;s hearts and minds in a Paris hotel. In Rome, grumpy American Scott meets the mysterious Monika, a Roma woman trying to rescue her daughter from a human trafficking ring. And in New York, Julia struggles to rebuild her life while battling her ex-husband for custody of their son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I picture the storyboards you created for the film, I see roughly-sketched panels that place characters where they need to be, indicate what they’re  and doing what they need to be doing at various points, without getting into any detail as to who they are, who they will become, or what motivates them. At that point in the process, they might just be stick figures or vague, featureless shapes. The fleshing out of the characters comes much later. Or at least it&amp;#39;s supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first act places everyone at a blank, dead-eyed starting point. Once we are sufficiently informed that everyone is sad about something, connections start to develop, and relationships are established. I began to be slightly charmed by some of what was taking shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfway through, it feels like someone abruptly realized the characters &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to be sad and angry, and the witty banter and flirting suddenly lapses into silences that I imagine are supposed to be brooding and/or pensive, but are really just flat and uninteresting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time each character has a Big Emotional Climax, it doesn&amp;#39;t quite fit with how they have developed thus far. Haggis knows where he wants his characters to end up, but the sudden shift from subtle, slow-burning character study to overwrought, hysterical dialogue and action is too jarring to make their journey engaging. The film goes from quiet contemplation to high melodrama so fast I was left wondering what the hell just happened. The plot twists feel like cantaloupes thrown at my head by someone yelling, &amp;quot;Here is a shocking twist! Be shocked now!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characters do and say a lot, and there are a few moments in which you see a glimmer of chemistry or life, especially in the Michael-Anna relationship. But for all the heavy-handed dialogue and over-the-top emoting, they remain the fleshless, featureless figures in a storyboard panel that merely serve as bland points of reference and scale for the image being constructed. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/10/third-person.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/10/third-person.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Babadook</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The best genre films are never by-the-numbers. They employ the comfort of convention as a way to explore deeper issues. Sci-fi, for example, is always richer as allegory. The most piercing comedy is often the simple result of tragedy plus time. Yet horror films are too often satisfied with immediate, visceral thrills—the kind of generic cinematic experience a “casual” director might be satisfied delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Babadook&lt;/em&gt; proves that Jennifer Kent is no casual director. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny, then, that she hired two “casual” ADs for this film. That word, both in North America and Australia (where &lt;em&gt;The Babadook&lt;/em&gt; was shot) can of course have multiple meanings. Perhaps you were only there on a part-time basis. After all, the film doesn’t feature any big international stars and was made for a modest 2 million. But “casual” also has more negative connotations: from unplanned, to superficial, to indifferent. None of which apply to the filmmaking I witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Babadook&lt;/em&gt; is a careful and considered entry into the crowded supernatural thriller genre. It can “casually” be described like a thousand other films: a mother tries to convince her child that the monster he is seeing in their house isn’t real—until, of course, the sinister force becomes too powerful to deny. As an entry point, that might be all the audience needs. But I hope you, at least, realized that the premise is actually an excellent way to explore PTSD, grappling with grief, and the pressures of being a single parent. None of that sounds too sexy for the poster, but in the same way the Babadook monster is explained through a hand-made pop-up kids book, the very menacing truth behind the message is what makes the film so haunting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also must have taken note, even in your cursory position, that Kent had structured her screenplay like an exorcism film, but made it secularized, and, ultimately, internalized. This evil-within-us approach is much more chilling, and brilliantly reinforced by one of those inexplicable news reports about a mother’s murder-suicide with her children. That simple injection of a familiar real-world horror story makes the fear very personal and much less outlandish that it could have been. In fact, the slow-burn of the film’s first act, devoid of any scares (earned or cheated), establishes believable characters in a recognizable world, all of which enhances the more fantastical events of the the following acts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two central performances by Essie Davis and the seven-year-old Noah Wiseman are easily the most memorable aspects of the film. But they’re also serviced by the perfectly atmospheric low-light cinematography, the rigorous art direction (with a strict adherence to moody colour palettes), and the subdued sound design that never once gives us cat-jumping false alarm jitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe your position makes sense. I can see how, after making a short film based on the same story almost a decade ago, Jennifer Kent might hire a couple young aspiring directors for her first feature film, sit back, and casually say: “Don’t worry. I got this shit.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/12/8/the-babadook.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
