<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Sunshine Superman</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m so so so sorry. I don&#39;t know what happened to me. Well, yes I do. I was rushing into the screening - pulled pork sandwich dripping in-hand - because I didn&#39;t want to miss a moment. Good thing, too, because the visual treats in Sunshine Superman come fast and early. You couldn&#39;t ask for a more visual subject than a documentary about the first BASE jumpers. Especially one that follows Carl, and accomplished director of (free-fall) photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as I sat there being consumed by the story, I also had to wolf down some lunch. Quickly, too, so I could capture some quotes from these odd balls in the late 70s who parachuted off cliffs and buildings. And as the story reached it&#39;s ominous ending, I couldn&#39;t dare leave. Which is why, in the film&#39;s most dramatic and extended silent pause, I accidentally let one rip. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not in my head. People turned around three rows away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, I&#39;m coming clean. If someone complains that the screening stunk, it wasn&#39;t the film. It was me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-2-sunshine-superman.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-2-sunshine-superman.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Force Majeure</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This is what I come here to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Force Majeure made waves at Cannes, and deserves a much bigger audience than the Swedish family drama will probably find. Tense and hilarious, Ruben Östlund has crafted a damn-near perfect exploration of modern masculinity and heterosexual relationships. The film is laser-focused on the very filmic principle that action reveals character, and entertainingly explores how a single instinct can overpower our entire understanding of a another human being. If only the film had stuck to its guns and ended one scene earlier to maintain the principle indictment, I would have fallen for the film whole-heatedly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-postcard-1-force-majeure.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Two</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Friday, September 5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-2014-day-two.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-2014-day-two.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Dead Lands</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The first ever film in the Maori language? And it’s all about Maori warriors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sign me up!&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This film was getting some nice buzz before the festival, largely because it was singled out by your head programmer, Cameron Bailey, as one to watch. But does it elevate itself past the novelty factor of a Kiwi beefcake action film? Not really. But it doesn&#39;t disappoint, either. The (many) fight scenes aren&#39;t always well framed, but it&#39;s satisfyingly bloody and often eye-opening (watching a Maori warrior take a shit on the skull of his ancestor will have that effect). All the macho posturing before battle – the literal tongue-wagging – worked for me, and represents the kind of fare you showcase so well: audience-friendly films that might otherwise get lost in the shuffle. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-3-the-dead-lands%20copy.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-3-the-dead-lands%20copy.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Whiplash</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What a perfect way to kick-off the festival. (No, I&#39;m not taking about The Judge.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whiplash was the first film I actually saw this year, since it played for the press as part of Thursday&#39;s programming of previously premiered films.  And, wow, did it ever live up to the Sundance hype.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Miles Teller gives a career-defining performance as an aspiring concert drummer. On top of his own ridiculous musical talents, which simply can&#39;t be faked, he manages to endear us with the same laser focus as writer/director Damien Chazelle, who has crafted a film that demonstrates a wisdom beyond his relatively young 29 years. As one might expect in a film about jazz rhythm, the pace is wonderfully unpredictable; the big moments are somehow expected and surprising, and the ending is a white-knuckle marvel. A must-see for every aspiring musician and fan of small, marvellous films.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-2-whiplash.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Judge</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;What does the official opening night film say about this year&#39;s festival? Everything, really. Safe, standard, and, if nothing else, reliable. The Judge parallels my overall feelings about this year&#39;s line-up in both form and content. There are solid performances, a bevy of stars, a mix between moments of artistic flourish and populist appeal, and a well-worn script that teeters on being overlong without ever actually being boring.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Of course, we all know the opener plays a very particular role here. You want to set a celebratory tone, while only teasing what&#39;s to come. However, between the new get-tough-on-premieres stance and outright scoops by the New York Film Festival (taking both David Fincher and P.T. Anderson&#39;s new titles), I fear that the real story this year will be the films that you&#39;re not playing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-1-the-judge.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-postcard-1-the-judge.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day One</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Thursday, September 4.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-2014-day-one.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-2014-day-one.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing coverage from the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-2014.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/tiff-2014.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>As Above So Below</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll admit it was a bit disappointing to learn that, contrary to what the promotional materials told us, the bulk of action in your new film As Above, So Below took place not in the famous Paris catacombs, but rather a series of offshoot tunnels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a set designer, it must come as a blow when you come onboard a project only to be told there will be no need for the liberal use of skulls as a decorative feature. Which, for this movie, feels especially like a missed opportunity. That said, like the oppressive stone labyrinth our protagonists find themselves trapped in, the whole film feels remarkably solid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get over the lack of skulls, one of As Above&amp;#39;s greatest strengths is the constant sense of unease and claustrophobia evoked by your sets; everything feels appropriately dark and cramped. Unlike past efforts like, say, The Cave, which was home to an underground system so spacious and well-lit there could have been a Starbucks tucked inside it. Also worth noting is the creepiness generated by the increasingly confusing geography of the tunnels as they begin looping back in on themselves—and even breaking all rational laws. The surviving leads are faced with the realization that the only way of reaching the surface is heading ever downwards.  It&amp;#39;s a pretty dynamite setting for a horror movie, and despite the lack of elaborate set decoration, it never feels cheap. You can definitely pat yourself on the back for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have to say that I was a bit surprised by how downplayed the actual horror elements are. It feels like a spiritual successor to Indiana Jones more than anything.  We get an opening scene establishing our heroine as a borderline lunatic willing to risk her life exploring a tomb set for demolition, then plenty o&amp;#39; cryptic riddle-solving as a documentarian films her team in their search for the Philosopher&amp;#39;s Stone, an artifact of untold power in the field of alchemy. It&amp;#39;s a good setup, and combined with the likeable (though admittedly one-dimensional) characters, it&amp;#39;s just enough to keep our attention before the scary shenanigans get under way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know about you, but I appreciated that the filmmakers didn&amp;#39;t needlessly explain the nature of the threat facing our intrepid explorers. There is mention of past sins coming back to haunt them, and the possibility is raised that they are, in fact, traversing Hell—but other than this, there&amp;#39;s no needless exposition. In fact, the horror here is most effective when it’s at its quietest: childhood items inexplicably appearing in the depths, creepy calls on rotary telephones, half-glimpsed apparitions, etc.  Too bad that the final twenty minutes or so devolve into the worst attributes of a found footage film, with lots of confused running around and the sudden appearance of hooded weirdos.  This loses much of the goodwill the film earns—though at least you make up for it with a satisfyingly non-tragic ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing I&amp;#39;d like to mention, because I&amp;#39;m very curious as to what happened on the set during that particular bit where a certain someone gets trapped in a crevice and has a prolonged panic attack before it begins to cave-in.  It&amp;#39;s certainly uncomfortable to watch, but also very clearly lifted from The Descent.  Is this a case of cinematic plagiarism? Or perhaps an homage of some kind?  Whatever the case, it&amp;#39;s incredibly distracting for anyone who has seen both films. I’m curious to know what your thoughts are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I&amp;#39;d say this film belongs squarely in the realm of in-one-ear-out-the-other entertainment, but it&amp;#39;s certainly watchable, and you can definitely do worse when it comes to end of summer fare. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/as-above-so-below.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/4/as-above-so-below.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Summer of 2014: The Revisitation</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our brief cinematic fling is over, and it’s time to look back on what we had together. Sure, I wasn’t your only lover. But where others chose to only &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/21/summer-of-2014.html&quot;&gt;look back on your biggest “objective” achievements and lament what could have been&lt;/a&gt;, I thought – hey wait, that’s no way to talk to a lover. Our affair was more nuanced and complex than that. Behind the predictable victories of Marvel and Disney movies at the box-office, there’s a more interesting story to be told. So let me fill in the cracks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, too many people have overlooked your best offering of the season. Maybe they simply assumed &lt;em&gt;Edge of Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;’s generic title was the sign of a generic product. Even the Warner Bros. marketing department seems to &lt;a href=&quot;http://thedissolve.com/news/2991-wait-edge-of-tomorrow-has-become-live-die-repeat-a/&quot;&gt;realize this mistake&lt;/a&gt;. Yet its certainly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/6/edge-of-tomorrow.html&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;the most fun I’ve had at the movies all summer&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; and gave me everything I could hope for in a big budget summer spectacle. And still, it was trounced at the box-office by a teenage romance with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/23/the-fault-in-our-stars.html&quot;&gt;comparatively unknown stars and faultless adherence to the genre&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what, though? My enthusiasm for the film wasn’t diminished by its returns at the box-office.  It does, however, highlight the way Marvel is creating a monopoly on what qualifies as a blockbuster film. Even the critical praise for &lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt; is mostly measured against other Marvel films. I certainly don’t mind visiting the Marvel universe, but I sure as hell don’t actually want to live in it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fellas have taken an unhealthy ownership of summer movies. We act like every film that doesn’t perfectly transport us back to being 13 years old &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/4/30/the-amazing-spider-man-2.html&quot;&gt;is a failure&lt;/a&gt; (even if the box-office says otherwise), and every film that energizes a female fan base is the end of cinema (see every &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; film—which, &lt;em&gt;mea culpa&lt;/em&gt;, we don’t even bother to review). This might be why two films this summer, both coincidentally starring Scarlett Johansson, were overlooked. One is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/6/11/under-the-skin.html&quot;&gt;striking technical achievement&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/31/he-said-she-said-dissecting-the-gender-politics-of-under-the.html&quot;&gt;challenging think-piece on gender politics&lt;/a&gt;, and the other is a rare female-lead action film that managed to destroy even &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/13/hercules.html&quot;&gt;Dwayne Johnson as the mighty &lt;em&gt;Hercules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the box-office. The story of &lt;em&gt;Under the Skin&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Lucy&lt;/em&gt; are both equally essential to assessing your true value to the cinematic landscape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people may have skipped the theatre completely on those non-Marvel opening weekends, but overall the box-office outlook really isn’t that bad. Yes, a 15 percent drop is large, but considering last year was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/seasonal/&quot;&gt;highest grossing summer of all-time&lt;/a&gt;, the sky is hardly falling. Plus, if last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/21/catching-fire.html&quot;&gt;dystopian vision of the future&lt;/a&gt; was any indication, the biggest earner of the year is yet to come with &lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mockingjay:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;. Presumably, another film with a strong female lead (well, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/24/the-hunger-games.html&quot;&gt;in the first film&lt;/a&gt;, anyway) coming after a year when Disney finally found a runaway hit by making it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/11/28/frozen.html&quot;&gt;cool to be a princess again&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t deemed suitable to your season, maybe we should forgive the relatively lackluster theatrical performance of another extreme winter picture like &lt;em&gt;Snowpiercer&lt;/em&gt;. Or better yet, we could look to understand how&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.indiewire.com/thompsononhollywood/exclusive-harvey-weinstein-explains-how-snowpiercer-became-a-gamechanger-we-crunch-theater-vs-vod-numbers-20140721&quot;&gt;revolutionary it actually was&lt;/a&gt; to have a multi-platform release of a major studio title. For once, box-office numbers don’t tell the whole story. Especially for a film with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/3/snowpiercer.html&quot;&gt;hard R rating&lt;/a&gt; that is never going to draw in the 13-year-olds necessary for a four quadrant hit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should really stop knocking boyhood though. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/5/boyhood.html&quot;&gt;I loved that film&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m trying to say is that our annual love affair may be over, but you gave me more than I was willing to admit. I just hope I can convince others of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/2/summer-of-2014-the-revisitation.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
