<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Superman v Star Wars: The Blockbuster Awakens</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Two movie trailers set the internet ablaze last week. At the annual Star Wars Celebration festival in Anaheim, director J.J. Abrams debuted the second &lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; trailer to an auditorium full of eager fans. Earlier that same afternoon, in what you might call a teaser for the teaser of the trailer, Zack Snyder offered a few quick (and rather feckless) clips from &lt;em&gt;Batman&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;v Superman: Dawn of Justice&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this pageantry and playing coy is considered best practice for film marketers; trailer releases have become almost as important as the actual release of the film—and probably &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; important to those opening weekend numbers than the actual quality of the film. But these two particular trailers –in the aesthetics they purport to represent and the manner in which they were debuted – are indicative of two very different attitudes towards the contemporary Hollywood blockbuster. One approach  has exhausted critics, seems to be on the brink of exhausting fans, and may soon exhaust its momentum at the box office. The other approach, rooted in the not-so-distant past, might revive the diminishing artistic returns of the major studios’ tent-pole popcorn flicks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, the two trailers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ngElkyQ6Rhs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; bets heavily on nostalgia: we begin with a panoramic view of a familiar desert planetscape (&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; Tattooine, but a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; arid, windswept world); we get X-Wings and tie fighters; and, most notably, a Luke Skywalker voice-over and our first glimpse of retirement-age Han Solo. If you’re not a &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; devotee (and no mystical energy field controls &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; destiny), much of this won’t matter to you. But if you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; a fan, the swell of John Williams’ melodic strings and winds likely dried your throat, and the glimpses of your old pals Artoo and Chewie may have brought tears to your eyes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IwfUnkBfdZ4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Batman&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;v Superman&lt;/em&gt; is a much different trailer. After Snyder’s flirtatious tweets, it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ew.com/article/2015/04/17/batman-v-superman-trailer-leak&quot;&gt;“leaked” a week early&lt;/a&gt; (who can say whether the marketing team at Warner Bros. is just incompetent, or so incompetent that they’re brilliant). It begins with the standard throb of ominous ambient noise, then gives us a little Charlie Rose voice-over (which isn’t quite as affecting as hearing Mark Hamill); then a slow tracking shot towards a shadowed statue that is revealed to be, yes, a monument to Superman with, yes, graffiti scrawled across the chest that reads: False God. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zack Snyder has never been one for subtlety. Whatever hope there had been that the influence of Christopher Nolan (who produced &lt;em&gt;Man Of Steel&lt;/em&gt;, as well as this quasi-sequel) might quell his instinct for misanthropic self-seriousness was crushed by the arrival of his misanthropic, self-serious Superman film. The &lt;em&gt;Dawn of Justice&lt;/em&gt; trailer suggests that his follow-up is exactly what you might expect from the much-maligned pop-artist: beautiful, hyper-real CGI shots that seem like moving Rubens paintings, and laughable, hyper-dramatic dialogue (“this is how it starts...the fear, the rage...the feeling of powerlessness...”). This sneak peek at this latest superhero crossover – with which DC Comics and Warner Bros. is hoping to establish an &lt;em&gt;Avengers&lt;/em&gt;-style cinematic continuity – is more of the same: lots of shadows, sneering, heavy weaponry and political metaphors so broad that not even the Last Son of Krypton could leap them in a single bound. But let’s be frank: more of the same isn’t a bad thing for the bottom line. Despite being a critical disappointment, Superman’s big screen comeback grossed $668 Million worldwide. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zack Snyder may not be seeking redemption (he’s admirably unapologetic), and neither is J.J. Abrams (though some people think he should be). But Abrams faces a different challenge with his new flick—perhaps no filmmakers in the history of filmmaking has ever faced higher expectations than Abrams does as the heir to the Holy Trilogy. Online reaction to the very first &lt;em&gt;SW:FA&lt;/em&gt; teaser is proof. A pitch perfect capsule of images and sounds that elicited every good feeling about the original trilogy that the prequels supposedly forgot, and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; the naysayers found something to complain about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this new &lt;em&gt;SW:FA&lt;/em&gt; trailer suggest about Abrams’ approach? And how does it differ, in its foundational approach to big-budget cinema, from the &lt;em&gt;BvS&lt;/em&gt; trailer? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it’s important to understand why it makes sense to compare these two pictures. What makes them relative variables is the simple fact that they &lt;em&gt;exist&lt;/em&gt;. As recently as a decade ago, the notion of a big-budget superhero film featuring both of DC Comics’ two most iconic characters (along with Wonder Woman &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Aquaman, who are featured in a series of promotional posters, and therefore, one supposes, appear in the film—once again WB’s genius/incompetent marketing at work) would have been preposterous. Likewise, the possibility of new &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; films – featuring the original cast, no less! – seemed utterly implausible even just a few short years ago. George Lucas’s prequels had seemed to annihilate the franchise’s big screen ambitions (animated properties like &lt;em&gt;Clone Wars&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rebels&lt;/em&gt; have thrived on television and in toy aisles). That these two films are being released within a few months of each other suggests that we are reaching the crest of the sea change that began when Marvel began intermingling its characters and bundling them into blockbuster franchises. The narrative continuity that is so important to sci-fi and comic book superfans now exists in theaters. What seemed impossible is now possible. More than possible, actually. &lt;em&gt;Profitable&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about Abrams? He’s already rebooted one beloved sci-fi franchise, and, while he didn’t always get the ratio of fan service to storytelling right (says one of the fans he serviced), he resurrected the Enterprise and its crew fairly well. &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; will require a defter touch, though, and if this latest trailer is any indication, Abrams may have gotten it right. And he gets it right in direct opposition to the approach Snyder takes. Optimism, positivity, clarity and, most significantly–– a palpable sense of &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; something that Hollywood seems to have completely forgotten when it comes to these types of films. What made Abrams’ second &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; flick such a disappointment was how much it felt like every other recent mega-action film: incomprehensible action, overwhelming effects, the sound and fury signifying nothing, and, worst of all, an obscenely high body count paired with imagery suggestive (almost offensively) of 9/11. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You might say he Zack Snyder-ed it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of this is speculation (and no small amount of barely-suppressed fanboy hope), which is precisely what trailers of this kind are meant to provoke. Maybe &lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; will be dark and gloomy and replete with the kind of slick CGI that contradicts the gritty Old-West aesthetic of the very first film. Maybe  &lt;em&gt;Batman&lt;/em&gt; v Superman will embrace the absurdity of a superpowered alien fighting a rich old white guy with an underground armory and a taste for cosplay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the trailers don’t suggest so. And while these little two-minute commercials the marketing department cuts together are rarely indicative of the &lt;em&gt;quality&lt;/em&gt; of the film, they tend to pretty accurately predict a film’s mood and tenor.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s little doubt that &lt;em&gt;The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt; will top the list of 2015’s biggest films (and with a Christmas release, might just end up being 2016’s box office champion, too). And there’s also little doubt that Abrams has made it a priority to recapture a bit of the innocence and wonder that made Lucas’ space adventures more than just films. The question is, will this return to a simpler, lighter, more positive approach to the blockbuster reverse the trend that started a decade ago with the Nolan’s first Batman film? Has the gritty reboot run its course? And is that necessarily a good thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good or not, it will be, in the meantime, a relief.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/22/superman-v-star-wars-the-blockbuster-awakens.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/22/superman-v-star-wars-the-blockbuster-awakens.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>True Story</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have never believed you. On a deep, molecular level I find you utterly unconvincing. No matter what character you may be playing I find it almost impossible to accept you as anything other than Jonah Hill pretending to be some guy. So the fact that you are the deeply flawed protagonist of a film called &lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; is kind of problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jonah Hill Effect is far less of a barrier for me in movies like &lt;em&gt;21 Jump Street&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;This is The End&lt;/em&gt; because you are not playing a character that requires much of a stretch—either on my part or yours. All I have to do is accept the premise of you as helpless schlub (and, in the case of &lt;em&gt;This is The End,&lt;/em&gt; demon spawn) and I’m in. In &lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; though, your singular capacity to undermine my suspension of disbelief is reflective of the films most glaring weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; is an account of the relationship between a journalist and an accused murderer. It is the kind of true crime story (like NPR’s &lt;em&gt;Serial&lt;/em&gt; or HBO’s &lt;em&gt;The Jinx: The Life and Deaths of Robert Durst&lt;/em&gt;) that demonstrates a reality that ethicist Janet Malcolm delineates in her book, &lt;em&gt;The Journalist and the Murderer:&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Every journalist who is not too stupid or too full of himself to notice what is going on knows that what he does is morally indefensible.&amp;quot;  It is the kind of work that—if it is to be successful at all, and not simply exploitative and inherently parasitic—requires the finest sort of calibrations regarding tone and presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; feels most thin when dealing with its central theme—what is the space between people’s stated intentions and their actions—largely because the two central characters are not presented credibly. I don’t believe James Franco’s portrayal as accused murderer Christian Longo and I certainly do not believe you in the role of disgraced NYT journalist Michael Finkel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your performance is arid, disengaged. Your scenes with Franco feel like a table read or a workshop, completely devoid of emotional content. The performance is so mechanical and workmanlike that I feel like I am watching particularly well rehearsed community theatre, competent enough but devoid of any real emotional truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt;’s problems do not begin and end with casting. The choice to break the film into vignettes that are so clearly delineated make the whole exercise feel dispassionate and removed. The point of making a fictional film based on true events would seem to be about reaching some deeper truths, something that lies behind a straightforward recitation of events. But the film’s structure undermines that goal, leaving it feeling emotionally sterile and disconnected from its subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;True Story&lt;/em&gt; certainly strives for a kind of authenticity—using natural light and low-key performances, long takes and a general reserve in the story telling. The pallet is cold and often muted and nothing about the visual presentation is over the top. Normally these would all be points in the film’s favor but in this case they tend to underline the vacuity of the central performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are the only way into this film for the audience but you are an unreadable cipher. The character you portray is the linchpin of the whole story and you just don’t give us enough to hang onto—despite the fact that, as a narrator, your character is inherently unreliable. I don’t even believe the truth of your lies, as it were. So at the end of the film all I could think was how interesting this story might have been if it had been a documentary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/20/true-story.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/20/true-story.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Conversation With Director Denis Villeneuve</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;On the day &lt;em&gt;Sicario&lt;/em&gt; was announced as part of the 2015 Festival de Cannes’ official competition, C. Redmond speaks with the incredible French-Canadian director about his chances of winning, maintaining his signature in Hollywood, and the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; sequel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean to you to be accepted into Cannes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the biggest honour – it’s a massive honour for me to be part of the competition this year. Cannes is the Mecca of cinema. To see the lineup, I go there with humility because just to be part of that lineup I’m already very proud, and grateful for the invitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You kind of got your start at Cannes. You worked your way from the Director’s Fortnight, and then Un Certain Regard. Did you feel it was almost inevitable that you would someday have a film in competition, or are you surprised?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my dream but sometimes you feel like dreams are fading because more and more I was making movies in America. So I thought I was going away from that world of film festivals, and right now this movie that was produced in Los Angeles is a nice compliment because it’s very important for me to keep my identity as a filmmaker when I’m shooting abroad. Just to be able to keep my point of view, to stay myself. And the fact that they are inviting me, they recognize the fact that I was able to protect my identity as a filmmaker in another system of production. That for me is a big compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Coen Brothers are going to be leading the jury. Do you think that will help your odds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, strangely, I’m feeling that because we share Roger Deakins as a cinematographer, I think it makes things tougher (laughs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you talk to me about working with Roger&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Deakins? Tell me what the difference was between working with him the first time and working with him a second time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second time I was much, much more comfortable with Roger. The first time I was always a bit impressed. I was feeling like a student and he’s the teacher. The second time it was more collaborative, the communication was much better. Stylistically we get along pretty well. The first experience was beautiful, but the second was better. Working with Roger, honestly, it’s rare in your lifetime that you will have a chance to work with a master. And he’s someone, even if I’m on set with him and I have to direct him, or nourish him so he’s able to create, I always feel like I’m in a learning process, because I’m learning all the time with Roger. Every shot, I’m learning something. It’s a massive privilege for me to get to work two times with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there someone you worked with on your most recent film &lt;em&gt;Sicario&lt;/em&gt;  that stood out to you as great, but might never get any media attention?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh boy. Yeah, I’ll give you one right now: the dolly pusher, his name is Bruce Hamme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve got to be kidding! I did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/9/10/prisoners.html&quot;&gt;review of &lt;em&gt;Prisoners&lt;/em&gt; and I wrote to Bruce Hamme &lt;/a&gt;. That’s too funny. I noticed his work.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the man. That guy is an artist. He’s the dolly grip and he’s the extension of Roger, the one who will create the dance of the camera, the one who will find the right rhythm. He’s the most precise, the way he pushes the camera is just an art form. I feel he is also the most lovely human being. Roger is using a specific crane in almost every shot, which means in almost every shot we have to build that crane, a little crane that is so precise and so delicate and Bruce is dancing with that crane all day long, and working and he never complains. And he’s the nicest human being. Bruce is definitely the one I will make an homage to, a tribute to Bruce. I could talk about him for hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s perfect. I met you at the Genie Awards four years ago, and you told me your friends were making fun of you saying, “Denis, when are you going to stop making these pretentious art films and make a sci-fi film, because you know that’s what you really love”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(laughs) Exactly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And now you’ve got two sci-fi films coming. Tell me how that finally happened.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I arrived in LA with &lt;em&gt;Incendies&lt;/em&gt;, all the studios were asking me, “What will you do? What would be your dream?”  And my only answer was always sci-fi, because I knew that if there was something that I could do in Hollywood that I couldn’t do at home it was sci-fi. With sci-fi you need a certain amount of resources. So I kept on saying this and at one point two young producers came with a fantastic little short story called &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt;. It was one of the best things that I’d read and I was like “Whoa!” this is poetic, beautiful and strong and exactly the kind of project that I would dream to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep saying I want to do sci-fi for adults, so like &lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt;. That was always the two examples I would give that I would want to do. Or &lt;em&gt;Close Encounters&lt;/em&gt;. So with 21 Laps, a company set in LA, I developed this little sci-fi project called &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt;. I’m going to shoot in next June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And now you’re going to work with Bradford Young as a cinematographer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I’m going to work with Bradford Young because Roger Deakins wasn’t available this summer. He wanted to do the project but there was a scheduling conflict. So I made a long research and came into contact with that cinematographer. He’s young but he already has a strong signature. I was very impressed. I fell in love with his work quite quickly, and to my great pleasure he agreed to get on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Would you consider working with (cinematographer) Nicolas Bolduc again?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to because I love Nico. Yeah, of course! But when you cast a DP, you cast a specific sensibility, and for &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt; I needed someone like Bradford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt;? That doesn’t seem like it would be in Roger Deakins’ normal palate of what he does. Would you consider him for that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot answer that, but I can tell you you have the wrong instincts (laughs). It would be a dream for me to do that with Roger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(laughs) Good to know!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Are you able to talk about at all what you want to do, how you want to put your stamp on revisiting that story?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a creative point of view unfortunately I can say nothing, other than that the script is pretty powerful and that it was a long decision for me to make. It was too much of a dream for me to participate on such a project and I’m aware of the massive pressure. The original &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; is one of my favourite movies of all time. I saw that movie maybe fifty times in my life. I will do my homework and I am uber excited. I wake up every morning pinching myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think there are any lessons to be taken from&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prometheus&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be very disappointed because unfortunately I can say nothing.  All I can say is that the script was written by Hampton Fancher, Ridley Scott and Michael Green and the three of them did very impressive work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any scripts that you’re writing that you want to do in the future?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest I cannot make a lineup of projects. For now I’m just concentrating on &lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life&lt;/em&gt; and the possibility of &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; right after is enough for me (laughs). After that, I will sleep for three weeks, or three months maybe. I feel that I lined up a lot of projects one after the other and after that I will probably take a break. Just for a few months and go back on to screenwriting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just promise it’s not going to be as long as the break you had between  &lt;em&gt;Maelstrom&lt;/em&gt; (2000) and &lt;em&gt;Polytechnique&lt;/em&gt; (2009). We need you too much.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(laughs) Don’t worry, that’s not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/17/a-conversation-with-director-denis-villeneuve.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Last Knights</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The vocal style you use, singing the same syllable over several notes, is called “&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melisma&quot;&gt;melisma&lt;/a&gt;”. Its intended purpose is to provide a hypnotic, or trance-like effect. You’ve found incredible success by blending this style with electronica, hip-hop and French torch songs and yet have always managed to sound completely original. &lt;em&gt;Last Knights&lt;/em&gt; repeats so many worn out tropes, visuals, and stock characters that it too induced a trance-like effect. A kind of deja-vu that nearly sent me into a deep sleep for its seemingly seven-plus hour duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen &lt;em&gt;47 Ronin&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;King Arthur&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;Robin Hood: Men&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;In&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Tights&lt;/em&gt; then you won’t see anything that hasn’t already been done better (and blessedly faster) than &lt;em&gt;Last Knights.&lt;/em&gt; I could try to elaborate on the plot, but the one-sentence IMDb description is vague and unfulfilling enough that I figured I’d follow in &lt;em&gt;Last Knight&lt;/em&gt;s’ phoned-in footsteps and just copy/paste it here. “A fallen warrior rises against a corrupt and sadistic ruler to avenge his dishonored master.” In fact, part of me is tempted to just write this review by cribbing sentences from reviews of better sword and sandal epics. But unlike the makers of &lt;em&gt;Last Knights&lt;/em&gt;, I’m at least half interested in creating something new. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clive Owen plays Raiden, who is part of an elite group of warriors in what I can only assume is some kind of alternate universe. According to Morgan Freeman’s voice over, this group was formed “during the long dark period of the Great War” and is made up of “all races, colours and creeds”, (but not all genders, unsurprisingly). These fierce fighters are sworn to protect their masters, who in Raiden’s case is Morgan Freeman’s Lord Bartok. When Gezza Mott, the fey, sociopathic Minister to the Emperor has Bartok killed and his people evicted, Raiden and his fellow warriors spend the next seven, or maybe it was eight hours of screen time trying to avenge his death.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sound is considered part of the nebulous “world music” genre, which encompasses everything from reggae, to Inuit throat singing, and Buddhist chanting. Your inclusion as a vocalist in this film was most likely meant to lend a trans-cultural vibe, since not once do we ever really know where the film is set. Describing it sounds like I’m trying to recall details of my own kidnapping while under hypnosis: it’s mostly snowy, and grey, there are mountains and forests, and the capital looks like a heavily CGI’d Medieval Times. Perhaps the film’s pedigree (it’s a Czech/South Korea co-production helmed by Japanese director Kazukai Kiriya) contributed to its identity crisis. Or perhaps by trying to be all things to all audiences it simply collapsed under the weight of its own hubris, and no one knew which country was legally bound to put it out of its misery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first heard your clear and powerful voice I thought it was my own inner monologue moaning “Anhhhhhhhh...anhhh...annnnnnnhhh” in agony from hearing dialogue desperately searching for gravitas, seeing characters so flimsily drawn I could have seen right through them if the sets weren’t so poorly lit, and watching bland fight scenes so tension-free they could have been choreographed by the WWE. The only thing that might have saved this film from being a complete snooze-fest would have been some unintentional humour, but &lt;em&gt;Last Knights&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t even have the decency to be camp. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Knights&lt;/em&gt; is a retrograde throwback celebrating “manly men doing manly things” that takes itself far too seriously. But through it all, your voice remains steady and true, and I welcomed it, since the only other women in the film were either crying, or whoring it up at the local tavern. I think Clive Owen’s wife might have been a twig vendor but I also might have imagined it when I went into one of the fugue states this film induced. Or maybe Clive Owen’s real life wife &lt;em&gt;really is&lt;/em&gt; a twig vendor and that’s why had to make this movie. I hope that’s the case, or else I’m going to have to get a band of rogue warriors together to avenge his honour. Any chance you’re interested in being our minstrel?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/16/last-nights.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/16/last-nights.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Down Here</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to attribute your editing skills (or lack thereof) to the fact that you were not only an editor, but a co-producer and actor as well. You played Ace, a no nonsense pimp with a total of about 12 minutes of screen time. If you can’t tell, I’m fucking with you. I’m not going to sugar-coat it—&lt;em&gt;Down Here&lt;/em&gt; wasn’t good, and your editing made it feel like I was enduring way more of it than I had to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know what to expect with &lt;em&gt;Down Here&lt;/em&gt;, but once I started, I quickly clued in that it was going to be long. Really long. Normally, a movie about a tortured alcoholic detective tracking a psychopath who targets young hookers and records their murders would have me itching to press play. You even have the perfect lead actor playing Detective Harris — he looks like the Trivago guy if he lived off a diet of cigarettes and fast food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the script is cheesy and its faults are emphasized by the drawn out interactions between the characters. The unnecessary extended shots of street signs, people walking and driving, facial expressions and dialogue all screamed lack of confidence. You obviously didn’t think the story was clear enough so you lingered on scenes to avoid any confusion for the viewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It actually got to a point where I was no longer just aware of, but &lt;em&gt;annoyed&lt;/em&gt; by how stretched everything was. A perfect example would be during our disheveled detective’s mental assessment. As he was being questioned by his doctor, I tuned out. The scene itself was only four minutes, but the prolonged use of a stationary camera and muffled audio made me feel like I was watching a medical documentary from the 80s—and considering this is where a bulk of Detective Harris’ past is revealed, audience attention is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d say the only saving grace was the awkward romance between Detective Harris and Stella. How did I know that Stella had a thing for Harris? Because you fixated on her while she gave him sex eyes. I couldn’t miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Down Here&lt;/em&gt; has many faults but if I had to choose one as the standout, I’d nominate your editing, which was about as long as the number of search results when I typed your name into Google (71 million to be exact).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ankit&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/15/down-here.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/15/down-here.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Danny Collins</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Danny Collins&lt;/em&gt; is a movie that absolutely depends upon the songs of John Lennon to make it work. That fact must have presented tremendous challenges for you, since you are not only responsible for obtaining the rights to the music used in the film, but also for helping place it within the narrative structure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This soundtrack is not simply a series of secondary aesthetic choices; it is the skeleton upon which the whole film rests. Al Pacino plays &lt;em&gt;Danny Collins&lt;/em&gt; as a dissolute impression of a latter day Neil Diamond. A former folk singer turned Vegas shill, Collins finds out that none other than John Lennon once mailed him a hand written letter. This is a letter that Collins only sees—for the first time—forty years after the fact, as his career is winding down. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details contained in that letter are what set the story, and your work, in motion. Lennon’s music is interspersed with the feel-good, folksy anthems that Collins regurgitates nightly to crowds of blue rinse groupies. The contrast between the two paints a pretty dismal picture of what kind of life Collins chose to pursue after his early success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Danny Collins&lt;/em&gt; often teeters on the edge of sentimentality, but is saved by three things: an understated and knowing performance by Pacino, a great supporting cast, and a script that contains enough nuance that it overcomes some pretty heavy handed plot devices. And your musical choices also help to shepherd the film through what could be maudlin nonsense to something with some occasional weight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lennon’s music lends a borrowed gravitas to the proceedings and Pacino strives to earn that substance by making the character of Collins something other than the usual late-life turn around. Pacino specifically plays against type—his performance is knowing and low key. The narrative tension isn’t built upon Collin’s awakening self-awareness (he is already well aware of his failings) but rather with whether or not he chooses to engage his shortcomings in a meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This inner struggle is an interesting echo of much of John Lennon’s later solo work, when he was trying to come to terms with who he was as a man and with his place in the world. Pacino—in a real return to form—manages to convey that struggle without it being Shakespearean in tone. This isn’t &lt;em&gt;Scent of a Woman&lt;/em&gt; Pacino; in fact it is an oddly intimate film, given its showbiz veneer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second and third act of the film trace Collins’ attempts to reconnect with both his family and his musical roots. It is here that the movie struggles most with tone, but the performances—from Annette Bening to Bobby Cannavale and Jennifer Garner, as well as a crusty turn by Christopher Plummer as Collin’s long-suffering friend/manager—really save the film from itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying themes of this film are more concerned with a grudging attentiveness than the usual forced epiphanies that Hollywood often thrives on. If Pacino, and by extension the film, echoes any particular sentiment of Lennon’s it is the idea that living is easy with your eyes closed. It is when you open them wide that it becomes complicated and messy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And worth living.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/13/danny-collins.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/13/danny-collins.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Miss Julie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;As prop hand, you’re surely familiar with the world’s most famous prop-based theory of drama: Chekhov’s Gun. The renowned playwright described the principle like this: “If you say in the first chapter that there is a rifle hanging on the wall, in the second or third chapter it absolutely must go off.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt;, written by Chekhov contemporary August Strindberg and adapted for the screen by Liv Ullmann, is a prime example of naturalism. It’s realistic, it’s a careful study of human behaviour, and, above all, it’s austere. Every prop is there for a reason. While you may not have had to provide a rifle to any of the actors in &lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt;, they will be wounded nonetheless. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What starts out as an exhilarating &lt;em&gt;pas de&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;deux&lt;/em&gt; of two desperate people bringing each other to the height of ecstasy and the depths of despair, things eventually grow tiresome. If you had hoped for a light summer job to supplement your regular gig of doing prop work on &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;, I’m sure you were soon wishing you had signed on for that Carrot Top movie instead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt; takes place at a Baron’s estate during Midsummer Night in 1890. The Baron’s valet, John, is engaged to the pious cook Kathleen, but must fend off the amorous attempts of the Baron’s daughter, Miss Julie. Throughout the course of the night, John and Miss Julie will enter into a dangerous affair that will have fatal consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ullmann is no stranger to cinematic tragedy. As one of famed director Ingmar Bergman’s muses, Ullmann starred in many of the legendary Swede’s films – &lt;em&gt;Cries and Whispers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Scenes From A Marriage&lt;/em&gt;, to name a few – all of which examine themes of class, faith, and redemption. As a director (&lt;em&gt;Faithless&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sofie&lt;/em&gt;) Ullman has often explored complex relationships between men and women. Strindberg’s study of a strong-willed aristocratic woman and an ambitious servant dancing between repulsion and desire would seem the perfect vehicle for Ullmann. And it is—almost to a fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a few noticeable exceptions, &lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt; is filmed mainly in the kitchen of the estate, which must have made your job easier. Unfortunately the static nature of the sets and the cinematography make it difficult for the film to overcome its stage origins, and threatens to undermine the naturalistic conceit. Thankfully, three very skilled actors are able to transcend these boundaries and deliver performances that are alternately heartbreaking, explosive, and agonizing. Jessica Chastain and Colin Farrell, as Miss Julie and John, take turns seducing and rebuffing one another, all to the point of physical and emotional exhaustion. But it’s Samantha Morton as Kathleen who steals the movie with her understated despair. As the moral center of the story, Kathleen might be a woman scorned, but she’s never pitiable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like your dedication to filling Tyrion Lannister’s wineskin, most of your job here involves drinking vessels. In an early scene in which Kathleen serves John lunch, he asks for his wine in a crystal glass. Later, when Miss Julie orders John to serve her a beer, he pours it into an earthenware mug. These class distinctions are constantly at play. After their affair is consummated and Miss Julie realizes she is a ruined woman, John shuns her by saying that intimacy between the working class doesn’t mean anything, but for the aristocracy, it means &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every scheme to save reputations is marked by one of the characters pulling out glasses from the cupboard and something dark and alcoholic from a dusty bottle. Here is where your skills must have been seriously tested. You no doubt had many a conversation with the script supervisor before each take to determine exactly how much alcohol needed to be in each goblet. While watching Chastain and Farrell treating each other so brutally day after day, were you ever tempted to switch their fake wine with the real stuff? Did you secretly long for a stiff drink yourself? I know after more than two hours of watching their bleak struggle I was begging for some relief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the third act, a pouch of money and a straight razor contribute to a tension already heightened by lust, loathing, and, of course, alcohol. It’s only a matter of time before these props bring the entire depressing scenario to an unsurprisingly grim conclusion. Ullmann tries to soften the rough edges by making the film look like a glowing 19th-century oil painting, and should be commended for her ability to draw out such tortured and raw performances. But as the film plods its way to its foregone and ugly conclusion, it seems she just didn’t know when to put it out of its misery. It’s a shame you couldn’t have handed her Chekhov’s gun. Or Tyrion’s wineskin. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/10/miss-julie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/10/miss-julie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>While We&#39;re Young</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m moving in a few weeks, so I recently went through some old boxes to de-clutter before packing. Inevitably the old yearbooks came out, encouragement and optimism scrawled across the pages in glittery gel ink. Old trophies, too. And certificates of achievement and excellence. It was all a startling reminder that I once had actual dreams . &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that sinking feeling of what-the-fuck-happened-to-me was something I could relate to when I saw &lt;em&gt;While We’re Young&lt;/em&gt; a few days later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the film, fortysomethings Josh and Cornelia are in a bit of a rut. They try to downplay it, but their discontent slowly reveals itself as their best friends become parents and start doing that really annoying thing parents do to their childless friends: “You &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to have kids, it’s the best thing &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;!” Josh’s filmmaking career is also at a standstill, as he struggles to piece together his documentary from ten years worth of footage about…actually, I still can’t figure out what that documentary was about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a good fifteen to twenty years away from a mid-life crisis, but I connected with Josh and Cornelia right away. There’s nothing drastically wrong with their lives, but once they realize they’ve lost that feeling of endless possibility, it starts to weigh on them. They are stagnant while everyone else in their lives appears to be moving steadily from one milestone to the next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spark that brings Josh and Cornelia out of their funk comes in the form of Jamie and Darby, bohemian twentysomethings (to whom I will refer as “The Hipsters”) who dazzle the older couple with their infectious enthusiasm and free-spiritedness. Suddenly, Josh is the cool, accomplished mentor to Jamie, and Cornelia can hang out with Darby in baby-free places, doing baby-free things. The contrast between the two couples is perhaps best represented by the homes you created for them. Josh and Cornelia’s place is well-appointed, if somewhat sterile. The Hipsters’ place, on the other hand, is shabby, disordered, and you crammed it with all kinds of cool stuff that had me wanting a similar look for &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; new place. Their apartment led me to reminisce fondly about the furniture in my first apartment, like the awesome couch I randomly scored from the curb. The Hipsters are kind of ridiculous and pretentious, but the combination of nostalgia and regret is no match for pragmatism and common sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did worry that the film would lose steam right around the halfway point. The two couples flit from one charming (mis)adventure to the next, and while it’s amusing, I worried that momentum would be lost and we’d spend the last 30 minutes schlepping towards an unsatisfying conclusion. But director Noah Baumbach throws in a twist that waves smelling salts under the nose of the plot and keeps it revived and energetic through to the end. As charming as the Hipsters are at the beginning of the film, I enjoyed watching the shine rub off of them. The film’s last act is like crashing after a sugar high. Darby and Jamie are a pack of Skittles: sweet, delightful, and you can’t get enough of them. But an hour later your head hurts and you realize they’re full of unhealthy shit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being effortlessly cool requires so much effort it’s downright exhausting. As Josh and Cornelia learn this and try to regain footing in their own, comfortable lives, I thought about the house you decorated for them, which I initially dismissed as boring and WASP-y. On second thought, it was comfortable, and the things in it were put there with care and thought. That is what I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want for my new home. Because that old couch I got from the curb was actually crap; I had to steam-clean and sanitize it four times before I could sit on it without getting a rash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, &lt;em&gt;While We’re Young&lt;/em&gt; struck a chord with me because I could relate to those feelings of being stuck after leaving your twenties behind. There are no big revelations or sea changes, but I walked away considering the merits of a little misadventure to help one feel &lt;em&gt;unstuck&lt;/em&gt;, and when the candy coating of nostalgia wore off entirely, I was back to browsing IKEA catalogues. Because I’m not some damn hipster. Now get off my lawn. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/9/while-were-young.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/9/while-were-young.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Conversation With &lt;em&gt;Pretend We&#39;re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; Writer/Director Matt Sadowski</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Di Golding talks to &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; writer/director Matt Sadowski  about the challenges of making a “non-rom-com” and how to film a perfectly awkward sex scene.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there something specific about the rom-com genre that turns you off, or made you want to make a non-rom-com?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen, I like movies like &lt;em&gt;Win A Date With Tad Hamilton&lt;/em&gt; as much as the next lad, but what I felt was missing was romantic comedies that accurately show that not everything &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; work out. I felt that I could connect to a lot of romantic comedies until the final act. Because for me – and maybe other people too – I never really got a second chance when I screwed things up. The main movie that really lit the fire for this was, back in 2004 there was only &lt;em&gt;Before Sunrise&lt;/em&gt;, it wasn’t a trilogy yet, and I really felt like once she (Celine) gets on the train and leaves at the end, I always felt like, if they hadn’t split up, if they’d spent one more day together, would they really have had that kind of connection? I totally buy that ten years later that fire is fuelled again. But after talking to a lot of people, everyone has had those flings where, whether it’s for a minute or an hour or a day or a week, you feel like “wow, we have everything going on,” and one thing can turn it completely off. I really wanted to show that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing a “non-rom com” film must be tricky. Who do you think the audience is for&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little bit of marketing speak, but I really believe it’s a romantic comedy for people who don’t think they like romantic comedies. And maybe they don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they don’t like romantic comedies. Maybe it is because they (rom-coms) have a kind of plastic coating to them, whether because of who they cast or a clichéd script or just a formulaic way of shooting it. I think some people, they know, and they can call it out. This is why I don’t make these kind of movies. But I think for some people it’s just a feeling that they have. And I really just wanted to make something that could make people feel just a little bit different and hope that they relate to it because it feels a little bit more real. And the problem with being real is that sometime you lose hope, and I wanted to make a film that kind of questions ideas about falling in love and destiny—but without being cynical about it, either. I think that’s sometimes hard to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You did something interesting that was not rom-commy: instead of doing a lot of close ups and soft focus, you did a lot of long takes and medium shots, and you just kind of let things happen. You let the actors act. Did you always know that you were going to film it this way?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a certain style that people know, oh, that’s an indie film, and it’s this kind of handheld, finding the focus, documentary kind of look that really does work for a lot of films. But I felt like it wasn’t the right look for this one. The films that I was inspired by were films from the 70s and 80s, and if you look at those films, their frames linger and they last a long time and it makes you listen in a different way and it makes you expect things in a completely different way. I kind of felt like when you’re in a relationship and it’s going well, you don’t blink. That’s the essence of the vibe I wanted the film to have. I wanted it to be long, gazing looks to make the whole thing a little bit dreamier, because that’s how you feel. And I also feel like relationships aren’t very funny, they’re all kind of awkward, and holding on the frame brings the awkwardness. Not just from the characters – because Benny is pretty awkward – but finding your way on a new date or a new relationship is kind of awkward in itself, and I feel like a long take really helps that especially when you as an audience are now trained to know I’m not going to cut, or you’re not going to see an insert, or you’re not going get a close up, and we get to the sex scene, you kind of know what’s going to happen so you get on the edge of your seat in embarrassment before something actually does happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ve often heard about actors in sex scenes saying that they’re not as easy as they look, that they need to be very precise in how they’re filmed. Did you storyboard this and did the actors rehearse a lot?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that was one of the scenes we rehearsed the most. I was also lucky that out of all the scenes in the script, Dov and Tommie really responded to that scene, more so than any other scene. Because other scenes were “Benny and Jordan walk down the sidewalk”, and that scene is very specific. “He gets on top of her, he moves his knee, he puts his hand on her hair,” so it was all inherent in the stage direction of the script. And I think that gave them a lot of confidence to just follow the script, because it read really awkward as well. So that will come across. And a little behind the scenes story as well is that you can’t shoot a sex scene without having a union rep there, and a union rep makes everyone more nervous. And that was Dov’s first romantic scene ever and I think he was already nervous, and then to have a union rep come in and be like, “Don’t do anything you’re uncomfortable with, these are your rights,” just put so much in his head, which halted production for quite a while, to be honest—but his character is so anxiety-ridden and in his head anyway that it kind of worked out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your last feature was a documentary (&lt;em&gt;Don’t You Forget About Me&lt;/em&gt;). Did that make it easier or harder for you to direct your first scripted feature?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the doc was harder to make because I would say the only thing original about the doc was the idea that I had. But then you’re relying on so many other things to make the film happen. Everyone literally has a voice. Every producer has a voice, every interviewee has a voice. Sometimes you’re not able to shoot where you want so you have to shoot it in a certain style. And that film took so long to make. For that kind of specific doc, it’s an amalgamation of a lot of people’s visions whereas for this film I kind of was able to drive the ship a little more and was very lucky to have a crew that believed in the same sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I read that (executive producer) Pete Harvey made the entire crew read the script before signing on to make the film.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought that was really cool. We shot in 14 days and we had almost 30 locations, which is unheard of. People thought we were crazy. Most indie films shoot in a 15 or 20-day window and there’s 8 locations. Or there’s &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; location. So right from the beginning he said the only way we’re gonna get a crew to work hard for us – and because of the shots that I did – its easier to shoot in a kind of verité handheld style, because you don’t need the same amount of equipment trucks and gaffing and all that kind of stuff. To make all these long shots work required a lot of production elements to kind of come together. So Pete was amazing. And I never understood it. I was like, “why does the PA have to read the script? Why does the 3rd grip have to read the scrip?” And he said: “because I want every single person to want to make the film because they think the film can be really cool.” And he was right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/8/a-conversation-with-matt-sadowski.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/8/a-conversation-with-matt-sadowski.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Furious 7</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Face it – nobody wanted you on this film. But it’s not your fault. Your position on &lt;em&gt;Furious 7&lt;/em&gt; was one born of tragedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;em&gt;Fast and Furious&lt;/em&gt; star Paul Walker was all-too-ironically killed while speeding in a Porsche Carrera GT, the only way to complete production was with the help of Walker’s two similar looking brothers, Caleb and Cody, and Weta’s top-notch team of special effects animators like you. There must have been moments when the collision between art and life felt a bit much to take. Still, you had a job to do. This red-hot action franchise has grown into an unstoppable machine, even more surreal than the chaos on screen. And that’s saying a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the film is complete, your work is seamless, and the result is… unreal. In the best possible way. Never once did I feel a camera cheat or compromise. Quite the opposite. &lt;em&gt;Furious 7&lt;/em&gt; is pushing what’s possible in action cinema, and often left me speechless in my chair.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try and paint you a picture in terms you’ll no doubt understand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dilated pupils, bated breath&lt;/em&gt; – the lights finally lower in the theatre and the Universal logo takes over the screen. I’m way too revved up to see this film considering I only hopped on the bandwagon at &lt;em&gt;Fast Five&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cheeks go flush&lt;/em&gt; – my man-crush, Jason Statham, makes his debut in the franchise, walking slowly out of a hospital in the aftermath of an encounter with a British tactical SWAT team. Without an ounce of sweat or expression, he struts away from explosions in slow motion like the boss he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Head cocks slightly to the left. A befuddled wince appears&lt;/em&gt; – the title reads &lt;em&gt;Furious Seven&lt;/em&gt;, instead of &lt;em&gt;Furious 7&lt;/em&gt; (like all the ads). I flash back to how the last film was promoted as &lt;em&gt;Fast &amp;amp; Furious 6,&lt;/em&gt; but the opening credits called it &lt;em&gt;Furious 6&lt;/em&gt;. Then the fourth film is just called &lt;em&gt;Fast &amp;amp; Furious&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;The Fast and The Furious&lt;/em&gt; … This franchise is a hot mess and I don’t care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biting the lower lip, à la Anastasia Steele –&lt;/em&gt; Vin Diesel and Michelle Rodriguez show up at some Race Wars contest in the desert, where an abundance of bikini babes may or may not be in front of expensive cars (I’m not really a car guy). More ass than an Iggy Azalea video. Speaking of which, there she is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forced laugh followed by a sad smile –&lt;/em&gt; the first close-up of Paul Walker, intercut with pressing foot pedals and jumping speed needles. Somehow, it’s predictably paid-off by revealing he’s behind the wheel of a mini-van, dropping his kid off at school. He really did have a lovely face. Whether or not it’s digital never crosses my mind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big-ass stupid grin&lt;/em&gt; – The whole team is together, in darkness, behind the wheels of different cars. Tyrese, of course, plays the clown, rhetorically asking how they keep getting into these situations. My jaw lowers in tandem with the loading ramp of the cargo plane they’re all aboard. Skydiving cars was the next logical adventure, and it doesn’t disappoint. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various vowels form on my lips, mainly Os and Es, trying to register the insanity on screen for the next two hours&lt;/em&gt; – it would take too long to describe each and every moment, from the OMGs of escaping buses on clifftops, to the WTFs of kicking the asses of hijab wearing female guards in Abu Dhabi, to the LOLs of The Rock flexing off his full arm cast. Suffice to say, no franchise commands a greater range of facial expressions than the &lt;em&gt;Fast and Furious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, there’s the dedication, “For Paul”. The final montage was as predictable and on-the-nose as every line of dialogue in this film, and equally as welcomed and satisfying. You may or may not have caught a small tear in the corner of my eye. Otherwise, this film was sheer joy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/7/furious-7.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/7/furious-7.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
