<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>9 Things You Probably Didn&#39;t Know About The Little Mermaid</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;To celebrate the 25th anniversary of &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, co-writers/co-directors Ron Clements and John Musker spoke at the 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animationfestival.ca&quot;&gt;Ottawa International Animation Festival&lt;/a&gt; about kick-starting the Disney Renaissance. Here are some of the behind-the-scenes tidbits they revealed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The idea for &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt; was &amp;quot;gonged&amp;quot; when it was first pitched to Disney.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In a classic case of almost-wasn&amp;#39;t, Ron Clements&amp;#39; original two-page proposal got shot down by Disney execs Michael Eisner and Jeffery Katzenberg at an animator presentation called &amp;quot;The Gong Show&amp;quot;. This was partly a knee-jerk reaction to rumours of a sequel to _Splash _being in the works. But that wasn&amp;#39;t the only reason…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Before &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt; , Disney hadn&amp;#39;t made a fairy tale since the 1950s.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Even though most people think of Disney as a fairy tale factory, the company hadn&amp;#39;t brought one to the big screen since &lt;em&gt;Sleeping Beauty&lt;/em&gt; in 1959. Audience sensibilities were thought to have moved too far away from the coming-of-age classics that focused on women. Or, in other words…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Executive Producer Jeffery Katzenberg believed that &amp;quot;girl movies don&amp;#39;t make money.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The budget for the film was modest for a big theatrical release because Katzenberg didn&amp;#39;t think the film would do any better than Disney&amp;#39;s release the previous year, &lt;em&gt;Oliver &amp;amp; Company&lt;/em&gt;. Oliver &amp;amp; Who? Oh, how the times have changed (well, not really).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. The name Ariel was inspired by a character in the &lt;em&gt;Footloose&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Forget Hans Christian Anderson—Clements had Kevin Bacon on the brain (or, more specifically, Lori Singer) when he came up with the name for his Siren. Clements says it wasn&amp;#39;t a conscious thing, but now admits that the parallels between a town that prohibited dancing and a women who has to give up her voice no doubt collided in his mind during the creative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Sebastian was originally going to be British, and named Desmond.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Clements and Musker originally wrote Ariel&amp;#39;s crabby sidekick as a stuffed-shirt British servant. Song producer and lyricist Howard Ashman is the one who suggested (insisted, even) that they make the character a Rastafarian Jamaican, which would allow him to bring in some Calypso-themed music. Good move, especially since the film won Ashman and composer Alan Menken an Oscar for &amp;quot;Under the Sea&amp;quot;. You can watch that night&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HIuTSrBtYF4&quot;&gt;cringe-worthy performance here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Ariel was supposed to have a dolphin best friend voiced by Robin Williams.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
It only makes sense to have a dolphin in a sea-themed movie, right? Problem was, Clements and Musker had overloaded their script with characters. They also realized that Ariel had been written as too passive—inspired by Laura from &lt;em&gt;The Glass Menagerie&lt;/em&gt;. So they decided to cut the dolphin and put that character&amp;#39;s agency into Ariel. Then they put Robin Williams in their next film, &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Jim Carrey auditioned for the role of Prince Eric.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Four years before he became Ace Ventura, Jim Carrey auditioned for the role of Ariel&amp;#39;s prince charming. He lost out to 16-year-old Christopher Daniel-Barnes, who everyone thought sounded much older than he actually was. While Jim Carrey went on to become – well, Jim Carrey – Barnes became famous for playing Greg Brady in &lt;em&gt;The Brady Bunch&lt;/em&gt; films before parlaying the skills he developed with Disney into a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0055549/&quot;&gt;fairly spectacular voice-acting career&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Ursula was inspired by Bea Arthur, Joan Collins, and Divine—and Roseanne Barr auditioned for the part.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Different animators brought different aspects to Ursula&amp;#39;s personality, but the script specifically referenced Bea Arthur in &lt;em&gt;The Golden Girls&lt;/em&gt;. This &amp;quot;unflattering&amp;quot; comparison to a sea-witch apparently turned Arthur (or her agent) off from considering the part. But that didn&amp;#39;t matter, because the personality was rounded out as part drag queen, part &amp;quot;matron of Miami&amp;quot;—complete with Octopus tentacles. Although the directors admit to cheating on the number of tentacles (because it was &amp;quot;easier to animate 6 than 8&amp;quot;). But Ursula also has two arms, so there you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Early focus-test screenings completely changed how the movie was marketed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In the final stretch of production, it became clear that Disney might have a hit on their hands. Even Jeffrey &amp;quot;Girl Movies Make No Money&amp;quot; Katzenberg came around. &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt; received the highest audience scores &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; for Disney at the time, and, most surprisingly to the suits, resonated with adults, too. In fact, Disney decided to do the first-ever all-adult test screening for an animated film, and realized how differently it played for them. The marketing department therefore decided to sell it as a date-night movie for adults—and the rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/23/9-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-the-little-mermaid.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/23/9-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-the-little-mermaid.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Frank</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Nothing sells tickets like plastering a big ol&amp;#39; movie star&amp;#39;s face on the poster. And who has a hotter face right now than Michael Fassbender? He&amp;#39;s one of the hottest actors on the planet, fresh off an unforgettable performance in the Oscar-winning Best Picture &lt;em&gt;12 Years a Slave&lt;/em&gt;. He&amp;#39;s also a critical darling, and a man revered by men as much as he is coveted by women. What could possibly be complicated about marketing his newest film &lt;em&gt;Frank&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe using the star&amp;#39;s head isn&amp;#39;t really an option when it&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; covered in plaster for most of the film. But instead of running away from that challenge, you faced it head on. The oversized cartoonish cranium is, after all, the heart and soul of the entire film, and the hook that&amp;#39;s going to get people talking. That was certainly the case for Chris Sievey – the musician and comedian from the 80s whose alter ego, Frank Sidebottom, inspired the film. Although in director Lenny Abrahamson&amp;#39;s version, Frank is the object of affection, and not the protagonist. This story follows a character named Jon (inspired by the film&amp;#39;s co-writer, Jon Ronson), who stumbles into Frank&amp;#39;s band as a keyboard player and becomes swept up in Frank&amp;#39;s eccentric allure. Luckily, the mystery of the man behind the mask doesn&amp;#39;t consume the entire narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, your whole campaign is promoting this as a film starring Michael Fassbender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So without the benefit of facial expressions, or even much mobility, Fassbender channels his emotions through the broken and comical cadence of a mid-western American accent. He doesn&amp;#39;t aim for brooding and mysterious. Instead, he sounds more like a lost child, eager to please and almost aloof to the fact that his mask is a choice. This allows for the film&amp;#39;s other main star, Domhall Gleeson, to feel like he&amp;#39;s witnessing the birth of a misunderstood genius, rather than being caught up in a gimmick gone too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is, will the audience buy it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did. Maggie Gyllenhaal&amp;#39;s performance as a loyal but no-bullshit band member provides a refreshing counterweight to the whole premise. Gleeson&amp;#39;s anti-charisma as an actor is also played just right, as he tweets about his banal efforts to write great songs between his #epicsandwiches. Even the music, which is always just to the left of ever being truly melodic, feels right for a band that&amp;#39;s trying to consciously break into the scene sideways. The filmmaking plays it a little safer, giving us an easy entry point with the Jon character and emotional arc to follow, even if it&amp;#39;s not a predictable path to stardom and success. Then again, I never expected Frank&amp;#39;s big fake head to make deadmau5 kind of waves ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.macleans.ca/work/jobs/a-sneak-peek-at-our-who-earns-what-issue/&quot;&gt;$23M last year alone&lt;/a&gt; – mouse mask and all). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frank&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;#39;t look to be headed towards that kind of business, but don&amp;#39;t consider that a failing on your part. Even &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/7/shame.html&quot;&gt;Fassbender&amp;#39;s penis&lt;/a&gt; has a hard time selling tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/22/frank.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/22/frank.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>10 Questions with Randall William Cook, Animation Supervisor.</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;11 years after &lt;em&gt;The Return of the King&lt;/em&gt; took home 11 Oscars, Christopher Redmond speaks with three-time Academy Award winner Randall William Cook about what it was like to work on the groundbreaking &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy, misconceptions about his profession, and the state of blockbuster filmmaking today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&amp;#39;re best known for your work on &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy. Can you talk about how you got that job?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hired and employed as Animation Director until about a month before the film came out, then I was told, &amp;quot;Oh, the DGA (Director&amp;#39;s Guild of America) won&amp;#39;t let us give you that. So can you come up with your own credit? Whatever you want.&amp;quot; Well I wanted Animation Director, but never mind. So we settled for Animation Designer and Supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter and I worked together in a way that isn&amp;#39;t industry standard - that is to say that he hired me and I was answerable directly to him. I was the first American hire that they made back in 1998 - and I was hired on to design action scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He actually said, &amp;quot;you can do that better than I can so you design the action scenes&amp;quot; which is funny knowing who he is now. But back then, he was still, flatteringly enough, someone who had liked my stop-motion and my 2nd Unit Directing and effects directing in films like &lt;em&gt;The Gate&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;I Mad Man&lt;/em&gt; and other bargain basement fare like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was called down there to supervise the pre-vis department and create scenes for him in computer animation, which would then be referred to and sometimes followed slavishly on the set. I got to lay-out, choreograph, pick cam angles, pick editorial cut points all that stuff, and Peter allowed me this freedom because he&amp;#39;d seen my other stuff, and we had had conversations and found that we shared similar aesthetic values. So when it came time for them to choose an Animation Director, they asked me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are Animation Supervisor&amp;#39;s always hired that early in the process?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual Animation Director, from what I can ascertain, is hired by the Visual Effects Director after the visual effects and the scenes have been designed. In my case, I was in on thinking up sequences, not just being a traffic cop as I had been on &lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; picture, where I didn&amp;#39;t design anything. I just said, &amp;quot;a little faster, a little slower, have him do this instead of that, make sure that all the limbs are in the frames so we know what he&amp;#39;s doing.&amp;quot; Fairly tame stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the day-to-day responsibilities of a standard Animation Supervisor, both during production and in between productions?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve never been an in-house Animation Supervisor, I&amp;#39;ve only been hired on a per case basis, but the prescribed duties are, in many ways secondary to the end result, which involves application of art and taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re overseeing animation, with any sort of authority, you need to be directing the animation characters, because an animation character who isn&amp;#39;t acting isn&amp;#39;t really pulling his weight. Even the monsters act. Going back to 1933 &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt;, there was a lot of acting there that&amp;#39;s what gave it its charm. It&amp;#39;s not that the brushstrokes in the original &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; yielded photographic results, but they were very bold and the brushstrokes were in the right places so they gave an impression of drama, an impression of fury, an impression of character. You got to know the character of that big monkey who was just little hunk of rubber and plastic. You got to know the character of that big monkey through the way he was compelled to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately it all comes down to the needs of the performance at any given moment in the arc of the story. I&amp;#39;m not somebody who makes a differentiation between acting and animating, I think it&amp;#39;s the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then talk to me about motion-capture performances and how that has changed in the past ten years.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well the past ten years it has greater fidelity to capturing all sorts of nuances. I haven&amp;#39;t worked with all the facial capture stuff they&amp;#39;ve done recently - but I&amp;#39;m told that a lot of that, as it was ten years ago, is still heavily edited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an evolving art form and it&amp;#39;s a tool which when it becomes more transparent can be better and better. It&amp;#39;s more about the end result of the performance and it doesn&amp;#39;t really matter how you get here so long as it&amp;#39;s compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To the average person who is not in the film business, what is the most misunderstood part of your profession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose it&amp;#39;s the notion that everything that goes through the computer is untouched by human hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a studio is rushing to complete a Christmas release, they&amp;#39;ll hire all the animators they can get a hold of, so they&amp;#39;ll all fly to wherever, work on the project then they&amp;#39;ll fly to another hemisphere to work on the summer releases. The studios can&amp;#39;t really publicize their personnel, so they have to publicize their technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, this emphasis on technology is generally the thing that&amp;#39;s talked about the most, to the devaluation of the artist, because the artist is just a temporary hire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re painting a house, it doesn&amp;#39;t matter if you have Picasso or Diego Rivera or some schmuck from down the street. You&amp;#39;re going to have a painted house. And a lot of the big movies are painted houses - some of them well-painted houses, but still - if you&amp;#39;re doing a heartfelt character there has to be not only guidance from a good director and animation director or supervisor, or whatever the DGA will let us call ourselves these days, but also guidance from top notch animators. So it&amp;#39;s a collaborative work. This all of course builds on top of a performance that may have come from an actor, and it may not have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there a standard career path to getting where you got?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell no! When I was seven I thought I was going to be Ray Harryhausen, not knowing that that job was already taken. I didn&amp;#39;t know what I was going to be. Because I&amp;#39;m interested in so many different things, I did a lot of butterfly chasing in my career. I guess I never made a huge success at any of it because I was not so interested at having a steady job as I was in doing something that was interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did films like &lt;em&gt;The Gate&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;I Mad Man&lt;/em&gt;, I pretty much had control of what the characters would be doing on screen and had control of how I would achieve the various effects, be it trick perspective shots or stop-motion. I gravitated towards opportunities that didn&amp;#39;t pigeonhole me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are people out there right now who you feel are really exciting in the world of animation? Can you name some specific animators?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, because I may not get them on my show. And why piss off the other ones?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll tell you one thing though, and I mean this sincerely; I was really worried when I took on &lt;em&gt;The Amazing Spider-Man&lt;/em&gt; because I didn&amp;#39;t know any of the crew, I didn&amp;#39;t know any of the animators. And a lot of them were Sony animators who&amp;#39;d just come off the fucking &lt;em&gt;Smurfs&lt;/em&gt; , so I was really worried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something&amp;#39;s changed in the last 15- 20 years, as things always do. When I got there, I was shocked at how many top-notch talents there were out there - a number of them superstars. Virtually all the people that we had on that crew, and it was like a 30-40 person crew, I lost count.I was shocked at the number of highly talented people. I say &amp;#39;people&amp;#39; because a lot of them were female animators, which wasn&amp;#39;t the case when I was a young stop-motion animator and it wasn&amp;#39;t the case when I was at Disney, really. Disney was a very patriarchal place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You worked there for a year, but were Disney films a big inspiration growing up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t have any interest in doing Disney animation because those films never particularly beguiled me. I spent my childhood with the Cyclops, and &lt;em&gt;The Beast from 20 Fathoms&lt;/em&gt;, not with Thumper and Jiminy and that lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But somebody online recently showed a picture of Mowgli climbing a tree, it was a Milt Kahl pencil test for The Jungle Book — it&amp;#39;s a kid climbing a tree using his hands and feet, but it was so well acted, and so well realized, and so entertaining because it&amp;#39;s a kid trying to climb a tree like a monkey. And this great animator, did a great job - if you were going to do it now, you&amp;#39;d get the stunt team in, you&amp;#39;d rig him up, put wires and all that shit, and the reality of just getting him from the ground to the top of the tree without any serious injury, sort of supercedes any attempts at pantomime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of lines on paper, drawn by a master, you have a wonderful human trying to be an animal performance that&amp;#39;s believable, and funny, and true. It&amp;#39;s not just doing things that are impossible, getting every fucking superhero jumping through the air for a quarter of a mile then making a heroic three-point landing in front of the camera. Yeah, people can&amp;#39;t do that, but eventually people won&amp;#39;t be able to stand watching it. The contribution of something that is human and true and funny and accessible is something that animation, like acting, when done well, can be surprising and wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Were there people you looked up to for guidance when you were coming up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell for &lt;em&gt;The7th Voyage of Sinbad&lt;/em&gt; when I was 7 yrs old. That was just a different way of seeing things. You can&amp;#39;t see that sort of thing in real life - this big cyclops stomping around a beach - and Ray Harryhausen was my first childhood idol in the movies. He idolized Willis O&amp;#39;Brien, who made &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; and was a big fan of &lt;em&gt;The Thief of Bagdad&lt;/em&gt; so he grew up making movies about &lt;em&gt;King Kong&lt;/em&gt; stomping around through Bagdad. I was fascinated by the fact that these unreal characters were doing things and interacting with human beings. I was inspired not only to the sense of the fantastic, but to a sense of design and imaginative happenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also inspired by Lon Chaney Sr. I found an encyclopedia with pictures of him very early on and since I had a budding ability to draw I was interested in artists and illustrators like NC Wyeth at an early age. He of course illustrated Treasure Island and a number of books of that ilk, all the classic Scribner children&amp;#39;s adventure books – &lt;em&gt;The Deerslayer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mysterious Island&lt;/em&gt;. I looked at the Chaney photos and thought, this is a guy who can change himself like an illustrator! It&amp;#39;s like delineating a character like N.C. Wyeth does. I thought that was fascinating so I got interested in makeup too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another boyhood crush of mine was Jonathan Winters who played all these characters. He&amp;#39;d create all these improvisational characters and all these different voices. The Winters voices and the Chaney faces were something that obsessed me for a long time, and got me to pay attention to more subtle kinds of acting. I was always interested in big overt things like Orson Welles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it safe to say that your greatest success would be winning those three Oscars?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a statistic, and it was real nice that we did work that was recognized by a number of voters. But that&amp;#39;s a team effort. Most Oscars are. When you&amp;#39;ve got a 12-man animation team on film one, and a 44 animation team on film three, you have to look at those statues and figure which percentage of it belongs to which other people on the crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night we got the first one, at an after ceremony dinner, I spoke to Robert Redford. He said &amp;quot;how does it feel?&amp;quot;, because he&amp;#39;d won one that night as well. I said, &amp;quot;it&amp;#39;s alright, but two weeks ago, Ray Harryhausen came down to visit in New Zealand to give a little talk, and he brought along the skeleton that had appeared in &lt;em&gt;The 7th Voyage of Sinbad&lt;/em&gt; and I got to hold that skeleton in my hands. That&amp;#39;s really what got me into this racket, and that was a lot bigger thrill.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/20/10-questions-with-randall-william-cook.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/20/10-questions-with-randall-william-cook.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Price We Pay‎</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Documentaries about corporations and the bad things they do always seem to be a popular choice with festival audiences, including this former Poli-Sci major (who, admittedly, napped through most of second-year International Political Economy). Harold Crooks&amp;#39; &lt;em&gt;The Price We Pay&lt;/em&gt; tackles the issue of corporate tax avoidance and offshore tax havens. While a decent primer on the subject, I found the film got carried away with spotlighting corporate bad guys and neglected to answer some key questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid relying too heavily on talking heads, Crooks incorporates footage from UK parliamentary commissions and hearings with various executives from companies like Apple, Google, and Amazon. The British MPs emerge as the stars of the production. Their feisty, acerbic take-downs of the suits in the hot seat approaches near fervor at times, giving the audience plenty to boo and hiss about. Enjoyable as that was, Crooks drops the ball when it comes to making the case for the link between corporate tax avoidance and an increasingly heavy tax burden on the public. I accept the thesis, but I would have liked to see some more numbers to back it up. You can&amp;#39;t call your film &lt;em&gt;The Price We Pay&lt;/em&gt; without telling me what that price actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-postcard-2-the-price-we-pay.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-postcard-2-the-price-we-pay.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Connection‎</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I usually avoid your Gala Presentations line-up. It&amp;#39;s stellar programming, but I know I&amp;#39;ll eventually get to see most of those films in theatres, and I&amp;#39;d rather save my money for selections I&amp;#39;ll probably never get another chance to see. I made an exception for Cédric Jimenez&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;The Connection&lt;/em&gt;, about the notorious drug trafficking network operating in Europe and North America in the 1970s, and and I&amp;#39;m kicking myself for not attending the actual premiere. Stargazing isn&amp;#39;t really my cup of tea, but I&amp;#39;d watch Jean Dujardin shell pistachios in silence for two hours and still consider it the most compelling thing I&amp;#39;d seen all year. Seriously, the man might have the most hard-working eyebrows in contemporary cinema. They are a supporting role unto themselves. So, just this once, I may not have minded the shrieking throngs on the red carpet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dujardin and Gilles Lellouche both deliver excellent performances as, respectively, a magistrate and a powerful drug lord. Set in 1970s Marseille, the film is slick and stylish on all fronts (questionable sideburns on all male actors notwithstanding), with a killer soundtrack and an gripping plot that garnered some of the most enthusiastic audience response I witnessed at the festival this year&amp;#39;s festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some dispute between me and my companion as to whether or not &lt;em&gt;The Connection&lt;/em&gt; can be considered a remake of William Friedkin’s &lt;em&gt;The French Connection&lt;/em&gt;. I lean towards looking at it as a loose remake, rather than a different take on the same story. Dujardin’s magistrate is no Popeye Doyle, but the obsessive cat-and-mouse dynamic between criminal and cop is the cornerstone of both films, and there are other such common elements that make comparisons and references between the two films unavoidable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. I have but one complaint; the most memorable part of the original &lt;em&gt;The French Connection&lt;/em&gt; was the chase sequence. You know the one. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; chase sequence. Jimenez passes on recreating or refashioning the sequence in his version, and after waiting for it on tenterhooks, I felt a bit let down.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-postcard-1-the-connection.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-postcard-1-the-connection.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Ten</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Saturday, September 13.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-2014-day-ten.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/13/tiff-2014-day-ten.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Tu dors Nicole‎</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A dead-pan comedy from Quebec? I never thought I&amp;#39;d see the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having programmed so many films from La Belle Province over the years, you know Quebeckers tend to like their humour a little… broad. Big comedy franchises like &lt;em&gt;Les Boys&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Elvis Gratton&lt;/em&gt; are obvious examples, as are the annual &lt;em&gt;Bye Bye&lt;/em&gt; New Year broadcasts, and omnipresent &lt;em&gt;Just For Laughs&lt;/em&gt; television specials. It seems like an inordinate amount of Quebec humour comes from banana peels. Then someone like Stéphane Lafleur comes along and breaks all the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tu dors Nicole&lt;/em&gt; is framed and paced like a socially detached black-and-white art-house film following the circuitous summer days of two small town girls. But hints of surrealism tip off the audience to the comic absurdity. This feels like the first Echo X film, but made for a generation who is still too young to have found its own voice. Although this is pretty a darn good start.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-postcard-2-tu-dors-nicole.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-postcard-2-tu-dors-nicole.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>99 Homes</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your line-up this year might have some problems, but &lt;em&gt;99 Homes&lt;/em&gt; ain&amp;#39;t one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writer/director Ramin Bahari steps out of indie obscurity to create a pointed and poignant look at the U.S. housing crash. Andrew Garfield and Michael Shannon face-off in this realistic drama about how the rich get richer, and the poor get fucked. Small details, like Garfield&amp;#39;s overgrown hair and Shannon&amp;#39;s smart (but not slick) manipulating ground the film rather than making it feel like it&amp;#39;s simply capitalizing on a cautionary tale du jour. It&amp;#39;s this year&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Margin Call&lt;/em&gt;, but with a better chance at breaking through to a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;99 Homes&lt;/em&gt; is essentially a horror film for home-owners. Only the ghosts are real, and they come knocking on your door with foreclosure orders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-postcard-1-99-homes.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-postcard-1-99-homes.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>TIFF 2014: Day Nine</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Our postcard dispatches form the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival for Friday, September 12.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-2014-day-nine.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/12/tiff-2014-day-nine.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Imitation Game‎</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This is The Important British film with a capital WWII that everyone at the festival has been waiting for. And wow, it delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of mathematician/code-cracking genius Alan Turing was Oscar-bait the moment it was conceived as a screenplay. But what&amp;#39;s amazing is how well everything is actually handled. The non-chronological structure helps to not only keep the pacing strong, the plot twists engaging, and the character turns more dynamic, but also ensures that the climax is properly chilling without a sagging denouement. It&amp;#39;s an exceptional story told exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cast is also in fine form, even if &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&amp;#39;s&lt;/em&gt; Benedict Cumberbatch was the too-obvious choice to play another brilliant, socially awkward techno wiz. Consider it his redemption for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/10/22/the-fifth-estate.html&quot;&gt;another similar role&lt;/a&gt; in a film that opened your fest last year. This time, he&amp;#39;s given real heart and a full character arc, which finds a great dramatic ally in the film&amp;#39;s already monumental historical stakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If enough people see the film, it&amp;#39;s easily the most obvious (and maybe appropriate) choice for winning this year&amp;#39;s famous Audience Award.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/11/tiff-postcard-2-the-imitation-game.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
