<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Get Hard</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You have quite the progressive pedigree: two dads—one black, one white. You were written by Tupac Shakur, but your melody and chorus is taken from the 1986 Bruce Hornsby song, “The Way It Is”. While your soft-rock side is rooted in the economic hardships faced by many during the recession of the 1980s, your rap half reflects the social issues of the 1990s, exploring themes of racial inequality and poverty. Nearly twenty years later, many of the things your two dads talked about - racism, poverty, drug addiction, and exploding prison populations - haven’t really improved in America. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an anthem for social change carries a lot of responsibility. It can probably feel pretty heavy. Maybe you needed a little break, and that’s why you decided to appear in an R-rated comedy. It’s the only explanation I can come up with for your inclusion in a film that’s essentially a 100-minute long prison-rape joke. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt; is about Jack King, a wealthy hedge fund manager wrongly convicted of fraud who has thirty days to get his affairs in order before starting a 10-year prison sentence at San Quentin. He wrongfully assumes that his African-American car detailer, Darnell, has been to prison, so hires him in order to learn to survive behind bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systemic racism and the growing disparity between the rich and the poor are topics that Tupac often explored. These same topics are fertile ground for satire, and, with Will Ferrell and Kevin Hart being two of the most popular comedians working today, it was only a matter of time before someone pulled all these elements together. It’s a formula that has worked countless times in the past. And here, it’s a formula that should have worked a little harder. Based on the trailer, I knew better than to expect &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt; to reach &lt;em&gt;Trading Places&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Blazing Saddles&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Stir Crazy&lt;/em&gt;-levels of comedic subversion. But I hoped that it would at least surpass &lt;em&gt;Big Stan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;I Now Pronounce You Chuck and Larry-&lt;/em&gt;levels of stupidity. It doesn’t. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film starts strong, focusing on how insulated James is in his 1% universe and how determined Darnell is to provide a better life for his wife and daughter. The whole plot hinges on the preconceived notion that James, using the statistic that one in three African-American males will be incarcerated, automatically assumes Darnell is a criminal. While trying to justify his scheme to his wife, Darnell says, “I’ll just be every stereotype he already thinks I am!” It’s a pointed statement for a promising premise—until Darnell actually shows up at James’ mansion for the first day of training. That’s when the film decides, fuck it, here are all the anal sex jokes &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;, drops the mic, and walks away. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; called &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt;, after all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tupac knew that when a mic was in his hand it was his responsibility to use it as a tool for social change (his Black Panther parents probably had something to do with shaping this philosophy). All great artists aspire to hold a mirror up to society in hopes of inspiring change. &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt; fails not because it isn’t funny, but because it squanders an opportunity to be funny &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First-time feature director Etan Cohen is no stranger to biting social commentary, having penned &lt;em&gt;Tropic Thunder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Idiocracy,&lt;/em&gt; both of which gleefully skewered American culture. Writers Jay Martel and Ian Roberts write for &lt;em&gt;Key &amp;amp; Peele&lt;/em&gt;, one of the sharpest comedy shows on television. Story contributor Adam McKay has had huge success working with Will Ferrell on &lt;em&gt;SNL&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Anchorman,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Funny or Die&lt;/em&gt;. You’d think that if anyone could create something that is both hilarious &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; culturally relevant, it would be them. The director and stars have been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/03/25/kevin-hart-will-ferrell-get-hard_n_6938526.html&quot;&gt;particularly defensive in interviews&lt;/a&gt;, each claiming that they worked very hard to find the right balance between comedy and commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, but don’t you believe them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t offended by the flaccid prosthetic penis slapped in James’ face, or the one-dimensional portrayal of women (horny WASP golddigger, drug-dealer’s ho, etc.), or even the gay panic subtext. I was offended by the film’s laziness. It confuses being shocking and obnoxious with being edgy. Instead of finding the line and cleverly crossing it, it finds the line and takes a greasy, self-righteous dump on it. And yet, despite it all, Ferrell and Hart manage to deliver a few laughs. Unfortunately, most are about as cheap as the film’s faux-prison sets and unimaginative camera work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of your lyrics, Tupac sings, “we ain’t ready to see a black president.” It’s sad that he didn’t live to see his country elect one. But Obama’s America still isn’t much different than the one your lyrics describe. To be fair to the makers of &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt;, no one could have predicted the impact of the Ferguson or Eric Garner tragedies that took place during filming. But when James yells, “this is post-racial America, assholes,” it’s a sentiment that might have been better left on the cutting room floor. It also goes to show just how tone-deaf the filmmakers are. But what should we have expected from people who still think the height of comedy is seeing Will Ferrell’s pasty white ass? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s just the way it is. Some things will never change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/27/get-hard.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/27/get-hard.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Insurgent’s Big Gay (and Pansexual) Metaphor</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how I missed it the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I saw &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; a few weeks ago, it struck me as just another dystopian teen picture with a human-race-divide-by-faction premise (after three &lt;em&gt;Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt; films, &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;, et al). The real-world parallel felt akin to teens choosing a major in university – divergents being the “dangerous” equivalent to undeclared students. The one thing that did stand out for me was how, for once, there &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; a love triangle used to hold the whole thing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know. I’m so naïve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, along comes &lt;em&gt;Insurgent&lt;/em&gt;. A little more confident, a little more forthright, but really, the haircut gave it away. The &lt;em&gt;Divergent Series&lt;/em&gt; is about experimenting in college – but not with classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/21/insurgent.html&quot;&gt;Shailene Woodley’s distracting new ‘do&lt;/a&gt;could mean any number of things, from the deeply emotional to purely practical. But for me, it was a deafening dog whistle that the filmmakers were ready to come out with a more pointed message for anyone willing to listen. The character of Triss isn’t really looking for a faction, she’s looking for a letter to claim in the ever growing LGBT banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap, the &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Series&lt;/em&gt; takes place in a world where characters take an elaborate aptitude test to determine what group their personality is best suited for – be it Abnegation (the selfless), Erudite (the intelligent), Dauntless (the brave), Aminity (the peaceful) or Candor (the honest). The test will tell you what lifestyle you “should” choose, but ultimately the decision rests with the individual. Those who don’t fit in anywhere become Factionless (and shunned). Those who fit in &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt; are considered Divergent (and a threat to the entire label-heavy system). Triss, of course, is Divergent – compatible with every faction, but drawn to one for reasons she can’t explain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Triss is treated like a Pansexual. And “P’s” don’t exactly fit the mainstream understanding of the LGBT label, therefore they need to be discarded. How can someone can be attracted to &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; gender identity, right? Yet at the same time, their molecular rejection of gender binaries could also unlock our entire understanding of human nature.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To drive the point home, the scientific leader of this world develops a system that rates where an individual lands on the divergent scale. Triss is a perfect 100. Most people land in the 40s and aren&amp;#39;t worth the time of day. Alfred Kinsey would be proud. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this lens, it’s hard not to see the phallic machines that send Triss into convulsions as equivalent to the eletro-shock therapy of the 1950s and 1960s that sent perfectly healthy queer people into personal hell. Even the guns used by the Erudite soldiers (read: the straight establishment) are closer to tranquilizers, simulating a chemical castration that deprives people of their true identity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language throughout the series is also consistent with a teen coming out of the closet. Triss literally imagines herself saving her mother from a flaming home (her mother was also Divergent) and breaking through glass walls that divide her from her family. Most pointedly, her brother represents heteronormative standards, where one can almost too easily chose a label and feel threatened by those who don’t. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Divergent Series&lt;/em&gt;’ central metaphor of not fitting in will no doubt strike a chord with all sorts of teens, but I’m happy to see the series itself is finally getting more comfortable in its own skin. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/24/insurgents-big-gay-and-pansexual-metaphor.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/24/insurgents-big-gay-and-pansexual-metaphor.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Tracks</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When your human, Robyn Davidson, decided  she was going to trek 1700 miles across the unforgiving Australian outback in 1975, there was never any question who would be by her side. In almost all of the &lt;em&gt;National Geographic&lt;/em&gt; photos taken on her journey, there you are — usually at the edge of the frame, your black, four-legged silhouette the embodiment of canine loyalty. Though you have long since passed on, you were well represented in &lt;em&gt;Tracks,&lt;/em&gt; the film of Davidson’s journey. In fact, it seems we learn the most about Davidson through her devotion to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dog that plays you, Special Agent Gibbs, looks eerily like my dog, a black Lab/Doberman/Shepherd mutt. This would explain my almost irrational emotional attachment to your character. But regardless of the doppelgänger effect tugging at my heartstrings, your presence is essential to the narrative. Davidson did indeed set out to traverse some of the harshest environment on the planet without human accompaniment, but despite her best attempts at solitude, she certainly wasn’t alone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some obvious parallels between Davidson in &lt;em&gt;Tracks&lt;/em&gt; and that other recently celebrated “woman walks alone” biopic subject Cheryl Strayed in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/1/4/wild.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wild&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Both films are anchored by strong and understated performances; here, MiaWasikowska plays Davidson with unglamorous, wounded determination. Both women are in their early twenties, both lost their mothers, and both are fiercely independent (almost to the point of recklessness). One of the main differences between the women are Strayed’s lackadaisical approach to preparation versus Davidson’s two year build-up to her journey. Davidson spent this time living off the grid with you in an abandoned house while learning how to tame feral camels to carry her supplies for the trek. Strayed’s journey began in part because she had lost faith in herself. Davidson, it’s clear, has little faith in anyone but herself. And, of course, you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davidson wasn&amp;#39;t a fan of  being around people, which may partly explain why she reveled in leading her non-human family across the Outback. Her backstory is hinted at in conversation and in hazy, dream-like, flashbacks. Many of which only obliquely reference her mother’s suicide while focusing on Davidson’s attachment to the family Retriever named Goldie. We begin to see why she became so dependent on you. Like the best dogs, you possess many admirable traits; you’re smart, loyal, protective, emotionally intelligent and affectionate. Best of all, you want next to nothing in return. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desperate for finances, Davidson begrudgingly approaches &lt;em&gt;National Geographic&lt;/em&gt; for sponsorship on advice from an American photographer she meets. Much to her chagrin, this photographer, Rick Smolan will join her at various points to document her journey. Adam Driver portrays Smolan as an irritating yet loveable cross between Woody Allen, and Dennis Hopper’s manic photojournalist character from &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse Now.&lt;/em&gt; His obvious affection for Davidson could only be described as puppyish, yet his gorgeous photos are credited as being the inspiration for the look of the film. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinematographer Mandy Walker deftly shows us that the Australian landscape is as visually stunning as it is brutal. Her approach is deliberate and hypnotic. With its rich orange sand and deep red rocks contrasted by an infinite azure sky, it’s no wonder Davidson didn’t want to share these views with anyone but you and her camels. When she needs accompaniment from an Aboriginal elder to traverse sacred grounds, she feels a great kinship with her escort, Mr. Eddy. For hundreds of miles the two conduct a true Aussie walkabout in silent reverence for their surroundings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about having a dog is never feeling alone. Davidson was fortunate to have you to tell all her secrets. But unfortunately for the audience, we aren’t privy to her motivations or desires, which makes her triumph less satisfying than it should be. But &lt;em&gt;Tracks&lt;/em&gt;’ breathtaking locations and lush cinematography more than make up for its trudging pace and unfulfilling character development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were anything like my dog, you didn’t care where you went, so long as you were outside. Dogs seem to understand that the journey is its own reward. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/23/tracks.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/23/tracks.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Insurgent</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In the pantheon of film tropes, a female character cutting off all of her hair is lazy shorthand for internal transformation. Either she’s survived a traumatic event and chopping off her locks symbolizes her emotional turmoil, or she’s making a bold statement by eschewing the trappings of mainstream femininity. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Insurgent’&lt;/em&gt;s protagonist, Triss, it’s a bit of both. After her radical coming of age, the &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; series seemed poised to emulate the level of dystopian cultural gravitas that the &lt;em&gt;Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt; series brings to its films. But you and &lt;em&gt;Insurgent&lt;/em&gt; made me realize what snazzy new haircuts and middling middle films have in common: both are expensive and fussy and, though initially exciting, fall flat if they aren’t shaped properly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumping into the middle of a second film in a series feels a little like overhearing gossip about strangers at a busy hair salon: it’s momentarily entertaining, yet ultimately inconsequential. Following a coup, &lt;em&gt;Insurgent&lt;/em&gt; finds Triss and her boyfriend, Four, on the run from Jeanine, head of the Erudite faction. Intent on defeating Jeanine and restoring order to their world, Triss, Four, and the remaining Dauntless faction must join forces with the Factionless, led by Four’s estranged mother, Evelyn. In order to maintain complete control over the factions (Erudite, Candor, Abnegation, Amity, and Dauntless), Jeanine needs Triss, the most powerful Divergent—and also the only person who can open a box containing a message from the elders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were quite the hot topic on the way to the theatre. My 16 year-old niece was rather irked that you were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, as the YA novel describes, cut just below the ear. Instead you were shorn into a short pixie-cut. This kind of detail matters to the teen girl readership (which is the same demographic that melted over the teens-with-cancer weeper &lt;em&gt;The Fault In Our Stars,&lt;/em&gt; the film adaptation also starring Woodley and the reason for your cut in the first place). Having not read the books, I was irked by &lt;em&gt;Insurgent’&lt;/em&gt;s inability to advance the characters beyond the people we left at the end of &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; by even a hair’s breadth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, the film is detail-heavy. Especially with regards to the special effects, which are elaborate and mesmerizing. Triss must undergo trance-like simulations that require her to rescue her mother from a burning house hurtling through dystopian Chicago. In another, she must fight a version of herself. These sequences and others render objects and people into flying fragments; pixels disintegrate in slow motion and particles dissolving before Triss’ eyes. The film is fascinating to watch—but only when it’s not exhausting. The obvious plot twists and relentless exposition left me yearning for characters I could root for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film industry has done much hair-pulling recently over &lt;a href=&quot;http://variety.com/2015/film/news/women-lead-roles-in-movies-study-hunger-games-gone-girl-1201429016/&quot;&gt;the dearth of roles for women&lt;/a&gt;, especially those of a certain age. In this regard, &lt;em&gt;Insurgent&lt;/em&gt; is a cut above. Though their characters don’t exactly jump off the page, Octavia Spencer, Ashley Judd, Naomi Watts, and Kate Winslet succeed in elevating this installment beyond its weary premise. No doubt any one of them would have killed for a lead in this series had it been conceived twenty years ago, happily shearing off their locks for the chance to portray a strong female protagonist in a lucrative franchise. Like the formidable actresses that surround her, Woodley definitely has the chops to survive in this industry. She, along with the rest of the cast, are the only thing that keeps this overblown ‘do from delving into the territory of SyFy Channel original programming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had my share of drastic long-to-short haircuts (out of boredom; I’m not a movie character). One thing is certain, once the stylist has made that first cut: you have no choice but to commit. &lt;em&gt;Insurgent&lt;/em&gt; is the halfway mark of a series, and, despite the dazzle, it failed to deliver the excitement or intensity that the first film (however naïve) promised. Let’s hope that both you and the series find a way to transition out of that awkward “in-between” phase.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just remember, it could have been worse. Triss could have gotten a perm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/21/insurgent.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/21/insurgent.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Gunman</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;My reaction at the end of &lt;em&gt;The Gunman&lt;/em&gt; was pretty simple… WTF did I just watch?  Try to imagine a flaccid remake of John Frankenheimer’s &lt;em&gt;Ronin—&lt;/em&gt; but without the car chases. Then also imagine the occasional incoherent stab at exposing corporate malfeasance and geopolitical manipulation. If you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; imagine all of that then you are about halfway to recreating the experience of watching &lt;em&gt;The Gunman&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sliding scale of expectation when it comes to evaluating a film like this. Going into &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/content/2015/1/12/taken-3.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taken3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a while back, I made sure I had some help to make it through the screening—mostly because I was pretty sure it was going to be awful. On the other hand, the run up to &lt;em&gt;The Gunman&lt;/em&gt; had completely seduced me by massaging my action movie sweet spots. The trailers were marvels of efficient editing. It is also a great cast: Javier Bardem, Idris Elba, and Sean Penn moving through beautiful locales like Barcelona, London, and the Ivory Coast. Finally, I had heard Sean Penn doing some interviews and he actually sounded mildly enthused about the project&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how could it go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where to start? The direction is incredibly ham-fisted, once it steps outside of the mayhem. And even then, when an awkward metaphor involving bull fighting and the potential demise of Penn’s ‘gunman’ character is introduced, the purity of an otherwise perfectly competent sequence is ruined. There is also—I kid you not—a sequence where the male and female leads rush towards one another and embrace after a perilous separation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That really happened. It wasn’t played for laughs. Or even a snicker. Although it sure received one in the theatre where I was sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem of all was Sean Penn. I had once believed there was something authentic about his performances but I’m beginning to see how it was mostly an extension of his Hemingway-esque posturing in the real world. There really isn’t much there, even in the quiet, perfectly lit moments of broody angst. It just doesn’t scan. And dude, you are in great shape for a man your age but keep your fucking shirt on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Penn’s character is ostensibly the moral center of the film, but &lt;em&gt;The Gunman&lt;/em&gt; wants it both ways; he is alternately a brutally efficient killing machine and a remorseful NGO aid worker—without any of the psychological complexity necessary to square that particular circle. He comes off as a reluctant psycho-killer whose Doctor Without Borders lover cannot resist, despite her full knowledge of his various war crimes. The whole relationship seems as contrived and ad hoc as the rest of the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my fellow movie traveler, don’t make the same sacrifice of time—and neurons—that I did.  Stay home and watch Robert De Niro and Sean Bean drive really fast cars through the French countryside. And know I have suffered for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it mean something, Private Ryan. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/19/the-gunman.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/19/the-gunman.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Will a Female Comedian Ever Be a Movie Star?</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Sometime around the year 2000, I had a sad epiphany. While talking movies with some friends, I realized there was no female equivalent to the big comedy stars of the day: Jim Carrey, Mike Myers, Adam Sandler, Eddie Murphy, etc. The only counterexample we could think of was Cameron Diaz. But other than &lt;em&gt;There’s Something About Mary,&lt;/em&gt; there wasn’t much to base that argument on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I had no answer as to why a woman hadn’t broken through with the same success as so many men. But I figured it was only a matter of time. A new century was upon us, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to last weekend: another epiphany. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently three sitcoms  in my weekly must-watch TV schedule: &lt;em&gt;Girls&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Broad City&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt&lt;/em&gt;. Three shows that don’t just feature female leads, but each boast deep rosters of hilarious female characters and creators. And this is on top of other shows chalk full of great female leads like &lt;em&gt;Veep&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Mindy Project&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Parks and Rec,&lt;/em&gt; and easily a dozen others.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I tried to think of equivalent female &lt;em&gt;movie&lt;/em&gt; stars. Women who are performing in comedy films with the same success as their small-screen counterparts. Needless to say, I couldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What gives? Why is it that television has long been, and is now (perhaps more than ever) filled with funny female actors and rich characters, while female film stars are always one-and-done when it comes to big comedy successes? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first instinct is to blame Kristen Wiig. Who can forget the fervor that surrounded &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids&lt;/em&gt;, and the countless think-pieces that heralded the coming of an exciting new world of female-driven comedies? The film’s wild crossover success (evidenced, for me, by the fact my 81-year-old grandma also loved the film) resulted in a critical and financial bonanza, including two Academy Award nominations (Best Original Screenplay for Wiig and Annie Mumolo, and a Supporting Actress nod for Melissa McCarthy). But Wiig seemingly took all that goodwill and burned it with a string of low-energy indie films (&lt;em&gt;Girl Most Likely&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hateship Loveship,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/3/30/friends-with-kids.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Friends With Kids&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, The Skeleton Twins&lt;/em&gt;). Maybe it was a conscious reaction to the pressure, but, so far, it certainly feels like a squandered opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the four years since &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids&lt;/em&gt;, I don’t feel like we’re much further ahead. There are exceptions, of course. &lt;em&gt;The Heat&lt;/em&gt; made almost as much money as &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids,&lt;/em&gt; and co-starred McCarthy, who has made a valiant effort to be crowned the queen of comedy. Her crude clowning can kick ass, but her big test at solo stardom was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/7/24/tammy.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tammy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which failed to generate significant business (or laughs). Her co-star, Sandra Bullock, also bucked the one-off comedy curse (&lt;em&gt;Miss Congeniality&lt;/em&gt;’s lackluster sequel, notwithstanding), but no one will ever consider the Academy Award-winner a comedy-first movie star. Same goes for Reese Witherspoon, Barbara Streisand, and Diane Keaton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiig still seems to be the Great White Hope for female comedy superstardom. Her campaign got a serious boost this January when she was announced as one of the leads in the upcoming, all-female &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/ghosts-of-ghostbusters.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; reboot (along with McCarthy, Kate McKinnon, and Leslie Jones). But any excitement generated by that bold decision was quickly deflated by the seemingly knee-jerk follow-up announcement telling us not to worry because, of course, there will  be an all-male &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters&lt;/em&gt; remake as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I’m so relieved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who’s to blame here? Is it the writers who can’t generate funny female-driven scripts? Is it the studios? Can they really be &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; entrenched in sexism when audience demand is so obvious? From &lt;em&gt;Clueless&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/10/3/pitch-perfect.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pitch Perfect&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, people buy tickets when something good is in theaters. And the talent pool for funny female performers has never been deeper: Emma Stone, Aubrey Plaza, Zooey Deschanel, Amy Schumer, Rose Byrne, Kat Dennings—all of them are talented enough toone day wear the crown. Even Rebel Wilson has a shot (even if she&amp;#39;s destined to always be the Josh Gad to McCarthy’s Jonah Hill). Then there’s Sarah Silverman, Tina Fey, Amy Poehler, Queen Latifa, Leslie Mann, Elizabeth Banks, and Jennifer Aniston, all of whom are proven comedic talents, but seem to have only a fleeting interest at headlining rom-less coms. Or maybe they’ve just never had the right chance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I know is that we need more of what we’re seeing on TV every single week. It’s not hard for women to be funny. Or for them to be movie stars. So why can’t they be both?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/18/will-a-female-comedian-ever-be-a-movie-star.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/18/will-a-female-comedian-ever-be-a-movie-star.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Run All Night</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Genre films always walk a slippery slope. On the one hand, they offer the comfort of the familiar: the audience and filmmakers enter into an unspoken contract that dictates certain simple expectations will be met. On the other, simply meeting expectations isn’t enough; that familiar stuff must be expertly executed, and, in the very best cases, shown to us in a unique light. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering why I’ve opened my letter to you with this Genre 101 lesson. It’s pretty simple, really: your new movie, &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt;, is very much a film ruled by genre conventions. Yet I get the feeling that director Jaume Collet-Sera and writer Brad Ingelsby might have seen your character as the convention-breaker. Because every time you show up, &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt; suddenly goes from being predictable and uninspired to flat out ridiculous. And, well, pretty stupid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everything about &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt; is cookie-cutter. Stop me if you’ve heard any of this before: an aging mob boss who has gone (mostly) straight has a hot-headed son who may undo what he’s tried to achieve; another aging ex-enforcer (the boss’s longtime friend, natch) has become a drunk, and has become estranged from his own straight-arrow son; through a series of plot contrivances, the two sons have a run-in that eventually leaves the old-timers gunning for each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may come as a shock, but regret, revenge, and betrayal are not the most unique themes to bring to the mob genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this all sounds facetious, but I’m being a little bit sincere. The way it plays out, Collet-Sera and Ingelsby seem to think they’ve invented these tragic mob archetypes from whole cloth. They want to play at the level of tragic opera. Structuring the film as a flashback from what appears to be our hero’s final minutes tips their hand: they want events to feel predetermined. But instead they’re merely predictable (see above re: the knife’s edge of genre picture). Their true intentions are revealed in the casting. When you cast Liam Neeson as the rundown killer forced back into action to protect his son, we all know the movie they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wanted to make: the Liam-Neeson-disposes-of-bad-men-with-ruthless-efficiency movie. The new twist here is that he feels, I don’t know, a little sadder about being such an efficient killer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe it was your character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filmmakers play it mostly straight, trying heir damnedest to convince us that everything is &lt;em&gt;really heavy.&lt;/em&gt; Lord knows Harry Gregson-Williams’s score attempts to portray the crushing moral weight behind every plot point. Sure there’s a lot actions scenes that use a shaky camera in place of actual choreography, but it’s a very sad shaky cam. The less said about the silly 3D computer effects that move us from one location to another, the better (okay, I’ll say this much: at least it’s abandoned early.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then you show up as the highly-skilled contract killer, Price. And you look – and act – like a cross between The Terminator and Brother Mouzone form &lt;em&gt;The Wire.&lt;/em&gt; Seriously, you’re just as ruthless, unstoppable, and even more impervious to pain. You’re even given a laser-sight pistol that shines through smoke, finding targets before they know you’re there (though no one specifies if it‘s actually a “phased plasma rifle with a 20 watt range”). Your character is imagined only in references to other, better characters. The most incongruous of these is your &lt;em&gt;Bullit&lt;/em&gt;-inspired trench coat—a better reference to that movie could have been made by filming coherent car chases. As you walked though corridors, killing policemen and mobsters with robot-like determination, the hollowness of &lt;em&gt;Run All Night&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#39;s pretensions are given harsh relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you disappeared for a while, and the movie continued on as if nothing out of the ordinary had happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It probably sounds like the ridiculous over-the-top-ness of your character was a welcome relief from the mediocrity of the rest of the movie – even rereading my own description of it strikes me that way – but it merely annoyed me. It was like eating at a restaurant that has reached beyond its abilities, then fed candy corn between courses: a bland meal made unpalatable by the addition of something that’s terrible even on its own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong—I don’t blame &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; for this. The conception and execution of your character speaks to the video game aesthetic Collet-Sera can’t quite escape. Like the movie itself, your character is a bunch of influences from better movies sloppily thrown together in the hope that their sum will some how create a better whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/16/run-all-night.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/16/run-all-night.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Cinderella</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Your track record is pretty impressive. &lt;em&gt;Hugo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Shutter Island&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Other Boleyn Girl&lt;/em&gt;—not only are you a master of period films, you’ve also had the pleasure of measuring Leonardo DiCaprio’s inseam more than a few times (yeah, I’m jealous—who wouldn’t be?). But even with all of those films on your resume, bringing a fairy tale like Cinderella to life must feel like one of the biggest feats of your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might think that adapting a classic like this would make your job easier. But, boy, would they be wrong. Crafting a revival like this is hard work. You have to get it exactly right. Especially with a story as familiar as Cinderella: she’s the innocent girl with a pure heart forced to serve her stepmom and stepsisters, only to be transformed into a princess by her fairy godmother so she can meet her prince. Stroke of midnight, glass slippers—you know, Disney 101.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, you didn’t let the expectations stifle you. You met the challenge and managed to perfectly capture the magic and flamboyance of the story through the wardrobe you created, from duotone slim-cut jackets that make princes charming to the the fluid movement of Victorian-era gowns that turn lonely country girls into the belle of the ball. Later, when the wicked stepsisters showed up, they didn’t need to say a word to reveal their idiocy—the loud, jewel-encrusted clothing they wore told me everything I needed to know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s during ballroom scene, when the men and maidens hit the dance floor, that your strategic use of colour is most striking. Draping all the other guests in warm tones while Cinderella is wrapped in striking light blue fabric kept my eyes locked on her as she drifted through the sea of revellers was brilliant. No spotlight needed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and director Kenneth Branagh clearly used the 1950 version as a template for this live-action adaptation, but you managed to avoid turning it into yet another reimagining basted in unnecessary grittiness. I’ll admit, after &lt;em&gt;Alice in Wonderland&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oz: The Great and Powerful&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Maleficent&lt;/em&gt;, it was refreshing to see a retelling that relied on the storybook enchantment that made the story popular in the first place. I don’t need to see Prince Charming riding a Harley and blasting fools with a sawed-off (or do I?). With live-action versions of &lt;em&gt;The Jungle Book&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Beauty and the Beast,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dumbo&lt;/em&gt; recently announced, I suspect there will be a creative tug-o’-war about which approach to take. If you happen to be involved in any of these upcoming movies, please do your best to steer them down the lighter path. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, this film is good. Not great, but good. Hell, all I know is that it’s been years since I’ve seen the old animated version, and you made me remember what it was like to feel the bippity, the boppity, and most definitely the boo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have Courage and Be Kind,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ankit&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/CInderella.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/CInderella.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>&#39;71</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It is films like &lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt; that remind all of us why cinema can be called an art form. There is no commercial rationale for this film, no real clamor for an intimate picture about one English soldier and his harrowing experiences in Northern Ireland during the height of the unrest in 1971. In fact, without you and your support it is unlikely &lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt; would have seen the light of day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an extraordinary film. Affecting and subtly peppered with the kind of bucolic tragedy that occupies sectarian conflicts across the world, &lt;em&gt;‘71&lt;/em&gt; honors the ideals you champion: developing young talent and helping to tell stories that are aesthetically rigorous while still remaining approachable to a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;’71&lt;/em&gt; is a straightforward thriller. A young British soldier gets separated from his unit during a daytime raid on a Catholic block in Belfast, and then the rest of the film is occupied with his struggle to find his way back to his barracks. The depth of the work comes from the young soldier’s interactions with the various factions (and the individuals that comprise them) as he makes his fraught journey back to what he believes is safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The filmmaking is remarkably assured for any director but especially for someone making their feature film debut. Yann Demange is, not incidentally, someone you (and other privately and publicly funded institutions) have helped nurture throughout his career. This is a fine example of how properly funded and supported infrastructure can lead to some extraordinary work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cinematography is top notch, the editing is fluid and clear, and the story bangs along at a pitch perfect clip. The performances are uniformly solid. The only real standout—aside from the lead performance by Jack O’Connell—is Corey McKinley, a young actor playing an unnamed Loyalist youth. He owns the screen for a seven-minute stretch that pivots the whole film. McKinley manages to be both precociously assertive and somehow tragic as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a visual artistry to the film that comes close to overshadowing the narrative but Demange ultimately exercises shrewd judgment in where he puts his camera. Thrillers seem to work best, for me at least, when they remain restrained and understated. This film never forgets that dramatic tension derives from humans having to make decisions in a fundamentally clouded moral universe. For each character there are no good options, just ones that are more, or less, evil and self-serving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘71&lt;/em&gt; contains useful echoes of Sydney Pollack’s &lt;em&gt;Three Days of The Condor&lt;/em&gt;. It features a protagonist who is resourceful and capable trying to work through a byzantine and largely inscrutable political maze. Ultimately though, he is at the mercy of the people he encounters along the way, and it is how those interactions play out that determine his fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘71&lt;/em&gt; also has echoes of some of the best of the American films made in the late sixties and early seventies. It seems that a lot of modern filmmakers (JC Chandor and now Demange, just to name two) are taking their cues from people like Lumet, Scorsese and even Friedkin–producing muscular, spare dramas with a strong emphasis on good scripts and interesting characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for whatever part you have in encouraging this kind of good work I cannot thank you enough, BFI. This was an unlooked for gem in what seems to be a bit of a renaissance for films made for adults.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/71.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/13/71.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Housebound</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s astonishing how easy you make it look, man. Blending horror and comedy in a manner that keeps one from overpowering the other is always a tricky feat. Frankly, it&amp;#39;s difficult to think of any recent films that have successfully managed it. That’s why your whip-smart script for &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; is so special—it brings the funny and the scary together beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with your strong handling of the characters. A question that inevitably comes up during the course of a haunted house flick is: &amp;quot;Why don&amp;#39;t they just leave?&amp;quot; Sure, you have your &lt;em&gt;Insidious&lt;/em&gt;es and your &lt;em&gt;Paranormal Activitie&lt;/em&gt;s which explain it away by revealing that the supernatural activity is bound to a person instead of a location. But I quite dig your practical solution: because of the electronic monitoring device around her ankle, petty criminal Kylie is forced to deal with sinister goings-on, lest she violate the terms of her house arrest.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neat and simple. Yet you provide us with a nice about-face later on when Kylie is given an opportunity to escape, only to stay for purely altruistic reasons. The more she learns about the house&amp;#39;s bloody past, as well as a killer who has escaped justice, the more her motivations evolve. She undergoes genuine moments of growth, and doesn’t just make decisions solely to benefit the script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to share a brief thought or two about Amos, the security guard tasked with monitoring our protagonist: you so easily could have made him the stock asshole who scoffs when evidence of the supernatural first rears its head, but his boyish enthusiasm and immediate willingness to help is incredibly charming. He’s yet another great character that elevates this already great movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit back to what I was saying before: it&amp;#39;s impressive how carefully you tread the line between comedic and full-on horror elements. There&amp;#39;s a great bit with dial-up internet, terrific banter between Kylie and Amos, and some outrageously zany gore gags that bring to mind the early work of Peter Jackson. But there is also genuine tension when there needs to be, and we never lose sight of just how high the stakes are for our protagonists. What best exemplifies this balancing of contrasting tones is the climax. It features one of the best extended showdown-with-a-killer sequences I&amp;#39;ve seen in recent memory, it manages to be gut-bustingly funny one second and hand-wringingly intense the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit that I felt a slight twinge of disappointment when the movie shifted gears and the nature of what&amp;#39;s was truly on at the house was cast in a different light. But that speaks more to my personal expectations, and it was certainly a clever and unexpected direction to take the story. It hit some unexpectedly emotional beats as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m guessing you&amp;#39;ve heard the news that &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; is already being optioned for an American remake. It’s so bafflingly unnecessary that I can&amp;#39;t even put it in words (maybe just a series of inarticulate noises). It seems a safe bet that we can save ourselves a little time and write it off as being inferior.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years from now, if &lt;em&gt;Housebound&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#39;t mentioned in the same breath as other horror-comedy classics like &lt;em&gt;Dead Alive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Evil Dead II&lt;/em&gt;, than I&amp;#39;ll be sure to eat my hat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/11/housebound.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/11/housebound.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
