<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Dear Cast &amp; Crew</title>
		<description>Open letter film reviews, essays, and exchanges.</description>		
		<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Miss Julie</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;As prop hand, you’re surely familiar with the world’s most famous prop-based theory of drama: Chekhov’s Gun. The renowned playwright described the principle like this: “If you say in the first chapter that there is a rifle hanging on the wall, in the second or third chapter it absolutely must go off.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt;, written by Chekhov contemporary August Strindberg and adapted for the screen by Liv Ullmann, is a prime example of naturalism. It’s realistic, it’s a careful study of human behaviour, and, above all, it’s austere. Every prop is there for a reason. While you may not have had to provide a rifle to any of the actors in &lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt;, they will be wounded nonetheless. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What starts out as an exhilarating &lt;em&gt;pas de&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;deux&lt;/em&gt; of two desperate people bringing each other to the height of ecstasy and the depths of despair, things eventually grow tiresome. If you had hoped for a light summer job to supplement your regular gig of doing prop work on &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;, I’m sure you were soon wishing you had signed on for that Carrot Top movie instead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt; takes place at a Baron’s estate during Midsummer Night in 1890. The Baron’s valet, John, is engaged to the pious cook Kathleen, but must fend off the amorous attempts of the Baron’s daughter, Miss Julie. Throughout the course of the night, John and Miss Julie will enter into a dangerous affair that will have fatal consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ullmann is no stranger to cinematic tragedy. As one of famed director Ingmar Bergman’s muses, Ullmann starred in many of the legendary Swede’s films – &lt;em&gt;Cries and Whispers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Scenes From A Marriage&lt;/em&gt;, to name a few – all of which examine themes of class, faith, and redemption. As a director (&lt;em&gt;Faithless&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sofie&lt;/em&gt;) Ullman has often explored complex relationships between men and women. Strindberg’s study of a strong-willed aristocratic woman and an ambitious servant dancing between repulsion and desire would seem the perfect vehicle for Ullmann. And it is—almost to a fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a few noticeable exceptions, &lt;em&gt;Miss Julie&lt;/em&gt; is filmed mainly in the kitchen of the estate, which must have made your job easier. Unfortunately the static nature of the sets and the cinematography make it difficult for the film to overcome its stage origins, and threatens to undermine the naturalistic conceit. Thankfully, three very skilled actors are able to transcend these boundaries and deliver performances that are alternately heartbreaking, explosive, and agonizing. Jessica Chastain and Colin Farrell, as Miss Julie and John, take turns seducing and rebuffing one another, all to the point of physical and emotional exhaustion. But it’s Samantha Morton as Kathleen who steals the movie with her understated despair. As the moral center of the story, Kathleen might be a woman scorned, but she’s never pitiable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like your dedication to filling Tyrion Lannister’s wineskin, most of your job here involves drinking vessels. In an early scene in which Kathleen serves John lunch, he asks for his wine in a crystal glass. Later, when Miss Julie orders John to serve her a beer, he pours it into an earthenware mug. These class distinctions are constantly at play. After their affair is consummated and Miss Julie realizes she is a ruined woman, John shuns her by saying that intimacy between the working class doesn’t mean anything, but for the aristocracy, it means &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every scheme to save reputations is marked by one of the characters pulling out glasses from the cupboard and something dark and alcoholic from a dusty bottle. Here is where your skills must have been seriously tested. You no doubt had many a conversation with the script supervisor before each take to determine exactly how much alcohol needed to be in each goblet. While watching Chastain and Farrell treating each other so brutally day after day, were you ever tempted to switch their fake wine with the real stuff? Did you secretly long for a stiff drink yourself? I know after more than two hours of watching their bleak struggle I was begging for some relief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the third act, a pouch of money and a straight razor contribute to a tension already heightened by lust, loathing, and, of course, alcohol. It’s only a matter of time before these props bring the entire depressing scenario to an unsurprisingly grim conclusion. Ullmann tries to soften the rough edges by making the film look like a glowing 19th-century oil painting, and should be commended for her ability to draw out such tortured and raw performances. But as the film plods its way to its foregone and ugly conclusion, it seems she just didn’t know when to put it out of its misery. It’s a shame you couldn’t have handed her Chekhov’s gun. Or Tyrion’s wineskin. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/10/miss-julie.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/10/miss-julie.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>While We&#39;re Young</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m moving in a few weeks, so I recently went through some old boxes to de-clutter before packing. Inevitably the old yearbooks came out, encouragement and optimism scrawled across the pages in glittery gel ink. Old trophies, too. And certificates of achievement and excellence. It was all a startling reminder that I once had actual dreams . &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that sinking feeling of what-the-fuck-happened-to-me was something I could relate to when I saw &lt;em&gt;While We’re Young&lt;/em&gt; a few days later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the film, fortysomethings Josh and Cornelia are in a bit of a rut. They try to downplay it, but their discontent slowly reveals itself as their best friends become parents and start doing that really annoying thing parents do to their childless friends: “You &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to have kids, it’s the best thing &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;!” Josh’s filmmaking career is also at a standstill, as he struggles to piece together his documentary from ten years worth of footage about…actually, I still can’t figure out what that documentary was about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a good fifteen to twenty years away from a mid-life crisis, but I connected with Josh and Cornelia right away. There’s nothing drastically wrong with their lives, but once they realize they’ve lost that feeling of endless possibility, it starts to weigh on them. They are stagnant while everyone else in their lives appears to be moving steadily from one milestone to the next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spark that brings Josh and Cornelia out of their funk comes in the form of Jamie and Darby, bohemian twentysomethings (to whom I will refer as “The Hipsters”) who dazzle the older couple with their infectious enthusiasm and free-spiritedness. Suddenly, Josh is the cool, accomplished mentor to Jamie, and Cornelia can hang out with Darby in baby-free places, doing baby-free things. The contrast between the two couples is perhaps best represented by the homes you created for them. Josh and Cornelia’s place is well-appointed, if somewhat sterile. The Hipsters’ place, on the other hand, is shabby, disordered, and you crammed it with all kinds of cool stuff that had me wanting a similar look for &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; new place. Their apartment led me to reminisce fondly about the furniture in my first apartment, like the awesome couch I randomly scored from the curb. The Hipsters are kind of ridiculous and pretentious, but the combination of nostalgia and regret is no match for pragmatism and common sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did worry that the film would lose steam right around the halfway point. The two couples flit from one charming (mis)adventure to the next, and while it’s amusing, I worried that momentum would be lost and we’d spend the last 30 minutes schlepping towards an unsatisfying conclusion. But director Noah Baumbach throws in a twist that waves smelling salts under the nose of the plot and keeps it revived and energetic through to the end. As charming as the Hipsters are at the beginning of the film, I enjoyed watching the shine rub off of them. The film’s last act is like crashing after a sugar high. Darby and Jamie are a pack of Skittles: sweet, delightful, and you can’t get enough of them. But an hour later your head hurts and you realize they’re full of unhealthy shit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being effortlessly cool requires so much effort it’s downright exhausting. As Josh and Cornelia learn this and try to regain footing in their own, comfortable lives, I thought about the house you decorated for them, which I initially dismissed as boring and WASP-y. On second thought, it was comfortable, and the things in it were put there with care and thought. That is what I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want for my new home. Because that old couch I got from the curb was actually crap; I had to steam-clean and sanitize it four times before I could sit on it without getting a rash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, &lt;em&gt;While We’re Young&lt;/em&gt; struck a chord with me because I could relate to those feelings of being stuck after leaving your twenties behind. There are no big revelations or sea changes, but I walked away considering the merits of a little misadventure to help one feel &lt;em&gt;unstuck&lt;/em&gt;, and when the candy coating of nostalgia wore off entirely, I was back to browsing IKEA catalogues. Because I’m not some damn hipster. Now get off my lawn. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/9/while-were-young.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/9/while-were-young.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Conversation With &lt;em&gt;Pretend We&#39;re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; Writer/Director Matt Sadowski</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Di Golding talks to &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; writer/director Matt Sadowski  about the challenges of making a “non-rom-com” and how to film a perfectly awkward sex scene.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there something specific about the rom-com genre that turns you off, or made you want to make a non-rom-com?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen, I like movies like &lt;em&gt;Win A Date With Tad Hamilton&lt;/em&gt; as much as the next lad, but what I felt was missing was romantic comedies that accurately show that not everything &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; work out. I felt that I could connect to a lot of romantic comedies until the final act. Because for me – and maybe other people too – I never really got a second chance when I screwed things up. The main movie that really lit the fire for this was, back in 2004 there was only &lt;em&gt;Before Sunrise&lt;/em&gt;, it wasn’t a trilogy yet, and I really felt like once she (Celine) gets on the train and leaves at the end, I always felt like, if they hadn’t split up, if they’d spent one more day together, would they really have had that kind of connection? I totally buy that ten years later that fire is fuelled again. But after talking to a lot of people, everyone has had those flings where, whether it’s for a minute or an hour or a day or a week, you feel like “wow, we have everything going on,” and one thing can turn it completely off. I really wanted to show that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing a “non-rom com” film must be tricky. Who do you think the audience is for&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little bit of marketing speak, but I really believe it’s a romantic comedy for people who don’t think they like romantic comedies. And maybe they don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they don’t like romantic comedies. Maybe it is because they (rom-coms) have a kind of plastic coating to them, whether because of who they cast or a clichéd script or just a formulaic way of shooting it. I think some people, they know, and they can call it out. This is why I don’t make these kind of movies. But I think for some people it’s just a feeling that they have. And I really just wanted to make something that could make people feel just a little bit different and hope that they relate to it because it feels a little bit more real. And the problem with being real is that sometime you lose hope, and I wanted to make a film that kind of questions ideas about falling in love and destiny—but without being cynical about it, either. I think that’s sometimes hard to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You did something interesting that was not rom-commy: instead of doing a lot of close ups and soft focus, you did a lot of long takes and medium shots, and you just kind of let things happen. You let the actors act. Did you always know that you were going to film it this way?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a certain style that people know, oh, that’s an indie film, and it’s this kind of handheld, finding the focus, documentary kind of look that really does work for a lot of films. But I felt like it wasn’t the right look for this one. The films that I was inspired by were films from the 70s and 80s, and if you look at those films, their frames linger and they last a long time and it makes you listen in a different way and it makes you expect things in a completely different way. I kind of felt like when you’re in a relationship and it’s going well, you don’t blink. That’s the essence of the vibe I wanted the film to have. I wanted it to be long, gazing looks to make the whole thing a little bit dreamier, because that’s how you feel. And I also feel like relationships aren’t very funny, they’re all kind of awkward, and holding on the frame brings the awkwardness. Not just from the characters – because Benny is pretty awkward – but finding your way on a new date or a new relationship is kind of awkward in itself, and I feel like a long take really helps that especially when you as an audience are now trained to know I’m not going to cut, or you’re not going to see an insert, or you’re not going get a close up, and we get to the sex scene, you kind of know what’s going to happen so you get on the edge of your seat in embarrassment before something actually does happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ve often heard about actors in sex scenes saying that they’re not as easy as they look, that they need to be very precise in how they’re filmed. Did you storyboard this and did the actors rehearse a lot?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that was one of the scenes we rehearsed the most. I was also lucky that out of all the scenes in the script, Dov and Tommie really responded to that scene, more so than any other scene. Because other scenes were “Benny and Jordan walk down the sidewalk”, and that scene is very specific. “He gets on top of her, he moves his knee, he puts his hand on her hair,” so it was all inherent in the stage direction of the script. And I think that gave them a lot of confidence to just follow the script, because it read really awkward as well. So that will come across. And a little behind the scenes story as well is that you can’t shoot a sex scene without having a union rep there, and a union rep makes everyone more nervous. And that was Dov’s first romantic scene ever and I think he was already nervous, and then to have a union rep come in and be like, “Don’t do anything you’re uncomfortable with, these are your rights,” just put so much in his head, which halted production for quite a while, to be honest—but his character is so anxiety-ridden and in his head anyway that it kind of worked out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your last feature was a documentary (&lt;em&gt;Don’t You Forget About Me&lt;/em&gt;). Did that make it easier or harder for you to direct your first scripted feature?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the doc was harder to make because I would say the only thing original about the doc was the idea that I had. But then you’re relying on so many other things to make the film happen. Everyone literally has a voice. Every producer has a voice, every interviewee has a voice. Sometimes you’re not able to shoot where you want so you have to shoot it in a certain style. And that film took so long to make. For that kind of specific doc, it’s an amalgamation of a lot of people’s visions whereas for this film I kind of was able to drive the ship a little more and was very lucky to have a crew that believed in the same sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I read that (executive producer) Pete Harvey made the entire crew read the script before signing on to make the film.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought that was really cool. We shot in 14 days and we had almost 30 locations, which is unheard of. People thought we were crazy. Most indie films shoot in a 15 or 20-day window and there’s 8 locations. Or there’s &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; location. So right from the beginning he said the only way we’re gonna get a crew to work hard for us – and because of the shots that I did – its easier to shoot in a kind of verité handheld style, because you don’t need the same amount of equipment trucks and gaffing and all that kind of stuff. To make all these long shots work required a lot of production elements to kind of come together. So Pete was amazing. And I never understood it. I was like, “why does the PA have to read the script? Why does the 3rd grip have to read the scrip?” And he said: “because I want every single person to want to make the film because they think the film can be really cool.” And he was right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/8/a-conversation-with-matt-sadowski.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/8/a-conversation-with-matt-sadowski.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Furious 7</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Face it – nobody wanted you on this film. But it’s not your fault. Your position on &lt;em&gt;Furious 7&lt;/em&gt; was one born of tragedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;em&gt;Fast and Furious&lt;/em&gt; star Paul Walker was all-too-ironically killed while speeding in a Porsche Carrera GT, the only way to complete production was with the help of Walker’s two similar looking brothers, Caleb and Cody, and Weta’s top-notch team of special effects animators like you. There must have been moments when the collision between art and life felt a bit much to take. Still, you had a job to do. This red-hot action franchise has grown into an unstoppable machine, even more surreal than the chaos on screen. And that’s saying a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the film is complete, your work is seamless, and the result is… unreal. In the best possible way. Never once did I feel a camera cheat or compromise. Quite the opposite. &lt;em&gt;Furious 7&lt;/em&gt; is pushing what’s possible in action cinema, and often left me speechless in my chair.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try and paint you a picture in terms you’ll no doubt understand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dilated pupils, bated breath&lt;/em&gt; – the lights finally lower in the theatre and the Universal logo takes over the screen. I’m way too revved up to see this film considering I only hopped on the bandwagon at &lt;em&gt;Fast Five&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cheeks go flush&lt;/em&gt; – my man-crush, Jason Statham, makes his debut in the franchise, walking slowly out of a hospital in the aftermath of an encounter with a British tactical SWAT team. Without an ounce of sweat or expression, he struts away from explosions in slow motion like the boss he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Head cocks slightly to the left. A befuddled wince appears&lt;/em&gt; – the title reads &lt;em&gt;Furious Seven&lt;/em&gt;, instead of &lt;em&gt;Furious 7&lt;/em&gt; (like all the ads). I flash back to how the last film was promoted as &lt;em&gt;Fast &amp;amp; Furious 6,&lt;/em&gt; but the opening credits called it &lt;em&gt;Furious 6&lt;/em&gt;. Then the fourth film is just called &lt;em&gt;Fast &amp;amp; Furious&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;The Fast and The Furious&lt;/em&gt; … This franchise is a hot mess and I don’t care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biting the lower lip, à la Anastasia Steele –&lt;/em&gt; Vin Diesel and Michelle Rodriguez show up at some Race Wars contest in the desert, where an abundance of bikini babes may or may not be in front of expensive cars (I’m not really a car guy). More ass than an Iggy Azalea video. Speaking of which, there she is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forced laugh followed by a sad smile –&lt;/em&gt; the first close-up of Paul Walker, intercut with pressing foot pedals and jumping speed needles. Somehow, it’s predictably paid-off by revealing he’s behind the wheel of a mini-van, dropping his kid off at school. He really did have a lovely face. Whether or not it’s digital never crosses my mind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big-ass stupid grin&lt;/em&gt; – The whole team is together, in darkness, behind the wheels of different cars. Tyrese, of course, plays the clown, rhetorically asking how they keep getting into these situations. My jaw lowers in tandem with the loading ramp of the cargo plane they’re all aboard. Skydiving cars was the next logical adventure, and it doesn’t disappoint. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various vowels form on my lips, mainly Os and Es, trying to register the insanity on screen for the next two hours&lt;/em&gt; – it would take too long to describe each and every moment, from the OMGs of escaping buses on clifftops, to the WTFs of kicking the asses of hijab wearing female guards in Abu Dhabi, to the LOLs of The Rock flexing off his full arm cast. Suffice to say, no franchise commands a greater range of facial expressions than the &lt;em&gt;Fast and Furious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, there’s the dedication, “For Paul”. The final montage was as predictable and on-the-nose as every line of dialogue in this film, and equally as welcomed and satisfying. You may or may not have caught a small tear in the corner of my eye. Otherwise, this film was sheer joy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/7/furious-7.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/7/furious-7.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Pretend We&#39;re Kissing</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, I’ll come out and say it—I’ve never been your biggest fan. Sometimes you act like you’re the only city in Canada. And, worse, sometimes the rest of the world agrees. While I have family and friends who live in Toronto, I’ve always found you a little disjointed, and, well, &lt;em&gt;cold.&lt;/em&gt; With your iconic CN Tower, SkyDome, and Lakefront District, it’s hard to see you as anything but a poser. If you were a character in a movie, you’d be the uptight yuppie striver. But one of the most pleasant surprises in &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; was getting to see a different side of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all watched films that are supposedly set in New York, L.A., or Chicago, only to have a Shoppers Drug Mart or Maple Leafs ad in the background give you away. There’s been a recent trend of Canadian filmmakers eager to show you off; Sarah Polley’s &lt;em&gt;Take This Waltz&lt;/em&gt;, Atom Egoyan’s &lt;em&gt;Chloe&lt;/em&gt;, and Michael Dowse’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/8/22/the-f-word.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The F-Word&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have been content to just let you be you. In his first scripted feature, &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt;, writer/director Matt Sadowski seems particularly besotted with you, and he’s not shy about letting it show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Billed as a “non-rom-com,” &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; is about what happens in the days that follow a couple’s first perfect night together. Benny is an introverted artist plagued with nagging self-doubt. When he connects with Jordan at a concert and is too shy to approach her, he figures he’s lost his one chance. But, of course, they run into each other again, and both of them see it as a sign that they were meant to meet. However, after their first romantic encounter, they learn that you can’t force a “happily ever after.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blame it on the influence of &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; rom-coms, but many of us secretly long to be swept off our feet. Unfortunately, the reality of falling for someone at first sight is never as perfect as the movies make it seem. The dialogue isn’t effortlessly witty, the first kiss isn’t always well-timed, and the sex isn’t always mind-blowing. Sadowski has fun with these genre conventions and lets the scenes between Benny and Jordan play out in a natural – and often uncomfortable – way. It helps that actors Dov Tiefenbach and Tommie-Amber Pirie look like regular, attractive twenty-somethings and not perfectly-coiffed Hollywood glamazons. They fumble, they overreact, they try too hard—just like real people. It would have been easy to play these characters for laughs, but it takes genuine talent to underact as naturally as they do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complicating Benny’s life is Autumn, a twist on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manic_Pixie_Dream_Girl&quot;&gt;Manic Pixie Dream Girl&lt;/a&gt;. She’s a childhood friend who’s been squatting in Benny’s living room for the past year, inviting strangers over for random hookups and using all his toilet paper. A self-diagnosed agoraphobic and faux spiritualist, Autumn is kind of a nightmare, but she does give Benny the back-handed advice (“don’t be a Benny”) that he uses to nab Jordan. Zoe Kravitz’ Autumn is adorably kooky and believably annoying. It’s no wonder Benny spends all his time outside the apartment and on your many bustling streets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s there, on your streets and in your neighbourhoods, that &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; overcomes it’s “non-rom’-com” conceit. As a band flyer designer and posterer, Benny’s vocation finds him in various locations around the city. I was charmed by your countless colourful surprises – the Dutch Dreams treat shop, the Cameron House tavern, a retro bus shelter, a brick building with “You’ve Changed” written scrawled in stories-high block letters – and the manner in which they were presented. Sadowski frames his shots thoughtfully and lingers on them. This approach overcomes both the usual indie style (shaky hand-held) and the clichéd rom-com conventions (soft-focus close ups). This works especially well when highlighting the characters’ most awkward and the most vulnerable moments. But at times this effect can be more plodding than pleasing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though &lt;em&gt;Pretend We’re Kissing&lt;/em&gt; does eventually cross the line into rom-com territory (the cutesy ending is a little pat) your environment feels surprisingly fresh. You can be every bit as charming and exotic as Paris or New York. Even your CN Tower reinvents itself as romantic: a scene in which a snuggling Benny and Jordan make their way back from Toronto Island Park is reminiscent of the Brooklyn Bridge scene in &lt;em&gt;Manhattan.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any new relationship, I suppose I was guilty of projecting my expectations onto you. I begrudgingly admit, you grew on me. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible to fall in love in Toronto. And &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; Toronto. But if this film taught me anything it’s that maybe we should wait and see what tomorrow brings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, if we can make it here, we can make it anywhere, eh?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/5/pretend-were-kissing.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/5/pretend-were-kissing.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>It Follows</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Another director might have used your initial onscreen appearance as the “Giant Man” in &lt;em&gt;It Follows&lt;/em&gt; as an opportunity for a cheap jolt, perhaps offering a piece of direction like: “Run at the camera and make scary faces!” But instead, as a beleaguered young woman attempts to convince a gang of her friends that the titular &lt;em&gt;It&lt;/em&gt; really does exist, you emerge silently from the shadows of the hallway and slowly brush past them in single-minded pursuit of our heroine.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a chilling moment, and it’s heightened by the fact that only those who have been targeted by &lt;em&gt;It&lt;/em&gt; are able to see it. No matter where she goes, despite the best efforts of her friends, ur heroine Jay is facing this evil alone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director David Robert Mitchell clearly has a firm grasp on how important understatement is when it comes to crafting an effective scare sequence. This movie isn’t about big, in-your-face frights (though there certainly are moments that are genuinely hair-raising); instead, the film operates on the same level of dread that makes classic zombie films effective. Even though the primary threat is slow and seems to be easily escapable, there is always the underlying possibility that sooner or later you’ll tire or make a mistake and eventually be overtaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that vein, Mitchell’s approach of having you and the other actors who portray the various iterations of &lt;em&gt;It&lt;/em&gt; move in a very controlled, assured manner goes a long way towards establishing the antagonist(s) of &lt;em&gt;It Follows&lt;/em&gt; as one of the scariest cinematic monsters in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, he is able to build nearly impossible-to-endure levels of suspense through the use of a 360-degree rotating camera that is perpetually giving the impression that the creature might, at any moment, enter the frame from any direction. This also allows for several nice moments of humour when random passersby are mistaken for &lt;em&gt;It&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the film&amp;#39;s greatest strength is a steadfast refusal to explain away the central threat. This withholding of exposition works beautifully. Sure, there are some consistent rules by which &lt;em&gt;It&lt;/em&gt;operates – such as transmission through sexual intercourse and having a physical form that can even be injured – but everything else is left in the dark, and the movie is all the better for it. There’s a primal level of fear that comes with knowing something is coming to kill you—even if it’s moving very slowly. You don&amp;#39;t know why, and nothing you can do – reasoning with it or standing your ground – will work in the end. As one character puts it, the only real option is to run far away and buy yourself just a little more time. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; is genuine horror.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that I would want you to be typecast as giant men (are you really that tall, by the way?), but if your few seconds of screen presence in &lt;em&gt;It Follows&lt;/em&gt; is any indication, I certainly hope you show up in future genre exercises. And I hope those directors know how to use you as well as David Robert Mitchell does here. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/2/it-follows.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/4/2/it-follows.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Women, Dream Smaller</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the funniest moments from the 2014 Golden Globes was the bit involving hosts Tina Fey and Amy Poehler calling out Julia Louis-Dreyfus, nominated for Best Actress in a Motion Picture Musical or Comedy, for sitting in the “film section.” The camera cut to Louis-Dreyfus wearing oversized sunglasses and puffing an E-cigarette while snubbing Reese Witherspoon’s attempts to get a selfie with her. Later in the broadcast, the camera caught Louis-Dreyfus eating a hot-dog in the “TV section,” where she’d slunk back after losing her second Golden Globe of the night (for Best Actress in a Television Series Musical or Comedy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gag played well because the three women in on the joke are huge television stars. Huge, even by the high standards of the film world. Amy, Tina, Julia: they’re household names. They have “fuck you” money. And while they’ve all had varying degrees of success on the big screen, none of them seems particularly fussed that they haven’t achieved Jim Carrey or Eddie Murphy levels of box-office success. And why should they? They know the film/TV paradigm has shifted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two decades have seen the rise of cable, satellite, and digital networks, which has lead to a steady increase in the quality of television programing. With fewer constraints and bigger budgets, networks like HBO, AMC, FX, Comedy Central, and now Netflix are creating content that rivals cinema in scale and popularity. Cable’s increase in quality scripted shows has meant that the once all-powerful Big Three networks have had to adapt to compete. The rising tide has raised all ships, and with it, the scope of comedic roles for women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when Christopher Redmond recently asked if a female comedian could ever be a movie star, it occurred to me that the real question is: why would she want to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female-driven TV comedies like &lt;em&gt;Broad City&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Girls&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt&lt;/em&gt; are continuing a long tradition of female dominance in comedy television. In my childhood and teenage years, shows like &lt;em&gt;The Mary Tyler Moore Show, Rhoda, Maude, Alice, Facts of Life, Laverne &amp;amp; Shirley, Kate &amp;amp; Allie, Roseanne, A Different World, Murphy Brown, Designing Women,&lt;/em&gt; and _The Golden Girls reigned supreme (of those twelve shows, eight of them were either created or produced by women). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to those aforementioned programs, Susan Harris, Marcy Carsey, Caryn Mandabach, Diane English, and Linda Bloodworth-Thomason were also responsible for creating and producing at least 20 more hit television comedies (including &lt;em&gt;Soap, 3rd Rock&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;From&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Sun, That 70s Show,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Nurse Jackie).&lt;/em&gt; These women paved the way for creators, writers, and showrunners like Amy Sherman-Palladino (&lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;), Jenji Kohan (&lt;em&gt;Orange Is&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;New Black&lt;/em&gt;), Diablo Cody (&lt;em&gt;United States of Tara),&lt;/em&gt; Jill Soloway (&lt;em&gt;Transparent&lt;/em&gt;), and many more. If we throw Lena Dunham (&lt;em&gt;Girls&lt;/em&gt;), Amy Schumer (&lt;em&gt;Inside Amy Schumer&lt;/em&gt;), Tina Fey (&lt;em&gt;30 Rock, Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt&lt;/em&gt;), Mindy Kaling (&lt;em&gt;The Office, The Mindy Project),&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Ilana Glazer and Abbi Jacobson (&lt;em&gt;Broad City&lt;/em&gt;) into the mix, we’re looking at the creators and stars of some of the most critically acclaimed – and popular – shows on television. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can films compete with that? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all seen the &lt;a href=&quot;http://womenintvfilm.sdsu.edu/research.html&quot;&gt;depressing statistics&lt;/a&gt; of the number of women behind the camera in Hollywood, so when a female-driven comedy, written by women becomes a sleeper hit and nets huge box office, we’re supposed to be happy. But I was one of the few women that didn’t drink the &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids&lt;/em&gt; Kool-Aid. I just didn’t see it as the game-changer everyone kept claiming it was. It had some funny moments, sure, but nothing that really spoke to me as a woman &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; a comedy fan (I much preferred the deliciously cynical &lt;em&gt;Bachelorette&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Bridesmaids&lt;/em&gt; felt compromised to me. With its poop jokes and pratfalls, Kristen Wiig and Annie Mumolo’s screenplay wanted to be a woman’s movie for 14 year-old boys (because that teen boy demo is still the holy grail for the film industry, at least for comedies—what else would explain how Adam Sandler projects still get greenlit?). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a wealth of juicy roles for women in television, it seems that the only thing left to lure you to the big screen (besides the big paycheck) is the prestige. Sure, headlining a box-office hit is a huge accomplishment. But, as the saying goes: “You’re only as good as your last film.” (Unless, once again, you’re Adam Sandler.) That’s a lot of pressure. Here’s my advice: why not just make a hit TV show where you can enjoy the challenge of building a complex and beloved character (and earn a steady income) over the course of several seasons, then, on your off time, you can take your pick of the clever and nuanced indie scripts piling up in your trailer? If you still don’t think television is distinguished enough you can build your own production company, like Mary Tyler Moore did (MTM Enterprises), and make dozens of popular TV shows (like &lt;em&gt;The Bob Newhart Show, WKRP In Cincinnati&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Hill Street Blues&lt;/em&gt;, just to name a few), and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; find time to get nominated for a Best Actress Oscar (&lt;em&gt;Ordinary People&lt;/em&gt;). Or maybe you can just run a major television studio, like universally adored comedy legend Lucille Ball did with Desilu, which produced shows like &lt;em&gt;Mission Impossible&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and there’s one other thing the movies can’t offer: syndication. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still not convinced? Ask Julia Louis-Dreyfus if she’d trade her four decades of steady television work on iconic shows like &lt;em&gt;Saturday Night Live&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt; (or her Emmys, Golden Globe, or SAG Awards) for one big comedy box office opening weekend? Better yet, ask one of the hottest and most popular comediennes working right now, Betty White.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can ask Jim Carrey and Eddie Murphy. Anybody seen them lately?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/31/women-dream-smaller.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/31/women-dream-smaller.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Home</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Given how important visual storytelling is to any movie, especially an animated movie, a good storyboard artist can be an essential part of a film’s success—or failure. However, no amount of storytelling acuity on your part would have saved &lt;em&gt;Home&lt;/em&gt; from its saccharine banality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Storyboard artists help create a shot-by-shot map for the director to follow, so they are partially responsible for each moment up on the screen. And &lt;em&gt;Home&lt;/em&gt; certainly has some fun moments—a flying car fueled by Slushie syrup is consistently enjoyable—but it is betrayed at every turn by a tedious script and a generally annoying protagonist. Although props for passing the Bechdel test, as there is not one human male character of any consequence in the whole film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story rests heavily on the relationship between an unctuous and socially inept alien called Oh and a young woman, Tip, who is separated from her Mom when the passively aggressive Boov take over earth. The plot revolves around these two and their initially uneasy alliance. If that sounds like a rehashed trope that has been worn to a nub— it is. Rihanna and Jim Parsons from &lt;em&gt;The Big Bang Theory&lt;/em&gt; are the leads, so originality doesn’t seem to have been a big priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film stutters every time it takes a breath. It looks pretty and the design and animation is generally well conceived and executed, but the talking bits constantly feel so watered down and cliché ridden that the whole plot feels like an afterthought. I enjoyed watching how effectively the story was told but I just didn’t care one bit about anything that was happening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exception of Steve Martin as the Boov Captain (and he really is criminally underused as a voice actor), each character seemed taken from a generically inoffensive manual of stock animation characters. In fact the whole film, from the threadbare plot to the mood ring color wheel of the Boov (they change color with each emotion, further telegraphing each beat) feels like it was workshopped by a test audience locked in a room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animation is most effective as a storytelling medium when it uses its seeming innocuousness to tell a slightly transgressive story—&lt;em&gt;Iron Giant&lt;/em&gt; and its pro single parent, anti-war underpinnings or &lt;em&gt;BoxTrolls&lt;/em&gt; with its critique of class divisions and the dangers of groupthink. But &lt;em&gt;Home&lt;/em&gt; has none of the above—instead we are fed a kind of goopy homily about courage and friendship that feels remarkably insincere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did your job as well as you could, Andrew; unfortunately the creative team you were employed by seemed otherwise occupied. I hope &lt;em&gt;Home&lt;/em&gt; serves at least to pad your resume and you find work on something more suited to your obvious talents.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/30/home.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/30/home.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Get Hard</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You have quite the progressive pedigree: two dads—one black, one white. You were written by Tupac Shakur, but your melody and chorus is taken from the 1986 Bruce Hornsby song, “The Way It Is”. While your soft-rock side is rooted in the economic hardships faced by many during the recession of the 1980s, your rap half reflects the social issues of the 1990s, exploring themes of racial inequality and poverty. Nearly twenty years later, many of the things your two dads talked about - racism, poverty, drug addiction, and exploding prison populations - haven’t really improved in America. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an anthem for social change carries a lot of responsibility. It can probably feel pretty heavy. Maybe you needed a little break, and that’s why you decided to appear in an R-rated comedy. It’s the only explanation I can come up with for your inclusion in a film that’s essentially a 100-minute long prison-rape joke. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt; is about Jack King, a wealthy hedge fund manager wrongly convicted of fraud who has thirty days to get his affairs in order before starting a 10-year prison sentence at San Quentin. He wrongfully assumes that his African-American car detailer, Darnell, has been to prison, so hires him in order to learn to survive behind bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systemic racism and the growing disparity between the rich and the poor are topics that Tupac often explored. These same topics are fertile ground for satire, and, with Will Ferrell and Kevin Hart being two of the most popular comedians working today, it was only a matter of time before someone pulled all these elements together. It’s a formula that has worked countless times in the past. And here, it’s a formula that should have worked a little harder. Based on the trailer, I knew better than to expect &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt; to reach &lt;em&gt;Trading Places&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Blazing Saddles&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Stir Crazy&lt;/em&gt;-levels of comedic subversion. But I hoped that it would at least surpass &lt;em&gt;Big Stan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;I Now Pronounce You Chuck and Larry-&lt;/em&gt;levels of stupidity. It doesn’t. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film starts strong, focusing on how insulated James is in his 1% universe and how determined Darnell is to provide a better life for his wife and daughter. The whole plot hinges on the preconceived notion that James, using the statistic that one in three African-American males will be incarcerated, automatically assumes Darnell is a criminal. While trying to justify his scheme to his wife, Darnell says, “I’ll just be every stereotype he already thinks I am!” It’s a pointed statement for a promising premise—until Darnell actually shows up at James’ mansion for the first day of training. That’s when the film decides, fuck it, here are all the anal sex jokes &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;, drops the mic, and walks away. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; called &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt;, after all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tupac knew that when a mic was in his hand it was his responsibility to use it as a tool for social change (his Black Panther parents probably had something to do with shaping this philosophy). All great artists aspire to hold a mirror up to society in hopes of inspiring change. &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt; fails not because it isn’t funny, but because it squanders an opportunity to be funny &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First-time feature director Etan Cohen is no stranger to biting social commentary, having penned &lt;em&gt;Tropic Thunder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Idiocracy,&lt;/em&gt; both of which gleefully skewered American culture. Writers Jay Martel and Ian Roberts write for &lt;em&gt;Key &amp;amp; Peele&lt;/em&gt;, one of the sharpest comedy shows on television. Story contributor Adam McKay has had huge success working with Will Ferrell on &lt;em&gt;SNL&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Anchorman,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Funny or Die&lt;/em&gt;. You’d think that if anyone could create something that is both hilarious &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; culturally relevant, it would be them. The director and stars have been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/03/25/kevin-hart-will-ferrell-get-hard_n_6938526.html&quot;&gt;particularly defensive in interviews&lt;/a&gt;, each claiming that they worked very hard to find the right balance between comedy and commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, but don’t you believe them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t offended by the flaccid prosthetic penis slapped in James’ face, or the one-dimensional portrayal of women (horny WASP golddigger, drug-dealer’s ho, etc.), or even the gay panic subtext. I was offended by the film’s laziness. It confuses being shocking and obnoxious with being edgy. Instead of finding the line and cleverly crossing it, it finds the line and takes a greasy, self-righteous dump on it. And yet, despite it all, Ferrell and Hart manage to deliver a few laughs. Unfortunately, most are about as cheap as the film’s faux-prison sets and unimaginative camera work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of your lyrics, Tupac sings, “we ain’t ready to see a black president.” It’s sad that he didn’t live to see his country elect one. But Obama’s America still isn’t much different than the one your lyrics describe. To be fair to the makers of &lt;em&gt;Get Hard&lt;/em&gt;, no one could have predicted the impact of the Ferguson or Eric Garner tragedies that took place during filming. But when James yells, “this is post-racial America, assholes,” it’s a sentiment that might have been better left on the cutting room floor. It also goes to show just how tone-deaf the filmmakers are. But what should we have expected from people who still think the height of comedy is seeing Will Ferrell’s pasty white ass? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s just the way it is. Some things will never change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/27/get-hard.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/27/get-hard.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Insurgent’s Big Gay (and Pansexual) Metaphor</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how I missed it the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I saw &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; a few weeks ago, it struck me as just another dystopian teen picture with a human-race-divide-by-faction premise (after three &lt;em&gt;Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt; films, &lt;em&gt;The Maze Runner&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Giver&lt;/em&gt;, et al). The real-world parallel felt akin to teens choosing a major in university – divergents being the “dangerous” equivalent to undeclared students. The one thing that did stand out for me was how, for once, there &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; a love triangle used to hold the whole thing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know. I’m so naïve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, along comes &lt;em&gt;Insurgent&lt;/em&gt;. A little more confident, a little more forthright, but really, the haircut gave it away. The &lt;em&gt;Divergent Series&lt;/em&gt; is about experimenting in college – but not with classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/21/insurgent.html&quot;&gt;Shailene Woodley’s distracting new ‘do&lt;/a&gt;could mean any number of things, from the deeply emotional to purely practical. But for me, it was a deafening dog whistle that the filmmakers were ready to come out with a more pointed message for anyone willing to listen. The character of Triss isn’t really looking for a faction, she’s looking for a letter to claim in the ever growing LGBT banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap, the &lt;em&gt;Divergent&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Series&lt;/em&gt; takes place in a world where characters take an elaborate aptitude test to determine what group their personality is best suited for – be it Abnegation (the selfless), Erudite (the intelligent), Dauntless (the brave), Aminity (the peaceful) or Candor (the honest). The test will tell you what lifestyle you “should” choose, but ultimately the decision rests with the individual. Those who don’t fit in anywhere become Factionless (and shunned). Those who fit in &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt; are considered Divergent (and a threat to the entire label-heavy system). Triss, of course, is Divergent – compatible with every faction, but drawn to one for reasons she can’t explain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Triss is treated like a Pansexual. And “P’s” don’t exactly fit the mainstream understanding of the LGBT label, therefore they need to be discarded. How can someone can be attracted to &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; gender identity, right? Yet at the same time, their molecular rejection of gender binaries could also unlock our entire understanding of human nature.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To drive the point home, the scientific leader of this world develops a system that rates where an individual lands on the divergent scale. Triss is a perfect 100. Most people land in the 40s and aren&amp;#39;t worth the time of day. Alfred Kinsey would be proud. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this lens, it’s hard not to see the phallic machines that send Triss into convulsions as equivalent to the eletro-shock therapy of the 1950s and 1960s that sent perfectly healthy queer people into personal hell. Even the guns used by the Erudite soldiers (read: the straight establishment) are closer to tranquilizers, simulating a chemical castration that deprives people of their true identity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language throughout the series is also consistent with a teen coming out of the closet. Triss literally imagines herself saving her mother from a flaming home (her mother was also Divergent) and breaking through glass walls that divide her from her family. Most pointedly, her brother represents heteronormative standards, where one can almost too easily chose a label and feel threatened by those who don’t. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Divergent Series&lt;/em&gt;’ central metaphor of not fitting in will no doubt strike a chord with all sorts of teens, but I’m happy to see the series itself is finally getting more comfortable in its own skin. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/24/insurgents-big-gay-and-pansexual-metaphor.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/3/24/insurgents-big-gay-and-pansexual-metaphor.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
