<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<link rel="hub" href="https://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com"/>

  <title type="text" xml:lang="en">Dear Cast & Crew</title>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2017-12-19T18:15:53Z</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <rights type="text">Copyright © 2017 . All rights reserved.</rights>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Shape of Water</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/19/the-shape-of-water.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheShapeofWater" />
    <published>2017-12-19T13:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-19T13:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/19/the-shape-of-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It’s sometimes easy to forget that a movie is a collection of still images. Hundreds of thousands of still images in fact. Each one following the last, each one helping to construct pictures in the audience’s head second by second, minute by minute. Each image incrementally pushing the story forward. Each one serving an important purpose as they spool out at the rate of twenty four per second.</p>

<p>But some are more important than others.</p>

<p>As a still photographer, you understand better than most the power a single image can hold. And you work hard to find them.</p>

<p>You spend your days (and nights) on set, searching for discrete images, negotiating the various demands the production makes upon you: a poster image perhaps, certainly galleries, character portraits, production stills used for print or online magazines, publicity, reference for costumes and continuity as well as any photographic material that actual appears on camera.</p>

<p>All of this you have to produce while remaining a ghost on set. An integral part of the production, yet in some ways outside of it—finding your solitary place in a morass of lighting techs, AD’s, camera people, and all the other folks that populate a film set. Remaining invisible to actors who have no problem with a boom mic almost grazing their forehead, but can get spooked just by someone holding a still camera anywhere near their line of sight.</p>

<p>On some films, like the deliberately low key and decidedly unflashy <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2015/11/13/spotlight.html"><em>Spotlight</em></a>, it must be a challenge to find those arresting, iconic, images. After all, how many different ways can you photograph four or five people sitting in a small room, talking to one another?</p>

<p>On others, like director Guillermo del Toro’s <em>The Shape Of Water</em>, I imagine the opposite to be true. Everywhere your camera looks there must be something interesting to see and record. The challenge isn’t a poverty of choice, it’s about excess. Although that strikes me as a good problem to have.</p>

<p>Del Toro’s films have a particular visual quality to them. More than most, they feel like paintings in motion. Each frame is lovingly composed and meticulously filled with detail that is purposeful—there is no drop of water or link of chain, no sliver of light or pooling shadow, that isn’t exactly where it was intended to be. But his films are never sterile. On the contrary, that detail contributes to an atmosphere filled with both promise and dread, even when the characters inhabiting it sometimes seem blind to its charms, or dangers.</p>

<p>And <em>The Shape Of Water</em> is filled with dangers, both real and imagined, and the monsters are never exactly whom you might think. This is an extraordinary film—a poetic slice of magic realist cinema that pushes and pulls at all kinds of different strings. It is a romance in the very old sense of the word, part Grimm’s fairy tale, part James Whale and German expressionism, all of it unique in the way del Toro binds it together.</p>

<p><em>The Shape of Water</em> is about awakenings—people are spun out of their orbits and sent careening into one another by the arrival of a creature at a Government research facility located somewhere in an alternate mid-western 1966 America. It is a place filled with finned, teal Cadillacs and huge concrete bunkers busy with exotic mysteries. Women cook and clean and men pontificate. The Russians are a different kind of threat than today, but they lurk around every corner. And then there’s a monster, or a god, or just a stranger in a strange land, bound in chains and tormented in the name of science.</p>

<p>The people who fill these discrete frames are equally byzantine and exotic, even if they, at first blush, seem anything but. Sally Hawkins, Michael Shannon, Octavia Spencer, Richard Jenkins — that right there is an impressive who’s who of character actors. But they are leads here, and it is gleefully subversive how much del Toro delights in twisting the usual conventions about who these people are and the passions they can barely conceal.</p>

<p>The centre that holds all of this together is a simple but deeply affecting story about the transformative power of compassion and love, a weird (in the 30’s pulp fiction sense of that word) romance that sees the most quiet among us risk everything for someone, or something, far from human.</p>

<p>All of this is framed by del Toro in a way that makes the mundane seem a thin veneer which both horror and beauty are constantly trying to claw through. A world of grey and shadow constantly being breached by shards of light.</p>

<p>And you can see that in the frames that illustrate this review. Single images that manage to connect these two opposing aesthetics, to give us all a taste of what might be in store for us, when the lights fade, and the images start to flow, one after another, up on the screen.</p>

<p>Just you, doing your job.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Square</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/19/the-square.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheSquare" />
    <published>2017-12-19T12:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-19T12:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/19/the-square</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>As you know, Andy Warhol famously didn’t play the fool when it came to separating art and commerce. “Making money is art and working is art and good business is the best art,” he’s quoted with saying. You’d think his naked ambition would have signalled the death of the art gallery industrial complex. Instead, the value of Warhol’s work has only ever soared and is still considered a “<a href="http://www.economist.com/node/14941229">bellwether of the art market</a>”. Even today, pop art disciple Damien Hirst makes over $100M annually by bypassing the gallery game altogether. Yet the crusty culture of institutionally inflated art prices continue to prosper nearly unfettered.</p>

<p>Really, has there ever been a more apt target to satirize?</p>

<p>Ruben Östlund’s latest film, of course, isn’t trying to take the piss out of artists themselves. Not entirely, anyway. People like you working their way up the art department ranks are absolutely essential to why his vision in <em>The Square</em> comes to life so exquisitely, both adoring and abhorring the world of contemporary art museums. The attention given to the film’s art direction and careful framing of each shot, combined with the petulant nonsense that happens within it, is what accentuates his theme in ways the narrative never has to.</p>

<p>Except, of course, when it does. The film opens with a simple question: if a common object, like the purse of Elizabeth Moss (who plays a naive art journalist) is placed in a gallery, does the space suddenly imbue the object with new meaning? Does it become art? It’s a bit of a philosophical wank, especially the way it’s posed with such convoluted rhetoric in the film. Moss’ confused/differential shrug offers about as satisfactory of an answer as one could hope for, and one that crystallizes everything right with <em>The Square</em>.</p>

<p>In the same way Östlund handily tore masculinity a new one in <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2014/9/5/tiff-2014-day-two.html"><em>Force Majeure</em></a>, his ability to undermine what’s revered about fine art galleries comes in sneaky waves. Focusing on the actions of a museum curator in Sweden, the film builds up a series of events that only ever get half pursued. We do get several scenes where he tries to find a pickpocket who robbed him of his wallet (and, more importantly, his moment of heroism), but other threads, both comedic and dramatic, are often left dangling rather than being fully indulged. Though he doesn’t spare a second of the extended anguish that occurs in the film’s nearly untelegraphed climax, where an artist agonizingly insists on intensifying his performance for a room of museum patrons. The scene could almost say as much completely out of context, but is of course greatly enriched for being included in the film (you know, like stuff in a gallery).  And in this case, the artist also embodies all the confidence and defiance missing from the staid life of the museum’s curator.</p>

<p>But what to say of the film’s titular Square that frames at least some of the story’s inner pretension and ambition? As fun as that set piece may have been to make, I can’t help but think it was also the film’s most obvious red herring. So let’s not fall into the trap of over selling or analyzing its simple and silly significance.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Justice League</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/19/justice-league.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=JusticeLeague" />
    <published>2017-12-19T01:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-19T01:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/19/justice-league</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p><em>“It shouldn’t have been approved internally let alone gone all the way to make it into the film. That shocked me a bit. We were all looking at each other when the film started like ’WTF is this?!’”</em></p>

<p>This is you, a DC effects artist, on the record (but withholding your name) during a Reddit AMA.  You’re speaking about the now-infamous post production repair work done in the opening scene of <em>Justice League</em>. Granted, you weren’t talking about your own contributions to removing Henry Cavill’s post-film moustache in other re-shot parts of the movie, but this quote still seems to perfectly summarize a lot about <em>Justice League</em>.</p>

<p>It’s not that <em>Justice League</em> is a terrible film, per se — it actually works much better than many of its forebears, especially the Zack Snyder-directed<a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2013/6/14/man-of-steel.html"> <em>Man of Steel</em></a> and <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/3/29/batman-v-superman-dawn-of-justice.html"><em>Batman v. Superman: Dawn of Justice</em></a> (although comes nowhere close to the thrills of <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/6/16/wonder-woman.html"><em>Wonder Woman</em></a>). No, like the clumsy depilation of Cavill’s Clark Kent, <em>Justice League</em> feels reactionary and rushed, not fully thought through.</p>

<p>It’s an exhausting affair: Fitting Batman, Superman, Wonder Woman, The Flash, Aquaman, and Cyborg would be hard enough without also worrying about side stories for Lois Lane and Martha Kent. Heck, I got tired just typing all those names out.</p>

<p>When you factor in a runtime of less than two hours, everything—and everyone—ends up being reduced to storytelling signifiers more than actual moments and characters. I mean, this is a movie co-written by Joss Whedon, co-starring Joe Morton as a scientist working on advance cybertronics that can’t even find a few seconds for a sly Miles Dyson reference. Yes, it’s a crying shame.</p>

<p>Factoring all this into account, it’s no wonder that the main plot of <em>Justice League</em>, which concerns a series of Skyrim-level scenes of a CGI character named Steppenwolf* trying to conquer Earth (natch) is near indecipherable.</p>

<p><em>*Seriously, as a special effects guy, can you provide any insider details on what kind of Faustian bargain Warner/DC made that’s resulted in the godawful, impenetrably dark CGI that plagues every one of these films?</em></p>

<p>I’m not just talking about the lack of groundwork laid in previous instalments for all the characters introduced in <em>Justice League</em>, however. True, Disney/Marvel did a lot more heavy lifting to get mainstream audiences ready for the first <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2012/5/11/the-avengers.html">Avengers</a> film. (Before 2008 did the average action fan know or care who or what an Iron Man is?)  Even if <em>Justice Leagues</em> three new characters didn’t have to rely on a hackneyed introduction in <em>Batman v. Superman</em>, in which they are introduced by that classic of cinematic conventions, email, <em>Justice League</em> would still feel like a patchwork quilt sewn together by multiple contributors.</p>

<p>The reason for that is most likely that <em>Justice League</em> was itself patched together by two main contributors: Snyder and Whedon, both of whom directed scenes. While I’m loathe to factor in extra-textual sources when reading a film, in this case the film itself makes this clear. Whedon and Snyder are such different stylists — one relies on more basic, TV-style camera setups; one interested in visual style to the detriment of any kind of coherent storytelling (I’ll let you guess who is who) — that seeing them in the same film creates an inescapable stylistic dissonance.</p>

<p>The true miracle of <em>Justice League</em> is that it does manage to create a few compelling moments for its ill-defined, underdeveloped cast. Through the late contributions of Whedon, brought in to add some much-needed levity and character,  <em>Justice League</em> escapes becoming the complete dirge that is <em>Batman v. Superman</em>.</p>

<p>Still, I can’t help but return to your opening quote. <em>Justice League</em>, like the shortcuts taken in the work forced on your and your fellow artists, shows the scars of being rushed to hit a release date more than make a good film. And no amount of digital trickery can erase that.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lady Bird</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/18/lady-bird.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=LadyBird" />
    <published>2017-12-18T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-18T08:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/18/lady-bird</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>We can’t help where we were born. Like our gender, race, socio-economic status, or generation, it’s one of the fundamental truths over which we have absolutely no control. Many of us, myself included, couldn’t wait to leave the place we grew up and start exploring the world. It often isn’t until years later (and usually with some physical distance) that we begin to feel a begrudging respect for the community we came from, a kind of affection for the places and people that unknowingly shaped us.</p>

<p>I’m not sure where you grew up, but I imagine if you were tasked with scouting locations for <em>Lady Bird</em> that you have more than just a passing knowledge of Sacramento, California. This is the type of coming-of-age story that could have been set anywhere, and yet <em>had</em> to be set there. It is universal while remaining weirdly specific to its writer/director Greta Gerwig who, in her first time out of the gate, establishes herself as a confident and intuitive 21<sup>st</sup> century American filmmaker.</p>

<p><em>Lady Bird</em> opens on a Joan Didion quote about Sacramento, which frankly, worried me. Not the quote itself, but the choice to open on a Didion quote. Anything that comes after must know exactly what it is or risk appearing precious at best, or pompous at worst. The particular quote deflates the assumption that California is a bastion of hedonism and excitement when in reality, Sacramento, as a place, proves quite the opposite. The quote perfectly sets the unselfconsciously comic tone for the entire film. So much so that using Didion quotes to open movies should be retired after <em>Lady Bird</em>.</p>

<p>Sacramento, a place full of southwest suburban blandness and mundane beauty, is where the not-so-titular Lady Bird lives, and longs to escape. We meet Christine (AKA Lady Bird) at the beginning of her senior year of high school in 2002, a year that feels recent, and though somehow – without smartphones  or social media dependences, and under the backdrop of the nascent War on Terror – feels like a lifetime ago. Christine’s personality is too big for Sacramento, and possibly too big for her own house. Like most teenagers, she is the center of her own universe, much to the chagrin of her strong-willed mother, Marion. The heart of the film beats on the precariousness of their relationship.</p>

<p>Much like last year’s coming-of-age-period-piece <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2017/2/2/20th-century-women.html"><em>20</em><sup>th</sup><em>Century Women</em></a> (which also starred Gerwig), the parental figures are given as much depth and nuance as the central, teen characters. And like that film, <em>Lady Bird</em> lives and dies on its performances. Saoirse Ronan, perhaps the most naturally, unaffected actor of her generation, is equal turns endearing and enraging, and understands instinctively that any move too far to either end of that spectrum would make her character insufferable. Laurie Metcalfe, consistently singular in any role, is heartbreaking as Marion, who, like most mothers of teen daughters, is damned if she does and damned if she doesn’t give her absolute all to her child. Keeping the two from emotional annihilation is the always underrated Tracy Letts, as the patriarch of the family caught between two forces of nature.</p>

<p>One particular scenario involves Christine self-defensively joking about living on the wrong side of the tracks from Sacramento’s “Fabulous 40s ”, a well-to-do neighbourhood made up of elegant, picturesque homes. It’s a joke that, like much of Christine’s self-serving behaviour and flippant remarks, cuts Marion to the core. It’s these types of seemingly insignificant comments and actions – particularly between family members - that fester and become slow-burning resentments that eventually explode, leaving everyone burned.</p>

<p>Gerwig understands the intense drama in these tiny moments, and lets them build organically. These are the moments that inform entire relationships, dictating their future, and influencing how we remember the past. Moments that take place on a country road, a cramped kitchen, or a thrift store change room - places that seem meaningless or banal at the time yet somehow shape who we will become.</p>

<p>As you drove around Sacramento, finding these particular places, perhaps you didn’t realize their import at the time. No one knows when they’re making a movie whether it’s going to work or not. The same can be said for building a life – one is rarely presently conscious of how certain circumstances will affect the outcome of their future. It’s often only later when we realize that where we’re from has a direct influence on where we’re going, for better or for worse. In this case, for the better.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Blade of the Immortal</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/17/blade-of-the-immortal.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=BladeoftheImmortal" />
    <published>2017-12-17T06:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-17T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/17/blade-of-the-immortal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>It is not surprising that your film credit is located in the Art Department alongside Calligraphy and Storyboard Artist, because many of the weapons used in <em>Blade Of The Immortal</em> are acts of pure fiction.</p>

<p>That may sound like the kind of esoteric detail that concerns .0000001% of the population that go to movies (and it is) but, in this case, it also says a lot about what kind of film director Takashi Miike decided to make.</p>

<p>There is a great deal of history at play, given what has come before in Japanese cinema. Much of the samurai genre—most often set during the time of the Tokugawa shogunate—has been slavish in its attention to period detail. From Kurosawa to small studio efforts, most were obsessed with accurate recreations of the times and places. Even when the stories themselves echoed more contemporary themes, the physical period detail had been a central concern. Costumes, architecture, locations, farm implements, weapons, all had to be as authentic as possible. Even Miike—who justifiably has a reputation as a maverick in Japanese cinema—had followed suit in his earlier films like <em>13 Assassins</em> and <em>Hari-Kiri: Death Of A Samurai</em>.</p>

<p><em>Blade Of The Immortal</em> is a different animal for a couple of reasons. I won’t try to recap because it would require almost as much time as it would to watch the movie; these films are plot heavy, echoing the layered complexity of the period. In that, this is very much a typical samurai film. It is how Miike chooses to portray the physical detail of the period that is new. He rejects the conventional approach to both the weapons depicted and the way they’re deployed. In some films this would be a small detail, but here it is a major break with tradition.</p>

<p>There are axes that seem as if they weigh as much as ship anchors, three piece weapons that look like they were built from a demented child’s schematic, and swords that have more prongs than a 16 point buck. All are wielded to devastating effect by characters as colourful and weird as their tools—in scenes that are completely unconcerned with correct forms and accurate representations of particular martial schools.</p>

<p>Like most Miike films, <em>Blade Of The Immortal</em> doesn’t shy away from violence. However, unlike some Miike films, the depictions of the consequences of those moments are less cartoonish than usual. The contrast between the outlandish weaponry and supernatural undertones with the grim reality of the carnage gives Miike an opportunity to deal with some weighty themes—themes that would otherwise seem discordant in the midst of all the flying bodies and suddenly unmoored limbs.</p>

<p>The break with these traditions is itself a statement, suggesting that earlier depictions of the period were hidebound and myopic in a way that made it difficult to do anything other reiterate specific tropes. <em>Blade Of The Immortal</em> breaks with these traditions partly because the manga it’s adapted from did (mostly out of the artists disinterest in authenticity), and partly because it serves Miike’s intention to create something new, while clothing it in the traditions of what came before. Unlike many of its predecessors, this is a film that interests itself in distinct individuals struggling to escape what seems to be their karma, as opposed to manfully accepting their fate.</p>

<p>It was a surprise, and a happy one for me, to see how well you succeeded in making these outlandish weapons work within this often traditional form. It was an early announcement that this film wasn’t just going to just travel well-trodden ground, but would follow a new path. That, combined with Miike’s often puckish disregard for convention, made <em>Blade Of The Immortal</em> an example of something old being made new again.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Last Jedi</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/16/the-last-jedi.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheLastJedi" />
    <published>2017-12-16T11:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-16T11:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/16/the-last-jedi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>There’s something wonderfully analog about the latest Star Wars film, <em>The Last Jedi</em>. Something gratingly modern about it, too, but the eight-year-old inside me compels me to focus on the positives first (and perhaps ignore the negatives altogether).</p>

<p>Much of this retro vibe comes through in the design of the film. The sets, costumes, props. All the stuff your hard work enabled (your CV is so wonderfully diverse it’s hard to guess what exactly you might have been assisting with). If there is a single image in this film that feels foundational to me, it’s those lovely wide shots of Supreme Leader Snoke’s chamber aboard the gigantic dreadnought spaceship. At first glance, it looks like the studio setting for an early-80s music video. Flat red backdrops, vignetted, glowing with light. Standing all around are guards in glossy red samurai armour. Snoke’s throne sits atop a sort of raised hexagon, and he appears to be wearing something that David Bowie left behind when he transcended to the Nth dimension. It all feels both utterly new and completely of the world that has been established over the course of the last eight Star Wars films (yes, even <em>those</em> ones). It’s something straight out of ’70s sci-fi—<em>Logan’s Run</em> or <em>Silent Running</em> or, yes, even <em>Zardoz</em>. It looks cheap. But in the best possible way. The broad, glossy floors are imperfect; we can see scuffs, lines, motes of dust. The helmets worn by the security guards on the casino planet (yes, the franchise borrows a page from its rival <em>Star Trek</em> and introduces us to a casino planet) display huge digital numbers and seem, in their matte flatness and simplicity, like something that might be drawn by a pre-teen fan. It’s all <em>real</em> in a way that so few contemporary blockbusters are, with their endlessly fiddled-with pixels. This sense of realness is what has always made the best parts of Star Wars the best parts: the practical effects, the <em>weight</em> of everything (look no further than the 1997 special editions to see how timeless those old models and masks look compared to computer VFX).</p>

<p>The plot spins and whirls around these images. Like the other middle act, <em>Empire Strikes Back</em>, this film is strangely structured. It betrays expectations because there is no way to expect it. A and B and C plots interweave and collide (not all of them successfully). There are mutinies and betrayals and flashbacks and non-sequiturs and all sorts of other common storytelling elements that nonetheless feel completely new to the Star Wars series. The story ebbs and flows. It pretends to take us to unexpected places, and then doesn’t, but then again, could it really? This is a generational myth, after all. There is no branch of Judeo-Christianity in which Jesus switches sides, becomes a Buddhist, moves to a sustainable farm in Northern California, gets married and divorced, opens an artisanal cheese shop. Some religious narratives can only be bent, not broken.</p>

<p>And the negatives? Well, I’m going listen to my inner eight-year-old and brush them off. They’re common, after all. The same things that plague every big movie these days; an exhausting plentitude meant to justify a twenty-dollar ticket price (perhaps the real magic of <em>The Force Awakens</em> was its seeming leanness). But if I am ever going to forgive a movie for being overstuffed, it will be a Star Wars movie, and so, here it is, my meaningless five-star rating. Why? Because Star Wars, that’s why.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Raw</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/14/raw.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=Raw" />
    <published>2017-12-14T02:35:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-14T02:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/14/raw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>To call Julia Ducournau’s cannibal coming-of-age story “sexy” would be wildly misleading, but there is at least one scene that deserves the label - initially, anyway. You know the one I mean. During hazing rituals at a veterinarian college, Justine, a sexual neophyte, wanders into a dorm room wearing only her underwear. She’s instantly covered with gallon of blue paint, but no one laughs at her expense. Instead, someone calmly picks out another student covered in yellow paint and sends both them into the bathroom. “Don’t come out until you’re both completely green,” the hazing leader says.</p>

<p>If nothing else, the painter in you must have seen the set-up as a literal wet dream come true. So simple and so carnal. Until, of course, Justine starts living out the fantasy with a little too much enthusiasm and bites off her partner’s lip.</p>

<p>The scene can be looked at like any good painting, and deconstructed to find wider meaning. It’s a simple distillation of Ducournau’s vision and talent as a filmmaker. For one, the concept is hot, but the execution quickly oscillates over to distant and cold. The moment is also a perfect evolution of Justine’s character, who came to college as a vegetarian/virgin and is suddenly acquiring an inexplicable taste for meat. The metaphor, however, isn’t as simplistic as it sounds. Ducournau packs so much meaning and emotion using what seem to be only base elements, but the result feels fresh, alive, and, well, raw.</p>

<p>The actual canvases Ducournau and her cinematographer Ruben Impens use, ie the framing choices of each shot, often favour wides and Westerns that allow plenty of other elements to enter the frame. The opening, for example, is shot at such a distance that we have to make assumptions about what’s happening - only receiving the true details near the end of the film. But withholding what we can see creates an even more satisfying finale when it’s all revealed. Justine’s sexual awakening follows the same path. She goes from wearing a dress overtop her clothes out of protest and modesty, to seducing herself in the mirror by dancing to a filthy rap song and making out with her own reflection. Later, she’ll passionately sinking her teeth into a few boys she also thinks look good.</p>

<p>In the hands of a male director, it’s all but certain many of these scenes would have lost their shading. Ducournau instead opts for the drabbest hellscape of a college you can imagine, then allows the debauched underground parties to explode with strobing danger and nudity. French nudity, of course, in that same liberal and matter-of-fact way that the some of the Old Masters would depict it.</p>

<p>Many of the dots painted early on are satisfyingly connected, and the resulting picture leaves a heavy impression. In the ever-growing gallery of female directors, Ducournau is one to watch out for.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Florida Project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/13/the-florida-project.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheFloridaProject" />
    <published>2017-12-13T11:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-13T11:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/13/the-florida-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>My first thought walking out of <em>The Florida Project</em> was “those weren’t actors.” Or more accurately, “those people weren’t acting.” That’s not an insult – it’s a compliment to your work. What I mean is that it felt like the people on screen, particularly Bria Vinaite and six-year-old Brooklynn Prince, weren’t pretending. I sensed none of the artifice that has come to define Hollywood filmmaking: actors cleanly delivering lines, posturing into arched positions,  carefully hitting lighting cues, etc. The stars of this film are wild and erratic and basically perfect.</p>

<p>Amateur, and perfect.</p>

<p>After finding critical success with his iPhone-shot feature <a href="http://www.dearcastandcrew.com/content/2016/1/26/tangerine.html"><em>Tangerine</em></a>, director Sean Baker decided to do at least one major professional upgrade for this go ’round and shot on 35mm film. I’ve heard him say that the whir of celluloid going through the camera helped keep the actors focused, and was a reminder that every second was like burning money. I have no idea if that was an effective directing technique for first-time actors (I suspect not), but I certainly can’t complain about the results. <em>The Florida Project</em> is loose and free in a way that is completely compelling - even if I wouldn’t have minded a bit tighter plotting at times.</p>

<p>The only recognizable member of the cast, Willem Dafoe, definitely adds a certain level of gravitas and legitimacy to the project, which is a strange thing to consider after I heaped compliments over the naturalistic acting. But that also befits his character, who is the calm at the center of a fuchsia storm: a low-cost-of-living motel in Kissimmee. The tenants are poor, unruly, semi-permanent, and only a stone’s throw away from Disney’s Magical Kingdom. But it’s that contrast of the American dream and American reality that informs every aspect of the film, and helps the film transcend standard narrative drama.</p>

<p>One of the most compelling aspects of the characters is simply the language they use. It’s foul, profane, and nothing short of shocking when coming from the mouth of a preschooler. Even simple acts like taking selfies in a bikini are laced with a layers of meaning that luckily do find fruition even within the film’s story. But it’s how natural (and wrong) they felt in the moment that really helps to define the characters.</p>

<p>So while you may have had some stressful days on set working with kids and rookies, I have to think that projects like these make your days fulfilling. Whatever your process, it certainly added up to worthwhile product.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Disaster Artist</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/8/the-disaster-artist.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheDisasterArtist" />
    <published>2017-12-08T11:35:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-08T11:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/8/the-disaster-artist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>How do you recreate the sound of a footstep, or the crash of glass breaking, in a way that heightens its effect without being cartoonish? The job of a foley artist is just that: to fill the sonic background of a film with everyday noises that don’t draw attention to the fact that they are created in a studio, rather than naturally occurring.</p>

<p>It’s similar to the challenge brothers James and Dave Franco face in trying to tell the story of Tommy Wiseau and his baffling masterpiece/garbage-fire of a film, <em>The Room</em>. Do you just play it straight, no frills? Or do you make choices that heighten the effect, and lean into the artifice?</p>

<p>Somehow <em>The Disaster Artist</em> succeeds in doing both.</p>

<p>The film works partly because it doesn’t do the same things that make <em>The Room</em> so improbably compelling. Much of what made that film impossible to turn away from was its complete ignorance of film grammar and apparent disinterest in the basics of storytelling.</p>

<p>Contrariwise, <em>The Disaster Artist</em> is quietly competent. The film is sharply edited, well written, and the performances are uniformly great—but, again, rarely showy or overt. Tommy Wiseau would be easy to parody, yet James Franco makes him genuine, and, in some odd way, tragic. There must have been a strong compulsion to MSTK the whole thing and go really broad. Instead they made the more difficult choice.</p>

<p>This is the strength of the film. <em>The Room</em> may be worthy of all the bemused scorn it has received over the past decade or so, but that isn’t what the makers of <em>The Disaster Artist</em> find interesting; what is human and universal about Wiseau’s ambitions and dreams is what they focus on. That Franco decides to spend time with that, instead of just an arch remake, is why <em>The Disaster Artist</em> works as well as it does.</p>

<p>In an inspired bit of casting James Franco’s brother Dave plays Sestero. Their scenes together are funny, uncomfortable, absurd, and even emotionally compelling.</p>

<p>Which is also a good way to describe the entire tone of the film.</p>

<p>The brothers’ interaction is the core of the film, and while it may come as a surprise to some, both are effective in shaping characters that feel grounded in reality, even as their shared project becomes increasingly outlandish. There are certainly moments that rely heavily on how unintentionally hilarious <em>The Room</em> is, but they support the characters rather than the comedy beats. What makes <em>The Disaster Artist</em> worth the effort is how effective it is in portraying a universal story about blind, naive ambition and its unintended consequences.</p>

<p>In the same way that a good foley artist chooses the correct moment to amp things up or pull them back, James Franco knows when to go big or go quiet. The resulting film portrays something surreal and outre in a way that never feels mocking. Instead, <em>The Disaster Artist</em> creates a subtle portrait of someone unique who, however imperfectly, realizes his life’s dream.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Beguiled.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/content/2017/12/8/the-beguiled.html/?utm_source=RSS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=TheBeguiled." />
    <published>2017-12-08T11:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-08T11:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>/content/2017/12/8/the-beguiled</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[ <p>You would have liked my grandmother. She was from a well-to-do family who placed the highest importance on being “ladylike”. But she had no compunction against ramming one of her knuckles into my back to make me sit up straight, or threatening to jab me with a fork if I dared put my elbows on the dinner table. Violence was merely a means of maintaining appearances. Needless to say, around her, I was quite the proper young lady. Almost to a fault.</p>

<p>From a young age, women are taught to be nice. Nice and pleasant and well-mannered. These virtues date back to a time not so long ago when a woman’s greatest ambitions were to marry well, bear healthy children, and run a respectable household. Today, etiquette feels like a quaint affectation, though for centuries it dictated how polite society was conducted. But when society falls into a state of war, etiquette, for some, is the only way to keep one’s humanity. It is a luxury that must be maintained at all costs.</p>

<p>Set three years into the American Civil War, <em>The Beguiled</em> opens on a young woman in Virginia singing to herself as she forages in the woods adjacent to Miss Farnsworth’s Seminary School for Girls. It is one of the few wide shots in the film, and we see her walking on a long, dusty road, dwarfed by the hanging moss and nearly drowned out by chirping cicadas and menacing crows. It is so hauntingly dreamlike, that when she stumbles upon an injured Union soldier he hardly seems real. Indeed, director Sofia Coppola’s film always feels contrived, outside of reality, a sumptuous, gauzy morality play that lingers like a guest who should have left long ago, and yet you’re not unhappy they stayed.</p>

<p>The seminary is home to five young women who have been left at the school for safe keeping, their mournful teacher Miss Edwina, and the school’s weary but capable head mistress, Miss Martha, who is quick to inform the lame soldier that he is not a guest, but “a most unwelcome visitor”. From the moment he enters the baroque plantation home, Corporal McBurney’s presence provides the ladies a welcome distraction from the mundane horrors of war, despite the fact that he is the enemy.</p>

<p>The ladies are simultaneously fearful, titillated, and intrigued by the grateful stranger, but three of them are particularly susceptible to McBurney’s charms - teen tempest, Alicia,  who roils with untamed sexuality and raging boredom, the palpably lonely Miss Edwina, who has never known love, and the unflappable Miss Martha who has loved and lost and therefore knows exactly what she’s missing. The tension of this love quadrangle is drawn so taut from the start that it isn’t a matter of if but when - and how - it will snap.</p>

<p>What starts as an ingrained responsibility to Southern Hospitality – tending to a stranger, sharing scant resources, retiring to the music room – quickly becomes something more seductive as the ladies actively make McBurney increasingly comfortable to the point of no return. A chance to turn him over to passing Confederate soldiers is dismissed. Giving up a wounded prisoner would be the opposite of the Christian charity that defines their cherished Southern values. The characters are constantly adjusting their moral compasses to justify their actions, and though many of these actions are telegraphed, the cast assembled is deft enough to dance us through these manipulations while maintaining the film’s delicious sense of unease. Elle Fanning’s dangerously lustful Alicia, Kirsten Dunst’s heartbreakingly brittle Edwina, and Nicole Kidman’s quietly confident Miss Martha are all evenly matched against Colin Farrell’s opportunistic McBurney, who contorts his personality to give each woman what she secretly wants.</p>

<p>Coppola has created a claustrophobic world in which her characters exist – from the shadowy, naturally lit interiors of the once-grand home, to the washed-out, virginal white pinafores and petticoats constraining the women, and the lush, fecund landscaping that has overgrown the plantation, seeming to trap them behind its filigreed gates – and begs the question, is the listless haven they inhabit behind these gates more dangerous than the war-ravaged world beyond them?</p>

<p>In a time of war, people must do things they may have never thought themselves capable of previously. These ethical conundrums are often directly at odds with the gentility and propriety that once defined them. Coppola constructs a diaphanous, ethereal universe for this melodrama, keeping us somewhat at arm’s length. It’s only when the women stop being nice, and polite, and finally find their power that this film finds its strength.</p>
 ]]></content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>